<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="sinemet1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  In controlled clinical trials, patients predominantly with moderate to severe motor fluctuations while on SINEMET were randomized to therapy with either SINEMET or SINEMET CR. The adverse experience frequency profile of SINEMET CR did not differ substantially from that of SINEMET, as shown in Table 1.



 Table 1: Clinical Adverse Experiences Occurring in 1% or Greater of Patients 
 Adverse Experience                                     SINEMET CRn=491%             SINEMETn=524%          
  
 Dyskinesia                                                   16.5                        12.2              
 Nausea                                                       5.5                         5.7               
 Hallucinations                                               3.9                         3.2               
 Confusion                                                    3.7                         2.3               
 Dizziness                                                    2.9                         2.3               
 Depression                                                   2.2                         1.3               
 Urinary tract infection                                      2.2                         2.3               
 Headache                                                     2.0                         1.9               
 Dream abnormalities                                          1.8                         0.8               
 Dystonia                                                     1.8                         0.8               
 Vomiting                                                     1.8                         1.9               
 Upper respiratory infection                                  1.8                         1.0               
 Dyspnea                                                      1.6                         0.4               
 'On-Off' phenomena                                           1.6                         1.1               
 Back pain                                                    1.6                         0.6               
 Dry mouth                                                    1.4                         1.1               
 Anorexia                                                     1.2                         1.1               
 Diarrhea                                                     1.2                         0.6               
 Insomnia                                                     1.2                         1.0               
 Orthostatic hypotension                                      1.0                         1.1               
 Shoulder pain                                                1.0                         0.6               
 Chest pain                                                   1.0                         0.8               
 Muscle cramps                                                0.8                         1.0               
 Paresthesia                                                  0.8                         1.1               
 Urinary frequency                                            0.8                         1.1               
 Dyspepsia                                                    0.6                         1.1               
 Constipation                                                 0.2                         1.5               
         Abnormal laboratory findings occurring at a frequency of 1% or greater in approximately 443 patients who received SINEMET CR and 475 who received SINEMET during controlled clinical trials included: decreased hemoglobin and hematocrit; elevated serum glucose; white blood cells, bacteria and blood in the urine.
 

 The adverse experiences observed in patients in uncontrolled studies were similar to those seen in controlled clinical studies.



 Other adverse experiences reported overall in clinical trials in 748 patients treated with SINEMET CR, listed by body system in order of decreasing frequency, include:



   Body as a Whole  



 Asthenia, fatigue, abdominal pain, orthostatic effects.



   Cardiovascular  



 Palpitation, hypertension, hypotension, myocardial infarction.



   Gastrointestinal  



 Gastrointestinal pain, dysphagia, heartburn.



   Metabolic  



 Weight loss.



   Musculoskeletal  



 Leg pain.



   Nervous System/Psychiatric  



 Chorea, somnolence, falling, anxiety, disorientation, decreased mental acuity, gait abnormalities, extrapyramidal disorder, agitation, nervousness, sleep disorders, memory impairment.



   Respiratory  



 Cough, pharyngeal pain, common cold.



   Skin  



 Rash.



   Special Senses  



 Blurred vision.



   Urogenital  



 Urinary incontinence.



   Laboratory Tests  



 Decreased white blood cell count and serum potassium; increased BUN, serum creatinine and serum LDH; protein and glucose in the urine.



 The following adverse experiences have been reported in postmarketing experience with SINEMET CR:



   Cardiovascular  



 Cardiac irregularities, syncope.



   Gastrointestinal  



 Taste alterations, dark saliva.



   Hypersensitivity  



 Angioedema, urticaria, pruritus, bullous lesions (including pemphigus-like reactions).



   Nervous System/Psychiatric  



 Increased tremor, peripheral neuropathy, psychotic episodes including delusions and paranoid ideation, pathological gambling, increased libido including hypersexuality, impulse control symptoms.



   Skin  



 Alopecia, flushing, dark sweat.



   Urogenital  



 Dark urine.



 Other adverse reactions that have been reported with levodopa alone and with various carbidopa levodopa formulations and may occur with SINEMET CR are:



   Cardiovascular  



 Phlebitis.



   Gastrointestinal  



 Gastrointestinal bleeding, development of duodenal ulcer, sialorrhea, bruxism, hiccups, flatulence, burning sensation of tongue.



   Hematologic  



 Hemolytic and non-hemolytic anemia, thrombocytopenia, leukopenia, agranulocytosis.



   Hypersensitivity  



 Henoch-Schonlein purpura.



   Metabolic  



 Weight gain, edema.



   Nervous System/Psychiatric  



 Ataxia, depression with suicidal tendencies, dementia, euphoria, convulsions (however, a causal relationship has not been established); bradykinetic episodes, numbness, muscle twitching, blepharospasm (which may be taken as an early sign of excess dosage; consideration of dosage reduction may be made at this time), trismus, activation of latent Horner's syndrome, nightmares.



   Skin  



 Malignant melanoma (see also  CONTRAINDICATIONS  ), increased sweating.



   Special Senses  



 Oculogyric crises, mydriasis, diplopia.



   Urogenital  



 Urinary retention, priapism.



   Miscellaneous  



 Faintness, hoarseness, malaise, hot flashes, sense of stimulation, bizarre breathing patterns.



   Laboratory Tests  



 Abnormalities in alkaline phosphatase, SGOT (AST), SGPT (ALT), bilirubin, Coombs test, uric acid.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
