<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="sitavig" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Most common adverse reactions (&gt; or =1%) are:  headache and application site pain  (6.1)  .



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Innocutis Holdings, LLC at 1-800-499-4468 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

    6     ADVERSE REACTIONS

    6.1      Clinical Trial Experience  



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The overall safety of SITAVIG was assessed in 378 adult subjects having at least 4 herpes labialis episodes the previous year.



 One randomized, double-blind, placebo controled trial was conducted in patients with recurrent herpes labialis (cold sores).  In this trial, 378 HSV infected subjects used SITAVIG as a single dose, and 397 subjects used placebo.



 



 Selected treatment emergent adverse events without regard to causality and reported in at least 1% of patients can be seen in Table 1.  



   Table 1:  



 Selected Treatment Emergent Adverse Events reported in at least 1% of patients  
                Event        SITAVIG   N = 378          Placebo  N = 397           
   Nervous System Disorders      Headache      Dizziness      Lethargy          3%      1%      1%         3%     1%     0       
   Gastrointestinal system Disorders      Gingival Pain      Aphthous Stomatitis          1%      1%                0.38%      0          
   Administration Site Conditions      Application Site Pain      Application Site Irritation        1%      1%                 1%      0              
   Skin and Subcutaneous Disorders      Erythema      Rash        1%      1%                 0.3%      0.3%         
      The treatment emergent adverse events considered related to the treatment that occurred in greater than or equal to 1% of patients included headache (1% SITAVIG vs. 2% placebo) and application site pain (1% both arms).  There was no discontinuation of SITAVIG due to adverse drug reactions.  Most treatment related to adverse events were mild or moderate in severity.  One report of headache from both treatment arms was classified as severe.
 

 

    17     PATIENT COUNSELING INFORMATION

  Patients should be informed that SITAVIG is not a cure for cold sores.  See FDA-approved patient labeling  (Patient Information and Instructions for Use)      .  



   17.1     Instructions For Use

  Read the Instructions for Use that comes with SITAVIG before you start using it. Talk to your doctor or pharmacist if you have any questions.



   Important:    SITAVIG should be applied to the area of the upper gum     above the incisor tooth.    SITAVIG tablets should not be crushed, sucked, chewed or    swallowed.      



   If it comes out before 6 hours have gone by, reapply it.    If this does not work then a new tablet should be applied.    It should not be applied to the inside of the lip or cheek.   Tablet should be applied on the same side of the mouth as the herpes labialis symptoms. Do not remove SITAVIG if it sticks to your upper gum. If SITAVIG does not stick or falls off of your upper gum within the first 6hours that you apply it, place it back onto your upper gum. If it still does not stick, replace it with a new SITAVIG tablet. Do not re-apply SITAVIG if it falls out or you swallow it after it has been in place 6 hours or longer. If you swallow SITAVIG within the first 6 hours of applying it, drink a glass of water and place a new SITAVIG tablet onto your upper gum.



   17.2 Adverse Reactions

  Patients may experience adverse reactions including headache, and application site pain.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
