<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="skyla" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious or otherwise important adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *    Ectopic Pregnancy [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *    Intrauterine Pregnancy [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *    Group A Streptococcal Sepsis (GAS) [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *    Pelvic Inflammatory Disease [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *    Bleeding Pattern Alterations [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *    Perforation [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *    Expulsion [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
 *    Ovarian Cysts [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions reported (&gt;10% users) are bleeding pattern alterations, vulvovaginitis, abdominal/pelvic pain, acne/seborrhea, ovarian cyst and headache. (6)
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Bayer HealthCare Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-888-842-2937 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The data described below reflect exposure to Skyla in 1,672 patients in two contraception studies, including 1,383 exposed for one year and 993 who completed the three year studies. The population was generally healthy, 18 to 40-year old females requesting contraception and predominately Caucasian (82.6%). The data cover more than 40,000 cycles of exposure. The frequencies of reported adverse drug reactions represent crude incidences.



 Most common adverse reactions (occurring in &gt;= 5% users) were increased bleeding (7.8%), vulvovaginitis (20.2%), abdominal/pelvic pain (18.9%), acne/seborrhea (15.0%), ovarian cyst (13.2%), headache (12.4%), dysmenorrhea (8.6%), breast pain/discomfort (8.6%) and nausea (5.5%).



 In the contraception studies, 18% discontinued prematurely due to an adverse reaction. The most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation (in &gt;1% of users) were uterine bleeding complaints (4.6%), device expulsion (3.2%), acne/seborrhea (2.9%), abdominal pain (2.5%) dysmenorrhea/uterine spasms (2.0%) and pelvic pain (1.8%).



 Other common adverse reactions (occurring in &gt;= 1% users) by System Organ Class (SOC): The frequencies of adverse reactions observed in clinical trials are summarized in Table 3 by SOC (presented as crude incidences).



 Table 3: Adverse reactions that occurred in at least 1% of Skyla users in clinical trials by SOC 
  System Organ Class                 Adverse Reaction                       Incidence (%)(N=1,672)         
  Reproductive System and Breast Disorders                                          Vulvovaginitis                        
                                                                                                              20.2                          
                                                                
                                                                           Ovarian cyst                          
                                                                                                              13.2                          
                                                                
                                                                           Dysmenorrhoea                         
                                                                                                              8.6                           
                                                                
                                                                           Increased bleeding                    
                                                                                                              7.8                           
                                                                
                                                                           Breast pain/discomfort                
                                                                                                              5.3/3.3                       
                                                                
                                                                           Genital discharge                     
                                                                                                              4.2                           
                                                                
                                                                           Device expulsion (complete and partial) 
                                                                                                              3.2                           
                                                                
                                                                           Upper genital tract infection         
                                                                                                              1.4                           
                                                                
  Gastrointestinal Disorders                                               Abdominal pain/pelvic pain            
                                                                                                              12.7/6.2                      
                                                                
                                                                           Nausea                                
                                                                                                              5.5                           
                                                                
  Skin and SubcutaneousTissue Disorders                                          Acne/Seborrhoea                       
                                                                                                              13.6/1.4                      
                                                                
                                                                           Alopecia                              
                                                                                                              1.2                           
                                                                
  Nervous System Disorders                                                 Headache                              
                                                                                                              12.4                          
                                                                
                                                                           Migraine                              
                                                                                                              2.3                           
                                                                
  Psychiatric Disorders                                                    Depression/ Depressed mood            
                                                                                                              3.8/0.5                       
                                                                
           6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of another LNG IUS. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 *    Hypersensitivity including rash, urticaria, and angioedema 
 *    Device breakage 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Remove Skyla if pregnancy occurs with Skyla in place. There is increased risk of ectopic pregnancy including loss of fertility, pregnancy loss, septic abortion (including septicemia, shock and death), and premature labor and delivery. (  5.1  ,  5.2  ) 
 *    Group A streptococcal infection has been reported; strict aseptic technique is essential during insertion. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Before using Skyla, consider the risks of PID. (  5.4  ) 
 *    Bleeding patterns become altered, may remain irregular and amenorrhea may ensue. (  5.5  ) 
 *    Perforation may occur and may reduce contraceptive effectiveness. Risk is increased if inserted in lactating women and may be increased if inserted in women with fixed retroverted uteri and postpartum. (  5.6  ) 
 *    Partial or complete expulsion may occur. (  5.7  ) 
 *    Evaluate persistent enlarged ovarian follicles. (  5.8  ) 
 *    Skyla can be safely scanned with MRI only under certain conditions (  5.11  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Ectopic Pregnancy



    *     Evaluate women for ectopic pregnancy if they become pregnant with Skyla in place because the likelihood of a pregnancy being ectopic is increased with Skyla. Approximately half of pregnancies that occur with Skyla in place are likely to be ectopic. Also consider the possibility of ectopic pregnancy in the case of lower abdominal pain, especially in association with missed periods or if an amenorrheic woman starts bleeding. 
    The incidence of ectopic pregnancy in clinical trials with Skyla, which excluded women with a history of ectopic pregnancy, was approximately 0.1% per year. The risk of ectopic pregnancy in women who have a history of ectopic pregnancy and use Skyla is unknown. Women with a previous history of ectopic pregnancy, tubal surgery or pelvic infection carry a higher risk of ectopic pregnancy. Ectopic pregnancy may result in loss of fertility.
 

    5.2 Intrauterine Pregnancy



  If pregnancy occurs while using Skyla, remove Skyla because leaving it in place may increase the risk of spontaneous abortion and preterm labor. Removal of Skyla or probing of the uterus may also result in spontaneous abortion. In the event of an intrauterine pregnancy with Skyla, consider the following:



     Septic abortion  



  In patients becoming pregnant with an IUD in place, septic abortion-with septicemia, septic shock, and death-may occur.



     Continuation of pregnancy  



  If a woman becomes pregnant with Skyla in place and if Skyla cannot be removed or the woman chooses not to have it removed, warn her that failure to remove Skyla increases the risk of miscarriage, sepsis, premature labor and premature delivery. Follow her pregnancy closely and advise her to report immediately any symptom that suggests complications of the pregnancy.



     Long-term effects and congenital anomalies  



  When pregnancy continues with Skyla in place, long-term effects on the offspring are unknown. With another LNG IUS, congenital anomalies in live births have occurred infrequently. No clear trend towards specific anomalies has been observed. Because of the local exposure of the fetus to LNG, the possibility of teratogenicity following exposure to Skyla cannot be completely excluded. Some observational data support a small increased risk of masculinization of the external genitalia of the female fetus following exposure to progestins at doses greater than those currently used for oral contraception. Whether these data apply to Skyla is unknown.



    5.3 Sepsis



  Severe infection or sepsis, including Group A streptococcal sepsis (GAS), have been reported following insertion of another LNG IUS. In some cases, severe pain occurred within hours of insertion followed by sepsis within days. Because death from GAS is more likely if treatment is delayed, it is important to be aware of these rare but serious infections. Aseptic technique during insertion of Skyla is essential in order to minimize serious infections such as GAS.



    5.4 Pelvic Infection



    Pelvic Inflammatory Disease (PID)  



  Skyla is contraindicated in the presence of known or suspected PID or in women with a history of PID unless there has been a subsequent intrauterine pregnancy [see Contraindications (  4  )]  . IUDs have been associated with an increased risk of PID, most likely due to organisms being introduced into the uterus during insertion.  1  In clinical trials, PID was observed in 0.4% of women overall and occurred more frequently within the first year and most often within the first month after insertion of Skyla.



 Promptly examine users with complaints of lower abdominal or pelvic pain, odorous discharge, unexplained bleeding ,  fever, genital lesions or sores. Remove Skyla in cases of recurrent endometritis or pelvic inflammatory disease, or if an acute pelvic infection is severe or does not respond to treatment.



     Women at increased risk for PID  



  PID is often associated with a sexually transmitted infection, and Skyla does not protect against sexually transmitted infection. The risk of PID is greater for women who have multiple sexual partners, and also for women whose sexual partner(s) have multiple sexual partners. Women who have had PID are at increased risk for a recurrence or re-infection. In particular, ascertain whether the woman is at increased risk of infection (for example, leukemia, acquired immune deficiency syndrome [AIDS], IV drug abuse).



     Asymptomatic PID  



  PID may be asymptomatic but still result in tubal damage and its sequelae.



     Treatment of PID  



  Following a diagnosis of PID, or suspected PID, bacteriologic specimens should be obtained and antibiotic therapy should be initiated promptly. Removal of Skyla after initiation of antibiotic therapy is usually appropriate. Guidelines for PID treatment are available from the Centers for Disease Control (CDC), Atlanta, Georgia.



     Actinomycosis  



  Actinomycosis has been associated with IUDs. Symptomatic women should have Skyla removed and should receive antibiotics. The significance of actinomyces-like organisms on Pap smear in an asymptomatic IUD user is unknown, and so this finding alone does not always require Skyla removal and treatment. When possible, confirm a Pap smear diagnosis with cultures.



    5.5 Bleeding Pattern Alterations



  Skyla can alter the bleeding pattern and result in spotting, irregular bleeding, heavy bleeding, oligomenorrhea and amenorrhea. During the first 3-6 months of Skyla use, the number of bleeding and spotting days may be higher and bleeding patterns may be irregular. Thereafter, the number of bleeding and spotting days usually decreases but bleeding may remain irregular. Amenorrhea develops by the end of the first year of use in approximately 6% of Skyla users. In Skyla clinical trials, a total of 77 subjects out of 1,672 (4.6%) discontinued due to uterine bleeding complaints. Table 1 shows the bleeding patterns as documented in the Skyla clinical trials based on 90-day reference periods. Table 2 shows the number of bleeding and spotting days based on 28-day cycle equivalents.



 Table 1: Bleeding Patterns Reported with Skyla in Contraception Studies (by 90-day reference periods) 
  Skyla                 First 90 daysN=1,531    Second 90 daysN=1,475    End of year 1N=1,329    End of year 3N=903    
  AmenorrheaDefined as subjects with no bleeding/spotting throughout the 90-day reference period    &lt;1%                   3%                    6%                    12%                   
  Infrequent bleedingDefined as subjects with 1 or 2 bleeding/spotting episodes in the 90-day reference period    8%                    19%                   20%                   22%                   
  Frequent bleedingDefined as subjects with more than 5 bleeding/spotting episodes in the 90-day reference period    31%                   12%                   8%                    4%                    
  Prolonged bleedingDefined as subjects with bleeding/spotting episodes lasting more than 14 days in the 90-day reference period. Subjects with prolonged bleeding may also be included in one of the other categories (excluding amenorrhea)    59%                   17%                   9%                    3%                    
  Irregular bleedingDefined as subjects with 3 to 5 bleeding/spotting episodes and less than 3 bleeding/spotting-free intervals of 14 or more days    42%                   28%                   23%                   - The End of year 3 result for irregular bleeding in particular is artificially inflated (46%) because removal was not timed to coincide with a complete 90-day reference period. The result from the preceding 90-day reference period (17%) provides a more relevant indication of the observed incidence near the end of the 3-year period.    
          Table 2: Mean number of Bleeding and Spotting Days per 28-day Cycle Equivalent 
  28-day Cycle Equivalent    Cycle 1  N=1,588    Cycle 4  N=1,535    Cycle 7  N=1,468    Cycle 13  N=1,345    Cycle 39  N=781    
  Days on treatment    1-28          85-112    169-196       337-364    1065-1092     
                   Mean          SD     Mean          SD     Mean          SD     Mean          SD     Mean          SD     
  Number of bleeding days    7.3           5.6    3.5           3.4    2.8           3.1    2.1           2.7    1.4           2.1    
  Number of spotting days    9.2           6.1    4.8           4.4    3.8           3.6    3.3           3.1    2.7           2.7    
                 Because irregular bleeding/spotting is common during the first months of Skyla use, exclude endometrial pathology (polyps or cancer) prior to the insertion of Skyla in women with persistent or uncharacteristic bleeding. If a significant change in bleeding develops during prolonged use, take appropriate diagnostic measures to rule out endometrial pathology .  The possibility of pregnancy should be considered if menstruation does not occur within six weeks of the onset of a previous menstruation. Once pregnancy has been excluded, repeated pregnancy tests are generally not necessary in amenorrheic women unless indicated, for example, by other signs of pregnancy or by pelvic pain.
 

    5.6 Perforation



  Perforation (total or partial, including penetration/embedment of Skyla in the uterine wall or cervix) may occur most often during insertion, although the perforation may not be detected until sometime later. Perforation may reduce contraceptive efficacy and result in pregnancy. The incidence of perforation during clinical trials was &lt; 0.1%.



 If perforation occurs, locate and remove Skyla. Surgery may be required. Delayed detection or removal of Skyla in case of perforation may result in migration outside the uterine cavity, adhesions, peritonitis, intestinal perforations, intestinal obstruction, abscesses and erosion of adjacent viscera.



 Clinical trials with Skyla excluded breast-feeding women. An interim analysis from a large postmarketing safety study with other IUDs shows an increased risk of perforation in lactating women. The risk of perforation may be increased if Skyla is inserted when the uterus is fixed retroverted or not completely involuted during the postpartum period. Delay Skyla insertion a minimum of six weeks or until involution is complete following a delivery or a second trimester abortion.



    5.7 Expulsion



  Partial or complete expulsion of Skyla may occur resulting in the loss of contraceptive protection. Expulsion may be associated with symptoms of bleeding or pain, or it may be asymptomatic and go unnoticed. Skyla typically decreases menstrual bleeding over time; therefore, an increase of menstrual bleeding may be indicative of an expulsion. The risk of expulsion may be increased when the uterus is not completely involuted. In clinical trials, a 3-year expulsion rate of 3.2% (54 out of 1665 subjects) was reported.



 Delay Skyla insertion a minimum of six weeks or until uterine involution is complete following a delivery or a second trimester abortion. Remove a partially expelled Skyla. If expulsion has occurred, Skyla may be replaced within 7 days of a menstrual period after pregnancy has been ruled out.



    5.8 Ovarian Cysts



  Because the contraceptive effect of Skyla is mainly due to its local effects within the uterus, ovulatory cycles with follicular rupture usually occur in women of fertile age using Skyla. During clinical trials, ovarian cysts (reported as adverse reactions if they were abnormal, non-functional cysts and/or had a diameter &gt;3 cm on ultrasound examination) were reported in 13.2% of women using Skyla. Most of these cysts are asymptomatic, although some may be accompanied by pelvic pain or dyspareunia. In most cases the ovarian cysts disappear spontaneously during two to three months observation. Persistent ovarian cysts should be evaluated. Surgical intervention is not usually required.



    5.9 Breast Cancer



  Women who currently have or have had breast cancer, or have a suspicion of breast cancer, should not use hormonal contraception because some breast cancers are hormone-sensitive [see Contraindications (  4  )]  .



 Spontaneous reports of breast cancer have been received during postmarketing experience with another LNG IUS. Two observational studies have not provided evidence of an increased risk of breast cancer during the use of the other LNG IUS.



    5.10 Clinical Considerations for Use and Removal



  Use Skyla with caution after careful assessment if any of the following conditions exist, and consider removal of the system if any of them arise during use:



 *    Coagulopathy or use of anticoagulants 
 *    Migraine, focal migraine with asymmetrical visual loss or other symptoms indicating transient cerebral ischemia 
 *    Exceptionally severe headache 
 *    Marked increase of blood pressure 
 *    Severe arterial disease such as stroke or myocardial infarction 
    In addition, consider removing Skyla if any of the following conditions arise during use [see Contraindications (  4  )]  :
 

 *    Uterine or cervical malignancy 
 *    Jaundice 
 *    If the threads are not visible or are significantly shortened they may have broken or retracted into the cervical canal or uterus. Consider the possibility that the system may have been displaced, (for example, expelled or perforated the uterus) [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  ,  5.7  )] . Exclude pregnancy and verify the location of Skyla, for example, by sonography, X-ray, or by gentle exploration of the cervical canal with a suitable instrument. If Skyla is displaced, remove it. A new Skyla may be inserted at that time or during the next menses if it is certain that conception has not occurred. If Skyla is in place with no evidence of perforation, no intervention is indicated. 
       5.11 Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) Information
 

  Non-clinical testing has demonstrated that Skyla is MR Conditional. Skyla can be safely scanned only under specific conditions:



 *    Static magnetic field of 3 Tesla or less 
 *    Spatial gradient field of 36,000 Gauss/cm (T/m) or less 
 *    Maximum whole body averaged specific absorption rate (SAR) of 4W/kg in the First Level Controlled mode for 15 minutes of continuous scanning 
    In non-clinical testing, the Skyla produced a temperature rise of less than 1.8 degrees C at a maximum whole body averaged specific absorption rate (SAR) of 2.9 W/kg, for 15 minutes of MR scanning at 3T using a transit/receive body coil.
 

 MR Image quality may be compromised (that is, a small amount of artifact may occur) if the area of interest is in the exact same area or relatively close to the position of Skyla. Image artifact extended up to 5 mm from Skyla in a Gradient Echo pulse sequence.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
