<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="sodium10" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most frequently reported adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=6%) are vomiting, hyperglycemia, hypokalemia, convulsions, and mental impairment. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Oceanside Pharmaceuticals, a division of Valeant Pharmaceuticals North America LLC at 1-800-321-4576 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The safety data were obtained from 316 patients who received Sodium Phenylacetate and Sodium Benzoate Injection as emergency (rescue) or prospective treatment for hyperammonemia as part of an uncontrolled, open-label study. The study population included patients between the ages of 0 to 53 years with a mean (SD) of 6.2 (8.54) years; 51% were male and 49% were female who had the following diagnoses: OTC (46%), ASS (22%), CPS (12%), ASL (2%), ARG (&lt;1%), THN (&lt;1%), and other (18%).



 Adverse reactions were reported with similar frequency in patients with OTC, ASS, CPS, and diagnoses categorized as "other." Nervous system disorders were more frequent in patients with OTC and CPS, compared with patients with ASS and patients with "other" diagnoses. Convulsions and mental impairment were reported in patients with OTC and CPS. These observations are consistent with literature reports that patients with enzyme deficiencies occurring earlier in the urea cycle (i.e., OTC and CPS) tend to be more severely affected.



 Adverse reactions profiles differed by age group. Patients &lt;=30 days of age had more blood and lymphatic system disorders and vascular disorders (specifically hypotension), while patients &gt;30 days of age had more gastrointestinal disorders (specifically nausea, vomiting and diarrhea).



 Less common adverse reactions (&lt;3% of patients) that are characterized as severe are listed below by body system.



 BLOOD AND LYMPHATIC SYSTEM DISORDERS: coagulopathy, pancytopenia, thrombocytopenia



 CARDIAC DISORDERS: atrial rupture, bradycardia, cardiac or cardiopulmonary arrest/failure, cardiogenic shock, cardiomyopathy, pericardial effusion



 EYE DISORDERS: blindness



 GASTROINTESTINAL DISORDERS: abdominal distension, gastrointestinal hemorrhage



 GENERAL DISORDERS AND ADMINISTRATION-SITE CONDITIONS: asthenia, brain death, chest pain, multiorgan failure, edema



 HEPATOBILIARY DISORDERS: cholestasis, hepatic artery stenosis, hepatic failure/hepatotoxicity, jaundice



 INFECTIONS AND INFESTATIONS: sepsis/septic shock



 INJURY, POISONING AND PROCEDURAL COMPLICATIONS: brain herniation, subdural hematoma, overdose



 INVESTIGATIONS: blood carbon dioxide changes, blood glucose changes, blood pH increased, cardiac output decreased, pCO2changes, respiratory rate increased



 METABOLISM AND NUTRITION DISORDERS: alkalosis, dehydration, fluid overload/retention, hypoglycemia, hyperkalemia, hypernatremia, alkalosis, tetany



 NEOPLASMS BENIGN, MALIGNANT AND UNSPECIFIED: hemangioma acquired



 NERVOUS SYSTEM DISORDERS: areflexia, ataxia, brain infarction, brain hemorrhage, cerebral atrophy, clonus, depressed level of consciousness, encephalopathy, nerve paralysis, intracranial pressure increased, subdural hematoma, tremor



 PSYCHIATRIC DISORDERS: acute psychosis, aggression, confusional state, hallucinations



 RENAL AND URINARY DISORDERS: anuria, renal failure, urinary retention



 RESPIRATORY, THORACIC AND MEDIASTINAL DISORDERS: acute respiratory distress syndrome, dyspnea, hypercapnia, hyperventilation, Kussmaul respiration, pneumonia aspiration, pneumothorax, pulmonary hemorrhage, pulmonary edema, respiratory acidosis or alkalosis, respiratory arrest/failure



 SKIN AND SUBCUTANEOUS TISSUE DISORDERS: alopecia, blister, pruritus generalized, rash, urticaria



 VASCULAR DISORDERS: flushing, hemorrhage, hypertension, phlebothrombosis/thrombosis



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=3% of Patients Treated with Sodium Phenylacetate and Sodium Benzoate Injection 
                                                                 Patients    N=316     
  
  Number of patients with any adverse event                     163 (52%)              
  Blood and lymphatic system disorders                          35 (11%)               
    Anemia                                                      12 (4%)                
    Disseminated intravascular coagulation                      11 (3%)                
  Cardiac disorders                                             28 (9%)                
  Gastrointestinal disorders                                    42 (13%)               
    Diarrhea                                                    10 (3%)                
    Nausea                                                      9 (3%)                 
    Vomiting                                                    29 (9%)                
  General disorders and administration-site conditions          45 (14%)               
    Injection-site reaction                                     11 (3%)                
    Pyrexia                                                     17 (5%)                
  Infections                                                    39 (12%)               
    Urinary tract infection                                     9 (3%)                 
  Injury, poisoning and procedural complications                12 (4%)                
  Investigations                                                32 (10%)               
  Metabolism and nutrition disorders                            67 (21%)               
    Acidosis                                                    8 (3%)                 
    Hyperammonemia                                              17 (5%)                
    Hyperglycemia                                               22 (7%)                
    Hypocalcemia                                                8 (3%)                 
    Hypokalemia                                                 23 (7%)                
    Metabolic acidosis                                          13 (4%)                
  Nervous system disorders                                      71 (22%)               
    Brain edema                                                 17 (5%)                
    Coma                                                        10 (3%)                
    Convulsions                                                 19 (6%)                
    Mental impairment                                           18 (6%)                
  Psychiatric disorders                                         16 (5%)                
    Agitation                                                   8 (3%)                 
  Renal and urinary disorders                                   14 (4%)                
  Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders               47 (15%)               
    Respiratory distress                                        9 (3%)                 
  Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                        19 (6%)                
  Vascular disorders                                            19 (6%)                
    Hypotension                                                 14 (4%)                
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *     Management of Acute Hyperammonemia : Monitor plasma ammonia levels during treatment. Prolonged exposure to elevated plasma ammonia levels can rapidly result in injury to the brain or death. Prompt use of all therapies necessary to reduce plasma ammonia levels is essential. (  5.1  ) 
 *     Decreased Potassium Levels : Plasma potassium levels should be carefully monitored and appropriate treatment given when necessary. (  5.2  ) 
 *     Conditions Associated with Fluid Overload : Sodium Phenylacetate and Sodium Benzoate Injection contains 30.5 mg of sodium per mL of undiluted product. Caution should be used if Sodium Phenylacetate and Sodium Benzoate Injection is administered to patients with congestive heart failure, severe renal insufficiency, or with conditions in which there is sodium retention with edema. (  5.3  ) 
 *     Extravasation : Extravasation of Sodium Phenylacetate and Sodium Benzoate Injection into the perivenous tissues during high flow bolus infusion may lead to skin necrosis, especially in infants. The infusion site must be monitored closely for possible tissue infiltration during drug administration. (  5.4  ) 
 *     Neurotoxicity of Phenylacetate: Because of prolonged plasma levels achieved by phenylacetate in pharmacokinetic studies, repeat loading doses should not be administered. Additionally, neurotoxicity related to phenylacetate has been reported in cancer patients. Monitor patients for symptoms of acute neurotoxicity. (  5.5  ) 
 *     Hyperventilation and Metabolic Acidosis: Sodium Phenylacetate and Sodium Benzoate Injection may cause side effects typically associated with salicylate overdose, such as hyperventilation and metabolic acidosis. Monitor patient blood chemistry profiles and perform frequent blood pH and pCO2measurements. (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Management of Acute Hyperammonemia



  Any episode of acute symptomatic hyperammonemia should be treated as a life-threatening emergency. Uncontrolled hyperammonemia can rapidly result in brain damage or death, and prompt use of all therapies necessary, including hemodialysis, to reduce ammonia levels is essential.



 Hyperammonemic coma (regardless of cause) in the newborn infant should be aggressively treated while the specific diagnosis is pursued. Hemodialysis should be promptly initiated in all newborn patients. A blood flow rate of 150 mL/min/m  2  should be targeted (ammonia clearance [mL/min] is similar to the blood flow rate [mL/min] through the dialyzer). Clearance of ammonia is approximately ten times greater by hemodialysis than by peritoneal dialysis or hemofiltration. Exchange transfusion is ineffective in the management of hyperammonemia. Hemodialysis may be repeated until the plasma ammonia level is stable at normal or near normal levels.



 Hyperammonemia due to urea cycle disorders should be managed in coordination with medical personnel experienced in metabolic disorders. Ongoing monitoring of plasma ammonia levels, neurological status, laboratory tests, and clinical response in patients receiving Sodium Phenylacetate and Sodium Benzoate Injection is crucial to assess patient response to treatment.



    5.2 Decreased Potassium Levels



  Because urine potassium loss is enhanced by the excretion of the non-reabsorbable anions, phenylacetylglutamine and hippurate, plasma potassium levels should be carefully monitored and appropriate treatment given when necessary.



    5.3 Conditions Associated with Fluid Overload



  Sodium Phenylacetate and Sodium Benzoate Injection contains 30.5 mg of sodium per mL of undiluted product. Thus, Sodium Phenylacetate and Sodium Benzoate Injection should be used with great care, if at all, in patients with congestive heart failure or severe renal insufficiency, and in clinical states in which there is sodium retention with edema. Discontinue administration of Sodium Phenylacetate and Sodium Benzoate Injection, evaluate the patient, and institute appropriate therapeutic countermeasures if an adverse event occurs.



    5.4 Extravasation



   Administration must be through a central line. Administration through a peripheral line may cause burns  . Bolus infusion flow rates are relatively high, especially for infants [see   Dosage and Administration (2)    ]. Extravasation of Sodium Phenylacetate and Sodium Benzoate Injection into the perivenous tissues may lead to skin necrosis. If extravasation is suspected, discontinue the infusion and resume at a different infusion site, if necessary. The infusion site must be monitored closely for possible infiltration during drug administration. Do not administer undiluted product.



    5.5 Neurotoxicity of Phenylacetate



  Because of prolonged plasma levels achieved by phenylacetate in pharmacokinetic studies, repeat loading doses of Sodium Phenylacetate and Sodium Benzoate Injection should not be administered. Additionally, neurotoxicity was reported in cancer patients receiving intravenous phenylacetate, 250-300 mg/kg/day for 14 days, repeated at 4-week intervals. Manifestations were predominantly somnolence, fatigue, and lightheadedness, with less frequent headaches, dysgeusia, hypoacusis, disorientation, impaired memory, and exacerbation of a pre-existing neuropathy. The acute onset of symptoms upon initiation of treatment and reversibility of symptoms when the phenylacetate was discontinued suggest a drug effect [see   Animal Toxicology and/or Pharmacology (13.2)  ]  .



    5.6 Hyperventilation and Metabolic Acidosis



  Due to structural similarities between phenylacetate and benzoate to salicylate, Sodium Phenylacetate and Sodium Benzoate Injection may cause side effects typically associated with salicylate overdose, such as hyperventilation and metabolic acidosis. Monitoring of blood chemistry profiles, blood pH and pCO2should be performed.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
