<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="sodium2" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  There have been no controlled clinical trials conducted to systematically assess the adverse events profile of sodium nitrite.



 The medical literature has reported the following adverse events in association with sodium nitrite administration. These adverse events were not reported in the context of controlled trials or with consistent monitoring and reporting methodologies for adverse events. Therefore, frequency of occurrence of these adverse events cannot be assessed.



   Cardiovascular system:  syncope, hypotension, tachycardia, methemoglobinemia, palpitations, dysrhythmia



   Hematological:  methemoglobinemia



   Central nervous system:  headache, dizziness, blurred vision, seizures, confusion, coma



   Gastrointestinal system:  nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain



   Respiratory system:  tachypnea, dyspnea



   Body as a Whole  : anxiety, diaphoresis, lightheadedness, injection site tingling, cyanosis, acidosis, fatigue, weakness, urticaria, generalized numbness and tingling



 Severe hypotension, methemoglobinemia, cardiac dysrhythmias, coma and death have been reported in patients without life-threatening cyanide poisoning but who were treated with injection of sodium nitrite at doses less than twice those recommended for the treatment of cyanide poisoning.



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions are:



 *  Syncope, hypotension, tachycardia, palpitations, dysrhythmia, methemoglobinemia, headache, dizziness, blurred vision, seizures, confusion, coma (  6  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Hope Pharmaceuticals at 1-800-755-9595 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

    WARNING: LIFE THREATENING HYPOTENSION AND METHEMOGLOBIN FORMATION  



   Sodium nitrite can cause serious adverse reactions and death in humans, even at doses less than twice the recommended therapeutic dose. Sodium nitrite causes hypotension and methemoglobin formation, which diminishes oxygen carrying capacity.  Hypotension and methemoglobin formation can occur concurrently or separately. Because of these risks, sodium nitrite should be used to treat acute life-threatening cyanide poisoning and be used with caution in patients where the diagnosis of cyanide poisoning is uncertain  .



   Patients should be closely monitored to ensure adequate perfusion and oxygenation during treatment with sodium nitrite.  



   Alternative therapeutic approaches should be considered in patients known to have diminished oxygen or cardiovascular reserve (e.g., smoke inhalation victims, pre-existing anemia, cardiac or respiratory compromise), and those at higher risk of developing methemoglobinemia (e.g., congenital methemoglobin reductase deficiency) as they are at greater risk for potentially life-threatening adverse events related to the use of sodium nitrite  .   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1   and   5.2)  ]  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: LIFE-THREATENING HYPOTENSION AND METHEMOGLOBIN FORMATION  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning    .  



   Sodium nitrite can cause serious adverse reactions and death from:  



 *  Hypotension (5.1) 
 *  Methemoglobin formation (5.2) 
      Patients should be closely monitored to ensure adequate perfusion and oxygenation during treatment with sodium nitrite.  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Methemoglobinemia: Sodium nitrite reacts with hemoglobin to form methemoglobin and should be used with caution in patients known to have anemia. Monitor oxyhemoglobin and methemoglobin levels by pulse oximetry or other measurements. Optimally, the sodium nitrite dose should be reduced in proportion to the oxygen carrying capacity. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Smoke inhalation: Carbon monoxide contained in smoke can result in the formation of carboxyhemoglobin that can reduce the oxygen carrying capacity of the blood. Sodium nitrite should be used with caution in patients with smoke inhalation injury because of the potential for worsening hypoxia due to methemoglobin formation. Carboxyhemoglobin and oxyhemoglobin levels should be monitored by pulse oximetry or other measurements in patients that present with evidence of smoke inhalation. Optimally, the sodium nitrite dose should be reduced in proportion to the oxygen carrying capacity. (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypotension



  See  Boxed Warning  . Sodium nitrite has been associated with severe hypotension, methemoglobinemia, and death at doses less than twice recommended therapeutic doses. Hypotension may occur concurrently or separately. Sodium nitrite should be used to treat life-threatening cyanide poisoning. When the diagnosis of cyanide poisoning is uncertain and/or the patient is not in extremis, special consideration should be given to administration of sodium nitrite if the patient is known or suspected to have diminished oxygen or cardiovascular reserve (e.g., smoke inhalation victims, pre-existing anemia, substantial blood loss, cardiac or respiratory compromise) or to be at higher risk of developing methemoglobinemia (e.g., congenital methemoglobin reductase deficiency).



    5.2 Methemoglobinemia



  Supportive care alone may be sufficient treatment without administration of antidotes for many cases of cyanide intoxication, particularly in conscious patients without signs of severe toxicity. Patients should be closely monitored to ensure adequate perfusion and oxygenation during treatment with sodium nitrite.



 Methemoglobin levels should be monitored and oxygen administered during treatment with sodium nitrite whenever possible. When sodium nitrite is administered to humans a wide range of methemoglobin concentrations occur. Methemoglobin concentrations as high as 58% have been reported after two 300-mg doses of sodium nitrite administered to an adult. Sodium nitrite should be used with caution in the presence of other drugs that may cause methemoglobinemia such as procaine and nitroprusside. Sodium nitrite should be used with caution in patients who may be particularly susceptible to injury from vasodilation and its related hemodynamic sequelae. Hemodynamics should be monitored closely during and after administration of sodium nitrite, and infusion rates should be slowed if hypotension occurs.



    5.3 Anemia



  Sodium nitrite should be used with caution in patients with known anemia. Patients with anemia will form more methemoglobin (as a percentage of total hemoglobin) than persons with normal red blood cell (RBC) volumes. Optimally, these patients should receive a sodium nitrite dose that is reduced in proportion to their oxygen carrying capacity.



    5.4 Smoke Inhalation Injury



  Sodium nitrite should be used with caution in persons with smoke inhalation injury or carbon monoxide poisoning because of the potential for worsening hypoxia due to methemoglobin formation.



    5.5 Neonates and Infants



  Neonates and infants may be more susceptible than adults and older pediatric patients to severe methemoglobinemia when sodium nitrite is administered. Reduced dosing guidelines should be followed in pediatric patients.



    5.6 G6PD Deficiency



  Because patients with G6PD deficiency are at increased risk of a hemolytic crisis with sodium nitrite administration, alternative therapeutic approaches should be considered in these patients. Patients with known or suspected G6PD deficiency should be monitored for an acute drop in hematocrit. Exchange transfusion may be needed for patients with G6PD deficiency who receive sodium nitrite.



    5.7 Use with Other Drugs



  Sodium nitrite should be used with caution in the presence of concomitant antihypertensive medications, diuretics or volume depletion due to diuretics, or drugs known to increase vascular nitric oxide, such as PDE5 inhibitors.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
