<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="soliqua" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere:



 *  Anaphylaxis and Serious Hypersensitivity Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Pancreatitis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Hypoglycemia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *  Acute Kidney Injury [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
 *  Hypokalemia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions commonly associated with SOLIQUA 100/33 include hypoglycemia, allergic reactions, nausea, nasopharyngitis, diarrhea, upper respiratory tract infection, headache. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact sanofi- aventis at 1-800-633-1610 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  .    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trial of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of SOLIQUA 100/33 (n=834, with a mean treatment duration of 203 days) has been evaluated in two clinical studies (30 weeks duration) in type 2 diabetes patients. The studies had the following characteristics: mean age was approximately 59 years; approximately 50% were male, 90% were Caucasian, 6% were Black or African American and 18 % were Hispanic. The mean duration of diabetes was 10.3 years, mean HbA1c at screening for Study A was 8.2 and Study B 8.5. The mean BMI at baseline was 32 kg/m  2  . Baseline eGFR was &gt;=60 mL/min in 87.2% of the pooled study population and mean baseline eGFR was 83.0 ml/min/1.73m  2  .



 Table 3: Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=5% of SOLIQUA 100/33-Treated Patients with Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus from Two Pooled Clinical Trials 
                                                                       SOLIQUA 100/33, %(n=834)           
  
 Nausea                                                                          10.0                     
 Nasopharyngitis                                                                 7.0                      
 Diarrhea                                                                        7.0                      
 Upper respiratory tract infection                                               5.5                      
 Headache                                                                        5.4                      
            Hypoglycemia  
 

 Hypoglycemia is the most commonly observed adverse reaction in patients using insulin, and insulin containing products including SOLIQUA 100/33  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  . The rates of reported hypoglycemia depend on the definition of hypoglycemia used, diabetes type, insulin dose, intensity of glucose control, background therapies, and other intrinsic and extrinsic patient factors. For these reasons, comparing rates of hypoglycemia in clinical trials for SOLIQUA 100/33 with the incidence of hypoglycemia for other products may be misleading and also, may not be representative of hypoglycemia rates that will occur in clinical practice.



 In the SOLIQUA 100/33 program, severe hypoglycemia was defined as an event requiring assistance of another person to actively administer carbohydrate, glucagon, or other resuscitative actions and documented symptomatic hypoglycemia was defined as an event with typical symptoms of hypoglycemia accompanied by a self-monitored plasma glucose value equal to or less than 70 mg/dL (see  Table 4  ).



 Table 4: Severe or Documented Symptomatic Hypoglycemic Episodes in SOLIQUA-Treated Patients with T2DM 
                                             SOLIQUA 100/33Study AN=469      SOLIQUA 100/33Study BN=365     
  
 Severe symptomatic hypoglycemia(%)                      0                              1.1                 
 Documented symptomatic hypoglycemia(%)                 25.6                             40                 
             Gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions  
 

 Gastrointestinal adverse reactions occur more frequently at the beginning of SOLIQUA 100/33 therapy. Gastrointestinal adverse reactions including nausea, diarrhea, vomiting, constipation, dyspepsia, gastritis, abdominal pain, flatulence, gastroesophageal reflux disease, abdominal distension and decreased appetite have been reported in patients treated with SOLIQUA 100/33.



     Lipodystrophy  



 Administration of insulin subcutaneously, including SOLIQUA 100/33, has resulted in lipoatrophy (depression in the skin) or lipohypertrophy (enlargement or thickening of tissue) in some patients  [see  Dosage and Administration (2.4)  ].  



     Anaphylaxis and Hypersensitivity  



   Lixisenatide



 In the lixisenatide development program anaphylaxis cases were adjudicated. Anaphylaxis was defined as a skin or mucosal lesion of acute onset associated with at least 1 other organ system involvement. Symptoms such as hypotension, laryngeal edema or severe bronchospasm could be present but were not required for the case definition. More cases adjudicated as meeting the definition for anaphylaxis occurred in lixisenatide-treated patients (incidence rate of 0.2% or 16 cases per 10,000 patient years) than placebo-treated patient (incidence rate of 0.1% or 7 cases per 10,000 patient years).



 Allergic reactions (such as anaphylactic reaction, angioedema and urticaria) adjudicated as possibly related to the study medication were observed more frequently in lixisenatide-treated patients (0.4%) than placebo-treated patients (0.2%)  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ].  



   Insulin glargine



 Severe, life-threatening, generalized allergy, including anaphylaxis, generalized skin reactions, angioedema, bronchospasm, hypotension, and shock may occur with any insulin, including SOLIQUA 100/33 and may be life threatening.



     Injection-Site Reactions  



 As with any insulin or GLP-1 receptor agonist-containing product, patients taking SOLIQUA 100/33 may experience injection-site reactions, including injection-site hematoma, pain, hemorrhage, erythema, nodules, swelling, discoloration, pruritus, warmth, and injection-site mass. In the clinical program the proportion of injection-site reactions occurring in patients treated with SOLIQUA 100/33 was 1.7%.



     Insulin Initiation and Intensification of Glucose Control  



 Intensification or rapid improvement in glucose control has been associated with a transitory, reversible ophthalmologic refraction disorder, worsening of diabetic retinopathy, and acute painful peripheral neuropathy. However, long-term glycemic control decreases the risk of diabetic retinopathy and neuropathy.



     Peripheral Edema  



 Some patients taking insulin glargine, a component of SOLIQUA 100/30 have experienced sodium retention and edema, particularly if previously poor metabolic control is improved by intensified insulin therapy.



     Weight Gain  



 Weight gain can occur with insulin containing products, including SOLIQUA 100/33, and has been attributed to the anabolic effects of insulin.



   6.2 Immunogenicity

    SOLIQUA 100/33  



 As with all therapeutic proteins, there is potential for immunogenicity. The detection of antibody formation is highly dependent on the sensitivity and specificity of the assay. Additionally, the observed incidence of antibody (including neutralizing antibody) positivity in an assay may be influenced by several factors including assay methodology, sample handling, timing of sample collection, concomitant medications, and underlying disease. For these reasons, comparison of the incidence of antibodies to SOLIQUA 100/33 in the studies described below with the incidence of antibodies in other studies or to other products may be misleading.



 After 30 weeks of treatment with SOLIQUA 100/33 in two phase 3 trials, the incidence of formation of anti-insulin glargine antibodies was 21.0% and 26.2%. In approximately 93% of the patients, anti-insulin glargine antibodies showed cross-reactivity to human insulin. The incidence of formation of anti-lixisenatide antibodies was approximately 43%.



   Lixisenatide



 In the pool of 9 placebo-controlled studies, 70% of patients exposed to lixisenatide tested positive for anti-lixisenatide antibodies during the trials. In the subset of patients (2.4%) with the highest antibody concentrations (&gt;100 nmol/L), an attenuated glycemic response was observed. A higher incidence of allergic reactions and injection-site reactions occurred in antibody positive patients  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]  .



 Anti-lixisenatide antibody characterization studies have demonstrated the potential for development of antibodies cross-reactive with endogenous GLP-1 and glucagon, but their incidence has not been fully determined and the clinical significance of these antibodies is not currently known.



 No information regarding the presence of neutralizing antibodies is currently available.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Anaphylaxis and serious hypersensitivity reactions : can occur with either of the components in SOLIQUA 100/33. Instruct patients to discontinue if a reaction occurs and promptly seek medical attention. (  5.1  ) 
 *   Pancreatitis : Discontinue promptly if pancreatitis is suspected. Do not restart if pancreatitis is confirmed. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Never share a SOLIQUA 100/33 prefilled pen between patients, even if the needle is changed. (  5.3  ) 
 *   Hyperglycemia or hypoglycemia with changes in SOLIQUA 100/33 regimen: Carry out under close medical supervision. (  5.4  ) 
 *   Overdose due to Medication errors : SOLIQUA 100/33 contains two drugs. Instruct patients to always check the label before each injection since accidental mix-ups with insulin-containing products can occur. Do not exceed the maximum dose or use with other GLP-1 receptor agonists. (  5.5  ) 
 *   Hypoglycemia: May be life-threatening. Increase frequency of glucose monitoring with changes to: insulin dosage, coadministered glucose lowering medications, meal pattern, physical activity; and in patients with renal or hepatic impairment and hypoglycemia unawareness. (  5.6  ) 
 *   Acute Kidney Injury : Monitor renal function in patients with renal impairment and in patients with severe GI adverse reactions. Use is not recommended in patients with end-stage renal disease (  5.7  ) 
 *   Immunogenicity : Patients may develop antibodies to insulin glargine and lixisenatide. If there is worsening glycemic control or failure to achieve targeted glycemic control, significant injection-site reactions or allergic reactions, alternative antidiabetic therapy should be considered. (  5.8  ) 
 *   Hypokalemia : May be life-threatening. Monitor potassium levels in patients at risk of hypokalemia and treat if indicated. (  5.9  ) 
 *   Fluid retention and heart failure with use of thiazolidinediones (TZDs) : Observe for signs and symptoms of heart failure; consider dosage reduction or discontinuation if heart failure occurs. (  5.10  ) 
 *   Macrovascular Outcomes : Clinical studies have not shown macrovascular risk reduction with SOLIQUA 100/33. (  5.11  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Anaphylaxis and Serious Hypersensitivity Reactions



  In clinical trials of lixisenatide, a component of SOLIQUA 100/33, there have been cases of anaphylaxis (frequency of 0.1% or 10 cases per 10,000 patient-years) and other serious hypersensitivity reactions including angioedema. Severe, life-threatening, generalized allergy, including anaphylaxis, generalized skin reactions, angioedema, bronchospasm, hypotension, and shock can occur with insulins, including insulin glargine, a component of SOLIQUA 100/33 [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



 Inform and closely monitor patients with a history of anaphylaxis or angioedema with another GLP-1 receptor agonist for allergic reactions, because it is unknown whether such patients will be predisposed to anaphylaxis with lixisenatide. SOLIQUA 100/33 is contraindicated in patients with known hypersensitivity to lixisenatide or insulin glargine [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  . If a hypersensitivity reaction occurs, the patient should discontinue SOLIQUA 100/33 and promptly seek medical attention.



    5.2 Pancreatitis



  Acute pancreatitis, including fatal and non-fatal hemorrhagic or necrotizing pancreatitis, has been reported postmarketing in patients treated with GLP-1 receptor agonists. In clinical trials of lixisenatide, a component of SOLIQUA 100/33, there were 21 cases of pancreatitis among lixisenatide-treated patients and 14 cases in comparator-treated patients (incidence rate of 21 vs 17 per 10,000 patient-years). Lixisenatide cases were reported as acute pancreatitis (n=3), pancreatitis (n=12), chronic pancreatitis (n=5), and edematous pancreatitis (n=1). Some patients had risk factors for pancreatitis, such as a history of cholelithiasis or alcohol abuse.



 After initiation of SOLIQUA 100/33, observe patients carefully for signs and symptoms of pancreatitis (including persistent severe abdominal pain, sometimes radiating to the back and which may or may not be accompanied by vomiting). If pancreatitis is suspected, promptly discontinue SOLIQUA 100/33 and initiate appropriate management. If pancreatitis is confirmed, restarting SOLIQUA 100/33 is not recommended. Consider antidiabetic therapies other than SOLIQUA 100/33 in patients with a history of pancreatitis.



    5.3 Never Share a SOLIQUA 100/33 Prefilled Pen Between Patients



  SOLIQUA 100/33 prefilled pens must never be shared between patients, even if the needle is changed. Sharing of the pen poses a risk for transmission of blood-borne pathogens.



    5.4 Hyperglycemia or Hypoglycemia with Changes in Insulin Regimen



  Changes in SOLIQUA 100/33 regimen may affect glycemic control and predispose to hypoglycemia or hyperglycemia. These changes should be made cautiously and only under close medical supervision, and the frequency of blood glucose monitoring should be increased. Adjustments in concomitant oral antidiabetic treatment may be needed. When converting from basal insulin therapy or lixisenatide to SOLIQUA 100/33 follow dosing recommendations [see  Dosage and Administration (2.1  ,  2.2)  ].  



    5.5 Overdose Due to Medication Errors



  SOLIQUA 100/33 contains two drugs: insulin glargine and lixisenatide. Administration of more than 60 units of SOLIQUA 100/33 daily can result in overdose of the lixisenatide component. Do not exceed the 20 mcg maximum recommended dose of lixisenatide or use with other glucagon-like peptide-1 receptor agonists.



 Accidental mix-ups between insulin products have been reported. To avoid medication errors between SOLIQUA 100/33 (an insulin containing product) and other insulins, instruct patients to always check the insulin label before each injection.



    5.6 Hypoglycemia



  Hypoglycemia is the most common adverse reaction associated with insulin containing products, including SOLIQUA 100/33 [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . Severe hypoglycemia can cause seizures, may be life-threatening or cause death. Hypoglycemia can impair concentration ability and reaction time; this may place an individual and others at risk in situations where these abilities are important (e.g., driving or operating other machinery). SOLIQUA 100/33 (an insulin-containing product), or any insulin, should not be used during episodes of hypoglycemia [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  .



 Hypoglycemia can happen suddenly and symptoms may differ in each individual and change over time in the same individual. Symptomatic awareness of hypoglycemia may be less pronounced in patients with longstanding diabetes, in patients with diabetic nerve disease, in patients using medications that block the sympathetic nervous system (e.g., beta-blockers) [see  Drug Interactions (7.1)  ]  , or in patients who experience recurrent hypoglycemia.



    Risk Factors for Hypoglycemia  



 The risk of hypoglycemia generally increases with intensity of glycemic control. The risk of hypoglycemia after an injection is related to the duration of action of the insulin and, in general, is highest when the glucose lowering effect of the insulin is maximal. As with all insulin containing preparations, the glucose lowering effect time course of SOLIQUA 100/33 may vary in different individuals or at different times in the same individual and depends on many conditions, including the area of injection as well as the injection-site blood supply and temperature [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2  )].  



 Other factors which may increase the risk of hypoglycemia include changes in meal pattern (e.g., macronutrient content or timing of meals), changes in level of physical activity, or changes to coadministered medication [see  Drug Interactions (7.1)  ].  Patients with renal or hepatic impairment may be at higher risk of hypoglycemia [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.6  ,  8.7)  ].  



    Risk Mitigation Strategies for Hypoglycemia  



 Patients and caregivers must be educated to recognize and manage hypoglycemia. Self-monitoring of blood glucose plays an essential role in the prevention and management of hypoglycemia. In patients at higher risk for hypoglycemia and patients who have reduced symptomatic awareness of hypoglycemia, increased frequency of blood glucose monitoring is recommended.



 The long-acting effect of the insulin glargine component of SOLIQUA 100/33 may delay recovery from hypoglycemia.



    5.7 Acute Kidney Injury



  Acute kidney injury and worsening of chronic renal failure, which may sometimes require hemodialysis, has been reported postmarketing in patients treated with GLP-1 receptor agonists, such as lixisenatide, a component of SOLIQUA 100/33. Some of these events were reported in patients without known underlying renal disease. A majority of the reported events occurred in patients who had experienced nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, or dehydration.



 Monitor renal function when initiating or escalating doses of SOLIQUA 100/33 in patients with renal impairment and in patients reporting severe gastrointestinal reactions. Advise patients of the potential risk of dehydration due to gastrointestinal adverse reactions and take precautions to avoid fluid depletion. SOLIQUA 100/33 is not recommended in patients with end-stage renal disease [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.6)  ].  



    5.8 Immunogenicity



  Patients may develop antibodies to insulin and lixisenatide, components of SOLIQUA 100/33, following treatment. A pooled analysis of studies of lixisenatide-treated patients showed that 70% were antibody positive at Week 24. In the subset of patients (2.4%) with the highest antibody concentrations (&gt;100 nmol/L), an attenuated glycemic response was observed. A higher incidence of allergic reactions and injection-site reactions occurred in antibody positive patients. [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ,  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ].  



 If there is worsening glycemic control or failure to achieve targeted glycemic control, significant injection-site reactions or allergic reactions, alternative antidiabetic therapy should be considered.



    5.9 Hypokalemia



  All insulin-containing products, including SOLIQUA 100/33, cause a shift in potassium from the extracellular to intracellular space, possibly leading to hypokalemia. Untreated hypokalemia may cause respiratory paralysis, ventricular arrhythmia, and death. Monitor potassium levels in patients at risk for hypokalemia if indicated (e.g., patients using potassium-lowering medications, patients taking medications sensitive to serum potassium concentrations).



    5.10 Fluid Retention and Heart Failure with Concomitant Use of PPAR-gamma Agonists



  Thiazolidinediones (TZDs), which are peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor (PPAR)-gamma agonists, can cause dose-related fluid retention, particularly when used in combination with insulin containing products, including SOLIQUA 100/33. Fluid retention may lead to or exacerbate heart failure. Patients treated with insulin containing products, including SOLIQUA 100/33, and a PPAR-gamma agonist should be observed for signs and symptoms of heart failure. If heart failure develops, it should be managed according to current standards of care, and discontinuation or dose reduction of the PPAR-gamma agonist must be considered.



    5.11 Macrovascular Outcomes



  There have been no clinical studies establishing macrovascular risk reduction with SOLIQUA 100/33 or any other antidiabetic drug.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
