<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="solodyn" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most commonly observed adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 5%) are headache, fatigue, dizziness, and pruritus. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Valeant Pharmaceuticals North America LLC at 1-800-321-4576 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug, and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The following table summarizes selected adverse reactions reported in clinical trials at a rate of &gt;= 1% for SOLODYN.



 Table 2: Selected Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions in at least 1% of Clinical Trial Subjects 
   Adverse Reactions                                   SOLODYN    (1 mg/kg)    N = 674 (%)      PLACEBO    N = 364 (%)     
  
  At least one treatment-emergent event               379 (56)                   197 (54)                   
  Headache                                            152 (23)                   83 (23)                    
  Fatigue                                             62 (9)                     24 (7)                     
  Dizziness                                           59 (9)                     17 (5)                     
  Pruritus                                            31 (5)                     16 (4)                     
  Malaise                                             26 (4)                     9 (3)                      
  Mood alteration                                     17 (3)                     9 (3)                      
  Somnolence                                          13 (2)                     3 (1)                      
  Urticaria                                           10 (2)                     1 (0)                      
  Tinnitus                                            10 (2)                     5 (1)                      
  Arthralgia                                          9 (1)                      2 (0)                      
  Vertigo                                             8 (1)                      3 (1)                      
  Dry mouth                                           7 (1)                      5 (1)                      
  Myalgia                                             7 (1)                      4 (1)                      
           6.2Postmarketing Experience
   Adverse reactions that have been reported with minocycline hydrochloride use in a variety of indications include:



 *      Skin and hypersensitivity reactions: fixed drug eruptions, balanitis, erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, anaphylactoid purpura, photosensitivity, pigmentation of skin and mucous membranes, hypersensitivity reactions, angioneurotic edema, anaphylaxis, DRESS syndrome [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ] . 
 *      Autoimmune conditions: polyarthralgia, pericarditis, exacerbation of systemic lupus, pulmonary infiltrates with eosinophilia, transient lupus-like syndrome. 
 *      Central nervous system: pseudotumor cerebri, bulging fontanels in infants, decreased hearing. 
 *      Endocrine: brown-black microscopic thyroid discoloration, abnormal thyroid function. 
 *      Oncology: thyroid cancer. 
 *      Oral: glossitis, dysphagia, tooth discoloration. 
 *      Gastrointestinal: enterocolitis, pancreatitis, hepatitis, liver failure. 
 *      Renal: reversible acute renal failure. 
 *      Hematology : hemolytic anemia, thrombocytopenia, eosinophilia. 
    Preliminary studies suggest that use of minocycline may have deleterious effects on human spermatogenesis  [see  Nonclinical Toxicology (13.1)  ]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    The use of SOLODYN during tooth development (last half of pregnancy, infancy, and childhood up to the age of 8 years) may cause permanent discoloration of the teeth (yellow-gray-brown). (  5.1  ) 
 *    If pseudomembranous colitis occurs, discontinue SOLODYN. (  5.2  ) 
 *    If liver injury is suspected, discontinue SOLODYN. (  5.3  ) 
 *    If renal impairment exists, SOLODYN doses may need to be adjusted to avoid excessive systemic accumulations of the drug and possible liver toxicity. (  5.4  ) 
 *    Minocycline may cause central nervous system side effects including light-headedness, dizziness, or vertigo. Advise patients. (  5.5  ) 
 *    Minocycline may cause pseudotumor cerebri (benign intracranial hypertension) in adults and adolescents. Discontinue SOLODYN if symptoms occur. (  5.6  ) 
 *    Minocycline has been associated with autoimmune syndromes; discontinue SOLODYN immediately if symptoms occur. (  5.7  ) 
 *    Minocycline has been associated with anaphylaxis, serious skin reactions, erythema multiforme, and DRESS syndrome. Discontinue SOLODYN immediately if symptoms occur. (  5.9  ) 
    
 

   5.1Teratogenic Effects



    *    MINOCYCLINE, LIKE OTHER TETRACYCLINE-CLASS DRUGS, CAN CAUSE FETAL HARM WHEN ADMINISTERED TO A PREGNANT WOMAN. IF ANY TETRACYCLINE IS USED DURING PREGNANCY OR IF THE PATIENT BECOMES PREGNANT WHILE TAKING THESE DRUGS, THE PATIENT SHOULD BE APPRISED OF THE POTENTIAL HAZARD TO THE FETUS.SOLODYN should not be used during pregnancy or by individuals of either gender who are attempting to conceive a child [see  Nonclinical Toxicology (13.1)  &amp;  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ] . 
 *    THE USE OF DRUGS OF THE TETRACYCLINE CLASS DURING TOOTH DEVELOPMENT (LAST HALF OF PREGNANCY, INFANCY, AND CHILDHOOD UP TO THE AGE OF 8 YEARS) MAY CAUSE PERMANENT DISCOLORATION OF THE TEETH (YELLOW-GRAY-BROWN).This adverse reaction is more common during long-term use of the drug but has been observed following repeated short-term courses. Enamel hypoplasia has also been reported. TETRACYCLINE DRUGS, THEREFORE, SHOULD NOT BE USED DURING TOOTH DEVELOPMENT. 
 *    All tetracyclines form a stable calcium complex in any bone-forming tissue. A decrease in fibula growth rate has been observed in premature human infants given oral tetracycline in doses of 25 mg/kg every 6 hours. This reaction was shown to be reversible when the drug was discontinued.Results of animal studies indicate that tetracyclines cross the placenta, are found in fetal tissues, and can cause retardation of skeletal development on the developing fetus. Evidence of embryotoxicity has been noted in animals treated early in pregnancy [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ] . 
       5.2Pseudomembranous Colitis
 

   Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea (CDAD) has been reported with nearly all antibacterial agents, including minocycline, and may range in severity from mild diarrhea to fatal colitis.



 Treatment with antibacterial agents alters the normal flora of the colon leading to overgrowth of C. difficile  .



  C. difficile  produces toxins A and B which contribute to the development of CDAD. Hypertoxin producing strains of C. difficile  cause increased morbidity and mortality, as these infections can be refractory to antimicrobial therapy and may require colectomy. CDAD must be considered in all patients who present with diarrhea following antibiotic use. Careful medical history is necessary since CDAD has been reported to occur over two months after the administration of antibacterial agents.



 If CDAD is suspected or confirmed, ongoing antibiotic use not directed against C. difficile  may need to be discontinued. Appropriate fluid and electrolyte management, protein supplementation, antibiotic treatment of C. difficile  , and surgical evaluation should be instituted as clinically indicated.



    5.3Hepatotoxicity



  Post-marketing cases of serious liver injury, including irreversible drug-induced hepatitis and fulminant hepatic failure (sometimes fatal) have been reported with minocycline use in the treatment of acne.



    5.4Metabolic Effects



  The anti-anabolic action of the tetracyclines may cause an increase in BUN. While this is not a problem in those with normal renal function, in patients with significantly impaired function, higher serum levels of tetracycline-class drugs may lead to azotemia, hyperphosphatemia, and acidosis. If renal impairment exists, even usual oral or parenteral doses may lead to excessive systemic accumulations of the drug and possible liver toxicity. Under such conditions, lower than usual total doses are indicated, and if therapy is prolonged, serum level determinations of the drug may be advisable.



    5.5Central Nervous System Effects



  Central nervous system side effects including light-headedness, dizziness or vertigo have been reported with minocycline therapy. Patients who experience these symptoms should be cautioned about driving vehicles or using hazardous machinery while on minocycline therapy. These symptoms may disappear during therapy and usually rapidly disappear when the drug is discontinued.



    5.6Benign Intracranial Hypertension



  Pseudotumor cerebri (benign intracranial hypertension) in adults and adolescents has been associated with the use of tetracyclines. Minocycline has been reported to cause or precipitate pseudotumor cerebri, the hallmark of which is papilledema. Clinical manifestations include headache and blurred vision. Bulging fontanels have been associated with the use of tetracyclines in infants. Although signs and symptoms of pseudotumor cerebri resolve after discontinuation of treatment, the possibility for permanent sequelae such as visual loss that may be permanent or severe exists. Patients should be questioned for visual disturbances prior to initiation of treatment with tetracyclines. If visual disturbance occurs during treatment, patients should be checked for papilledema. Concomitant use of isotretinoin and minocycline should be avoided because isotretinoin, a systemic retinoid, is also known to cause pseudotumor cerebri.



    5.7Autoimmune Syndromes



  Tetracyclines have been associated with the development of autoimmune syndromes. The long-term use of minocycline in the treatment of acne has been associated with drug-induced lupus-like syndrome, autoimmune hepatitis and vasculitis. Sporadic cases of serum sickness have presented shortly after minocycline use. Symptoms may be manifested by fever, rash, arthralgia, and malaise. In symptomatic patients, liver function tests, ANA, CBC, and other appropriate tests should be performed to evaluate the patients. Use of all tetracycline-class drugs should be discontinued immediately.



    5.8Photosensitivity



  Photosensitivity manifested by an exaggerated sunburn reaction has been observed in some individuals taking tetracyclines. This has been reported rarely with minocycline. Patients should minimize or avoid exposure to natural or artificial sunlight (tanning beds or UVA/B treatment) while using minocycline. If patients need to be outdoors while using minocycline, they should wear loose-fitting clothes that protect skin from sun exposure and discuss other sun protection measures with their physician.



    5.9Serious Skin/Hypersensitivity Reaction



  Cases of anaphylaxis, serious skin reactions (e.g. Stevens Johnson syndrome), erythema multiforme, and drug rash with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms (DRESS) syndrome have been reported postmarketing with minocycline use in patients with acne. DRESS syndrome consists of cutaneous reaction (such as rash or exfoliative dermatitis), eosinophilia, and one or more of the following visceral complications such as: hepatitis, pneumonitis, nephritis, myocarditis, and pericarditis. Fever and lymphadenopathy may be present. In some cases, death has been reported. If this syndrome is recognized, the drug should be discontinued immediately.



    5.10Tissue Hyperpigmentation



  Tetracycline-class antibiotics are known to cause hyperpigmentation. Tetracycline therapy may induce hyperpigmentation in many organs, including nails, bone, skin, eyes, thyroid, visceral tissue, oral cavity (teeth, mucosa, alveolar bone), sclerae and heart valves. Skin and oral pigmentation has been reported to occur independently of time or amount of drug administration, whereas other tissue pigmentation has been reported to occur upon prolonged administration. Skin pigmentation includes diffuse pigmentation as well as over sites of scars or injury.



    5.11Development of Drug-Resistant Bacteria



  Bacterial resistance to the tetracyclines may develop in patients using SOLODYN, therefore, the susceptibility of bacteria associated with infection should be considered in selecting antimicrobial therapy. Because of the potential for drug-resistant bacteria to develop during the use of SOLODYN, it should be used only as indicated.



    5.12Superinfection



  As with other antibiotic preparations, use of SOLODYN may result in overgrowth of nonsusceptible organisms, including fungi. If superinfection occurs, SOLODYN should be discontinued and appropriate therapy instituted.



    5.13Laboratory Monitoring



  Periodic laboratory evaluations of organ systems, including hematopoietic, renal and hepatic studies should be performed. Appropriate tests for autoimmune syndromes should be performed as indicated.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
