<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="somatuline" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions are diarrhea, cholelithiasis, abdominal pain, nausea and injection site reactions (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Ipsen Biopharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-866-837-2422 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  The data described below reflect exposure to Somatuline Depot in 416 acromegalic patients in seven studies. One study was a fixed-dose pharmacokinetic study. The other six studies were open-label or extension studies, one had a placebo controlled run-in period and another had an active control. The population was mainly Caucasian (329/353, 93%) with a median age of 53.0 years of age (range 19-84 years). Fifty-four subjects (13%) were age 66-74 and eighteen subjects (4.3%) were &gt;= 75 years of age. Patients were evenly matched for gender (205 males and 211 females). The median average monthly dose was 91.2 mg (e.g., 90 mg injected via the deep subcutaneous route every 4 weeks) over 385 days with a median cumulative dose of 1290 mg. Of the patients reporting acromegaly severity at baseline (N=265), serum GH levels were &lt; 10 ng/mL for 69% (183/265) of the patients and &gt;= 10 ng/mL for 31% (82/265) of the patients.



 The most commonly reported adverse reactions reported by &gt; 5% of patients who received Somatuline Depot (N=416) in the overall pooled safety studies in acromegaly patients were gastrointestinal disorders (diarrhea, abdominal pain, nausea, constipation, flatulence, vomiting, loose stools), cholelithiasis and injection site reactions.



 Tables 1 and 2 present adverse reaction data from clinical studies with Somatuline Depot in acromegalic patients. The tables include data from a single clinical study and pooled data from seven clinical studies.



     Adverse Reactions in Parallel Fixed-Dose Phase of Study 1:  



 The incidence of treatment-emergent adverse reactions for Somatuline Depot 60 mg, 90 mg, and 120 mg by dose as reported during the first 4 months (fixed-dose phase) of Study 1 [  see  Clinical Studies (14)    ], are provided in Table 1.



 Table 1 Adverse Reactions at an Incidence &gt; 5% Lanreotide Overall and Occurring at Higher Rate in Drug than Placebo: Placebo-Controlled and Fixed-Dose Phase of Study 1 by Dose 
                          Placebo-Controlled Double-Blind PhaseWeeks 0 to 4  Fixed-Dose PhaseDouble-Blind + Single-BlindWeeks 0 to 20   
 Body System  Preferred Term  Placebo(N=25)N (%)  LanreotideOverall(N=83)N (%)  Lanreotide60 mg(N=34)N (%)  Lanreotide90 mg(N=36)N (%)  Lanreotide120 mg(N=37)N (%)  Lanreotide Overall(N=107)N (%)   
  
  A patient is counted only once for each body system and preferred term.    
  Dictionary = WHOART.     
  
   Gastrointestinal System Disorders      1 (4%)        30 (36%)       12 (35%)       21 (58%)       27 (73%)       60 (56%)      
   Diarrhea               0             26 (31%)       9 (26%)        15 (42%)       24 (65%)       48 (45%)        
   Abdominal pain         1 (4%)        6 (7%)         3 (9%)         6 (17%)        7 (19%)        16 (15%)        
   Flatulence             0             5 (6%)         0 (0%)         3 (8%)         5 (14%)        8 (7%)          
   Application Site Disorders      0 (0%)        5 (6%)         3 (9%)         4 (11%)        8 (22%)        15 (14%)      
 (Injection site mass/ pain/ reaction/ inflammation)                                                                                            
   Liver and Biliary System Disorders      1 (4%)        3 (4%)         9 (26%)        7 (19%)        4 (11%)        20 (19%)      
   Cholelithiasis         0             2 (2%)         5 (15%)        6 (17%)        3 (8%)         14 (13%)        
   Heart Rate &amp; Rhythm Disorders      0             8 (10%)        7 (21%)        2 (6%)         5 (14%)        14 (13%)      
   Bradycardia            0             7 (8%)         6 (18%)        2 (6%)         2 (5%)         10 (9%)         
   Red Blood Cell Disorders      0             6 (7%)         2 (6%)         5 (14%)        2 (5%)         9 (8%)        
   Anemia                 0             6 (7%)         2 (6%)         5 (14%)        2 (5%)         9 (8%)          
   Metabolic &amp; Nutritional Disorders      3 (12%)       13 (16%)       8 (24%)        9 (25%)        4 (11%)        21 (20%)      
   Weight decrease        0             7 (8%)         3 (9%)         4 (11%)        2 (5%)         9 (8%)          
             In Study 1, the adverse reactions of diarrhea, abdominal pain and flatulence increased in incidence with increasing dose of Somatuline Depot.
 

     Adverse Reactions in Long-Term Clinical Trials:  



 Table 2 provides the most common adverse reactions that occurred in 416 acromegalic patients treated with Somatuline Depot in seven studies. The analysis of safety compares adverse reaction rates of patients at baseline from the two efficacy studies, to the overall pooled data from seven studies. Patients with elevated GH and IGF-1 levels were either naive to somatostatin analog therapy or had undergone a 3-month washout [  see  Clinical Studies (14)    ].



 Table 2 Adverse Reactions at an Incidence &gt; 5.0% in Overall Group Reported in Clinical Studies 
 System Organ Class                        Number and Percentage of Patients   
 Studies 1 &amp; 2                             Overall Pooled Data   
 (N = 170)                                 (N = 416)         
 N                                         %                N                %                 
  
  Dictionary - MedDRA 7.1                   
  
   Patients with any Adverse Reactions       157              92               356              86              
   Gastrointestinal disorders                121              71               235              57              
   Diarrhea                                81               48               155              37                
   Abdominal pain                          34               20               79               19                
   Nausea                                  15               9                46               11                
   Constipation                            9                5                33               8                 
   Flatulence                              12               7                30               7                 
   Vomiting                                8                5                28               7                 
   Loose stools                            16               9                23               6                 
   Hepatobiliary disorders                   53               31               99               24              
   Cholelithiasis                          45               27               85               20                
   General disorders and administration site conditions      51               30               91               22              
   (Injection site pain /mass / induration /nodule /pruritus)  28               17               37               9                 
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders      44               26               70               17              
   Arthralgia                              17               10               30               7                 
   Nervous system disorders                  34               20               80               19              
   Headache                                9                5                30               7                 
           In addition to the adverse reactions listed in Table 2, the following reactions were also seen:
 

 *  Sinus bradycardia occurred in 7% (12) of patients in the pooled Study 1 and 2 and in 3% (13) of patients in the overall pooled studies. 
 *  Hypertension occurred in 7% (11) of patients in the pooled Study 1 and 2 and in 5% (20) of patients in the overall pooled studies. 
 *  Anemia occurred in 7% (12) of patients in the pooled Study 1 and 2 and in 3% (14) of patients in the overall pooled studies. 
        Gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions  
 

 In the pooled clinical studies of Somatuline Depot therapy, a variety of gastrointestinal reactions occurred, the majority of which were mild to moderate in severity. One percent of acromegalic patients treated with Somatuline Depot in the pooled clinical studies discontinued treatment because of gastrointestinal reactions.



 Pancreatitis was reported in &lt; 1% of patients.



     Gallbladder Adverse Reactions  



 In clinical studies involving 416 acromegalic patients treated with Somatuline Depot, cholelithiasis and gallbladder sludge were reported in 20% of the patients. Among 167 acromegalic patients treated with Somatuline Depot who underwent routine evaluation with gallbladder ultrasound, 17.4% had gallstones at baseline. New cholelithiasis was reported in 12.0% of patients. Cholelithiasis may be related to dose or duration of exposure [  see  Cholelithiasis and Gallbladder Sludge (5.1)    ].



     Injection Site Reactions  



 In the pooled clinical studies, injection site pain (4.1%) and injection site mass (1.7%) were the most frequently reported local adverse drug reactions that occurred with the administration of Somatuline Depot. In a specific analysis 20 of 413 patients (4.8%) presented indurations at the injection site. Injection site adverse reactions were more commonly reported soon after the start of treatment and were less commonly reported as treatment continued. Such adverse reactions were usually mild or moderate but did lead to withdrawal from clinical studies in two subjects.



     Glucose Metabolism Adverse Reactions  



 In the clinical studies in acromegalic patients treated with Somatuline Depot, adverse reactions of dysglycemia (hypoglycemia, hyperglycemia, diabetes) were reported by 14% (47/332) of patients and were considered related to study drug in 7% (24/332) of patients [  see  Hyperglycemia and Hypoglycemia (5.2)    ].



     Cardiac Adverse Reactions  



 In the pooled clinical studies, sinus bradycardia (3.1%) was the most frequently observed heart rate and rhythm disorder. All other cardiac adverse drug reactions were observed in &lt; 1% of patients. The relationship of these events to Somatuline Depot could not be established because many of these patients had underlying cardiac disease [  see  Cardiovascular Abnormalities (5.4)    ].



 A comparative echocardiography study of lanreotide and another somatostatin analog demonstrated no difference in the development of new or worsening valvular regurgitation between the two treatments over one year. The occurrence of clinically significant mitral regurgitation (i.e., moderate or severe in intensity) or of clinically significant aortic regurgitation (i.e., at least mild in intensity) was low in both groups of patients throughout the study.



     Other Adverse Reactions  



 For the most commonly occurring adverse reactions in the pooled analysis, diarrhea, abdominal pain and cholelithiasis, there was no apparent trend for increasing incidence with age. GI disorders and renal and urinary disorders were more common in patients with documented hepatic impairment; however, the incidence of cholelithiasis was similar between groups.



 Laboratory investigations of acromegalic patients treated with Somatuline Depot in clinical studies show that the percentage of patients with putative antibodies at any time point after treatment is low (&lt;1% to 4% of patients in specific studies whose antibodies were tested). The antibodies did not appear to affect the efficacy or safety of Somatuline Depot.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  As adverse reactions experienced post approval use are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 The profile of reported adverse reactions for Somatuline Depot was consistent with that observed for treatment-related adverse reactions in the clinical studies. Those reported most frequently being gastrointestinal disorders (abdominal pain, diarrhea, and steatorrhea), hepatobiliary disorders (cholecystitis), and general disorders and administration site conditions (injection site reactions). Occasional cases of pancreatitis have also been observed.



 A small number of allergic reactions associated with lanreotide (including angioedema, anaphylaxis, and hypersensitivity) have been reported in the postmarketing environment.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Gallbladder: Gallstones may occur; consider periodic monitoring (  5.1  ) 
 *  Glucose Metabolism: Hypo- and/or hyperglycemia may occur. Glucose monitoring is recommended and anti-diabetic treatment adjusted accordingly (  5.2  ) 
 *  Cardiac Function: Decrease in heart rate may occur. Use with caution in at-risk patients (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Cholelithiasis and Gallbladder Sludge



  Lanreotide may reduce gallbladder motility and lead to gallstone formation therefore, patients may need to be monitored periodically [ see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ,  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)    ].



    5.2 Hyperglycemia and Hypoglycemia



  Pharmacological studies in animals and humans show that lanreotide, like somatostatin and other somatostatin analogs, inhibits the secretion of insulin and glucagon. Hence, patients treated with Somatuline Depot may experience hypoglycemia or hyperglycemia. Blood glucose levels should be monitored when lanreotide treatment is initiated, or when the dose is altered, and antidiabetic treatment should be adjusted accordingly [ see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ].



    5.3 Thyroid function Abnormalities



  Slight decreases in thyroid function have been seen during treatment with lanreotide in acromegalic patients, though clinical hypothyroidism is rare (&lt;1%). Thyroid function tests are recommended where clinically indicated.



    5.4 Cardiovascular Abnormalities



  The most common overall cardiac adverse reactions observed in three pooled Somatuline Depot Cardiac Studies in patients with acromegaly were sinus bradycardia (12/217, 5.5%), bradycardia (6/217, 2.8%) and hypertension (12/217, 5.5%) [ see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ].



 In patients without underlying cardiac disease, lanreotide may lead to a decrease in heart rate without necessarily reaching the threshold of bradycardia. In patients suffering from cardiac disorders prior to lanreotide treatment, sinus bradycardia may occur. Care should be taken when initiating treatment with lanreotide in patients with bradycardia.



    5.5 Drug Interactions



  The pharmacological gastrointestinal effects of Somatuline Depot may reduce the intestinal absorption of concomitant drugs.



 Lanreotide may decrease the relative bioavailability of cyclosporine. Concomitant administration of Somatuline Depot and cyclosporine may necessitate the adjustment of cyclosporine dose to maintain therapeutic levels [ see  Drug Interactions (7.2)    ].



    5.6 Monitoring: Laboratory Tests



  Serum GH and IGF-1 levels are useful markers of the disease and the effectiveness of treatment [ see  Dosage and Administration (2)    ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
