<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="somavert" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Clinically significant adverse reactions that appear in other section of the labeling include:



 *  Hypoglycemia associated with GH lowering in patients with Diabetes Mellitus [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Liver test elevations [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Cross-reactivity with GH assay [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Lipohypertrophy [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Systemic hypersensitivity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
    Elevations of serum concentrations of ALT and AST greater than ten times the ULN were reported in two patients (0.8%) exposed to SOMAVERT in pre-approval clinical studies. One patient was rechallenged with SOMAVERT, and the recurrence of elevated transaminase levels suggested a probable causal relationship between administration of the drug and the elevation in liver enzymes. A liver biopsy performed on the second patient was consistent with chronic hepatitis of unknown etiology. In both patients, the transaminase elevations normalized after discontinuation of the drug.
 

 Elevations in ALT and AST levels were not associated with increased levels of TBIL and ALP, with the exception of two patients with minimal associated increases in ALP levels (i.e., less than 3 times ULN). The transaminase elevations did not appear to be related to the dose of SOMAVERT administered, generally occurred within 4 to 12 weeks of initiation of therapy, and were not associated with any identifiable biochemical, phenotypic, or genetic predictors.



   EXCERPT:   Most common reported adverse reactions (&gt; 6%) are infection, pain, nausea, diarrhea, abnormal liver tests, flu syndrome, injection site reaction (  6  )  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer at (phone 1-800-438-1985 andwww.pfizer.com) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reactions rates observed in clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In a 12-week randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind, fixed-dose study of SOMAVERT in subjects with acromegaly, 32 subjects received placebo and 80 subjects received SOMAVERT once daily  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  . A total of 108 subjects (30 placebo, 78 Somavert) completed 12 weeks of study treatment. .



 Overall, eight patients with acromegaly (5.3%) withdrew from pre-marketing clinical studies because of adverse events, including two patients with marked transaminase elevations, one patient with lipohypertrophy at the injection sites, and one patient with substantial weight gain. Most adverse events did not appear to be dose-dependent. Table 3 shows the incidence of adverse events that were reported in at least two patients treated with SOMAVERT and at frequencies greater than placebo during the 12-week, placebo-controlled study.



 Table 3. Adverse Reactions in in a 12-week Placebo-Controlled Study in Patients with AcromegalyTable includes only those events that were reported in at least 2 patients and at a higher incidence in patients treated with SOMAVERT than in patients treated with placebo. 
                                                Placebon=32      SOMAVERT      
 10 mg/dayn=26                                 15 mg/dayn=26  20 mg/dayN=28    
  
 Infection                                        2 (6%)         6 (23%)            0                0          
 Pain                                             2 (6%)          2 (8%)          1 (4%)          4 (14%)       
 Nausea                                           1 (3%)            0             2 (8%)          4 (14%)       
 Diarrhea                                         1 (3%)          1 (4%)            0             4 (14%)       
 Abnormal liver function tests                    1 (3%)         3 (12%)          1 (4%)          1 (4%)        
 Flu syndrome                                        0            1 (4%)         3 (12%)          2 (7%)        
 Injection site reaction                             0            2 (8%)          1 (4%)          3 (11%)       
 Dizziness                                        2 (6%)          2 (8%)          1 (4%)          1 (4%)        
 Accidental injury                                1 (3%)          2 (8%)          1 (4%)             0          
 Back pain                                        1 (3%)          2 (8%)            0             1 (4%)        
 Sinusitis                                        1 (3%)          2 (8%)            0             1 (4%)        
 Chest pain                                          0            1 (4%)          2 (8%)             0          
 Peripheral edema                                    0            2 (8%)            0             1 (4%)        
 Hypertension                                        0              0             2 (8%)             0          
 Paresthesia                                      2 (6%)            0               0             2 (7%)        
             6.2 Immunogenicity
   In pre-marketing clinical studies, approximately 17% of the SOMAVERT-treated patients developed low titer, non-neutralizing anti-GH antibodies. Although the presence of these antibodies did not appear to impact the efficacy of SOMAVERT, the long-term clinical significance of these antibodies is not known. No assay for anti-pegvisomant antibodies is commercially available for patients receiving SOMAVERT.



 The data above reflect the percentage of patients whose test results were considered positive for antibodies to SOMAVERT. The detection of antibody formation is highly dependent on the sensitivity and specificity of the assay. Additionally, the observed incidence of antibody positivity in an assay may be influenced by several factors including sample handling, timing of sample collection, concomitant medications, and underlying disease. For these reasons, comparison of the incidence of antibodies to SOMAVERT with the incidence of antibodies to other products may be misleading.



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of SOMAVERT. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Systemic hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylactic reactions, laryngospasm, angioedema, generalized skin reactions (rash, erythema, pruritus, urticaria) have been reported in post-marketing use. Some patients required hospitalization. Symptoms did not re-occur in all patients after re-challenge  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  .



     Registry of Patients with Acromegaly Treated with SOMAVERT  



 ACROSTUDY is an international observational registry that captures long term safety data in patients with acromegaly treated with SOMAVERT, as used in clinical practice. Treatment dose and schedule were at the discretion of each treating physician. Although safety monitoring as per the recommended schedule was mandatory, not all assessments were performed at all time points for every patient. Because of this, comparison of rates of adverse events to those in the original clinical trial is not appropriate. In an interim report, there were 1288 patients enrolled (mean duration of treatment 3.7 years).



 At the start of SOMAVERT treatment 648 patients were on SOMAVERT monotherapy for acromegaly. Of the 454 patients who had a normal AST and ALT at baseline, 4 patients had elevated tests &gt;3 times ULN, two of whom had elevated tests &gt;5 times ULN.



 Lipohypertrophy was reported in 6 (0.5%) patients.



 MRIs were compared to any previous ones, and a change in tumor volume was reported as significant locally only if the diameter increased by more than 3 mm for microadenomas or volume increased by more than 20% for macroadenomas. All MRI changes considered significant at the local reading were reanalyzed centrally. Of the 747 patients who had a MRI reported at baseline and at least once during follow up in the study, 51 (7%) were reported to have an increase by local MRI. Of these, 16 patients (2%) had confirmation of this increase, 6 patients had a decrease, 12 had "no change"; there was 1 with insufficient data and 16 patients did not have a central MRI reading.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Liver Test Elevations: Should have more frequent liver tests and/or discontinue SOMAVERT (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypoglycemia associated with GH lowering in patients with Diabetes Mellitus



  GH opposes the effects of insulin on carbohydrate metabolism by decreasing insulin sensitivity; thus, glucose tolerance may improve in some patients treated with SOMAVERT. Patients should be carefully monitored and doses of anti-diabetic drugs reduced as necessary to avoid hypoglycemia in patients with diabetes mellitus.



    5.2 Liver Test Elevations



  Baseline serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), serum total bilirubin (TBIL), and alkaline phosphatase (ALP) levels should be obtained prior to initiating therapy with SOMAVERT. Table 1 lists recommendations regarding initiation of treatment with SOMAVERT, based on the results of these liver tests (LTs).



 Asymptomatic, transient elevations in transaminases up to 15 times ULN have been observed in &lt; 2% of subjects among two open-label trials (with a total of 147 patients). These reports were not associated with an increase in bilirubin. Transaminase elevations normalized with time, most often after suspending treatment (SOMAVERT should be used in accordance with the information presented in Table 2 with respect to liver test abnormalities while on Somavert treatment).



 Table 1. Recommendations of Initiating SOMAVERT Based on Baseline LTs and Periodic Monitoring of LTs During SOMAVERT Treatment 
 Baseline LT Levels                   Recommendations                                                     
  
 Normal                               May treat with SOMAVERT.                                          
 Monitor LTs at monthly intervals during the first 6 months of treatment, quarterly for the next 6 months and then bi-annually for the next year. 
                                                                                                                                        
 Elevated, but less than or equal to 3 times ULN  May treat with SOMAVERT; however, monitor LTs monthly for at least one year after initiation of therapy and then bi-annually for the next year.   
 Greater than 3 times ULN             Do not treat with SOMAVERT until a comprehensive workup establishes the cause of the patient's liver dysfunction. 
 Determine if cholelithiasis or choledocholithiasis is present, particularly in patients with a history of prior therapy with somatostatin analogs. 
 Based on the workup, consider initiation of therapy with SOMAVERT. 
 If the decision is to treat, LTs and clinical symptoms should be monitored very closely. 
                                                                                                                                        
        If a patient develops LT elevations, or any other signs or symptoms of liver dysfunction while receiving SOMAVERT, the following patient management is recommended (Table 2).
 

 Table 2. Clinical Recommendations Based on Liver Test Results While on SOMAVERT 
 LT Levels and Clinical Signs/Symptoms          Recommendations                                           
  
 Greater than or equal to 3 but less than 5 times ULN (without signs/symptoms of hepatitis or other liver injury, or increase in serum TBIL)  May continue therapy with SOMAVERT. However, monitor LTs weekly to determine if further increases occur (see below). 
 Perform a comprehensive hepatic workup to discern if an alternative cause of liver dysfunction is present. 
                                                                                                                    
 At least 5 times ULN, or transaminase elevations at least 3 times ULN associated with any increase in serum TBIL (with or without signs/symptoms of hepatitis or other liver injury)  Discontinue SOMAVERT immediately.                       
 Perform a comprehensive hepatic workup, including serial LTs, to determine if and when serum levels return to normal. 
 If LTs normalize (regardless of whether an alternative cause of the liver dysfunction is discovered), consider cautious re-initiation of therapy with SOMAVERT, with frequent LT monitoring. 
                                                                                                                    
 Signs or symptoms suggestive of hepatitis or other liver injury (e.g., jaundice, bilirubinuria, fatigue, nausea, vomiting, right upper quadrant pain, ascites, unexplained edema, easy bruisability)  Immediately perform a comprehensive hepatic workup.     
 If liver injury is confirmed, the drug should be discontinued. 
                                                                                                                    
           5.3 Cross-Reactivity with GH Assays
 

  SOMAVERT has significant structural similarity to growth hormone (GH) which causes it to cross-react in commercially available GH assays. Since serum concentrations of therapeutically effective doses of SOMAVERT are generally 100 to 1000 times higher than the actual serum GH concentrations seen in patients with acromegaly, measurements of serum GH concentrations will appear falsely elevated.



    5.4 Lipohypertrophy



  There have been cases of lipohypertrophy in patients treated with SOMAVERT. In a double-blind, 12-week, placebo-controlled study, there was one case (1.3%) of injection site lipohypertrophy reported in a subject receiving 10 mg/day. The subject recovered while on treatment. Among two open-label trials (with a total of 147 patients), there were two subjects, both receiving 10 mg/day, who developed lipohypertrophy. One case recovered while on treatment, and one case resulted in a discontinuation of treatment. Injection sites should be rotated daily to help prevent lipohypertrophy (different area than the last injection).



    5.5 Systemic Hypersensitivity



  In subjects with systemic hypersensitivity reactions, caution and close monitoring should be exercised when re-initiating Somavert therapy [see  Adverse Reactions (6.3)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
