<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="soriatane" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Hypervitaminosis A produces a wide spectrum of signs and symptoms primarily of the mucocutaneous, musculoskeletal, hepatic, neuropsychiatric, and central nervous systems. Many of the clinical adverse reactions reported to date with administration of SORIATANE resemble those of the hypervitaminosis A syndrome.



   Adverse Events/Postmarketing Reports:

  In  addition  to the events listed in the tables for the clinical trials, the following adverse events have been identified during postapproval use of SORIATANE. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



     Cardiovascular:  

  Acute myocardial infarction, thromboembolism (see WARNINGS), stroke



     Immune System Disorders:  

  Hypersensitivity, including angioedema and urticaria (see CONTRAINDICATIONS).



     Nervous System:  

  Myopathy with peripheral neuropathy has been reported during therapy with SORIATANE. Both conditions improved with discontinuation of the drug.



     Psychiatric:  

  Aggressive feelings and/or suicidal thoughts have been reported. These events, including self-injurious behavior, have been reported in patients taking other systemically administered retinoids, as well as in patients taking SORIATANE. Since other factors may have contributed to these events, it is not known if they are related to SORIATANE (see PRECAUTIONS).



     Reproductive:  

  Vulvo-vaginitis due to  Candida albicans.  



     Skin and Appendages:  

  Thinning of the skin, skin fragility, and scaling may occur all over the body, particularly on the palms and soles; nail fragility is frequently observed. Madarosis and exfoliative dermatitis/erythroderma have been reported (see WARNINGS).



     Vascular Disorders:  

  Capillary leak syndrome (see WARNINGS).



   Clinical Trials:

  During clinical trials with SORIATANE, 513 of 525 (98%) subjects reported a total of 3,545 adverse events. One-hundred sixteen subjects (22%) left trials prematurely, primarily because of adverse experiences involving the mucous membranes and skin. Three subjects died. Two of the deaths were not drug-related (pancreatic adenocarcinoma and lung cancer); the other subject died of an acute myocardial infarction, considered remotely related to drug therapy.  In clinical trials, SORIATANE was associated with elevations in liver function test results or triglyceride levels and hepatitis.  



 The tables below list by body system and frequency the adverse events reported during clinical trials of 525 subjects with psoriasis.



   Table 3. Adverse Events Frequently Reported during Clinical Trials  



 Percent of Subjects Reporting (N = 525) 
  Body System               &gt;75%         50% to 75%       25% to 50%       10% to 25%                           
  CNS                                                                      Rigors                               
  Eye Disorders                                                            Xerophthalmia                        
  Mucous Membranes          Cheilitis                     Rhinitis         Dry mouth  Epistaxis                 
  Musculoskeletal                                                          Arthralgia  Spinal hyperostosis  (progression of existing lesions)    
  Skin and Appendages                    Alopecia  Skin peeling    Dry skin  Nail disorder  Pruritus    Erythematous rash  Hyperesthesia  Paresthesia  Paronychia  Skin atrophy  Sticky skin    
             Table 4. Adverse Events Less Frequently Reported during Clinical Trials (Some of Which May Bear No Relationship to Therapy)  
 

 Percent of Subjects Reporting (N = 525) 
   Body System             1% to 10%            &lt;1%              
  
  Body as a Whole         Anorexia  Edema  Fatigue  Hot flashes  Increased  appetite                      Alcohol  intolerance  Dizziness  Fever  Influenza-like  symptoms    Malaise  Moniliasis  Muscle weakness  Weight increase    
  Cardiovascular          Flushing                               Chest pain  Cyanosis  Increased  bleeding time    Intermittent  claudication  Peripheral  ischemia    
  CNS (also see Psychiatric)    Headache  Pain                         Abnormal gait  Migraine  Neuritis    Pseudotumor  cerebri  (intracranial  hypertension)    
  Eye Disorders           Abnormal/  blurred vision  Blepharitis  Conjunctivitis/  irritation  Corneal epithelial  abnormality    Decreased night  vision/night  blindness  Eye abnormality  Eye pain  Photophobia    Abnormal  lacrimation  Chalazion  Conjunctival  hemorrhage  Corneal ulceration  Diplopia  Ectropion    Itchy eyes and lids  Papilledema  Recurrent sties  Subepithelial  corneal lesions    
  Gastrointestinal        Abdominal pain  Diarrhea  Nausea  Tongue disorder                      ConstipationDyspepsiaEsophagitisGastritisGastroenteritis    GlossitisHemorrhoidsMelenaTenesmusTongue ulceration    
  Liver and Biliary                                              Hepatic function  abnormal  HepatitisJaundice                         
  Mucous Membranes        Gingival bleeding  Gingivitis  Increased saliva    StomatitisThirstUlcerative  stomatitis    Altered saliva Anal disorderGum hyperplasia    HemorrhagePharyngitis    
  Musculoskeletal         Arthritis  Arthrosis  Back pain  Hypertonia  Myalgia    OsteodyniaPeripheral joint  hyperostosis  (progression of  existing lesions)    Bone disorderOlecranon bursitisSpinal hyperostosis  (new lesions)Tendonitis                         
  Psychiatric             Depression Insomnia  Somnolence                      AnxietyDysphonia  Libido decreased Nervousness                         
  Reproductive                                                   Atrophic vaginitis Leukorrhea                         
  Respiratory             Sinusitis                              Coughing  Increased sputum  Laryngitis                         
  Skin and Appendages     Abnormal skin  odor  Abnormal hair  texture  Bullous eruption  Cold/clammy  skin  Dermatitis  Increased  sweating  Infection    Psoriasiform rash  PurpuraPyogenic  granulomaRashSeborrheaSkin fissuresSkin ulcerationSunburn    Acne Breast pain Cyst Eczema Fungal infectionFurunculosisHair discolorationHerpes simplexHyperkeratosisHypertrichosisHypoesthesiaImpaired healingOtitis media    Otitis externaPhotosensitivity  reactionPsoriasis aggravated  SclerodermaSkin noduleSkin hypertrophySkin disorderSkin irritationSweat gland  disorderUrticariaVerrucae    
  Special Senses/ Other    Earache  Taste perversion  Tinnitus                      CeruminosisDeafnessTaste loss                         
  Urinary                                                        Abnormal urineDysuriaPenis disorder                         
             Laboratory:
   Therapy with SORIATANE induces changes in liver function tests in a significant number of patients. Elevations of AST (SGOT), ALT (SGPT) or LDH were experienced by approximately 1 in 3 subjects treated with SORIATANE. In most subjects, elevations were slight to moderate and returned to normal either during continuation of therapy or after cessation of treatment. In subjects receiving SORIATANE during clinical trials, 66% and 33% experienced elevation in triglycerides and cholesterol, respectively. Decreased high density lipoproteins (HDL) occurred in 40% (see WARNINGS). Transient, usually reversible elevations of alkaline phosphatase have been observed.



 *     Table 5 lists the laboratory abnormalities reported during clinical trials. 
      Table 5. Abnormal Laboratory Test Results Reported during Clinical Trials  
 

 Percent of Subjects Reporting 
  Body System          50% to 75%           25% to 50%           10% to 25%             1% to 10%              
  Electrolytes                                                   Increased: -Phosphorus-Potassium-Sodium    Decreased:-Phosphorus-Potassium-Sodium    
                                                                 Increased and  decreased: -Magnesium    Increased and  decreased: -Calcium-Chloride    
  Hematologic                               Increased:-Reticulocytes    Decreased: -Hematocrit-Hemoglobin -WBCIncreased:-Haptoglobin-Neutrophils-WBC    Increased: -Bands-Basophils -Eosinophils-Hematocrit-Hemoglobin-Lymphocytes-Monocytes    
                                                                                        Decreased:-Haptoglobin-Lymphocytes-Neutrophils-ReticulocytesIncreased or  decreased: -Platelets-RBC    
  Hepatic                                   Increased: -Cholesterol-LDH-SGOT-SGPTDecreased: -HDL  cholesterol    Increased:-Alkaline  phosphatase-Direct bilirubin-GGTP    Increased:-Globulin-Total bilirubin-Total proteinIncreased and  decreased:-Serum albumin    
  Miscellaneous        Increased:-Triglycerides    Increased:-CPK-Fasting blood  sugar    Decreased:-Fasting blood  sugar-High occult  blood    Increased and  decreased:-Iron    
  Renal                                                          Increased:-Uric acid    Increased:-BUN-Creatinine    
  Urinary                                   WBC in urine         AcetonuriaHematuriaRBC in urine    Glycosuria Proteinuria    
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

  SORIATANE  (r)  



 (acitretin)



 Capsules



   

    CONTRAINDICATIONS AND WARNINGS: Pregnancy  



   SORIATANE must not be used by females who are pregnant, or who intend to become pregnant during therapy or at any time for at least 3 years following discontinuation of therapy. SORIATANE also must not be used by females who may not use reliable contraception while undergoing treatment and for at least 3 years following discontinuation of treatment. Acitretin is a metabolite of etretinate (TEGISON  (r)  ), and major human fetal abnormalities have been reported with the administration of acitretin and etretinate. Potentially, any fetus exposed can be affected.  



   Clinical evidence has shown that concurrent ingestion of acitretin and ethanol has been associated with the formation of etretinate, which has a significantly longer elimination half-life than acitretin. Because the longer elimination half-life of etretinate would increase the duration of teratogenic potential for female patients, ethanol must not be ingested by female patients of childbearing potential either during treatment with SORIATANE or for 2 months after cessation of therapy. This allows for elimination of acitretin, thus removing the substrate for transesterification to etretinate. The mechanism of the metabolic process for conversion of acitretin to etretinate has not been fully defined. It is not known whether substances other than ethanol are associated with transesterification.  



   Acitretin has been shown to be embryotoxic and/or teratogenic in rabbits, mice, and rats at oral doses of 0.6, 3, and 15 mg per kg, respectively. These doses are approximately 0.2, 0.3, and 3 times the maximum recommended therapeutic dose, respectively, based on a mg per m  2   comparison.  



   Major human fetal abnormalities associated with acitretin and/or etretinate administration have been reported including meningomyelocele; meningoencephalocele; multiple synostoses; facial dysmorphia; syndactyly; absence of terminal phalanges; malformations of hip, ankle, and forearm; low-set ears; high palate; decreased cranial volume; cardiovascular malformation; and alterations of the skull and cervical vertebrae.  



   SORIATANE should be prescribed only by those who have special competence in the diagnosis and treatment of severe psoriasis, are experienced in the use of systemic retinoids, and understand the risk of teratogenicity.  



   Because of the teratogenicity of SORIATANE, a program called the   Do Your P.A.R.T.   program, Pregnancy Prevention Actively Required During and After Treatment, has been developed to educate women of childbearing potential and their healthcare providers about the serious risks associated with acitretin and to help prevent pregnancies from occurring with the use of this drug and for 3 years after its discontinuation. The   Do Your P.A.R.T.   program requirements are described below and program materials are available at www.soriatane.com/doyour-part-Program.html or may be requested by calling 1-888-784-3335 (1-888-STIEFEL). (see also PRECAUTIONS section).  



 *   Important Information for Women of Childbearing Potential: 
 *   SORIATANE should be considered only for women with severe psoriasis unresponsive to other therapies or whose clinical condition contraindicates the use of other treatments. 
      Females of reproductive potential must not be given a prescription for SORIATANE until pregnancy is excluded. SORIATANE is contraindicated in females of reproductive potential   unless the patient meets ALL of the following conditions:    
 

 *  Must have had 2 negative urine or serum pregnancy tests with a sensitivity of at least 25 mIU per mL before receiving the initial prescription for SORIATANE. The first test (a screening test) is obtained by the prescriber when the decision is made to pursue therapy with SORIATANE. The second pregnancy test (a confirmation test) should be done during the first 5 days of the menstrual period immediately preceding the beginning of therapy with SORIATANE. For patients with amenorrhea, the second test should be done at least 11 days after the last act of unprotected sexual intercourse (without using 2 effective forms of contraception [birth control] simultaneously). If the second pregnancy test is negative, initiation of treatment with SORIATANE should begin with 7 days of the specimen collection. SORIATANE should be limited to a monthly supply. 
 *  Must have a pregnancy test with a sensitivity of at least 25mIU per mL repeated every month during treatment with SORIATANE. The patient must have a negative result from a urine or serum pregnancy test before receiving a prescription for SORIATANE. To encourage compliance with this recommendation, a monthly supply of the drugshould be prescribed. For at least 3 years after discontinuing therapy with SORIATANE, a pregnancy test must be repeated every 3 months. 
 *  Must have selected and have committed to use 2 effective forms of contraception (birth control) simultaneously, at least 1 of which must be a primary form, unless absolute abstinence is the chosen method, or the patient has undergone a hysterectomy or is clearly postmenopausal. 
 *  Patients must use 2 effective forms of contraception (birth control) simultaneously for at least 1 month prior to initiation of therapy with SORIATANE, during therapy with SORIATANE, and for at least 3 years after discontinuing therapy with SORIATANE. A Contraception Counseling Referral Form is available so that patients can receive an initial free contraception counseling session and pregnancy testing. Counseling about contraception and behaviors associated with an increased risk of pregnancy must be repeated on a monthly basis by the prescriber during therapy with SORIATANE and every 3 months for at least 3 years following discontinuation of SORIATANE. 
      Effective forms of contraception include both primary and secondary forms of contraception. Primary forms of contraception include: tubal ligation, partner's vasectomy, intrauterine devices, birth control pills, and injectable/implantable/insertable/topical hormonal birth control products. Secondary forms of contraception include condoms (with or without spermicide), diaphragms and cervical caps (which must be used with a spermicide, and vaginal sponges (contains spermicide).     Any birth control method can fail. Therefore, it is critically important that women of childbearing potential use 2 effective forms of contraception (birth control) simultaneously. It has not been established if there is a pharmacokinetic interaction between acitretin and combined oral contraceptives. However, it has been established that acitretin interferes with the contraceptive effect of microdosed progestin preparations.  1   Microdosed "minipill" progestin preparations are not recommended for use with SORIATANE.   It is not known whether other progestin-only contraceptives, such as implants and injectables, are adequate methods of contraception during acitretin therapy.   Prescribers are advised to consult the package insert of any medication administered concomitantly with hormonal contraceptives, since some medications may decrease the effectiveness of these birth control products. Patients should be prospectively cautioned not to self-medicate with the herbal supplement St. John's wort because a possible interaction has been suggested with hormonal contraceptives based on reports of breakthrough bleeding on oral contraceptives shortly after starting St. John's wort. Pregnancies have been reported by users of combined hormonal contraceptives who also used some form of St. John's wort (see PRECAUTIONS).  
 

 *  Must have signed a Patient Agreement/Informed Consent for Female Patients that contains warnings about the risk of potential birth defects if the fetus is exposed to SORIATANE, about contraceptive failure, about the fact that they must not ingest beverages or products containing ethanol while taking SORIATANE and for 2 months after treatment with SORIATANE has been discontinued, and about preventing pregnancy while taking SORIATANE and for at least 3 years after discontinuing SORIATANE. If pregnancy does occur during therapy with SORIATANE or at any time for at least 3 years following discontinuation of SORIATANE, the prescriber and patient should discuss the possible effects on the pregnancy. The available information is as follows:Acitretin, the active metabolite of etretinate, is teratogenic and is contraindicated during pregnancy. The risk of severe fetal malformations is well established when systemic retinoids are taken during pregnancy. Pregnancy must also be prevented after stopping acitretin therapy, while the drug is being eliminated to below a threshold blood concentration that would be associated with an increased incidence of birth defects. Because this threshold has not been established for acitretin in humans and because elimination rates vary among patients, the duration of posttherapy contraception to achieve adequate elimination cannot be calculated precisely. It is strongly recommended that contraception be continued for at least 3 years after stopping treatment with acitretin, based on the following considerations:In the absence of transesterification to form etretinate, greater than 98% of the acitretin would be eliminated within 2 months, assuming a mean elimination half-life of 49 hours.In cases where etretinate is formed, as has been demonstrated with concomitant administration of acitretin and ethanol,greater than 98% of the etretinate formed would be eliminated in 2 years, assuming a mean elimination half-life of 120 days.greater than 98% of the etretinate formed would be eliminated in 3 years, based on the longest demonstrated elimination half-life of 168 days.However, etretinate was found in plasma and subcutaneous fat in one patient reported to have had sporadic alcohol intake, 52 months after she stopped acitretin therapy.2 
 *  Severe birth defects have been reported where conception occurred during the time interval when the patient was being treated with acitretin and/or etretinate. In addition, severe birth defects have also been reported when conception occurred after the mother completed therapy. These cases have been reported both prospectively (before the outcome was known) and retrospectively (after the outcome was known). The events below are listed without distinction as to whether the reported birth defects are consistent with retinoid-induced embryopathy or not.There have been 318 prospectively reported cases involving pregnancies and the use of etretinate, acitretin or both. In 238 of these cases, the conception occurred after the last dose of etretinate (103 cases), acitretin (126), or both (9). Fetal outcome remained unknown in approximately one-half of these cases, of which 62 were terminated and 14 were spontaneous abortions. Fetal outcome is known for the other 118 cases and 15 of the outcomes were abnormal (including cases of absent hand/wrist, clubfoot, GI malformation, hypocalcemia, hypotonia, limb malformation, neonatal apnea/anemia, neonatal ichthyosis, placental disorder/death, undescended testicle, and 5 cases of premature birth). In the 126 prospectively reported cases where conception occurred after the last dose of acitretin only, 43 cases involved conception at least 1 year but less than 2 years after the last dose. There were 3 reports of abnormal outcomes out of these 43 cases (involving limb malformation, GI tract malformations, and premature birth). There were only 4 cases where conception occurred at least 2 years after the last dose but there were no reports of birth defects in these cases.There is also a total of 35 retrospectively reported cases where conception occurred at least 1 year after the last dose of etretinate, acitretin or both. From these cases there are 3 reports of birth defects when the conception occurred at least 1 year but less than 2 years after the last dose of acitretin (including heart malformations, Turner's Syndrome, and unspecified congenital malformations) and 4 reports of birth defects when conception occurred 2 or more years after the last dose of acitretin (including foot malformation, cardiac malformations [2 cases], and unspecified neonatal and infancy disorder). There were 3 additional abnormal outcomes in cases where conception occurred 2 or more years after the last dose of etretinate (including chromosome disorder, forearm aplasia, and stillbirth).Females who have taken TEGISON (etretinate) must continue to follow the contraceptive recommendations for TEGISON. TEGISON is no longer marketed in the US; for information, call Stiefel at 1-888-784-3335 (1-888-STIEFEL).Patients should not donate blood during and for at least 3 years following the completion of therapy with SORIATANE because women of childbearing potential must not receive blood from patients being treated with SORIATANE. 
      Important Information for Males Taking SORIATANE:  
 

 *  Patients should not donate blood during and for at least 3 years following therapy with SORIATANE because women of childbearing potential must not receive blood from patients being treated with SORIATANE. 
 *  Samples of seminal fluid from 3 male patients treated with acitretin and 6 male patients treated with etretinate have been assayed for the presence of acitretin. The maximum concentration of acitretin observed in the seminal fluid of these men was 12.5 ng per mL. Assuming an ejaculate volume of 10 mL, the amount of drug transferred in semen would be 125 ng, which is 1/200,000 of a single 25 mg capsule. Thus, although it appears that residual acitretin in seminal fluid poses little, if any, risk to a fetus while a male patient is taking the drug or after it is discontinued, the no-effect limit for teratogenicity is unknown and there is no registry for birth defects associated with acitretin. The available data are as follows: 
      There have been 25 cases of reported conception when the male partner was taking acitretin. The pregnancy outcome is known in 13 of these 25 cases. Of these, 9 reports were retrospective and 4 were prospective (meaning the pregnancy was reported prior to knowledge of the outcome)  3  .  
 

     For All Patients:   A SORIATANE MEDICATION GUIDE MUST BE GIVEN TO THE PATIENT EACH TIME SORIATANE IS DISPENSED, AS REQUIRED BY LAW.  



  boxed warning table.jpg  Causes Birth Defects Image 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
