<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="sorilux" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions reported in &gt;=1% of subjects treated with SORILUX Foam and at a higher incidence than subjects treated with vehicle were application site erythema and application site pain. (6.1)



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Stiefel Laboratories, Inc. at 1-888-784-3335 (1-888-STIEFEL) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 SORILUX Foam was studied in four vehicle-controlled trials. A total of 1094 subjects with plaque psoriasis, including 654 exposed to SORILUX Foam, were treated twice daily for 8 weeks.



 Adverse reactions reported in &gt;=1% of subjects treated with SORILUX Foam and at a higher incidence than subjects treated with vehicle were application site erythema (2%) and application site pain (3%). The incidence of these adverse reactions was similar between the body and scalp.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Contents are flammable. Instruct the patient to avoid fire, flame, and smoking during and immediately following application. (5.1) 
 *    If elevation of serum calcium occurs, instruct patients to discontinue treatment until normal calcium levels are restored. (5.2) 
 *    Avoid excessive exposure of the treated areas to natural or artificial sunlight. (5.3) 
    
 

   5.1 Flammability



  The propellant in SORILUX Foam is flammable. Instruct the patient to avoid fire, flame, and smoking during and immediately following application.



    5.2 Effects on Calcium Metabolism



  Transient, rapidly reversible elevation of serum calcium has occurred with use of calcipotriene. If elevation in serum calcium outside the normal range should occur, discontinue treatment until normal calcium levels are restored.



    5.3 Risk of Ultraviolet Light Exposure



  Instruct the patient to avoid excessive exposure of the treated areas to either natural or artificial sunlight, including tanning booths and sun lamps. Physicians may wish to limit or avoid use of phototherapy in patients who use SORILUX Foam. [See Nonclinical Toxicology (13.1).]  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
