<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="spiriva0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6  ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are described, or described in greater detail, in other sections:



 *  Immediate hypersensitivity reactions [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  ) ] 
 *  Paradoxical bronchospasm [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  ) ] 
 *  Worsening of narrow-angle glaucoma [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  ) ] 
 *  Worsening of urinary retention [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  ) ] 
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;3% incidence in the placebo-controlled trials with treatment durations of between 4 and 48 weeks) were pharyngitis, cough, dry mouth, and sinusitis. (  6.1  ).
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Boehringer Ingelheim Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at (800) 542-6257 or (800) 459-9906 TTY, or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, the incidence of adverse reactions observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to the incidences in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the incidences observed in practice.



 The SPIRIVA RESPIMAT clinical development program included ten placebo controlled clinical trials in COPD. Two trials were four-week cross-over trials and eight were parallel group trials. The parallel groups trials included a three week dose-ranging trial, two 12-week trials, three 48-week trials, and two trials of 4-week and 24-week duration conducted for a different program that contained tiotropium bromide 5 mcg treatment arms. The primary safety database consists of pooled data from the 7 randomized, parallel-group, double-blind, placebo-controlled studies of 4-48 weeks in treatment duration: These trials included 6565 adult COPD patients (75% males and 25% females) 40 years of age and older. Of these patients, 3282 patients were treated with SPIRIVA RESPIMAT and 3283 received placebo. The SPIRIVA RESPIMAT group was composed mostly of Caucasians (78%) with a mean age of 65 years and a mean baseline percent predicted post-bronchodilator FEV1of 46%.



 In these 7 clinical trials, 68.3% of patients exposed to SPIRIVA RESPIMAT reported an adverse event compared to 68.7% of patients in the placebo group. There were 68 deaths in the SPIRIVA RESPIMAT treatment group (2.1%) and 52 deaths (1.6%) in patients who received placebo [  see Clinical Studies (  14  ) Long-term active controlled mortality trial: Survival  ]. The percentage of SPIRIVA RESPIMAT patients who discontinued due to an adverse event were 7.3% compared to 10% with placebo patients. The percentage of SPIRIVA RESPIMAT patients who experienced a serious adverse event were 15.0% compared to 15.1% with placebo patients. In both groups, the adverse event most commonly leading to discontinuation was COPD exacerbation (SPIRIVA RESPIMAT 2.0%, placebo 4.0%) which was also the most frequent serious adverse event. The most commonly reported adverse reactions were pharyngitis, cough, dry mouth, and sinusitis (Table 1). Other adverse reactions reported in individual patients and consistent with possible anticholinergic effects included constipation, dysuria, and urinary retention.



 Table 1 shows all adverse reactions that occurred with an incidence of &gt;3% in the SPIRIVA RESPIMAT treatment group, and a higher incidence rate on SPIRIVA RESPIMAT than on placebo.



   Table 1 Number (percentage) of COPD patients exposed to SPIRIVA RESPIMAT with adverse reactions &gt;3% (and higher than placebo): Pooled data from 7 clinical trials with treatment periods ranging between 4 and 48 weeks in COPD patients  




 *Adverse reactions include a grouping of similar terms   
  
   Body System (Reaction)*               SPIRIVA RESPIMAT[n=3282]                Placebo[n=3283]            
                                                                                                            
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                               
      Dry mouth                                  134 (4.1)                          52 (1.6)                
   Infections and Infestations                                                                              
      Pharyngitis                               378 (11.5)                         333 (10.1)               
   Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal                                                                           
      Cough                                      190 (5.8)                          182 (5.5)               
      Sinusitis                                  103 (3.1)                          88 (2.7)                
      Other reactions that occurred in the SPIRIVA RESPIMAT group at an incidence of 1% to 3%, and at a higher incidence rate on SPIRIVA RESPIMAT than on placebo included:  Cardiac disorders:  palpitations;  Gastrointestinal disorders:  constipation; gastroesophageal reflux disease; oropharyngeal candidiasis;  Nervous system disorders:  dizziness;  Respiratory system disorders (Upper):  dysphonia;  Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  pruritus, rash;  Renal and urinary disorders:  urinary tract infection.
 

   Less Common Adverse Reactions  Among the adverse reactions observed in the clinical trials with an incidence of &lt;1% and at a higher incidence rate on SPIRIVA RESPIMAT than on placebo were: dysphagia, gingivitis, intestinal obstruction including ileus paralytic, joint swelling, dysuria, urinary retention, epistaxis, laryngitis, angioedema, dry skin, skin infection, and skin ulcer.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  In addition to the adverse reactions observed during the SPIRIVA RESPIMAT clinical trials, the following adverse reactions have been identified during the worldwide use of SPIRIVA RESPIMAT and another tiotropium formulation, SPIRIVA  (r)  HandiHaler  (r)  (tiotropium bromide inhalation powder): glaucoma, intraocular pressure increased, vision blurred, atrial fibrillation, tachycardia, supraventricular tachycardia, bronchospasm, glossitis, stomatitis, dehydration, insomnia, hypersensitivity (including immediate reactions), and urticaria.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Not for acute use, i.e., not a rescue medication (  5.1  ) 
 *  Immediate hypersensitivity reactions: Discontinue SPIRIVA RESPIMAT at once and consider alternatives if immediate hypersensitivity reactions, including angioedema, bronchospasm, or anaphylaxis, occur. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Paradoxical bronchospasm: Discontinue SPIRIVA RESPIMAT and consider other treatments if paradoxical bronchospasm occurs. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Worsening of narrow-angle glaucoma may occur. Use with caution in patients with narrow-angle glaucoma and instruct patients to consult a physician immediately if this occurs. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Worsening of urinary retention may occur. Use with caution in patients with prostatic hyperplasia or bladder-neck obstruction and instruct patient to consult a physician immediately if this occurs. (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Not For Acute Use



  SPIRIVA RESPIMAT is intended as a once-daily maintenance treatment for COPD and should not be used for the relief of acute symptoms, i.e., as rescue therapy for the treatment of acute episodes of bronchospasm.



    5.2 Immediate Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Immediate hypersensitivity reactions, including urticaria, angioedema (including swelling of the lips, tongue or throat), rash, bronchospasm, anaphylaxis, or itching may occur after administration of SPIRIVA RESPIMAT. If such a reaction occurs, therapy with SPIRIVA RESPIMAT should be stopped at once and alternative treatments should be considered. Given the similar structural formula of atropine to tiotropium, patients with a history of hypersensitivity reactions to atropine or its derivatives should be closely monitored for similar hypersensitivity reactions to SPIRIVA RESPIMAT.



    5.3 Paradoxical Bronchospasm



  Inhaled medicines, including SPIRIVA RESPIMAT, may cause paradoxical bronchospasm. If this occurs, it should be treated immediately with an inhaled short-acting beta2-agonist such as albuterol. Treatment with SPIRIVA RESPIMAT should be stopped and other treatments considered.



    5.4 Worsening of Narrow-Angle Glaucoma



  SPIRIVA RESPIMAT should be used with caution in patients with narrow-angle glaucoma. Prescribers and patients should be alert for signs and symptoms of acute narrow-angle glaucoma (e.g., eye pain or discomfort, blurred vision, visual halos or colored images in association with red eyes from conjunctival congestion and corneal edema). Instruct patients to consult a physician immediately should any of these signs or symptoms develop.



    5.5 Worsening of Urinary Retention



  SPIRIVA RESPIMAT should be used with caution in patients with urinary retention. Prescribers and patients should be alert for signs and symptoms of urinary retention (e.g., difficulty passing urine, painful urination), especially in patients with prostatic hyperplasia or bladder neck obstruction. Instruct patients to consult a physician immediately should any of these signs or symptoms develop.



    5.6 Renal Impairment



  As a predominantly renally excreted drug, patients with moderate to severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance of &lt;60 mL/min) treated with SPIRIVA RESPIMAT should be monitored closely for anticholinergic side effects [ see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )  ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
