<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="sporanox0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  SPORANOX  (r)  has been associated with rare cases of serious hepatotoxicity, including liver failure and death. Some of these cases had neither pre-existing liver disease nor a serious underlying medical condition. If clinical signs or symptoms develop that are consistent with liver disease, treatment should be discontinued and liver function testing performed. The risks and benefits of SPORANOX  (r)  use should be reassessed. (See  WARNINGS: Hepatic Effects  and  PRECAUTIONS: Hepatotoxicity  and  Information for Patients  .)



   Adverse Events in the Treatment of Systemic Fungal Infections

  Adverse event data were derived from 602 patients treated for systemic fungal disease in U.S. clinical trials who were immunocompromised or receiving multiple concomitant medications. Treatment was discontinued in 10.5% of patients due to adverse events. The median duration before discontinuation of therapy was 81 days (range: 2 to 776 days). The table lists adverse events reported by at least 1% of patients.



 Clinical Trials of Systemic Fungal Infections: Adverse Events Occurring with an Incidence of Greater than or Equal to 1% 
 Body System/Adverse Event                                                   Incidence (%) (N=602)        
  
   Gastrointestinal                                                                                       
 Nausea                                                                                11                 
 Vomiting                                                                              5                  
 Diarrhea                                                                              3                  
 Abdominal Pain                                                                        2                  
 Anorexia                                                                              1                  
   Body as a Whole                                                                                        
 Edema                                                                                 4                  
 Fatigue                                                                               3                  
 Fever                                                                                 3                  
 Malaise                                                                               1                  
   Skin and Appendages                                                                                    
 Rash                                                                                  9                  
 Pruritus                                                                              3                  
   Central/Peripheral Nervous System                                                                      
 Headache                                                                              4                  
 Dizziness                                                                             2                  
   Psychiatric                                                                                            
 Libido Decreased                                                                      1                  
 Somnolence                                                                            1                  
   Cardiovascular                                                                                         
 Hypertension                                                                          3                  
   Metabolic/Nutritional                                                                                  
 Hypokalemia                                                                           2                  
   Urinary System                                                                                         
 Albuminuria                                                                           1                  
   Liver and Biliary System                                                                               
 Hepatic Function Abnormal                                                             3                  
   Reproductive System, Male                                                                              
 Impotence                                                                             1                  
        Adverse events infrequently reported in all studies included constipation, gastritis, depression, insomnia, tinnitus, menstrual disorder, adrenal insufficiency, gynecomastia, and male breast pain.
 

   Adverse Events Reported in Toenail Onychomycosis Clinical Trials

  Patients in these trials were on a continuous dosing regimen of 200 mg once daily for 12 consecutive weeks.



 The following adverse events led to temporary or permanent discontinuation of therapy.



 Clinical Trials of Onychomycosis of the Toenail: Adverse Events Leading to Temporary or Permanent Discontinuation of Therapy 
 Adverse Event                                               Incidence (%)Itraconazole (N=112)            
  
 Elevated Liver Enzymes (greater than twice the upper limit of normal)                          4                            
 Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                  4                            
 Rash                                                                        3                            
 Hypertension                                                                2                            
 Orthostatic Hypotension                                                     1                            
 Headache                                                                    1                            
 Malaise                                                                     1                            
 Myalgia                                                                     1                            
 Vasculitis                                                                  1                            
 Vertigo                                                                     1                            
        The following adverse events occurred with an incidence of greater than or equal to 1% (N=112): headache: 10%; rhinitis: 9%; upper respiratory tract infection: 8%; sinusitis, injury: 7%; diarrhea, dyspepsia, flatulence, abdominal pain, dizziness, rash: 4%; cystitis, urinary tract infection, liver function abnormality, myalgia, nausea: 3%; appetite increased, constipation, gastritis, gastroenteritis, pharyngitis, asthenia, fever, pain, tremor, herpes zoster, abnormal dreaming: 2%.
 

   Adverse Events Reported in Fingernail Onychomycosis Clinical Trials

  Patients in these trials were on a pulse regimen consisting of two 1-week treatment periods of 200 mg twice daily, separated by a 3-week period without drug.



 The following adverse events led to temporary or permanent discontinuation of therapy.



 Clinical Trials of Onychomycosis of the Fingernail: Adverse Events Leading to Temporary or Permanent Discontinuation of Therapy 
 Adverse Event                                                           Incidence (%)Itraconazole (N=37)   
  
 Rash/Pruritus                                                                         3                  
 Hypertriglyceridemia                                                                  3                  
        The following adverse events occurred with an incidence of greater than or equal to 1% (N=37): headache: 8%; pruritus, nausea, rhinitis: 5%; rash, bursitis, anxiety, depression, constipation, abdominal pain, dyspepsia, ulcerative stomatitis, gingivitis, hypertriglyceridemia, sinusitis, fatigue, malaise, pain, injury: 3%.
 

   Post-marketing Experience

  Adverse drug reactions that have been identified during post-approval use of SPORANOX  (r)  (all formulations) are listed in the table below. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, reliably estimating their frequency or establishing a causal relationship to drug exposure is not always possible.



 Postmarketing Reports of Adverse Drug Reactions 
   Blood and lymphatic system disorders:             Leukopenia, neutropenia, thrombocytopenia            
                                                                                                          
   Immune system disorders:                          Anaphylaxis; anaphylactic, anaphylactoid and allergic reactions; serum sickness; angioneurotic edema   
                                                                                                          
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders:               Hypertriglyceridemia, hypokalemia                    
                                                                                                          
   Nervous system disorders:                         Peripheral neuropathy, paresthesia, hypoesthesia, headache, dizziness   
                                                                                                          
   Eye disorders:                                    Visual disturbances, including vision blurred and diplopia   
                                                                                                          
   Ear and labyrinth disorders:                      Transient or permanent hearing loss, tinnitus        
                                                                                                          
   Cardiac disorders:                                Congestive heart failure                             
                                                                                                          
   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:    Pulmonary edema, dyspnea                             
                                                                                                          
   Gastrointestinal disorders:                       Pancreatitis, abdominal pain, vomiting, dyspepsia, nausea, diarrhea, constipation, dysgeusia   
                                                                                                          
   Hepato-biliary disorders:                         Serious hepatotoxicity (including some cases of fatal acute liver failure), hepatitis, reversible increases in hepatic enzymes   
                                                                                                          
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:           Toxic epidermal necrolysis, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, acute generalized exanthematous pustulosis, exfoliative dermatitis, leukocytoclastic vasculitis, erythema multiforme, alopecia, photosensitivity, rash, urticaria, pruritus   
                                                                                                          
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:    Myalgia, arthralgia                                  
                                                                                                          
   Renal and urinary disorders:                      Urinary incontinence, pollakiuria                    
                                                                                                          
   Reproductive system and breast disorders:         Menstrual disorders, erectile dysfunction            
                                                                                                          
   General disorders and administration site conditions:    Peripheral edema, pyrexia                            
        There is limited information on the use of SPORANOX  (r)  during pregnancy. Cases of congenital abnormalities including skeletal, genitourinary tract, cardiovascular and ophthalmic malformations as well as chromosomal and multiple malformations have been reported during post-marketing experience. A causal relationship with SPORANOX  (r)  has not been established. (See  CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY: Special Populations  ,  CONTRAINDICATIONS  ,  WARNINGS  , and  PRECAUTIONS: Drug Interactions  for more information.)
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: Congestive Heart Failure, Cardiac Effects and Drug Interactions:

    Congestive Heart Failure, Cardiac Effects and Drug Interactions:  

    SPORANOX   (r)   (itraconazole) Capsules should not be administered for the treatment of onychomycosis in patients with evidence of ventricular dysfunction such as congestive heart failure (CHF) or a history of CHF  . If signs or symptoms of congestive heart failure occur during administration of SPORANOX  (r)   Capsules, discontinue administration. When itraconazole was administered intravenously to dogs and healthy human volunteers, negative inotropic effects were seen. (See   CONTRAINDICATIONS  ,   WARNINGS  ,   PRECAUTIONS: Drug Interactions  ,   ADVERSE REACTIONS: Post-marketing Experience  , and   CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY: Special Populations   for more information.)



   Drug Interactions

    Coadministration of cisapride, oral midazolam, nisoldipine, felodipine, pimozide, quinidine, dofetilide, triazolam, levacetylmethadol (levomethadyl), lovastatin, simvastatin, ergot alkaloids such as dihydroergotamine, ergometrine (ergonovine), ergotamine and methylergometrine (methylergonovine) or methadone with SPORANOX  (r)   (itraconazole) Capsules or Oral Solution is contraindicated.   SPORANOX  (r)  , a potent cytochrome P450 3A4 isoenzyme system (CYP3A4) inhibitor, may increase plasma concentrations of drugs metabolized by this pathway. Serious cardiovascular events, including QT prolongation, torsades de pointes, ventricular tachycardia, cardiac arrest, and/or sudden death have occurred in patients using cisapride, pimozide, methadone, levacetylmethadol (levomethadyl), or quinidine, concomitantly with SPORANOX  (r)   and/or other CYP3A4 inhibitors. See   CONTRAINDICATIONS  ,   WARNINGS  , and   PRECAUTIONS: Drug Interactions   for more information.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
