<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="sporanox1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 SPORANOX  (r)  has been associated with rare cases of serious hepatotoxicity, including liver failure and death. Some of these cases had neither pre-existing liver disease nor a serious underlying medical condition. If clinical signs or symptoms develop that are consistent with liver disease, treatment should be discontinued and liver function testing performed. The risks and benefits of SPORANOX  (r)  use should be reassessed. (See  WARNINGS: Hepatic Effects  and  PRECAUTIONS: Hepatotoxicity  and  Information for Patients  .)



   Adverse Events Reported in Oropharyngeal or Esophageal Candidiasis Trials

  U.S. adverse experience data are derived from 350 immunocompromised patients (332 HIV seropositive/AIDS) treated for oropharyngeal or esophageal candidiasis. Table 2 below lists adverse events reported by at least 2% of patients treated with SPORANOX  (r)  Oral Solution in U.S. clinical trials. Data on patients receiving comparator agents in these trials are included for comparison.



 Table 2: Summary of Adverse Events Reported by &gt;=2% of SPORANOX(r) Treated Patients in U.S. Clinical Trials (Total) 
 Body System/ Adverse Event   Itraconazole                                             
 Total(n = 350) %             All controlled studies(n = 272) %  Fluconazole(n = 125) %   Clotrimazole (n = 81) %    
  
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                             
   Nausea                          11            10                   11                         5              
   Diarrhea                        11            10                   10                         4              
   Vomiting                        7              6                    8                         1              
   Abdominal pain                  6              4                    7                         7              
   Constipation                    2              2                    1                         0              
   Body as a whole                                                                     
   Fever                           7              6                    8                         5              
   Chest pain                      3              3                    2                         0              
   Pain                            2              2                    4                         0              
   Fatigue                         2              1                    2                         0              
   Respiratory disorders                                                               
   Coughing                        4              4                   10                         0              
   Dyspnea                         2              3                    5                         1              
   Pneumonia                       2              2                    0                         0              
   Sinusitis                       2              2                    4                         0              
   Sputum increased                2              3                    3                         1              
   Skin and appendages disorders                                                             
   Rash                            4              5                    4                         6              
   Increased sweating              3              4                    6                         1              
   Skin disorder unspecified       2              2                    2                         1              
   Central/peripheral nervous system                                                             
   Headache                        4              4                    6                         6              
   Dizziness                       2              2                    4                         1              
   Resistance mechanism disorders                                                             
   Pneumocystis carinii infection       2              2                    2                         0              
   Psychiatric disorders                                                               
   Depression                      2              1                    0                         1              
           Adverse events reported by less than 2% of patients in U.S. clinical trials with SPORANOX  (r)  included: adrenal insufficiency, asthenia, back pain, dehydration, dyspepsia, dysphagia, flatulence, gynecomastia, hematuria, hemorrhoids, hot flushes, implantation complication, infection unspecified, injury, insomnia, male breast pain, myalgia, pharyngitis, pruritus, rhinitis, rigors, stomatitis ulcerative, taste perversion, tinnitus, upper respiratory tract infection, vision abnormal, and weight decrease. Edema, hypokalemia and menstrual disorders have been reported in clinical trials with itraconazole capsules.
 

   Adverse Events Reported from Other Clinical Trials

  A comparative clinical trial in patients who received intravenous itraconazole followed by SPORANOX  (r)  Oral Solution or received Amphotericin B reported the following adverse events in the itraconazole intravenous/SPORANOX  (r)  Oral Solution treatment arm which are not listed above in the subsection "Adverse Events Reported in Oropharnyngeal or Esophageal Candidiasis Trials" or listed below as postmarketing reports of adverse drug reactions: serum creatinine increased, blood urea nitrogen increased, renal function abnormal, hypocalcemia, hypomagnesemia, hypophosphatemia, hypotension, tachycardia and pulmonary infiltration.



 In addition, the following adverse drug reactions were reported in patients who participated in SPORANOX  (r)  Oral Solution clinical trials:



   Cardiac Disorders:  cardiac failure;



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  edema;



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:  hepatic failure, hyperbilirubinemia;



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  hypokalemia;



   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders:  menstrual disorder



 The following is a list of additional adverse drug reactions associated with itraconazole that have been reported in clinical trials of SPORANOX  (r)  Capsules and itraconazole IV excluding the adverse reaction term "Injection site inflammation" which is specific to the injection route of administration:



   Cardiac Disorders:  left ventricular failure;



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  gastrointestinal disorder;



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  face edema;



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:  jaundice, hepatic function abnormal;



   Investigations:  alanine aminotransferase increased, aspartate aminotransferase increased, blood alkaline phosphatase increased, blood lactate dehydrogenase increased, gamma-glutamyltransferase increased, urine analysis abnormal;



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  hyperglycemia, hyperkalemia;



   Nervous System Disorders:  somnolence;



   Psychiatric Disorders:  confusional state;



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  renal impairment;



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  dysphonia;



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  rash erythematous;



   Vascular Disorders:  hypertension



 In addition, the following adverse drug reaction was reported in children only who participated in SPORANOX  (r)  Oral Solution clinical trials: mucosal inflammation.



   Post-marketing Experience

  Adverse drug reactions that have been first identified during post-marketing experience with SPORANOX  (r)  (all formulations) are listed in the table below. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, reliably estimating their frequency or establishing a causal relationship to drug exposure is not always possible.



 Table 3: Postmarketing Reports of Adverse Drug Reactions 
   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:             Leukopenia, neutropenia, thrombocytopenia            
   Immune System Disorders:                          Anaphylaxis; anaphylactic, anaphylactoid and allergic reactions; serum sickness; angioneurotic edema   
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:               Hypertriglyceridemia                                 
   Nervous System Disorders:                         Peripheral neuropathy, paresthesia, hypoesthesia, tremor   
   Eye Disorders:                                    Visual disturbances, including vision blurred and diplopia   
   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders:                      Transient or permanent hearing loss                  
   Cardiac Disorders:                                Congestive heart failure                             
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:    Pulmonary edema                                      
   Gastrointestinal Disorders:                       Pancreatitis                                         
   Hepatobiliary Disorders  :                        Serious hepatotoxicity (including some cases of fatal acute liver failure), hepatitis, reversible increases in hepatic enzymes   
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:           Toxic epidermal necrolysis, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, acute generalized exanthematous pustulosis, erythema multiforme, exfoliative dermatitis, leukocytoclastic vasculitis, alopecia, photosensitivity, urticaria   
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:    Arthralgia                                           
   Renal and Urinary Disorders:                      Urinary incontinence, pollakiuria                    
   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders:         Erectile dysfunction                                 
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:    Peripheral edema                                     
   Investigations:                                   Blood creatine phosphokinase increased               
        There is limited information on the use of SPORANOX  (r)  during pregnancy. Cases of congenital abnormalities including skeletal, genitourinary tract, cardiovascular and ophthalmic malformations as well as chromosomal and multiple malformations have been reported during post-marketing experience. A causal relationship with SPORANOX  (r)  has not been established. (See  CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY: Special Populations  ,  CONTRAINDICATIONS  ,  WARNINGS  , and  PRECAUTIONS: Drug Interactions  for more information.)
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: BOXED WARNING

    BOXED WARNING  

  Congestive Heart Failure, Cardiac Effects and Drug Interactions

  If signs or symptoms of congestive heart failure occur during administration of SPORANOX  (r)   (itraconazole) Oral Solution, continued SPORANOX  (r)   use should be reassessed. When itraconazole was administered intravenously to dogs and healthy human volunteers, negative inotropic effects were seen. (See    CONTRAINDICATIONS  ,   WARNINGS  ,   PRECAUTIONS: Drug Interactions  ,    ADVERSE REACTIONS: Post-marketing Experience  , and    CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY: Special Populations   for more information.) 



   Drug Interactions

    Coadministration of the following drugs are contraindicated with SPORANOX  (r)   Oral Solution: methadone, disopyramide, dofetilide, dronedarone, quinidine, ergot alkaloids (such as dihydroergotamine, ergometrine (ergonovine), ergotamine, methylergometrine (methylergonovine)), irinotecan, lurasidone, oral midazolam, pimozide, triazolam, felodipine, nisoldipine, ranolazine, eplerenone, cisapride, lovastatin, simvastatin, ticagrelor, and, in subjects with varying degrees of renal or hepatic impairment, colchicine, fesoterodine, telithromycin and solifenacin. See   PRECAUTIONS: Drug Interactions   Section for specific examples. Coadministration with itraconazole can cause elevated plasma concentrations of these drugs and may increase or prolong both the pharmacologic effects and/or adverse reactions to these drugs. For example, increased plasma concentrations of some of these drugs can lead to QT prolongation and ventricular tachyarrhythmias including occurrences of torsades de pointes, a potentially fatal arrhythmia. See    CONTRAINDICATIONS   and    WARNINGS   Sections, and    PRECAUTIONS: Drug Interactions   Section for specific examples.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
