<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="spritam" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are described below and elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Behavioral Abnormalities and Psychotic Symptoms [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *  Suicidal Behavior and Ideation [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
 *  Somnolence and Fatigue [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ] 
 *  Serious Dermatological Reactions [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   ] 
 *  Coordination Difficulties [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)   ] 
 *  Hematologic Abnormalities [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)   ] 
 *  Increase in Blood Pressure [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)   ] 
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 5% more than placebo) include:
 

 *  Adults: somnolence, asthenia, infection, and dizziness (  6.1  ) 
 *  Pediatrics: fatigue, aggression, nasal congestion, decreased appetite, and irritability (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Aprecia Pharmaceuticals Company at 1-844-882-7732 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Partial Onset Seizures  



   Adults  



 In controlled clinical studies in adults with partial onset seizures, the most common adverse reactions in patients receiving levetiracetam in combination with other AEDs, for events with rates greater than placebo, were somnolence, asthenia, infection, and dizziness. Of the most common adverse reactions in adults experiencing partial onset seizures, asthenia, somnolence, and dizziness occurred predominantly during the first 4 weeks of treatment with levetiracetam.



   Table 3  lists adverse reactions that occurred in at least 1% of adult epilepsy patients receiving levetiracetam in placebo-controlled studies and were numerically more common than in patients treated with placebo. In these studies, either levetiracetam or placebo was added to concurrent AED therapy.



 Table 3: Adverse Reactions in Pooled Placebo-Controlled, Add-On Studies in Adults with Partial Onset Seizures 
 Adverse Reaction  Levetiracetam(N=769)%  Placebo(N=439)%   
 Asthenia    15          9            
 Somnolence  15          8            
 Headache    14          13           
 Infection   13          8            
 Dizziness   9           4            
 Pain        7           6            
 Pharyngitis  6           4            
 Depression  4           2            
 Nervousness  4           2            
 Rhinitis    4           3            
 Anorexia    3           2            
 Ataxia      3           1            
 Vertigo     3           1            
 Amnesia     2           1            
 Anxiety     2           1            
 Cough Increased  2           1            
 Diplopia    2           1            
 Emotional Lability  2           0            
 Hostility   2           1            
 Paresthesia  2           1            
 Sinusitis   2           1            
         In controlled adult clinical studies, 15% of patients receiving levetiracetam and 12% receiving placebo either discontinued or had a dose reduction as a result of an adverse reaction.  Table 4  lists the most common (&gt; 1%) adverse reactions that resulted in discontinuation or dose reduction and that occurred more frequently in levetiracetam-treated patients than in placebo-treated patients.
 

 Table 4: Adverse Reactions that Resulted in Discontinuation or Dose Reduction in Pooled Placebo-Controlled Studies in Adults with Partial Onset Seizures 
 Adverse Reaction  Levetiracetam(n=769)%  Placebo(N=439)%   
 Somnolence  4           2            
 Dizziness   1           0            
         Pediatric Patients 4 Years to Less Than 16 Years of Age
 

 The adverse reaction data presented below was obtained from a pooled analysis of two controlled clinical studies in pediatric patients 4 to less than 16 years of age with partial onset seizures. The most common adverse reactions in pediatric patients 4 to less than 16 years of age receiving levetiracetam in combination with other AEDs, for events with rates greater than placebo, were fatigue, aggression, nasal congestion, decreased appetite, and irritability.



   Table 5  lists adverse reactions from the pooled pediatric controlled studies (4 to less than 16 years of age) that occurred in at least 2% of pediatric levetiracetam-treated patients and were numerically more common than in pediatric patients treated with placebo. In these studies, either levetiracetam or placebo was added to concurrent AED therapy.



 Table 5: Adverse Reactions in Pooled Placebo-Controlled, Add-On Studies in Pediatric Patients 4 to 16 Years of Age with Partial Onset Seizures 
 Adverse Reaction                Levetiracetam(N=165)%           Placebo(N=131)%                  
 Headache                        19                              15                               
 Nasopharyngitis                 15                              12                               
 Vomiting                        15                              12                               
 Somnolence                      13                              9                                
 Fatigue                         11                              5                                
 Aggression                      10                              5                                
 Cough                           9                               5                                
 Nasal Congestion                9                               2                                
 Upper Abdominal Pain            9                               8                                
 Decreased Appetite              8                               2                                
 Abnormal Behavior               7                               4                                
 Dizziness                       7                               5                                
 Irritability                    7                               1                                
 Pharyngolaryngeal Pain          7                               4                                
 Diarrhea                        6                               2                                
 Lethargy                        6                               5                                
 Insomnia                        5                               3                                
 Agitation                       4                               1                                
 Anorexia                        4                               3                                
 Head Injury                     4                               0                                
 Altered Mood                    3                               1                                
 Constipation                    3                               1                                
 Contusion                       3                               1                                
 Depression                      3                               1                                
 Fall                            3                               2                                
 Influenza                       3                               1                                
 Affect Lability                 2                               1                                
 Anxiety                         2                               1                                
 Arthralgia                      2                               0                                
 Confusional State               2                               0                                
 Conjunctivitis                  2                               0                                
 Ear Pain                        2                               1                                
 Gastroenteritis                 2                               0                                
 Joint Sprain                    2                               1                                
 Mood Swings                     2                               1                                
 Neck Pain                       2                               1                                
 Rhinitis                        2                               0                                
 Sedation                        2                               1                                
         In the controlled pooled pediatric clinical studies in patients 4 years to 16 years of age, 7% of patients receiving levetiracetam and 9% receiving placebo discontinued as a result of an adverse reaction.
 

 Myoclonic Seizures



 Although the pattern of adverse reactions in this study seems somewhat different from that seen in patients with partial seizures, this is likely due to the much smaller number of patients in this study compared to partial seizure studies. The adverse reaction pattern for patients with JME is expected to be essentially the same as for patients with partial seizures.



 In the controlled clinical study in patients 12 years of age and older with myoclonic seizures, the most common adverse reactions in patients receiving levetiracetam in combination with other AEDs, for events with rates greater than placebo, were somnolence, neck pain, and pharyngitis.



   Table 6  lists adverse reactions that occurred in at least 5% of juvenile myoclonic epilepsy patients experiencing myoclonic seizures treated with levetiracetam and were numerically more common than in patients treated with placebo. In this study, either levetiracetam or placebo was added to concurrent AED therapy.



 Table 6: Adverse Reactions in a Placebo-Controlled, Add-On Study in Patients 12 Years of Age and Older with Myoclonic Seizures 
 Adverse Reaction  Levetiracetam(N=60)%  Placebo(N=60)%   
 Somnolence  12          2            
 Neck pain   8           2            
 Pharyngitis  7           0            
 Depression  5           2            
 Influenza   5           2            
 Vertigo     5           3            
         In the placebo-controlled study, 8% of patients receiving levetiracetam and 2% receiving placebo either discontinued or had a dose reduction as a result of an adverse reaction. The adverse reactions that led to discontinuation or dose reduction and that occurred more frequently in levetiracetam-treated patients than in placebo-treated patients are presented in  Table 7  .
 

 Table 7: Adverse Reactions that Resulted in Discontinuation or Dose Reduction in a Placebo-Controlled Study in Patients with Juvenile Myoclonic Epilepsy 
 Adverse Reaction                Levetiracetam(N=60)%            Placebo(N=60)%                   
 Anxiety                         3                               2                                
 Depressed mood                  2                               0                                
 Depression                      2                               0                                
 Diplopia                        2                               0                                
 Hypersomnia                     2                               0                                
 Insomnia                        2                               0                                
 Irritability                    2                               0                                
 Nervousness                     2                               0                                
 Somnolence                      2                               0                                
         Primary Generalized Tonic-Clonic Seizures
 

 Although the pattern of adverse reactions in this study seems somewhat different from that seen in patients with partial seizures, this is likely due to the much smaller number of patients in this study compared to partial seizure studies. The adverse reaction pattern for patients with primary generalized tonic-clonic (PGTC) seizures is expected to be essentially the same as for patients with partial seizures.



 In the controlled clinical trial in patients with PGTC seizures, the most common adverse reaction in patients receiving levetiracetam in combination with other AEDs, for events with rates greater than placebo, was nasopharyngitis.



   Table 8  lists adverse reactions that occurred in at least 5% of idiopathic generalized epilepsy patients experiencing PGTC seizures treated with levetiracetam and were numerically more common than in patients treated with placebo. In this study, either levetiracetam or placebo was added to concurrent AED therapy.



 Table 8: Adverse Reactions in a Placebo-Controlled, Add-On Study in Patients 4 Years of Age and Older with PGTC Seizures 
 Adverse Reaction                Levetiracetam(N=79)%            Placebo(N=84)%                   
 Nasopharyngitis                 14                              5                                
 Fatigue                         10                              8                                
 Diarrhea                        8                               7                                
 Irritability                    6                               2                                
 Mood swings                     5                               1                                
         In the placebo-controlled study, 5% of patients receiving levetiracetam and 8% receiving placebo either discontinued or had a dose reduction during the treatment period as a result of an adverse reaction.
 

 This study was too small to adequately characterize the adverse reactions that could be expected to result in discontinuation of treatment in this population. It is expected that the adverse reactions that would lead to discontinuation in this population would be similar to those resulting in discontinuation in other epilepsy trials (see  Table 4  and  Table 7  ).



 In addition, the following adverse reactions were seen in other controlled adult studies of levetiracetam: balance disorder, disturbance in attention, eczema, memory impairment, myalgia, and blurred vision.



 Comparison of Gender, Age, and Race



 The overall adverse reaction profile of levetiracetam was similar between females and males. There are insufficient data to support a statement regarding the distribution of adverse reactions by age and race.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of levetiracetam. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 The listing is alphabetized: abnormal liver function test, choreoathetosis, drug reaction with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms (DRESS), dyskinesia, erythema multiforme, hepatic failure, hepatitis, hyponatremia, muscle weakness, pancreatitis, pancytopenia (with bone marrow suppression identified in some of these cases), panic attack, thrombocytopenia, and weight loss. Alopecia has been reported with levetiracetam use; recovery was observed in majority of cases where levetiracetam was discontinued.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Behavioral Abnormalities: psychotic symptoms, irritability, and aggressive behavior have been observed: Monitor for signs and symptoms (  5.1  ) 
 *  Suicidal Behavior and Ideation: Monitor for new or worsening depression, suicidal thoughts/behavior, and/or changes in mood or behavior (  5.2  ) 
 *  Monitor for somnolence and fatigue and advise patients not to drive or operate machinery until they have gained experience on SPRITAM (  5.3  ) 
 *  Withdrawal Seizures: SPRITAM must be gradually withdrawn (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Behavioral Abnormalities and Psychotic Symptoms



  SPRITAM may cause behavioral abnormalities and psychotic symptoms.



  Behavioral abnormalities  



 In clinical studies, 13% of adult levetiracetam-treated patients and 38% of pediatric levetiracetam-treated patients (4 to 16 years of age), compared to 6% and 19% of adult and pediatric placebo-treated patients, respectively, experienced non-psychotic behavioral symptoms (reported as aggression, agitation, anger, anxiety, apathy, depersonalization, depression, emotional lability, hostility, hyperkinesias, irritability, nervousness, neurosis, and personality disorder).



 A randomized double-blind, placebo-controlled study was performed to assess the neurocognitive and behavioral effects of levetiracetam as adjunctive therapy in pediatric patients (4 to 16 years of age). The results from an exploratory analysis indicated a worsening in levetiracetam-treated patients on aggressive behavior (one of eight behavior dimensions) as measured in a standardized and systematic way using a validated instrument, the Achenbach Child Behavior Checklist (CBCL/6-18).



 In clinical studies in pediatric patients 1 month to &lt; 4 years of age, irritability was reported in 12% of the levetiracetam-treated patients compared to 0% of placebo-treated patients.



 In clinical studies, 1.7% of adult levetiracetam-treated patients discontinued treatment due to behavioral adverse reactions, compared to 0.2% of placebo-treated patients. The treatment dose was reduced in 0.8% of adult levetiracetam-treated patients and in 0.5% of placebo-treated patients. Overall, 11% of levetiracetam-treated pediatric patients experienced behavioral symptoms associated with discontinuation or dose reduction, compared to 6% of placebo-treated patients.



  Psychotic symptoms  



 In clinical studies, 1% of levetiracetam-treated adult patients, 2% of levetiracetam-treated pediatric patients 4 to 16 years of age, and 17% of levetiracetam-treated pediatric patients 1 month to &lt; 4 years of age experienced psychotic symptoms, compared to 0.2%, 2%, and 5% in the corresponding age groups treated with placebo. In the controlled study that assessed the neurocognitive and behavioral effects of levetiracetam in pediatric patients 4 to 16 years of age, 1.6% of levetiracetam-treated patients experienced paranoia, compared to 0% of placebo-treated patients. In the same study, 3.1% of levetiracetam-treated patients experienced confusional state, compared to 0% of placebo-treated patients [see   Use in Specific Populations (8.4)    ].



 In clinical studies, two (0.3%) levetiracetam-treated adult patients were hospitalized and their treatment was discontinued due to psychosis. Both events, reported as psychosis, developed within the first week of treatment and resolved within 1 to 2 weeks following treatment discontinuation. There was no difference between drug and placebo-treated patients in the incidence of the pediatric patients who discontinued treatment due to psychotic and non-psychotic adverse reactions.



    5.2 Suicidal Behavior and Ideation



  Antiepileptic drugs (AEDs), including SPRITAM, increase the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior in patients taking these drugs for any indication. Patients treated with any AED for any indication should be monitored for the emergence or worsening of depression, suicidal thoughts or behavior, and/or any unusual changes in mood or behavior.



 Pooled analyses of 199 placebo-controlled clinical trials (mono- and adjunctive therapy) of 11 different AEDs showed that patients randomized to one of the AEDs had approximately twice the risk (adjusted Relative Risk 1.8, 95% CI:1.2, 2.7) of suicidal thinking or behavior compared to patients randomized to placebo. In these trials, which had a median treatment duration of 12 weeks, the estimated incidence rate of suicidal behavior or ideation among 27,863 AED-treated patients was 0.43%, compared to 0.24% among 16,029 placebo-treated patients, representing an increase of approximately one case of suicidal thinking or behavior for every 530 patients treated. There were four suicides in drug-treated patients in the trials and none in placebo-treated patients, but the number is too small to allow any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.



 The increased risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with AEDs was observed as early as one week after starting drug treatment with AEDs and persisted for the duration of treatment assessed. Because most trials included in the analysis did not extend beyond 24 weeks, the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior beyond 24 weeks could not be assessed.



 The risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior was generally consistent among drugs in the data analyzed. The finding of increased risk with AEDs of varying mechanisms of action and across a range of indications suggests that the risk applies to all AEDs used for any indication. The risk did not vary substantially by age (5-100 years) in the clinical trials analyzed.  Table 2  shows absolute and relative risk by indication for all evaluated AEDs.



 Table 2: Risk by Indication for Antiepileptic Drugs in the Pooled Analysis 
  Indication            PlaceboPatients withEvents Per1000 Patients     DrugPatients withEvents Per1000 Patients     Relative Risk:Incidence ofEvents in DrugPatients/Incidence inPlacebo Patients     Risk Difference:Additional DrugPatients withEvents Per 1000Patients     
 Epilepsy              1.0                   3.4                   3.5                   2.4                    
 Psychiatric           5.7                   8.5                   1.5                   2.9                    
 Other                 1.0                   1.8                   1.9                   0.9                    
 Total                 2.4                   4.3                   1.8                   1.9                    
           The relative risk for suicidal thoughts or behavior was higher in clinical trials for epilepsy than in clinical trials for psychiatric or other conditions, but the absolute risk differences were similar for the epilepsy and psychiatric indications.
 

 Anyone considering prescribing SPRITAM or any other AED must balance the risk of suicidal thoughts or behaviors with the risk of untreated illness. Epilepsy and many other illnesses for which AEDs are prescribed are themselves associated with morbidity and mortality and an increased risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior. Should suicidal thoughts and behavior emerge during treatment, the prescriber needs to consider whether the emergence of these symptoms in any given patient may be related to the illness being treated.



 Patients, their caregivers, and families should be informed that AEDs increase the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior and should be advised of the need to be alert for the emergence or worsening of the signs and symptoms of depression, any unusual changes in mood or behavior, or the emergence of suicidal thoughts, behavior, or thoughts about self-harm. Behaviors of concern should be reported immediately to healthcare providers.



    5.3 Somnolence and Fatigue



  SPRITAM may cause somnolence and fatigue. Patients should be monitored for these signs and symptoms and advised not to drive or operate machinery until they have gained sufficient experience on SPRITAM to gauge whether it adversely affects their ability to drive or operate machinery.



  Somnolence  



 In controlled trials of adult patients with epilepsy experiencing partial onset seizures, 15% of levetiracetam-treated patients reported somnolence, compared to 8% of placebo-treated patients. There was no clear dose response up to 3000 mg/day. In a study where there was no titration, about 45% of patients receiving 4000 mg/day reported somnolence. The somnolence was considered serious in 0.3% of levetiracetam-treated patients, compared to 0% in the placebo group. About 3% of levetiracetam-treated patients discontinued treatment due to somnolence, compared to 0.7% of placebo-treated patients. In 1.4% of levetiracetam-treated patients and 0.9% of placebo-treated patients, the dose was reduced, while 0.3% of the levetiracetam-treated patients were hospitalized due to somnolence.



  Asthenia  



 In controlled trials of adult patients with epilepsy experiencing partial onset seizures, 15% of levetiracetam-treated patients reported asthenia, compared to 9% of placebo-treated patients. Treatment was discontinued due to asthenia in 0.8% of levetiracetam-treated patients as compared to 0.5% of placebo-treated patients. In 0.5% of levetiracetam-treated patients and in 0.2% of placebo-treated patients, the dose was reduced due to asthenia.



 Somnolence and asthenia occurred most frequently within the first 4 weeks of treatment. In general, the incidences of somnolence and fatigue in the pediatric partial onset seizure studies, and in pediatric and adult myoclonic and primary generalized tonic-clonic studies were comparable to those of the adult partial onset seizure studies.



    5.4 Serious Dermatological Reactions



  Serious dermatological reactions, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome (SJS) and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), have been reported in both pediatric and adult patients treated with levetiracetam. The median time of onset is reported to be 14 to 17 days, but cases have been reported at least four months after initiation of treatment. Recurrence of the serious skin reactions following rechallenge with levetiracetam has also been reported. SPRITAM should be discontinued at the first sign of a rash, unless the rash is clearly not drug-related. If signs or symptoms suggest SJS/TEN, use of this drug should not be resumed and alternative therapy should be considered.



    5.5 Coordination Difficulties



  SPRITAM may cause coordination difficulties.



 In controlled clinical studies in adult patients with partial onset seizures, 3.4% of adult levetiracetam-treated patients experienced coordination difficulties (reported as either ataxia, abnormal gait, or incoordination), compared to 1.6% of placebo-treated patients. A total of 0.4% of patients in controlled clinical studies discontinued levetiracetam treatment due to ataxia, compared to 0% of placebo-treated patients. In 0.7% of levetiracetam-treated patients and in 0.2% of placebo-treated patients, the dose was reduced due to coordination difficulties, while one of the levetiracetam-treated patients was hospitalized due to worsening of pre-existing ataxia. These events occurred most frequently within the first 4 weeks of treatment.



 Patients should be monitored for these signs and symptoms and advised not to drive or operate machinery until they have gained sufficient experience on SPRITAM to gauge whether it could adversely affect their ability to drive or operate machinery.



    5.6 Withdrawal Seizures



  Antiepileptic drugs, including SPRITAM, should be withdrawn gradually to minimize the potential of increased seizure frequency.



    5.7 Hematologic Abnormalities



  SPRITAM can cause hematologic abnormalities. Hematologic abnormalities occurred in clinical trials with levetiracetam and included decreases in red blood cell (RBC) counts, hemoglobin and hematocrit, and increases in eosinophil counts. Decreased white blood cell (WBC) and neutrophil counts also occurred in clinical trials. Cases of agranulocytosis have been reported in the postmarketing setting.



  Partial Onset Seizures  



  Adults  



 Minor, but statistically significant decreases compared to placebo, in total mean RBC count (0.03 x 10  6  /mm  3  ), mean hemoglobin (0.09 g/dL), and mean hematocrit (0.38%), were seen in levetiracetam-treated patients in controlled trials.



 A total of 3.2% of levetiracetam-treated and 1.8% of placebo-treated patients had at least one possibly significant (&lt;= 2.8 * 10  9  /L) decreased WBC, and 2.4% of levetiracetam-treated and 1.4% of placebo-treated patients had at least one possibly significant (&lt;= 1.0 * 10  9  /L) decreased neutrophil count. Of the levetiracetam-treated patients with a low neutrophil count, all but one rose towards or to baseline with continued treatment. No patient was discontinued secondary to low neutrophil counts.



  Pediatric Patients 4 Years to Less Than 16 Years of Age  



 Statistically significant decreases in WBC and neutrophil counts were seen in levetiracetam-treated patients as compared to placebo. The mean decreases from baseline in the levetiracetam-treated group were -0.4 * 10  9  /L and -0.3 * 10  9  /L, respectively, whereas there were small increases in the placebo group. Mean relative lymphocyte counts increased by 1.7% in levetiracetam-treated patients, compared to a decrease of 4% in placebo-treated patients (statistically significant).



 In a controlled trial, more levetiracetam-treated patients had a possibly clinically significant abnormally low WBC value (3% of levetiracetam-treated patients versus 0% of placebo-treated patients); however, there was no apparent difference between treatment groups with respect to neutrophil count (5% of levetiracetam-treated patients versus 4.2% of placebo-treated patients). No patient was discontinued secondary to low WBC or neutrophil counts.



 In a controlled cognitive and neuropsychological safety study, 5 patients (8.6%) in the levetiracetam-treated group and two patients (6.1%) in the placebo-treated group had high eosinophil count values that were possibly clinically significant (&gt;= 10% or &gt;= 0.7*10  9  /L).



    5.8 Increase in Blood Pressure



  In a randomized, placebo-controlled study in patients 1 month to &lt; 4 years of age, a significantly higher risk of increased diastolic blood pressure was observed in levetiracetam-treated patients (17%), compared to the placebo-treated patients (2%). There was no overall difference in mean diastolic blood pressure between the treatment groups. This disparity between the levetiracetam and placebo treatment groups was not observed in the studies of older pediatric patients or in adults.



 Monitor patients 1 month to &lt;4 years of age for increases in diastolic blood pressure.



    5.9 Seizure Control During Pregnancy



  Physiological changes may gradually decrease plasma levels of levetiracetam throughout pregnancy. This decrease is more pronounced during the third trimester. It is recommended that patients be monitored carefully during pregnancy. Close monitoring should continue through the postpartum period especially if the dose was changed during pregnancy.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
