<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="sprix" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Gastrointestinal effects [see  Boxed Warning  and Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Hemorrhage [see  Boxed Warning  and Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *  Renal effects [see  Boxed Warning  and Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  Anaphylactoid reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *  Cardiovascular thrombotic events [see  Boxed Warning  and Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *  Hypertension [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *  Congestive heart failure and edema [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *  Serious skin reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
 *  Hepatic effects [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.9  )]  
    The most frequently reported adverse reactions were related to local symptoms, i.e., nasal discomfort or irritation. These reactions were generally mild and transient in nature.
 

 The most common drug-related adverse events leading to premature discontinuation were nasal discomfort or nasal pain (rhinalgia).



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt; 2%) in patients treated with SPRIX and occurring at a rate at least twice that of placebo are nasal discomfort, rhinalgia, increased lacrimation, throat irritation, oliguria, rash, bradycardia, decreased urine output, increased ALT and/or AST, hypertension, and rhinitis. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact American Regent, Inc. at 1-800-734-9236 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Experience from SPRIX Clinical Studies

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The data described below reflect exposure to SPRIX in patients enrolled in placebo-controlled efficacy studies of acute pain following major surgery. The studies enrolled 828 patients (183 men, 645 women) ranging from 18 years to over 75 years of age.



 The patients in the postoperative pain studies had undergone major abdominal, orthopedic, gynecologic, or other surgery; 455 patients received SPRIX (31.5 mg) three or four times a day for up to 5 days, and 245 patients received placebo. Most patients were receiving concomitant opioids, primarily PCA morphine.



 Table 1. Post-operative Patients with Adverse Reactions Observed at a rate of 2% or more and at least twice the incidence of the placebo group. 
                                       SPRIX    (N=455)                   Placebo    (N= 245)               
   Nasal discomfort                  15%                                2%                                  
   Rhinalgia                         13%                                &lt;1%                                 
   Lacrimation increased             5%                                 0%                                  
   Throat irritation                 4%                                 &lt;1%                                 
   Oliguria                          3%                                 1%                                  
   Rash                              3%                                 &lt;1%                                 
   Bradycardia                       2%                                 &lt;1%                                 
   Urine output decreased            2%                                 &lt;1%                                 
   ALT and/or AST increased          2%                                 1%                                  
   Hypertension                      2%                                 1%                                  
   Rhinitis                          2%                                 &lt;1%                                 
         In controlled clinical trials in major surgery, primarily knee and hip replacements and abdominal hysterectomies, seven patients (N=455, 1.5%) treated with SPRIX experienced serious adverse events of bleeding (4 patients) or hematoma (3 patients) at the operative site versus one patient (N=245, 0.4%) treated with placebo (hematoma).  Six of the seven patients treated with SPRIX underwent a surgical procedure and/or blood transfusion and the placebo patient subsequently required a blood transfusion.
 

   6.2 Adverse Reactions Reported in Clinical Trials with Other Dosage Forms of Ketorolac or Other NSAIDs

  Adverse reaction rates increase with higher doses of ketorolac. It is necessary to remain alert for the severe complications of treatment with ketorolac, such as GI ulceration, bleeding, and perforation, postoperative bleeding, acute renal failure, anaphylactic and anaphylactoid reactions, and liver failure. These complications can be serious in certain patients for whom ketorolac is indicated, especially when the drug is used inappropriately.



 In patients taking ketorolac or other NSAIDs in clinical trials, the most frequently reported adverse experiences in approximately 1% to 10% of patients are:



 Gastrointestinal (GI) experiences including:




  *Incidence greater than 10%        
  
 abdominal pain                     constipation/diarrhea              dyspepsia                           
 flatulence                         GI fullness                        GI ulcers (gastric/duodenal)        
 gross bleeding/perforation         heartburn                          nausea*                             
 stomatitis                         vomiting                                                               
                                                                                                           
 Other experiences:                                                                                        
 abnormal renal function            anemia                             dizziness                           
 drowsiness                         edema                              elevated liver enzymes              
 headache*                          hypertension                       increased bleeding time             
 injection site pain                pruritus                           purpura                             
 rash                               tinnitus                           sweating                            
         Additional adverse experiences reported occasionally (&lt;1% in patients taking ketorolac or other NSAIDs in clinical trials) include:
 

   Body as a Whole:  fever, infection, sepsis



   Cardiovascular System:  congestive heart failure, palpitation, pallor, tachycardia, syncope



   Digestive System:  anorexia, dry mouth, eructation, esophagitis, excessive thirst, gastritis, glossitis, hematemesis, hepatitis, increased appetite, jaundice, melena, rectal bleeding



   Hemic and Lymphatic:  ecchymosis, eosinophilia, epistaxis, leukopenia, thrombocytopenia



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  weight change



   Nervous System:  abnormal dreams, abnormal thinking, anxiety, asthenia, confusion, depression, euphoria, extrapyramidal symptoms, hallucinations, hyperkinesis, inability to concentrate, insomnia, nervousness, paresthesia, somnolence, stupor, tremors, vertigo, malaise



   Respiratory:  asthma, dyspnea, pulmonary edema, rhinitis



   Special Senses:  abnormal taste, abnormal vision, blurred vision, hearing loss



   Urogenital:  cystitis, dysuria, hematuria, increased urinary frequency, interstitial nephritis, oliguria/polyuria, proteinuria, renal failure, urinary retention



   6.3 Adverse Reactions from Postmarketing Experience with Other Dosage Forms of Ketorolac or Other NSAIDs

  Other observed reactions (reported from postmarketing experience in patients taking ketorolac or other NSAIDs) are:



   Body as a Whole:  angioedema, death, hypersensitivity reactions such as anaphylaxis, anaphylactoid reaction, laryngeal edema, tongue edema, myalgia



   Cardiovascular:  arrhythmia, bradycardia, chest pain, flushing, hypotension, myocardial infarction, vasculitis



   Dermatologic:  exfoliative dermatitis, erythema multiforme, Lyell's syndrome, bullous reactions including Stevens-Johnson syndrome and toxic epidermal necrolysis



   Gastrointestinal:  acute pancreatitis, liver failure, ulcerative stomatitis, exacerbation of inflammatory bowel disease (ulcerative colitis, Crohn's disease)



   Hemic and Lymphatic:  agranulocytosis, aplastic anemia, hemolytic anemia, lymphadenopathy, pancytopenia, postoperative wound hemorrhage (rarely requiring blood transfusion)



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  hyperglycemia, hyperkalemia, hyponatremia



   Nervous System:  aseptic meningitis, convulsions, coma, psychosis



   Respiratory:  bronchospasm, respiratory depression, pneumonia



   Special Senses:  conjunctivitis



   Urogenital:  flank pain with or without hematuria and/or azotemia, hemolytic uremic syndrome
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING; LIMITATIONS OF USE, GASTROINTESTINAL, BLEEDING, CARDIOVASCULAR, and RENAL RISK



  WARNING; LIMITATIONS OF USE, GASTROINTESTINAL, BLEEDING, CARDIOVASCULAR, and RENAL RISK



    Limitations of Use  



 SPRIX (ketorolac tromethamine), a nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug (NSAID), is indicated for short-term (up to 5 days in adults) management of moderate to moderately severe pain that requires analgesia at the opioid level. Do not exceed a total combined duration of use of SPRIX and other ketorolac formulations (IM/IV or oral) of 5 days   [see Dosage and Administration, (  2.1  ) and Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  .





 SPRIX is not indicated for use in pediatric patients and it is not indicated for minor or chronic painful conditions.





   Gastrointestinal Risk  



 Ketorolac tromethamine, including SPRIX, can cause peptic ulcers, gastrointestinal bleeding and/or perforation of the stomach or intestines, which can be fatal. These events can occur at any time during use and without warning symptoms. Therefore, SPRIX is   contraindicated   in patients with active peptic ulcer disease, in patients with recent gastrointestinal bleeding or perforation, and in patients with a history of peptic ulcer disease or gastrointestinal bleeding.  Elderly patients are at greater risk for serious gastrointestinal events    [see Contraindications (  4  ), Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )].  



   Bleeding Risk  



 Ketorolac tromethamine inhibits platelet function and is, therefore,   contraindicated   in patients with suspected or confirmed cerebrovascular bleeding, patients with hemorrhagic diathesis, incomplete hemostasis and those at high risk of bleeding   [see Contraindications (  4  ), Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )].  



   Cardiovascular Risk  



 NSAIDs may cause an increased risk of serious cardiovascular thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. This risk may increase with duration of use. Patients with cardiovascular disease or risk factors for cardiovascular disease may be at greater risk   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )].  



 SPRIX Nasal spray is   contraindicated   for treatment of peri-operative pain in the setting of coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery   [see Contraindications (  4  )].  



   Renal Risk  



 SPRIX is   contraindicated   in patients with advanced renal impairment and in patients at risk for renal failure due to volume depletion   [see Contraindications (  4  ), Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  .





    EXCERPT:   
 WARNING: LIMITATIONS OF USE, GASTROINTESTINAL, BLEEDING, CARDIOVASCULAR, and RENAL RISK                
         See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  
 

 *  Limitations of Use - The total duration of use of SPRIX and other ketorolac formulations should not exceed 5 days. (2.1) 
 *  Gastrointestinal (GI) Risk - Ketorolac can cause peptic ulcers, GI bleeding, and/or perforation of the stomach or intestines, which can be fatal. SPRIX is CONTRAINDICATED in patients with peptic ulcer disease or history of GI bleeding. (4) 
 *  Bleeding Risk - SPRIX inhibits platelet function and is CONTRAINDICATED in patients with suspected or confirmed cerebrovascular bleeding, hemorrhagic diathesis, incomplete hemostasis, or high risk of bleeding. (4) 
 *  Cardiovascular (CV) Risk - NSAIDs may cause an increased risk of serious CV thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. This risk may increase with duration of use. Patients with CV disease or risk factors for CV disease may be at greater risk. (5.6) SPRIX is CONTRAINDICATED for treatment of peri-operative pain in the setting of coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery. (4) 
 *  Renal risk - SPRIX is CONTRAINDICATED in patients with advanced renal impairment and in patients at risk for renal failure due to volume depletion. (4) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  SPRIX should not be used concomitantly with IM/IV or oral ketorolac, aspirin, or other NSAIDs. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Ketorolac can cause serious GI adverse events including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation. SPRIX should be prescribed with caution in patients with a prior history of ulcer disease or GI bleeding. Elderly patients are at greater risk for serious GI events. (  4  ,  5.2  ) 
 *  NSAIDs affect platelet aggregation and may cause bleeding complications. SPRIX should be used with caution in patients who have coagulation disorders or are on therapy that affects hemostasis. Do not use SPRIX in patients for whom hemostasis is critical. (  4  ,  5.3  ) 
 *  Ketorolac can cause renal injury. SPRIX should not be used in patients with advanced renal disease or patients at risk for renal failure due to volume depletion, and should be used with caution in patients taking diuretics or ACE inhibitors. (  4  ,  5.4  ,  12.4  ) 
 *  Anaphylactoid reactions may occur in patients with or without a history of allergic reactions to aspirin or NSAIDs. SPRIX should be discontinued immediately in patients with allergic reactions. (  4  ,  5.5  ,  5.7  ,  5.11  ) 
 *  Serious and potentially fatal cardiovascular thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke can occur with NSAID treatment. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Fluid retention and edema have been observed in patients taking NSAIDs. SPRIX should be used with caution in patients with cardiac decompensation or similar conditions. (  5.4  ,  5.6  ) 
 *  NSAIDs can cause serious dermatologic adverse reactions such as exfoliative dermatitis, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and toxic epidermal necrolysis, which can be fatal. SPRIX should be discontinued immediately in patients with skin reactions. (  4  ,  5.7  ) 
 *  During pregnancy, use of SPRIX beyond 30 weeks gestation can cause premature closure of the ductus arteriosus, resulting in fetal harm. (  5.8  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Limitations of Use



  The total duration of use of SPRIX alone or sequentially with other forms of ketorolac is not to exceed 5 days. SPRIX must not be used concomitantly with other forms of ketorolac or other NSAIDs [see Dosage and Administration (  2.1  )].  



    5.2 Gastrointestinal (GI) Effects - Risk of Ulceration, Bleeding, and Perforation



  SPRIX is contraindicated in patients with previously documented peptic ulcers and/or GI bleeding [see Contraindications (  4  )]  . Ketorolac tromethamine can cause serious GI adverse events including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach, small intestine, or large intestine, which can be fatal. These serious adverse events can occur at any time, with or without warning symptoms, in patients treated with ketorolac.



 Only one in five patients who develop a serious upper GI adverse event on NSAID therapy is symptomatic. Minor upper GI problems, such as dyspepsia, are common and may also occur at any time during NSAID therapy. The incidence and severity of GI complications increases with increasing dose of, and duration of treatment with, ketorolac. Even short-term therapy is not without risk. In addition to past history of ulcer disease, other factors that increase the risk for GI bleeding in patients treated with NSAIDs include concomitant use of oral corticosteroids or anticoagulants, longer duration of NSAID therapy, smoking, use of alcohol, older age, and poor general health status. Most spontaneous reports of fatal GI events are in elderly or debilitated patients, and therefore, special care should be taken in treating this population.



  To minimize the potential risk for an adverse GI event, the lowest effective dose should be used for the shortest possible duration.  Remain alert for signs and symptoms of GI ulceration and bleeding during NSAID therapy, and promptly initiate additional evaluation and treatment if a serious GI adverse event is suspected. This should include discontinuation of SPRIX until a serious GI adverse event is ruled out. For high risk patients, consider alternate therapies that do not involve NSAIDs. Use great care when giving SPRIX to patients with a history of inflammatory bowel disease (ulcerative colitis, Crohn's disease) as their condition may be exacerbated.



    5.3 Hematological Effects



  Because prostaglandins play an important role in hemostasis and NSAIDs affect platelet aggregation as well, use caution with use of ketorolac tromethamine in patients who have coagulation disorders, and monitor these patients carefully. The effects of NSAIDs other than aspirin on platelet function are reversible. Patients on therapeutic doses of anticoagulants (e.g., heparin or dicumarol derivatives) have an increased risk of bleeding complications if given ketorolac tromethamine concurrently; therefore, administer such concomitant therapy only with extreme caution. The concurrent use of ketorolac tromethamine and therapy that affects hemostasis, including prophylactic low dose heparin (2500 to 5000 units q12h), warfarin and dextrans, has not been studied extensively, but may also be associated with an increased risk of bleeding. Until data from such studies are available, carefully weigh the benefits against the risks and use such concomitant therapy in these patients only with extreme caution. Monitor patients receiving therapy that affects hemostasis closely.



 In clinical trials, serious adverse events related to bleeding were more common in patients treated with SPRIX than placebo. In clinical trials and in postmarketing experience with ketorolac IV and IM dosing, postoperative hematomas and other signs of wound bleeding have been reported in association with peri-operative use. Therefore, use SPRIX with caution in the postoperative setting when hemostasis is critical.



 Anemia is sometimes seen in patients receiving NSAIDs. This may be due to fluid retention, occult or gross GI blood loss, or an incompletely described effect upon erythropoiesis. Do not use SPRIX in patients for whom hemostasis is critical [see Contraindications (  4  ), Drug Interactions (  7.1  ,  7.2  ,  7.10  )].  



    5.4 Renal Effects



  Ketorolac and its metabolites are eliminated primarily by the kidneys. Patients with reduced creatinine clearance will have diminished clearance of the drug [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.4  )].  SPRIX is contraindicated in patients with advanced renal impairment [see Contraindications (  4  )].  



 In patients in whom renal prostaglandins have a compensatory role in the maintenance of renal perfusion, administration of an NSAID may cause a dose-dependent reduction in prostaglandin formation and renal blood flow, which may precipitate overt renal decompensation. Decreased intravascular volume such as when oral intake is poor increases the risks of renal toxicity with NSAIDs. Therefore, patients treated with SPRIX should be adequately hydrated. Discontinuation of NSAID therapy is usually followed by recovery to the pretreatment state.



 Use SPRIX with caution in patients with impaired renal function, heart failure, liver dysfunction, those taking diuretics or ACE inhibitors, and the elderly. Assess the risks and benefits prior to giving SPRIX to these patients, and follow these patients closely during SPRIX therapy. Long-term administration of NSAIDs has resulted in renal papillary necrosis and other renal injury such as interstitial nephritis and nephrotic syndrome.



    5.5 Anaphylactoid Reactions



  As with other NSAIDs, anaphylactoid reactions may occur in patients with or without a history of allergic reactions to aspirin or NSAIDs and in patients without known prior exposure to ketorolac. SPRIX should be discontinued immediately in patients with allergic reactions. SPRIX should not be given to patients with the aspirin triad. This symptom complex typically occurs in asthmatic patients who experience rhinitis with or without nasal polyps, or who exhibit severe, potentially fatal bronchospasm after taking aspirin or other NSAIDs [see Contraindications (  4  ), Warnings and Precautions (  5.11  )].  Emergency help should be sought in cases where an anaphylactoid reaction occurs.



    5.6 Cardiovascular Effects



    *   Cardiovascular (CV) Thrombotic Events  
    Clinical trials of several COX-2 selective and nonselective NSAIDs of up to three years duration have shown an increased risk of serious CV thrombotic events, myocardial infarction and stroke, which can be fatal. All NSAIDs, both COX-2 selective and nonselective, may have a similar risk. Patients with known CV disease or risk factors for CV disease may be at greater risk. To minimize the potential risk for an adverse CV event in patients treated with an NSAID, the lowest effective dose should be used for the shortest duration possible. Physicians and patients should remain alert for the development of such events, even in the absence of previous CV symptoms. Patients should be informed about the signs and/or symptoms of serious CV events and the steps to take if they occur. There is no consistent evidence that concurrent use of aspirin mitigates the increased risk of serious CV thrombotic events associated with NSAID use. The concurrent use of aspirin and an NSAID increases the risk of serious GI events. Two large, controlled clinical trials of a COX-2 selective NSAID for the treatment of pain in the first 10-14 days following CABG surgery found an increased incidence of myocardial infarction and stroke [see Contraindications (  4  ), Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  ), Drug Interactions (  7.2  ,  7.3  ,  7.7  )].  
 

     *   Hypertension  
    NSAIDs can lead to onset of new hypertension or worsening of preexisting hypertension, either of which may contribute to the increased incidence of CV events. Patients taking thiazides or loop diuretics may have impaired response to these therapies when taking NSAIDs [see Drug Interactions (  7.3  )].  
 

     *   Congestive Heart Failure and Edema  
    Fluid retention, edema, retention of NaCl, oliguria, and elevations of serum urea nitrogen and creatinine have been reported in clinical trials with ketorolac. Therefore, only use SPRIX very cautiously in patients with cardiac decompensation or similar conditions.
 

    5.7 Skin Reactions



  NSAIDs, including ketorolac, can cause serious skin adverse events such as exfoliative dermatitis, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome (SJS), and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), which can be fatal. These serious events may occur without warning. Inform patients about the signs and symptoms of serious skin manifestations, and discontinue use of the drug at the first appearance of skin rash or any other sign of hypersensitivity [see Contraindications (  4  )]  .



    5.8 Pregnancy



  Starting at 30 weeks gestation, SPRIX can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman due to an increased risk of premature closure of the ductus arteriosus. If SPRIX is used at or after 30 weeks gestation, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to a fetus [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  )]  .



    5.9 Hepatic Effects



  Use SPRIX with caution in patients with impaired hepatic function or a history of liver disease. Borderline elevations of one or more liver tests may occur in up to 15% of patients taking NSAIDs, including ketorolac. These laboratory abnormalities may progress, may remain unchanged, or may be transient with continuing therapy. Notable elevations of ALT or AST (approximately three or more times the upper limit of normal) have been reported in approximately 1% of patients in clinical trials with NSAIDs. In addition, rare cases of severe hepatic reactions, including jaundice, fulminant hepatitis, liver necrosis, and hepatic failure, some of them with fatal outcomes, have been reported [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  ,  5.6  ),Clinical Pharmacology (  12.4  )]  .



 Evaluate patients with symptoms and/or signs suggesting liver dysfunction, or in whom an abnormal liver test has occurred, for evidence of the development of a more severe hepatic reaction while on therapy with SPRIX. If clinical signs and symptoms consistent with liver disease develop, or if systemic manifestations occur (e.g., eosinophilia, rash, etc.), discontinue SPRIX.



    5.10 Inflammation and Fever



  The pharmacological activity of SPRIX in reducing inflammation and fever may diminish the utility of these diagnostic signs in detecting infections.



    5.11 Preexisting Asthma



  Patients with asthma may have aspirin-sensitive asthma. The use of aspirin in patients with aspirin-sensitive asthma has been associated with severe bronchospasm which can be fatal. Since cross reactivity, including bronchospasm, between aspirin and other NSAIDs has been reported in such aspirin-sensitive patients, do not administer SPRIX to patients with this form of aspirin sensitivity, and use with caution in patients with preexisting asthma [see Contraindications (  4  ), Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  .



    5.12 Eye Exposure



  Avoid contact of SPRIX with the eyes. If eye contact occurs, wash out the eye with water or saline, and consult a physician if irritation persists for more than an hour.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
