<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="sprycel" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6    ADVERSE REACTIONS

    EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=10%) in patients with newly diagnosed chronic phase CML included myelosuppression, fluid retention, diarrhea, headache, musculoskeletal pain, and rash. Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=20%) in patients with resistance or intolerance to prior imatinib therapy included myelosuppression, fluid retention events, diarrhea, headache, dyspnea, skin rash, fatigue, nausea, and hemorrhage.  (6.1)  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Bristol-Myers Squibb at 1-800-721-5072 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Myelosuppression [see Dosage and Administration  (2.3)   and Warnings and Precautions  (5.1)  ] . 
 *  Bleeding related events [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.2)  ] . 
 *  Fluid retention [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.3)  ] . 
 *  QT prolongation [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.4)  ] . 
 *  Congestive heart failure, left ventricular dysfunction, and myocardial infarction [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.5)  ] . 
 *  Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.6)  ] . 
    Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.
 

 The data described below reflect exposure to SPRYCEL in clinical studies including 258 patients with newly diagnosed chronic phase CML and in 2182 patients with imatinib resistant or intolerant CML or Ph+ ALL.



 In the newly diagnosed chronic phase CML trial, the median duration of therapy was 18 months; the median average daily dose was 99 mg.



 In the imatinib resistant or intolerant CML or Ph+ ALL clinical trials, patients had a minimum of 2 years follow-up (starting dosage 100 mg once daily, 140 mg once daily, 50 mg twice daily, or 70 mg twice daily). Among patients with chronic phase CML and resistance or intolerance to prior imatinib therapy, the median duration of treatment with SPRYCEL 100 mg once daily was 24 months (range 1-33 months). The median duration of treatment with SPRYCEL 140 mg once daily was 15 months (range 0.03-36 months) for accelerated phase CML, 3 months (range 0.03-29 months) for myeloid blast phase CML, and 3 months (range 0.1-10 months) for lymphoid blast CML.



 The majority of SPRYCEL-treated patients experienced adverse reactions at some time. In the newly diagnosed chronic phase CML trial, drug was discontinued for adverse reactions in 6% of SPRYCEL-treated patients. Among patients with resistance or intolerance to prior imatinib therapy, the rates of discontinuation for adverse reaction were 15% in chronic phase CML, 16% in accelerated phase CML, 15% in myeloid blast phase CML, 8% in lymphoid blast phase CML, and 8% in Ph+ ALL. In a dose-optimization study in patients with resistance or intolerance to prior imatinib therapy and chronic phase CML, the rate of discontinuation for adverse reaction was lower in patients treated with 100 mg once daily than in patients treated with other dosing regimens (10% and 16%, respectively).



 The most frequently reported adverse reactions reported in &gt;=10% of patients in newly diagnosed chronic phase CML included myelosuppression, fluid retention events (pleural effusion, superficial localized edema, generalized edema), diarrhea, headache, musculoskeletal pain, and rash. Pleural effusions were reported in 31 patients (see Table 2).



 The most frequently reported adverse reactions reported in &gt;=20% of patients with resistance or intolerance to prior imatinib therapy included myelosuppression, fluid retention events, diarrhea, headache, dyspnea, skin rash, fatigue, nausea, and hemorrhage.



 The most frequently reported serious adverse reactions in patients with newly diagnosed chronic phase CML included pleural effusion (2%), hemorrhage (2%), congestive heart failure (1%), and pyrexia (1%). The most frequently reported serious adverse reactions in patients with resistance or intolerance to prior imatinib therapy included pleural effusion (11%), gastrointestinal bleeding (4%), febrile neutropenia (4%), dyspnea (3%), pneumonia (3%), pyrexia (3%), diarrhea (3%), infection (2%), congestive heart failure/cardiac dysfunction (2%), pericardial effusion (1%), and CNS hemorrhage (1%).



   6.1   Chronic Myeloid Leukemia (CML)

  Adverse reactions (excluding laboratory abnormalities) that were reported in at least 10% of patients are shown in Table 2 for newly diagnosed patients with chronic phase CML and Table 3 for CML patients with resistance or intolerance to prior imatinib therapy.



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=10% of Patients with Newly Diagnosed Chronic Phase CML 
                                             All Grades       Grade 3/4       
                                           SPRYCEL(n=258)   Imatinib(n=258)  SPRYCEL(n=258)   Imatinib(n=258)   
   Preferred Term                            Percent (%) of Patients     
  
   a  Includes cardiac failure acute, cardiac failure congestive, cardiomyopathy, diastolic dysfunction, ejection fraction decreased, and left ventricular dysfunction.   
   b  Includes erythema, erythema multiforme, rash, rash generalized, rash macular, rash papular, rash pustular, skin exfoliation, and rash vesicular.   
   c  Adverse reaction of special interest with &lt;10% frequency.   
   d  Includes conjunctival hemorrhage, ear hemorrhage, ecchymosis, epistaxis, eye hemorrhage, gingival bleeding, hematoma, hematuria, hemoptysis, intra-abdominal hematoma, petechiae, scleral hemorrhage, uterine hemorrhage, and vaginal hemorrhage.   
  
 Fluid retention                           23               43               1                1                 
     Pleural effusion                      12               0                &lt;1               0                 
     Superficial localized edema           10               36               0                &lt;1                
     Generalized edema                     3                7                0                0                 
     Congestive heart failure/        cardiac dysfunction  a    2                1                &lt;1               &lt;1                
     Pericardial effusion                  2                &lt;1               &lt;1               0                 
     Pulmonary hypertension                1                0                0                0                 
     Pulmonary edema                       &lt;1               0                0                0                 
 Diarrhea                                  18               19               &lt;1               1                 
 Headache                                  12               10               0                0                 
 Musculoskeletal pain                      12               16               0                &lt;1                
 Rash  b                                   11               17               0                1                 
 Nausea                                    9                21               0                0                 
 Fatigue                                   8                11               &lt;1               0                 
 Myalgia                                   6                12               0                0                 
 Hemorrhage  c                             6                5                1                1                 
     Gastrointestinal bleeding             2                &lt;1               1                0                 
     Other bleeding  d                     5                5                0                1                 
     CNS bleeding                          0                &lt;1               0                &lt;1                
 Vomiting                                  5                10               0                0                 
 Muscle inflammation                       4                19               0                &lt;1                
     Table 3: Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=10% of Patients with CML Resistant or Intolerant to Prior Imatinib Therapy 
                                 100 mg Once Daily      140 mg Once Daily     
                                 Chronic(n=165)      Accelerated(n=157)      Myeloid Blast(n=74)      Lymphoid Blast(n=33)     
   Preferred Term                All Grades      Grade 3/4      All Grades      Grade 3/4      All Grades      Grade 3/4      All Grades      Grade 3/4     
   Percent (%) of Patients      
  
   a  Includes ventricular dysfunction, cardiac failure, cardiac failure congestive, cardiomyopathy, congestive cardiomyopathy, diastolic dysfunction, ejection fraction decreased, and ventricular failure.   
   b  Includes drug eruption, erythema, erythema multiforme, erythrosis, exfoliative rash, generalized erythema, genital rash, heat rash, milia, rash, rash erythematous, rash follicular, rash generalized, rash macular, rash maculopapular, rash papular, rash pruritic, rash pustular, skin exfoliation, skin irritation, urticaria vesiculosa, and rash vesicular.   
  
 Fluid Retention               34        4         35         8         34        7         21         6          
    Superficial localized edema  18        0         18         1         14        0         3          0          
    Pleural effusion           18        2         21         7         20        7         21         6          
       Generalized edema       3         0         1          0         3         0         0          0          
       Pericardial effusion    2         1         3          1         0         0         0          0          
       Congestive heart failure/          cardiac dysfunction  a    0         0         0          0         4         0         0          0          
       Pulmonary edema         0         0         1          0         4         3         0          0          
 Headache                      33        1         27         1         18        1         15         3          
 Diarrhea                      27        2         31         3         20        5         18         0          
 Fatigue                       24        2         19         2         20        1         9          3          
 Dyspnea                       20        2         20         3         15        3         3          3          
 Musculoskeletal pain          19        2         11         0         8         1         0          0          
 Nausea                        18        1         19         1         23        1         21         3          
 Skin rash  b                  17        2         15         0         16        1         21         0          
 Myalgia                       13        0         7          1         7         1         3          0          
 Arthralgia                    12        1         10         0         5         1         0          0          
 Infection (including bacterial,    viral, fungal, and    non-specified)  12        1         10         6         14        7         9          0          
 Abdominal pain                12        1         6          0         8         3         3          0          
 Hemorrhage                    11        1         26         8         19        9         24         9          
    Gastrointestinal bleeding  2         1         8          6         9         7         9          3          
    CNS bleeding               0         0         1          1         0         0         3          3          
 Vomiting                      7         1         11         1         12        0         15         0          
 Pyrexia                       5         1         11         2         18        3         6          0          
 Febrile neutropenia           1         1         4          4         12        12        12         12         
        Laboratory Abnormalities
   Myelosuppression was commonly reported in all patient populations. The frequency of Grade 3 or 4 neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, and anemia was higher in patients with advanced phase CML than in chronic phase CML (Tables 4 and 5). Myelosuppression was reported in patients with normal baseline laboratory values as well as in patients with pre-existing laboratory abnormalities.



 In patients who experienced severe myelosuppression, recovery generally occurred following dose interruption or reduction; permanent discontinuation of treatment occurred in 2% of patients with newly diagnosed chronic phase CML and 5% of patients with resistance or intolerance to prior imatinib therapy  [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.1)  ]  .



 Grade 3 or 4 elevations of transaminase or bilirubin and Grade 3 or 4 hypocalcemia, hypokalemia, and hypophosphatemia were reported in patients with all phases of CML but were reported with an increased frequency in patients with myeloid or lymphoid blast phase CML. Elevations in transaminase or bilirubin were usually managed with dose reduction or interruption. Patients developing Grade 3 or 4 hypocalcemia during the course of SPRYCEL therapy often had recovery with oral calcium supplementation.



 Laboratory abnormalities reported in patients with newly diagnosed chronic phase CML are shown in Table 4. There were no discontinuations of SPRYCEL therapy in this patient population due to biochemical laboratory parameters.



 Table 4: CTC Grade 3/4 Laboratory Abnormalities in Patients with Newly Diagnosed Chronic Phase CML 
                                           SPRYCEL(n=258)                  Imatinib(n=258)                  
                                           Percent (%) of Patients          
  
 CTC grades: neutropenia (Grade 3 &gt;=0.5-&lt;1.0 * 10  9  /L, Grade 4 &lt;0.5 * 10  9  /L); thrombocytopenia (Grade 3 &gt;=25-&lt;50 * 10  9  /L, Grade 4 &lt;25 * 10  9  /L); anemia (hemoglobin Grade 3 &gt;=65-&lt;80 g/L, Grade 4 &lt;65 g/L); elevated creatinine (Grade 3 &gt;3-6 * upper limit of normal range (ULN), Grade 4 &gt;6 * ULN); elevated bilirubin (Grade 3 &gt;3-10 * ULN, Grade 4 &gt;10 * ULN); elevated SGOT or SGPT (Grade 3 &gt;5-20 * ULN, Grade 4 &gt;20 * ULN); hypocalcemia (Grade 3 &lt;7.0-6.0 mg/dL, Grade 4 &lt;6.0 mg/dL); hypophosphatemia (Grade 3 &lt;2.0-1.0 mg/dL, Grade 4 &lt;1.0 mg/dL); hypokalemia (Grade 3 &lt;3.0-2.5 mmol/L, Grade 4 &lt;2.5 mmol/L).   
  
   Hematology Parameters                                                                                    
     Neutropenia                           22                              20                               
     Thrombocytopenia                      19                              10                               
     Anemia                                11                              7                                
   Biochemistry Parameters                                                                                  
     Hypophosphatemia                      5                               24                               
     Hypokalemia                           0                               2                                
     Hypocalcemia                          3                               2                                
     Elevated SGPT (ALT)                   &lt;1                              1                                
     Elevated SGOT (AST)                   &lt;1                              1                                
     Elevated Bilirubin                    1                               0                                
     Elevated Creatinine                   &lt;1                              1                                
      Laboratory abnormalities reported in patients with CML resistant or intolerant to imatinib who received the recommended starting doses of SPRYCEL are shown by disease phase in Table 5.
 

 Table 5: CTC Grade 3/4 Laboratory Abnormalities in Clinical Studies of CML: Resistance or Intolerance to Prior Imatinib Therapy 
                                                     Advanced Phase CML     
                                 Chronic Phase CML      140 mg Once Daily     
                                 100 mg Once Daily    (n=165)      Accelerated Phase    (n=157)      Myeloid Blast Phase    (n=74)      Lymphoid Blast Phase    (n=33)     
                                   Percent (%) of Patients       
  
 CTC grades: neutropenia (Grade 3 &gt;=0.5-&lt;1.0 * 10  9  /L, Grade 4 &lt;0.5 * 10  9  /L); thrombocytopenia (Grade 3 &gt;=25-&lt;50 * 10  9  /L, Grade 4 &lt;25 * 10  9  /L); anemia (hemoglobin Grade 3 &gt;=65-&lt;80 g/L, Grade 4 &lt;65 g/L); elevated creatinine (Grade 3 &gt;3-6 * upper limit of normal range (ULN), Grade 4 &gt;6 * ULN); elevated bilirubin (Grade 3 &gt;3-10 * ULN, Grade 4 &gt;10 * ULN); elevated SGOT or SGPT (Grade 3 &gt;5-20 * ULN, Grade 4 &gt;20 * ULN); hypocalcemia (Grade 3 &lt;7.0-6.0 mg/dL, Grade 4 &lt;6.0 mg/dL); hypophosphatemia (Grade 3 &lt;2.0-1.0 mg/dL, Grade 4 &lt;1.0 mg/dL); hypokalemia (Grade 3 &lt;3.0-2.5 mmol/L, Grade 4 &lt;2.5 mmol/L).   
  
   Hematology Parameters                                                                                        
     Neutropenia               36                  58                  77                  79                   
     Thrombocytopenia          23                  63                  78                  85                   
     Anemia                    13                  47                  74                  52                   
   Biochemistry Parameters                                                                                      
     Hypophosphatemia          10                  13                  12                  18                   
     Hypokalemia               2                   7                   11                  15                   
     Hypocalcemia              &lt;1                  4                   9                   12                   
     Elevated SGPT (ALT)       0                   2                   5                   3                    
     Elevated SGOT (AST)       &lt;1                  0                   4                   3                    
     Elevated Bilirubin        &lt;1                  1                   3                   6                    
     Elevated Creatinine       0                   2                   8                   0                    
        6.2   Philadelphia Chromosome-Positive Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (Ph+ ALL)
   A total of 135 patients with Ph+ ALL were treated with SPRYCEL in clinical studies. The median duration of treatment was 3 months (range 0.03-31 months). The safety profile of patients with Ph+ ALL was similar to those with lymphoid blast phase CML. The most frequently reported adverse reactions included fluid retention events, such as pleural effusion (24%) and superficial edema (19%), and gastrointestinal disorders, such as diarrhea (31%), nausea (24%), and vomiting (16%). Hemorrhage (19%), pyrexia (17%), rash (16%), and dyspnea (16%) were also frequently reported. The most frequently reported serious adverse reactions included pleural effusion (11%), gastrointestinal bleeding (7%), febrile neutropenia (6%), infection (5%), pyrexia (4%), pneumonia (3%), diarrhea (3%), nausea (2%), vomiting (2%), and colitis (2%).



   6.3   Additional Data From Clinical Trials

  The following adverse reactions were reported in patients in the SPRYCEL clinical studies at a frequency of 1%-&lt;10%, 0.1%-&lt;1%, or &lt;0.1%. These events are included on the basis of clinical relevance.



     Gastrointestinal Disorders:      1%-&lt;10%  - mucosal inflammation (including mucositis/stomatitis), dyspepsia, abdominal distension, constipation, gastritis, colitis (including neutropenic colitis), oral soft tissue disorder;  0.1%-&lt;1%  - ascites, dysphagia, anal fissure, upper gastrointestinal ulcer, esophagitis, pancreatitis;  &lt;0.1%  - protein losing gastroenteropathy.



     General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:      1%-&lt;10% -  asthenia, pain, chest pain, chills;  0.1%-&lt;1%  - malaise, temperature intolerance.



     Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:      1%-&lt;10%  - pruritus, alopecia, acne, dry skin, hyperhidrosis, urticaria, dermatitis (including eczema);  0.1%-&lt;1%  - pigmentation disorder, skin ulcer, bullous conditions, photosensitivity, nail disorder, acute febrile neutrophilic dermatosis, panniculitis, palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia syndrome.



   Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal Disorders:    1%-&lt;10%  - cough, lung infiltration, pneumonitis, pulmonary hypertension;  0.1%-&lt;1%  - asthma, bronchospasm;  &lt;0.1%  - acute respiratory distress syndrome.



     Nervous System Disorders:      1%-&lt;10%  - neuropathy (including peripheral neuropathy), dizziness, dysgeusia, somnolence;  0.1%-&lt;1%  - amnesia, tremor, syncope;  &lt;0.1%  - convulsion, cerebrovascular accident, transient ischemic attack, optic neuritis.



     Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:      1%-&lt;10%  - pancytopenia;  &lt;0.1%  - aplasia pure red cell.



     Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:      1%-&lt;10% -  muscular weakness;  0.1%-&lt;1%  - musculoskeletal stiffness, rhabdomyolysis;  &lt;0.1% -  tendonitis.



     Investigations:      1%-&lt;10%  - weight increased, weight decreased;  0.1%-&lt;1%  - blood creatine phosphokinase increased.



     Infections and Infestations:      1%-&lt;10%  - pneumonia (including bacterial, viral, and fungal), upper respiratory tract infection/inflammation, herpes virus infection, enterocolitis infection;  0.1%-&lt;1%  - sepsis (including fatal outcomes).



     Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:      1%-&lt;10%  - anorexia, appetite disturbances;  0.1%-&lt;1%  - hyperuricemia, hypoalbuminemia.



     Cardiac Disorders:      1%-&lt;10%  - arrhythmia (including tachycardia), palpitations;  0.1%-&lt;1%  - angina pectoris, cardiomegaly, pericarditis, ventricular arrhythmia (including ventricular tachycardia);  &lt;0.1%  - cor pulmonale, myocarditis, acute coronary syndrome.



     Eye Disorders:      1%-&lt;10%  - visual disorder (including visual disturbance, vision blurred, and visual acuity reduced), dry eye;  0.1% -&lt;1%  - conjunctivitis.



     Vascular Disorders:      1%-&lt;10%  - flushing, hypertension;  0.1%-&lt;1%  - hypotension, thrombophlebitis;  &lt;0.1%  - livedo reticularis.



     Psychiatric Disorders:      1%-&lt;10%  - insomnia, depression;  0.1%-&lt;1%  - anxiety, affect lability, confusional state, libido decreased.



     Reproductive System and Breast Disorders:      0.1%-&lt;1%  - gynecomastia, menstruation irregular.



     Injury, Poisoning, and Procedural Complications:      1%-&lt;10%  - contusion.



     Ear and Labyrinth Disorders:      1%-&lt;10% -  tinnitus;  0.1%-&lt;1%  - vertigo.



     Hepatobiliary Disorders:      0.1%-&lt;1%  - cholestasis, cholecystitis, hepatitis.



     Renal and Urinary Disorders:      0.1%-&lt;1%  - urinary frequency, renal failure, proteinuria.



     Neoplasms Benign, Malignant, and Unspecified:      0.1%-&lt;1%  - tumor lysis syndrome.



     Immune System Disorders:      0.1%-&lt;1%  - hypersensitivity (including erythema nodosum).



   6.4   Postmarketing Experience

  The following additional adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of SPRYCEL. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Cardiac disorders:  atrial fibrillation/atrial flutter



   Vascular disorders:  thrombosis/embolism (including pulmonary embolism, deep vein thrombosis)



   Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders:  interstitial lung disease, pulmonary arterial hypertension
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5    WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



     EXCERPT:    *   Myelosuppression: Severe thrombocytopenia, neutropenia, and anemia may occur and require dose interruption or reduction. Monitor complete blood counts regularly.  (2.3  ,  5.1  ,  6.1)   
 *   Bleeding Related Events (mostly associated with severe thrombocytopenia): CNS and gastrointestinal hemorrhages, including fatalities, have occurred. Severe hemorrhage may require treatment interruptions and transfusions. Use SPRYCEL with caution in patients requiring medications that inhibit platelet function or anticoagulants.  (5.2  ,  6.1)   
 *   Fluid Retention: SPRYCEL is associated with fluid retention, sometimes severe, including ascites, edema, and pleural and pericardial effusions. Manage with appropriate supportive care measures.  (5.3  ,  6.1)   
 *   QT Prolongation: Use SPRYCEL with caution in patients who have or may develop prolongation of the QT interval.  (5.4)   
 *   Congestive Heart Failure, Left Ventricular Dysfunction and Myocardial Infarction: Monitor patients for signs and symptoms consistent with cardiac dysfunction and treat appropriately.  (5.5  ,  6.1)   
 *   Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension (PAH): SPRYCEL may increase the risk of developing PAH which may be reversible on discontinuation. Evaluate patients for signs and symptoms of underlying cardiopulmonary disease prior to initiating SPRYCEL and during treatment.  (5.6)   
 *   Use in Pregnancy: Fetal harm may occur when administered to a pregnant woman. Women should be advised of the potential hazard to the fetus and to avoid becoming pregnant.  (5.7  ,  8.1)   
    
 

   5.1   Myelosuppression



  Treatment with SPRYCEL is associated with severe (NCI CTC Grade 3 or 4) thrombocytopenia, neutropenia, and anemia. Their occurrence is more frequent in patients with advanced phase CML or Ph+ ALL than in chronic phase CML. In a dose-optimization study in patients with resistance or intolerance to prior imatinib therapy and chronic phase CML, Grade 3 or 4 myelosuppression was reported less frequently in patients treated with 100 mg once daily than in patients treated with other dosing regimens.



 Perform complete blood counts weekly for the first 2 months and then monthly thereafter, or as clinically indicated. Myelosuppression was generally reversible and usually managed by withholding SPRYCEL temporarily or dose reduction [see Dosage and Administration  (2.3)    and Adverse Reactions  (6.1)  ]  .



    5.2   Bleeding Related Events



  In addition to causing thrombocytopenia in human subjects, dasatinib caused platelet dysfunction in vitro  . In all clinical studies, severe central nervous system (CNS) hemorrhages, including fatalities, occurred in 1% of patients receiving SPRYCEL. Severe gastrointestinal hemorrhage, including fatalities, occurred in 4% of patients and generally required treatment interruptions and transfusions. Other cases of severe hemorrhage occurred in 2% of patients. Most bleeding events were associated with severe thrombocytopenia.



 Patients were excluded from participation in initial SPRYCEL clinical studies if they took medications that inhibit platelet function or anticoagulants. In subsequent trials, the use of anticoagulants, aspirin, and non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) was allowed concurrently with SPRYCEL if the platelet count was &gt;50,000-75,000 per microliter. Exercise caution if patients are required to take medications that inhibit platelet function or anticoagulants.



    5.3   Fluid Retention



  SPRYCEL is associated with fluid retention. In clinical trials, severe fluid retention was reported in up to 10% of patients. Ascites and generalized edema were each reported in &lt;1% of patients. Severe pulmonary edema was reported in 1% of patients. Patients who develop symptoms suggestive of pleural effusion, such as dyspnea or dry cough, should be evaluated by chest X-ray. Severe pleural effusion may require thoracentesis and oxygen therapy. Fluid retention events were typically managed by supportive care measures that include diuretics or short courses of steroids. In dose-optimization studies, fluid retention events were reported less frequently with once daily dosing than with other dosing regimens.



    5.4   QT Prolongation



   In vitro  data suggest that dasatinib has the potential to prolong cardiac ventricular repolarization (QT interval). Of the 2440 patients with CML treated with SPRYCEL in clinical studies, 15 patients (&lt;1%) had QTc prolongation reported as an adverse reaction. Twenty-two patients (1%) experienced a QTcF &gt;500 ms. In 865 patients with leukemia treated with SPRYCEL in five Phase 2 single-arm studies, the maximum mean changes in QTcF (90% upper bound CI) from baseline ranged from 7.0 ms to 13.4 ms.



 Administer SPRYCEL with caution to patients who have or may develop prolongation of QTc. These include patients with hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia, patients with congenital long QT syndrome, patients taking anti-arrhythmic medicines or other medicinal products that lead to QT prolongation, and cumulative high-dose anthracycline therapy. Correct hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia prior to SPRYCEL administration.



    5.5   Congestive Heart Failure, Left Ventricular Dysfunction, and Myocardial Infarction



  Cardiac adverse reactions were reported in 5.8% of 258 patients taking SPRYCEL, including 1.6% of patients with cardiomyopathy, heart failure congestive, diastolic dysfunction, fatal myocardial infarction, and left ventricular dysfunction. Monitor patients for signs or symptoms consistent with cardiac dysfunction and treat appropriately.



    5.6   Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension



   SPRYCEL may increase the risk of developing pulmonary arterial hypertension (PAH) which may occur anytime after initiation, including after more than one year of treatment. Manifestations include dyspnea, fatigue, hypoxia, and fluid retention. PAH may be reversible on discontinuation of SPRYCEL. Evaluate patients for signs and symptoms of underlying cardiopulmonary disease prior to initiating SPRYCEL and during treatment. If PAH is confirmed, SPRYCEL should be permanently discontinued.  



    5.7   Use in Pregnancy



  SPRYCEL may cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. In nonclinical studies, at plasma concentrations below those observed in humans receiving therapeutic doses of dasatinib, embryo-fetal toxicities, including skeletal malformations, were observed in rats and rabbits. There are no adequate and well-controlled studies of SPRYCEL in pregnant women. Women of childbearing potential should be advised to avoid becoming pregnant while receiving treatment with SPRYCEL [see Use in Specific Populations  (8.1)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
