<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="standardized5" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      ADVERSE REACTIONS      Adverse reactions include, but are not necessarily limited to urticaria; itching; edema of extremities; respiratory wheezing or asthma; dyspnea; cyanosis; tachycardia; lacrimation; marked perspiration; flushing of face, neck or upper chest; mild persistent clearing of throat; hacking cough or persistent sneezing.1)    Local ReactionsA mild burning immediately after injection is expected; this usually subsides in 10-20 seconds.Prolonged pain or pain radiating up arm is usually the result of intramuscular injection, making this injection route undesirable.  Subcutaneous injection is the recommended route.    Small amounts of erythema and swelling at the site of injection are common.  Reactions should not be considered significant unless they persist for at least 24 hours or exceed 50 mm in diameter.    Larger local reactions are not only uncomfortable, but indicate the possibility of a severe systemic reaction if dosage is increased.  In such cases dosage should be reduced to the last level not causing reaction and maintained for two or three treatments before cautiously increasing.    Large, persistent local reactions or minor exacerbations of the patient's allergic symptoms may be treated by local cold applications and/or use of oral antihistamines.2)    Systemic Reactions    Systemic reactions range from mild exaggeration of patient's allergic symptoms to anaphylactic reactions.  12    Very sensitive patients may show a rapid response.  It cannot be overemphasized that, under certain unpredictable combinations of circumstances, anaphylactic shock is always a possibility.  Fatalities are rare but can occur.  16    Other possible adverse reactions include unusual swelling and/or tenderness at injection site, rhinorrhea, sneezing, coughing, wheezing, shortness of breath, nausea, dizziness, fainting, pallor, bradycardia, hypotension, angioedema, conjunctivitis, rhinitis, and urticaria.  8,9       Careful attention to dosage and administration limits such reactions.  Allergenic extracts are highly potent to sensitive individuals and OVERDOSE could result in anaphylactic symptoms.  Therefore, it is imperative that physicians administering allergenic extracts understand and prepare for treatment of severe reactions.  Refer to "OVERDOSAGE" section.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

    WARNINGS        Standardized Short Ragweed allergenic extract is intended for use by, or under the guidance of, physicians who are experienced in the administration of allergenic extracts for diagnosis and/or immunotherapy and the emergency care of anaphylaxis.      Patients being switched from other manufacturers' extracts to Antigen Laboratories' allergenic extracts should be started as though they were receiving treatment for the first time.        (See "WARNINGS" section below.)     Severe systemic reactions may occur with all allergenic extracts.  In certain individuals, these life-threatening reactions may result in death.  Patients should be observed for at least 20 minutes following allergenic extract injections.  Treatment and emergency measures, as well as personnel trained in their use, must be available in the event of a life-threatening reaction.  Sensitive patients may experience severe anaphylactic reactions resulting in respiratory obstruction, shock, coma and/or death.  Patients being switched from one lot of extract to another lot from the same manufacturer should have the dose reduced by 75%.    Report serious adverse events to MedWatch, 5600 Fishers Lane, Rockville, MD 20852-9787, phone 1-800-FDA-1088.Allergenic extracts should not be injected intravenously.  Deep subcutaneous routes have proven to be safe. See the "WARNINGS", "PRECAUTIONS", "ADVERSE REACTIONS" and "OVERDOSAGE" sections.    Patients receiving beta-blockers may not be responsive to epinephrine or inhaled bronchodilators.  Patients with respiratory obstruction not responding to parenteral or inhaled bronchodilators may require theophylline, oxygen, intubation and life support systems.  Parenteral fluid and/or plasma expanders may be utilized for treatment of shock.  Adrenocorticosteroids may be administered parenterally or intravenously.  Refer to "ADVERSE REACTIONS" section.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
