<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="standardized6" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6 ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  Allergenic extracts including Standardized Cat Hair can cause local reactions at the injection site, which may include erythema, itching, swelling, tenderness and pain.  3  Additionally, systemic reactions, which may indicate anaphylaxis, can occur and may include generalized skin erythema, urticaria, pruritus, angioedema, rhinitis, wheezing, chest tightness, laryngeal edema and hypotension.



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions, occuring in over 25% of all patients, are local reactions at the injection site (e.g., erythema, itching, swelling, tenderness, pain).  (6)  Systemic reactions, occurring in &lt;= 7% of patients, include generalized skin erythema, urticaria, pruritus, angioedema, rhinitis, wheezing, laryngeal edema, and hypotension. These can be fatal.  (6)    To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GREER Laboratories, Inc. at 1-800-438-0088 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

    FULL PRESCRIBING INFORMATION  




 WARNING: SEVERE ALLERGIC REACTIONSCat Hair allergenic extract can cause severe life-threatening systemic reactions, including anaphylaxis. (5.1)Do not administer Cat Hair allergenic extract to patients with severe, unstable, or uncontrolled asthma. (4)Observe patients in the office for at least 30 minutes following treatment. Emergency measures and personnel trained in their use must be available immediately in the event of a life-threatening reaction. (5.1)Patients with extreme sensitivity to Cat Hair allergenic extract, those on an accelerated immunotherapy build-up schedule, switching to another allergenic lot, and those receiving high doses of the Cat Hair allergenic extract or are also exposed to similar allergens may be at increased risk of a severe allergic reaction. (5.1)Cat Hair allergenic extract may not be suitable for patients with certain underlying medical conditions that may reduce their ability to survive a systemic reaction. (5.1)Cat Hair allergenic extract may not be suitable for patients who are receiving beta blockers as they may be unresponsive to epinephrine. (5.2)Standardized Cat Hair Allergenic Extract with potency labeling in Bioequivalent Allergy Units/milliliter is not interchangeable with Standardized Cat Pelt Allergenic Extracts labeled in Bioequivalent Allergy Units/milliliter. (5.3)   
    
 WARNING: SEVERE ALLERGIC REACTIONSSee full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.Cat Hair allergenic extract can cause severe life-threatening systemic reactions, including anaphylaxis. (5.1)Do not administer Cat Hair allergenic extract to patients with severe, unstable or uncontrolled asthma. (4)Observe patients in the office for at least 30 minutes following treatment. Emergency measures and personnel trained in their use must be available immediately in the event of a life-threatening reaction. (5.1)Patients with extreme sensitivity, on an accelerated immunotherapy build-up, switching to another lot, or receiving high doses of Cat Hair extract, or those also exposed to similar allergens may be at increased risk of a severe allergic reaction. (5.1)Cat Hair allergenic extract may not be suitable for patients with certain underlying medical conditions that may reduce their ability to survive a systemic reaction, or who are receiving beta blockers as they may be unresponsive to epinephrine. (5.1,5.2)Cat Hair extracts with potency labeling in Bioequivalent Allergy Units/milliliter is not interchangeable with Cat Pelt extracts labeled in Bioequivalent Allergy Units/milliliter. (5.3)   
        EXCERPT:   
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">     5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



  EXCERPT:   Severe allergic reactions have occurred following the administration of other allergenic extracts and may occur in individuals following the administration of Cat Hair allergenic extract in the following situations:



 *  Extreme sensitivity to cat hair, or receiving high doses of Cat Hair extract or concomitant exposure to similar environmental allergens. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Receiving an accelerated immunotherapy build-up schedule (e.g., "rush" immunotherapy), or changing from one allergenic lot to another. (  5.1  ) 
    
 

       5.1 Serious Systemic Reactions  



  Severe allergic reactions have occurred following the administration of other allergenic extracts and may occur in individuals following the administration of Standardized Cat Hair Allergenic Extract in the following situations:



 *  Extreme sensitivities to Cat Hair allergenic extract. 
 *  Receiving an accelerated immunotherapy build-up schedule (e.g., "rush" immunotherapy). 
 *  Receiving high doses of Cat Hair allergenic extracts or concomitant exposure to similar environmental allergens. 
 *  Changing from one allergenic lot to another allergenic lot. 
    High-risk patients have had fatal reactions. In addition, patients who are not high-risk, but are on beta blockers, have had fatal reactions because beta blockers interfere with beta adrenergics, such as epinephrine, used in the treatment of anaphylaxis.
 

 Administer Cat Hair Allergenic Extract in a healthcare setting under the supervision of a physician prepared to manage a severe systemic or a severe local allergic reaction. Observe patients in the office for at least 30 minutes following administration.  3  



        5.2 Patients on Beta Blockers  



  Patients receiving beta blockers may be unresponsive to the usual doses of epinephrine used to treat serious systemic reactions, including anaphylaxis [see  Drug Interactions  (  7.1  )].



        5.3 Cross-Reactions and Dose Sensitivity  



  GREER Standardized Cat Hair Allergenic Extract is labeled in BAU/milliliter. This allergenic extract is not interchangeable with Standardized Cat Pelt Extract or with cat extracts labeled in Allergy Units.



    Determine the initial dilution of allergenic extract, starting dose, and progression of dosage based on the patient's history and results of skin tests  1  [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ]. Strongly positive skin tests can be an indicator for potential systemic reactions.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
