<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="staxyn" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions with the use of STAXYN (vardenafil) are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *    Cardiovascular effects [see Contraindications (  4.1  ) and Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *    Priapism [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *    QT Prolongation [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
 *    Effects on eye [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *    Sudden hearing loss [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
      EXCERPT:     Adverse reactions reported by &gt;= 2% of patients treated with STAXYN: Headache, flushing, nasal congestion, dyspepsia, dizziness, back pain. (  6.1  )  
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact BayerHealthCare Pharmaceuticals at 1-888-84-BAYER (1-888-842-2937) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   STAXYN  : Safety of STAXYN was evaluated in two identical multi-national, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trials. In both pivotal studies, enrollment was stratified so that approximately 50% of patients were &gt;=65 years old. Approximately 8% (n=29) were &gt;=75 years old. An integrated analysis of both studies included a total of 355 subjects that received STAXYN compared to 340 subjects that received placebo (mean age was 61.7, range 21.0 to 88.0; 68% White, 5% Black, 6% Asian, 11% Hispanic and 11% Other). The discontinuation rates due to adverse reactions were 1.4% for STAXYN compared to 0.6% for placebo. Table 1 below details the most frequently reported adverse reactions.



 Table 1: Adverse drug reactions reported by &gt;=2% of the patients treated with STAXYN and more frequent on drug than placebo in controlled trials 
  Adverse Drug Reaction                                     STAXYN  (n=355)          Placebo  (n=340)       
  Headache                                                  14.4%                    1.8%                   
  Flushing                                                  7.6%                     0.6%                   
  Nasal Congestion                                          3.1%                     0.3%                   
  Dyspepsia                                                 2.8%                     0%                     
  Dizziness                                                 2.3%                     0%                     
  Back Pain                                                 2%                       0.3%                   
          
 

 Adverse drug reactions reported in the STAXYN placebo controlled trials were comparable to the adverse drug reactions reported in earlier vardenafil film-coated tablets placebo controlled trials.



   All Vardenafil Studies:  Vardenafil film-coated tablets and STAXYN has been administered to over 17,000 men (mean age 54.5, range 18-89 years; 70% White, 5% Black, 13% Asian, 4% Hispanic and 8% Other) during controlled and uncontrolled clinical trials worldwide. The number of patients treated for 6 months or longer was 3357, and 1350 patients were treated for at least 1 year.



 In the placebo-controlled clinical trials for vardenafil film-coated tablets and STAXYN, the discontinuation rate due to adverse events was 1.9% for vardenafil compared to 0.8% for placebo.



 Placebo-controlled trials suggested a dose effect in the incidence of some adverse reactions (for example, dizziness, headache, flushing, dyspepsia, nausea, nasal congestion) over the 5 mg, 10 mg, and 20 mg doses of vardenafil film-coated tablets.



 The following section identifies additional, less frequent adverse reactions (&lt;2%) reported during the clinical development of vardenafil film-coated tablets and STAXYN. Excluded from this list are those adverse reactions that are infrequent and minor, those events that may be commonly observed in the absence of drug therapy, and those events that are not reasonably associated with the drug:



   Body as a whole:  allergic edema and angioedema, feeling unwell, allergic reactions, chest pain



   Auditory:  tinnitus, vertigo



   Cardiovascular:  palpitation, tachycardia, angina pectoris, myocardial infarction, ventricular tachyarrhythmias, hypotension



   Digestive:  nausea, gastrointestinal and abdominal pain, dry mouth, diarrhea, gastroesophageal reflux disease, gastritis, vomiting, increase in transaminases



   Musculoskeletal:  increase in creatine phosphokinase (CPK), increased muscle tone and cramping, myalgia



   Nervous:  paresthesia and dysesthesia, somnolence, sleep disorder, syncope, amnesia, seizure



   Respiratory:  dyspnea, sinus congestion



   Skin and appendages:  erythema, rash



   Ophthalmologic:  visual disturbance, ocular hyperemia, visual color distortions, eye pain and eye discomfort, photophobia, increase in intraocular pressure, conjunctivitis



   Urogenital:  increase in erection, priapism



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of vardenafil in the film-coated tablet formulation. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Ophthalmologic:  Non-arteritic anterior ischemic optic neuropathy (NAION), a cause of decreased vision including permanent loss of vision, has been reported rarely postmarketing in temporal association with the use of PDE5 inhibitors, including vardenafil. Most, but not all, of these patients had underlying anatomic or vascular risk factors for development of NAION, including but not necessarily limited to: low cup to disc ratio ("crowded disc"), age over 50, diabetes, hypertension, coronary artery disease, hyperlipidemia and smoking. It is not possible to determine whether these events are related directly to the use of PDE5 inhibitors, to the patient's underlying vascular risk factors or anatomical defects, to a combination of these factors, or to other factors  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  ) and Patient Counseling Information (  17.8  )]  .



 Visual disturbances including vision loss (temporary or permanent), such as visual field defect, retinal vein occlusion, and reduced visual acuity, have also been reported rarely in postmarketing experience. It is not possible to determine whether these events are related directly to the use of vardenafil.



   Neurologic:  Seizure, seizure recurrence and transient global amnesia have been reported postmarketing in temporal association with vardenafil.



   Otologic:  Cases of sudden decrease or loss of hearing have been reported postmarketing in temporal association with the use of PDE5 inhibitors, including vardenafil. In some cases, medical conditions and other factors were reported that may have also played a role in the otologic adverse events. In many cases, medical follow-up information was limited. It is not possible to determine whether these reported events are related directly to the use of vardenafil, to the patient's underlying risk factors for hearing loss, a combination of these factors, or to other factors  [see Patient Counseling Information (  17.9  )]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  The evaluation of erectile dysfunction should include a medical assessment, a determination of potential underlying causes and the identification of appropriate treatment.



 Before prescribing STAXYN, it is important to note the following:



    EXCERPT:    *    Cardiovascular Effects: Patients should not use STAXYN if sex is inadvisable due to cardiovascular status. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Potent and Moderate CYP3A4 Inhibitors: Do not use STAXYN in patients taking potent or moderate CYP3A4 inhibitors. (  5.2  ,  7.2  ) 
 *    Risk of Priapism: In the event that an erection lasts more than 4 hours, the patient should seek immediate medical assistance. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Effects on the Eye: Patients should stop use of STAXYN, and seek medical attention in the event of sudden loss of vision in one or both eyes, which could be a sign of non arteritic anterior ischemic optic neuropathy (NAION). STAXYN should be used with caution, and only when the anticipated benefits outweigh the risks, in patients with a history of NAION. Patients with a "crowded" optic disc may also be at an increased risk of NAION. (  5.5  ,  6.2  ) 
 *    Alpha-Blockers: Caution is advised when PDE5 inhibitors are co-administered with alpha-blockers. In some patients, concomitant use of these two drug classes can lower blood pressure significantly leading to symptomatic hypotension (for example, fainting). In patients taking alpha-blockers, do not initiate vardenafil therapy with STAXYN. (  2.4  ,  5.6  ) 
 *    QT Prolongation: Patients with congenital QT syndrome or taking class IA or III antiarrhythmics should avoid using STAXYN. (  5.7  ,  12.2  ) 
 *    Phenylketonurics: Each STAXYN tablet contains 1.01 mg phenylalanine per tablet, which could be harmful for patients with phenylketonuria. (  5.12  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Cardiovascular Effects



   General



  Physicians should consider the cardiovascular status of their patients, since there is a degree of cardiac risk associated with sexual activity. Therefore, treatment for erectile dysfunction, including STAXYN, should not be used in men for whom sexual activity is not recommended because of their underlying cardiovascular status.



 There are no controlled clinical data on the safety or efficacy of vardenafil in the following patients; and therefore its use is not recommended until further information is available: unstable angina; hypotension (resting systolic blood pressure of &lt;90 mmHg); uncontrolled hypertension (&gt;170/110 mmHg); recent history of stroke, life-threatening arrhythmia, or myocardial infarction (within the last 6 months); severe cardiac failure.



    Left Ventricular Outflow Obstruction



  Patients with left ventricular outflow obstruction (for example, aortic stenosis and idiopathic hypertrophic subaortic stenosis) can be sensitive to the action of vasodilators including PDE5 inhibitors.



    Blood Pressure Effects



  Vardenafil has systemic vasodilatory properties that resulted in transient decreases in supine blood pressure in healthy volunteers (mean maximum decrease of 7 mmHg systolic and 8 mmHg diastolic) [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  )]  . While this normally would be expected to be of little consequence in most patients, prior to prescribing STAXYN, physicians should carefully consider whether their patients with underlying cardiovascular disease could be affected adversely by such vasodilatory effects.



    5.2 Potential for Drug Interactions with Potent or Moderate CYP3A4 Inhibitors



  Concomitant administration with potent CYP3A4 inhibitors (such as ritonavir, indinavir, ketoconazole) or moderate CYP3A4 inhibitors (such as erythromycin) increases plasma concentrations of vardenafil. Do not use STAXYN in patients taking potent or moderate CYP3A4 inhibitors. [See Dosage and Administration (  2.4  ), Drug Interactions (  7.2  ) and Patient Counseling Information (  17.11  ).]  



    5.3 Risk of Priapism



  There have been rare reports of prolonged erections greater than 4 hours and priapism (painful erections greater than 6 hours in duration) for this class of compounds, including vardenafil. In the event that an erection persists longer than 4 hours, the patient should seek immediate medical assistance. If priapism is not treated immediately, penile tissue damage and permanent loss of potency may result.



 STAXYN should be used with caution by patients with anatomical deformation of the penis (such as angulation, cavernosal fibrosis, or Peyronie's disease) or by patients who have conditions that may predispose them to priapism (such as sickle cell anemia, multiple myeloma, or leukemia).



    5.4 Effects on the Eye



   Physicians should advise patients to stop use of all phosphodiesterase type 5 (PDE5) inhibitors, including STAXYN, and seek medical attention in the event of sudden loss of vision in one or both eyes. Such an event may be a sign of non-arteritic anterior ischemic optic neuropathy (NAION), a rare condition and a cause of decreased vision, including permanent loss of vision, that has been reported rarely postmarketing in temporal association with the use of all PDE5 inhibitors. Based on published literature, the annual incidence of NAION is 2.5-11.8 cases per 100,000 in males aged &gt;=50. An observational study evaluated whether recent use of PDE5 inhibitors, as a class, was associated with acute onset of NAION. The results suggest an approximate 2 fold increase in the risk of NAION within 5 half-lives of PDE5 inhibitor use. From this information, it is not possible to determine whether these events are related directly to the use of PDE5 inhibitors or to other factors [see Adverse Reactions (  6.2  )].  



  Physicians should consider whether their patients with underlying NAION risk factors could be adversely affected by use of PDE5 inhibitors. Individuals who have already experienced NAION are at increased risk of NAION recurrence. Therefore, PDE5 inhibitors, including Staxyn, should be used with caution in these patients and only when the anticipated benefits outweigh the risks. Individuals with "crowded" optic disc are also considered at greater risk for NAION compared to the general population, however, evidence is insufficient to support screening of prospective users of PDE5 inhibitors, including STAXYN, for this uncommon condition.  



 STAXYN has not been evaluated in patients with known hereditary degenerative retinal disorders, including retinitis pigmentosa, therefore its use is not recommended until further information is available in those patients.



    5.5 Sudden Hearing Loss



  Physicians should advise patients to stop taking all PDE5 inhibitors, including STAXYN, and seek prompt medical attention in the event of sudden decrease or loss of hearing. These events, which may be accompanied by tinnitus and dizziness, have been reported in temporal association to the intake of PDE5 inhibitors, including vardenafil. It is not possible to determine whether these events are related directly to the use of PDE5 inhibitors or to other factors [see Adverse Reactions (  6.2  )].  



    5.6 Alpha-Blockers



  In patients taking alpha-blockers, do not initiate vardenafil therapy with STAXYN. Patients treated with alpha-blockers who have previously used vardenafil film-coated tablets may be changed to STAXYN at the advice of their healthcare provider. Caution is advised when PDE5 inhibitors are co-administered with alpha-blockers. PDE5 inhibitors, including STAXYN, and alpha-adrenergic blocking agents are both vasodilators with blood-pressure lowering effects. When vasodilators are used in combination, an additive effect on blood pressure may be anticipated. In some patients, concomitant use of these two drug classes can lower blood pressure significantly [see Drug Interactions (  7.1  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  )]  leading to symptomatic hypotension (for example, fainting). Consideration should be given to the following:



 *    Patients should be stable on alpha-blocker therapy prior to initiating a PDE5 inhibitor. Patients who demonstrate hemodynamic instability on alpha-blocker therapy alone are at increased risk of symptomatic hypotension with concomitant use of PDE5 inhibitors. 
 *    In those patients who are stable on alpha-blocker therapy, PDE5 inhibitors should be initiated at the lowest recommended starting dose. In patients taking alpha-blockers, do not initiate vardenafil therapy with STAXYN. Lower doses of vardenafil film-coated tablets should be used as initial therapy in these patients [see Dosage and Administration (  2.4  )] . 
 *    In those patients already taking an optimized dose of PDE5 inhibitor, alpha-blocker therapy should be initiated at the lowest dose. Stepwise increases in alpha-blocker dose may be associated with further lowering of blood pressure in patients taking a PDE5 inhibitor. 
 *    Safety of combined use of PDE5 inhibitors and alpha-blockers may be affected by other variables, including intravascular volume depletion and other anti-hypertensive drugs. 
       5.7 Congenital or Acquired QT Prolongation
 

  In a study of the effect of vardenafil on QT interval in 59 healthy males [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  )]  , therapeutic (10 mg film-coated tablets) and supratherapeutic (80 mg) doses of vardenafil and the active control moxifloxacin (400 mg) produced similar increases in QTc interval. A postmarketing study evaluating the effect of combining vardenafil with another drug of comparable QT effect showed an additive QT effect when compared with either drug alone [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  )]  . These observations should be considered in clinical decisions when prescribing vardenafil to patients with known history of QT prolongation or patients who are taking medications known to prolong the QT interval.



 Patients taking Class 1A (for example, quinidine, procainamide) or Class III (for example, amiodarone, sotalol) antiarrhythmic medications or those with congenital QT prolongation, should avoid using STAXYN.



    5.8 Hepatic Impairment



  Do not use STAXYN in patients with moderate (Child-Pugh B) or severe (Child-Pugh C) hepatic impairment [see Dosage and Administration (  2.3  ) Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )] and Use in Specific Populations (  8.6  )]  .



    5.9 Renal Impairment



  Do not use STAXYN in patients on renal dialysis, as vardenafil has not been evaluated in this population [see Dosage and Administration (  2.3  ) and Use in Specific Populations (  8.7  )].  



    5.10 Combination with Other Erectile Dysfunction Therapies



  The safety and efficacy of STAXYN used in combination with other treatments for erectile dysfunction have not been studied. Therefore, the use of such combinations is not recommended.



    5.11 Effects on Bleeding



  In humans, vardenafil film-coated tablet alone in doses up to 20 mg does not prolong the bleeding time. There is no clinical evidence of any additive prolongation of the bleeding time when vardenafil is administered with aspirin. STAXYN has not been administered to patients with bleeding disorders or significant active peptic ulceration. Therefore STAXYN should be administered to these patients after careful benefit-risk assessment.



    5.12 Phenylketonurics



  STAXYN contains aspartame, a source of phenylalanine which may be harmful for people with phenylketonuria.



 Phenylketonurics: Each STAXYN tablet contains 1.01 mg phenylalanine per tablet.



    5.13 Fructose Intolerance



  STAXYN contains sorbitol. Patients with rare hereditary problems of fructose intolerance should not take STAXYN.



    5.14 Sexually Transmitted Disease



  The use of STAXYN offers no protection against sexually transmitted diseases. Counseling of patients about protective measures necessary to guard against sexually transmitted diseases, including the Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV), should be considered.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
