<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="strattera" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">       6 ADVERSE REACTIONS            6.1 Clinical Trials Experience STRATTERA was administered to 5382 children or adolescent patients with ADHD and 1007 adults with ADHD in clinical studies. During the ADHD clinical trials, 1625 children and adolescent patients were treated for longer than 1 year and 2529 children and adolescent patients were treated for over 6 months.



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



           Child and Adolescent Clinical Trials  



           Reasons for discontinuation of treatment due to adverse reactions in child and adolescent clinical trials   - In acute child and adolescent placebo-controlled trials, 3.0% (48/1613) of atomoxetine subjects and 1.4% (13/945) placebo subjects discontinued for adverse reactions. For all studies, (including open-label and long-term studies), 6.3% of extensive metabolizer (EM) patients and 11.2% of poor metabolizer (PM) patients discontinued because of an adverse reaction. Among STRATTERA-treated patients, irritability (0.3%, N=5); somnolence (0.3%, N=5); aggression (0.2%, N=4); nausea (0.2%, N=4); vomiting (0.2%, N=4); abdominal pain (0.2%, N=4); constipation (0.1%, N=2); fatigue (0.1%, N=2); feeling abnormal (0.1%, N=2); and headache (0.1%, N=2) were the reasons for discontinuation reported by more than 1 patient.



           Seizures  - STRATTERA has not been systematically evaluated in pediatric patients with seizure disorder as these patients were excluded from clinical studies during the product's premarket testing. In the clinical development program, seizures were reported in 0.2% (12/5073) of children whose average age was 10 years (range 6 to 16 years). In these clinical trials, the seizure risk among poor metabolizers was 0.3% (1/293) compared to 0.2% (11/4741) for extensive metabolizers.



           Commonly observed adverse reactions in acute child and adolescent, placebo-controlled trials   - Commonly observed adverse reactions associated with the use of STRATTERA (incidence of 2% or greater) and not observed at an equivalent incidence among placebo-treated patients (STRATTERA incidence greater than placebo) are listed in  Table 1  . Results were similar in the BID and the QD trial except as shown in  Table 2  , which shows both BID and QD results for selected adverse reactions based on statistically significant Breslow-Day tests. The most commonly observed adverse reactions in patients treated with STRATTERA (incidence of 5% or greater and at least twice the incidence in placebo patients, for either BID or QD dosing) were: nausea, vomiting, fatigue, decreased appetite, abdominal pain, and somnolence (  see     Tables 1    and     2  ).



 The following adverse reactions occurred in at least 2% of PM patients and were either twice as frequent or statistically significantly more frequent in PM patients compared with EM patients: insomnia (15% of PMs, 10% of EMs); weight decreased (7% of PMs, 4% of EMs); constipation (7% of PMs, 4% of EMs); depression  1  (7% of PMs, 4% of EMs); tremor (5% of PMs, 1% of EMs); excoriation (4% of PMs, 2% of EMs); conjunctivitis (3% of PMs, 1% of EMs); syncope (3% of PMs, 1% of EMs); early morning awakening (2% of PMs, 1% of EMs); mydriasis (2% of PMs, 1% of EMs).



   1  Depression includes the following terms: depression, major depression, depressive symptoms, depressed mood, dysphoria.



           Adult Clinical Trials  



           Reasons for discontinuation of treatment due to adverse reactions in acute adult placebo-controlled trials   - In the acute adult placebo-controlled trials, 11.3% (61/541) atomoxetine subjects and 3.0% (12/405) placebo subjects discontinued for adverse reactions. Among STRATTERA-treated patients, insomnia (0.9%, N=5); nausea (0.9%, N=5); chest pain (0.6%, N=3); fatigue (0.6%, N=3); anxiety (0.4%, N=2); erectile dysfunction (0.4%, N=2); mood swings (0.4%, N=2); nervousness (0.4%, N=2); palpitations (0.4%, N=2); and urinary retention (0.4%, N=2) were the reasons for discontinuation reported by more than 1 patient.



           Seizures  - STRATTERA has not been systematically evaluated in adult patients with a seizure disorder as these patients were excluded from clinical studies during the product's premarket testing. In the clinical development program, seizures were reported on 0.1% (1/748) of adult patients. In these clinical trials, no poor metabolizers (0/43) reported seizures compared to 0.1% (1/705) for extensive metabolizers.



           Commonly observed adverse reactions in acute adult placebo-controlled trials  - Commonly observed adverse reactions associated with the use of STRATTERA (incidence of 2% or greater) and not observed at an equivalent incidence among placebo-treated patients (STRATTERA incidence greater than placebo) are listed in  Table 3  . The most commonly observed adverse reactions in patients treated with STRATTERA (incidence of 5% or greater and at least twice the incidence in placebo patients) were: constipation, dry mouth, nausea, fatigue, decreased appetite, insomnia, erectile dysfunction, urinary hesitation and/or urinary retention and/or dysuria, dysmenorrhea, and hot flush (  see     Table 3  ).



   Male and female sexual dysfunction  - Atomoxetine appears to impair sexual function in some patients. Changes in sexual desire, sexual performance, and sexual satisfaction are not well assessed in most clinical trials because they need special attention and because patients and physicians may be reluctant to discuss them. Accordingly, estimates of the incidence of untoward sexual experience and performance cited in product labeling are likely to underestimate the actual incidence.  Table 3  above displays the incidence of sexual side effects reported by at least 2% of adult patients taking STRATTERA in placebo-controlled trials.



 There are no adequate and well-controlled studies examining sexual dysfunction with STRATTERA treatment. While it is difficult to know the precise risk of sexual dysfunction associated with the use of STRATTERA, physicians should routinely inquire about such possible side effects.



            6.2 Postmarketing Spontaneous Reports The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of STRATTERA. Unless otherwise specified, these adverse reactions have occurred in adults and children and adolescents. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Cardiovascular system  - QT prolongation, syncope.



   General disorders and administration site conditions  - Lethargy.



   Nervous system disorders  - Hypoaesthesia; paraesthesia in children and adolescents; sensory disturbances; tics.



   Psychiatric disorders  - Depression and depressed mood; anxiety.



   Seizures  - Seizures have been reported in the postmarketing period. The postmarketing seizure cases include patients with pre-existing seizure disorders and those with identified risk factors for seizures, as well as patients with neither a history of nor identified risk factors for seizures. The exact relationship between STRATTERA and seizures is difficult to evaluate due to uncertainty about the background risk of seizures in ADHD patients.



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders  - Hyperhidrosis.



   Urogenital system  - Male pelvic pain; urinary hesitation in children and adolescents; urinary retention in children and adolescents.



   EXCERPT:     Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5% and at least twice the incidence of placebo patients)  



 *  Child and Adolescent Clinical Trials - Nausea, vomiting, fatigue, decreased appetite, abdominal pain, and somnolence. (  6.1  ) 
 *  Adult Clinical Trials - Constipation, dry mouth, nausea, fatigue, decreased appetite, insomnia, erectile dysfunction, urinary hesitation and/or urinary retention and/or dysuria, dysmenorrhea, and hot flush. (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Eli Lilly and Company at 1-800-LillyRx (1-800-545-5979) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

     WARNING: SUICIDAL IDEATION IN CHILDREN AND ADOLESCENTS    STRATTERA (atomoxetine) increased the risk of 

suicidal ideation in short-term studies in children or adolescents with 

Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD). Anyone considering the use of 

STRATTERA in a child or adolescent must balance this risk with the clinical 

need. Co-morbidities occurring with ADHD may be associated with an increase in 

the risk of suicidal ideation and/or behavior. Patients who are started on 

therapy should be monitored closely for suicidality (suicidal thinking and 

behavior), clinical worsening, or unusual changes in behavior. Families and 

caregivers should be advised of the need for close observation and communication 

with the prescriber. STRATTERA is approved for ADHD in pediatric and adult 

patients. STRATTERA is not approved for major depressive disorder.  



   Pooled analyses of short-term (6 to 18 weeks) 

placebo-controlled trials of STRATTERA in children and adolescents (a total of 

12 trials involving over 2200 patients, including 11 trials in ADHD and 1 trial 

in enuresis) have revealed a greater risk of suicidal ideation early during 

treatment in those receiving STRATTERA compared to placebo. The average risk of 

suicidal ideation in patients receiving STRATTERA was 0.4% (5/1357 patients), 

compared to none in placebo-treated patients (851 patients). No suicides 

occurred in these trials     [see Warnings and 

Precautions (  5.1  )]  . 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
