<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="subsys" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions during treatment (frequency &gt;=5%): vomiting, nausea, constipation, dyspnea, and somnolence. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Insys Therapeutics, Inc., at 1-855-978-2797 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/ medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of SUBSYS has been evaluated in a total of 359 opioid-tolerant patients with breakthrough cancer pain. The duration of SUBSYS use varied during the open-label study. Safety data from a long-term extension study showed that the average duration of therapy in the open-label study was 66 days. The maximum duration of therapy was 149 days. The dose range studied in these trials ranged from 100 mcg per dose to 1600 mcg per dose.



 The most commonly observed adverse reactions seen with SUBSYS are typical opioid side effects such as nausea, vomiting, somnolence, and constipation. Expect opioid side effects and manage them accordingly.



 The most serious adverse reactions associated with all opioids including SUBSYS are respiratory depression (potentially leading to apnea or respiratory arrest), circulatory depression, hypotension, and shock. Follow all patients for symptoms of respiratory depression.



 The most common adverse reaction leading to discontinuation of SUBSYS was nausea. There were also adverse reactions of abdominal distension, anorexia, confusional state, disorientation, somnolence, and constipation.



 The clinical trials of SUBSYS were designed to evaluate safety and efficacy in treating breakthrough cancer pain; all patients were also taking concomitant opioids, such as sustained-release morphine or transdermal fentanyl, for their persistent cancer pain. The adverse event data presented here reflect the actual percentage of patients experiencing each adverse effect among patients who received SUBSYS for breakthrough cancer pain along with a concomitant opioid for persistent cancer pain.



 Table 3 lists adverse reactions with an overall frequency of 5% or greater that occurred during titration in the clinical trials. Adverse reactions are listed in descending order of frequency within each system organ class.



 Table 3. Percent of Patients with Specific Adverse Events During Titration in the Clinical Trials (Events in 5% or More of Patients) 
 System Organ Class                                                       Titrationn=359 (%)              
  
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                             
   Nausea                                                                     47 (13.1%)                  
   Vomiting                                                                   37 (10.3%)                  
   Constipation                                                               18 (5.0%)                   
   Nervous System Disorders                                                                               
   Somnolence                                                                 34 (9.5%)                   
   Dizziness                                                                  26 (7.2%)                   
        A patient was counted only once within each category.
 

 The following adverse reactions occurred during titration in the clinical trials with an overall frequency of 1% or greater and are listed in descending order of frequency within each system organ class.



   Cardiac Disorders:  Tachycardia



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  Diarrhea, stomatitis, dry mouth



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  Application site irritation, pyrexia, edema peripheral, fatigue, asthenia



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  Decreased appetite



   Nervous System Disorders:  Lethargy, sedation, tremor, headache



   Psychiatric Disorders:  Depression, confusional state, hallucination, insomnia



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  Dyspnea



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  Pruritus



 The following reactions occurred during titration in the clinical trials with an overall frequency of less than 1% and are listed in descending order of frequency within each system organ class.



   Eye Disorders:  Vision blurred, dry eye



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  Abdominal pain



   Infections and Infestations:  Oral candidiasis, cellulitis



   Injury, Poisoning and Procedural Complications:  Fall



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  Dehydration, anorexia



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  Back pain, arthralgia, joint swelling



   Psychiatric Disorders:  Anxiety, agitation



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  Urinary retention



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  Cough, increased bronchial secretion, dysphonia, pharyngolaryngeal pain



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  Hyperhidrosis



   Vascular Disorders:  Hot flush



 Table 4 lists adverse reactions with an overall frequency of 5% or greater for the total safety database subsequent to titration during the clinical trials.



 Table 4. Adverse Reactions Subsequent to Titration in 5% or More of Patients 
 System Organ Class                                                          Dosingn=269                  
  
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                             
 Vomiting                                                                     43 (16.0%)                  
 Nausea                                                                       28 (10.4%)                  
 Constipation                                                                 28 (10.4%)                  
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions                                                   
 Asthenia                                                                     26 (9.7%)                   
   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders                                                        
 Dyspnea                                                                      28 (10.4%)                  
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                  
 Anxiety                                                                      16 (5.9%)                   
        A patient was counted only once within each category.
 

 The following adverse reactions occurred during the dosing period of the clinical trial with an overall frequency of 1% or greater and are listed in descending order of frequency within each system organ class.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  Anemia, neutropenia, lymphadenopathy, thrombocytopenia, leukopenia



   Cardiac Disorders:  Tachycardia, sinus tachycardia



   Gastrointestinal Disorders  : Diarrhea, stomatitis, abdominal pain, abdominal distension, gastritis, dysphagia, dyspepsia, gastroesophageal reflux disease, ascites, hematemesis



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  Edema peripheral, fatigue, pyrexia, chest pain, drug withdrawal syndrome, chills, irritability, malaise, application site irritation



   Infections and Infestations:  Oral candidiasis, pneumonia, urinary tract infection, oral herpes, gastroenteritis, laryngitis



   Injury, Poisoning and Procedural Complications:  Contusion



   Investigations:  Weight decreased, aspartate aminotransferase increased, blood alkaline phosphatase increased, blood glucose increased, blood lactate increased



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  Anorexia, dehydration, hypokalemia, decreased appetite, hyponatremia, hypocalcemia, hypoalbuminemia, cachexia



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  Back pain, arthralgia, muscular weakness



   Nervous System Disorders:  Hypoesthesia, lethargy, sedation, tremor, somnolence, headache, dizziness



   Psychiatric Disorders:  Depression, restlessness, agitation, confusional state, insomnia, hallucination, disorientation



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  hypertension, hypotension



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  Cough, increased bronchial secretion, wheezing, pharyngolaryngeal pain, hypoxia, dyspnea exertional



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  hyperhidrosis, pruritus



 In a single-dose mucositis study, a group of patients with Grade 1 or 2 oral mucositis (n=9) and without oral mucositis (n=9) were included in a clinical trial designed to support the safety of SUBSYS. Two of the nine subjects with mucositis (one with Grade 1 and one with Grade 2) reported a burning sensation in the oral mucosa after treatment. Both of these events were considered mild and probably related to treatment. There was no change in grade of mucositis after treatment for any subject.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: RISK OF RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION, MEDICATION ERRORS, ABUSE POTENTIAL

    WARNING: RISK OF RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION, MEDICATION ERRORS, ABUSE POTENTIAL  

    Respiratory Depression  



   Fatal respiratory depression has occurred in patients treated with transmucosal immediate-release fentanyl products such as SUBSYS, including following use in opioid non-tolerant patients and improper dosing. The substitution of SUBSYS for any other fentanyl product may result in fatal overdose.  



   Due to the risk of respiratory depression, SUBSYS is contraindicated in the management of acute or postoperative pain including headache/migraine and in opioid non-tolerant patients.  



   Death has been reported in children who have accidentally ingested transmucosal immediate-release fentanyl products. SUBSYS must be kept out of reach of children.   [see   Patient Counseling Information (17)   and   How Supplied/Storage and Handling (16.1)        ]  



 The concomitant use of SUBSYS with CYP3A4 inhibitors may result in an increase in fentanyl plasma concentrations, and may cause potentially fatal respiratory depression   [see   Drug Interactions (7)  ]  . 



   Medication Errors  



   Substantial differences exist in the pharmacokinetic profile of SUBSYS compared to other fentanyl products that result in clinically important differences in the extent of absorption of fentanyl that could result in fatal overdose.  



 *  -When prescribing, do not convert patients on a mcg per mcg basis from any other fentanyl products to SUBSYS. [see Dosage and Administration (2.1),Warnings and Precautions (5.2,) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)] 
 *  -When dispensing, do not substitute a SUBSYS prescription for other fentanyl products. 
      Abuse Potential  
 

   SUBSYS contains fentanyl, an opioid agonist and a Schedule II controlled substance, with an abuse liability similar to other opioid analgesics.  



   SUBSYS can be abused in a manner similar to other opioid agonists, legal or illicit.  This should be considered when prescribing or dispensing SUBSYS in situations where the physician or pharmacist is concerned about an increased risk of misuse, abuse or diversion.  



   Because of the risk for misuse, abuse, addiction, and overdose, SUBSYS is available only through a restricted program required by the Food and Drug Administration, called a R  isk   E  valuation and   M  itigation   S  trategy   (REMS)  . Under the   T  ransmucosal   I  mmediate-  R  elease   F  entanyl (TIRF) REMS Access program, outpatients, healthcare professionals who prescribe to outpatients, pharmacies, and distributors must enroll in the program.   [See   Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]   Further information is available at www.TIRFREMSaccess.com or by calling 1-866-822-1483.



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: RISK OF RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION, MEDICATION ERRORS, ABUSE POTENTIAL



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Due to the risk of fatal respiratory depression, SUBSYS is contraindicated in opioid non-tolerant patients (1) and in management of acute or postoperative pain, including headache/migraines. (4) 
 *  Keep out of reach of children. (5.3) 
 *  Use with CYP3A4 inhibitors may cause fatal respiratory depression. (7) 
 *  When prescribing, do not convert patients on a mcg per mcg basis from any other oral transmucosal fentanyl product to SUBSYS. ( 5.1) 
 *  When dispensing, do not substitute with any other fentanyl products. (5.1) 
 *  Contains fentanyl, a Schedule II controlled substance with abuse liability similar to other opioid analgesics. (9.1) 
 *  SUBSYS is available only through a restricted program called the TIRF REMS Access program. Outpatients, healthcare professionals who prescribe to outpatients, pharmacies, and distributors are required to enroll in the program. (5.10) 
    
 







    BOXED WARNING: Medication Guide

  Medication Guide

    SUBSYS  (r)   (sub sis) CII(fentanyl)sublingual spray100 mcg, 200 mcg, 400 mcg, 600 mcg, 800 mcg  



     IMPORTANT:  



   Do not use SUBSYS unless you are regularly using another opioid pain medicine around-the-clock for your cancer pain and your body is used to these medicines (this means that you are opioid tolerant). You can ask your healthcare provider if you are opioid tolerant.  



   Keep SUBSYS in a safe place away from children.  



   Get emergency medical help right away if:  



 *  a child uses SUBSYS. SUBSYS can cause an overdose and death in any child who uses it. 
 *  an adult who has not been prescribed SUBSYS uses it 
 *  an adult who is not already taking opioids around-the-clock, uses SUBSYS 
      These are medical emergencies that can cause death.  
 

     Read this Medication Guide completely   before you start using SUBSYS, and each time you get a new prescription. There may be new information. This Medication Guide does not take the place of talking to your healthcare provider about your medical condition or your treatment. Be sure to share this important information with members of your household and other caregivers.



   What is the most important information I should know about SUBSYS  ?



   SUBSYS can cause life-threatening breathing problems which can lead to death  . 



 *  Do not take SUBSYS if you are not opioid tolerant. 
 *  If you stop taking your around-the-clock opioid pain medicine for your cancer pain, you must stop using SUBSYS. You may no longer be opioid tolerant. Talk to your healthcare provider about how to treat your pain. 
 *  Use SUBSYS exactly as prescribed by your healthcare provider.You must not use more than 2 doses of SUBSYS for each episode of breakthrough cancer pain.You must wait four hours before treating a new episode of breakthrough pain with SUBSYS. See the Medication Guide section "How should I use SUBSYS?" and the "Instructions for Use" section at the end of this Medication Guide for detailed information about how to use SUBSYS the right way. 
 *  Do not switch from SUBSYS to other medicines that contain fentanyl without talking with your healthcare provider. The amount of fentanyl in a dose of SUBSYS is not the same as the amount of fentanyl in other medicines that contain fentanyl. Your healthcare provider will prescribe a starting dose of SUBSYS that may be different than other fentanyl containing medicines you may have been taking. 
 *  Do not use SUBSYS for short-term pain that you would expect to go away in a few days, such as:pain after surgeryheadache or migrainedental pain 
 *  Never give SUBSYS to anyone else, even if they have the same symptoms you have. It may harm them or even cause death. 
    SUBSYS is a federally controlled substance (CII) because it is a strong opioid (narcotic) pain medicine that can be misused by people who abuse prescription medicines or street drugs.
 

 *  Prevent theft, misuse or abuse. Keep SUBSYS in a safe place to protect it from being stolen. SUBSYS can be a target for people who abuse opioid (narcotic) medicines or street drugs. 
 *  Selling or giving away this medicine is against the law. 
    SUBSYS is available only through a program called the TIRF REMS ACCESS program. To receive SUBSYS, you must:
 

 *  talk to your healthcare provider 
 *  understand the benefits and risks of SUBSYS 
 *  agree to all of the instructions 
 *  sign the Patient-Prescriber Agreement form 
      What is SUBSYS?  
 

 *  SUBSYS is a prescription medicine that contains the medicine fentanyl. 
 *  SUBSYS is used to manage breakthrough pain in adults with cancer, who are already routinely taking other opioid pain medicines around-the-clock for cancer pain. 
 *  SUBSYS is started only after you have been taking other opioid pain medicines and your body has become used to them (you are opioid tolerant). Do not use SUBSYS if you are not opioid tolerant. 
 *  You must stay under your healthcare provider's care while taking SUBSYS. 
 *  SUBSYS is a liquid medicine that is sprayed underneath your tongue (sublingual) and allowed to absorb. 
 *  SUBSYS is only:available through the TIRF REMS ACCESS programgiven to people who are opioid tolerant 
    It is not known if SUBSYS is safe and effective in children under 18 years of age.
 

   Who should not use SUBSYS?  



   Do not use SUBSYS:  



 *  if you are not opioid tolerant. Opioid tolerant means that you are already taking other opioid pain medicines around-the-clock for your cancer pain, and your body is used to these medicines. 
 *  for short-term pain that you would expect to go away in a few days, such as:pain after surgeryheadache or migrainedental pain 
 *  if you are allergic to any of the ingredients in SUBSYS. See the end of this Medication Guide for a complete list of other ingredients in SUBSYS. 
      What should I tell my healthcare provider before using SUBSYS?  
 

 Before using SUBSYS, tell your healthcare provider if you:



 *  have sores or ulcers in your mouth 
 *  have trouble breathing or lung problems such as asthma, wheezing, or shortness of breath 
 *  have or had a head injury or brain problem 
 *  have liver or kidney problems 
 *  have seizures 
 *  have a slow heart rate or other heart problems 
 *  have low blood pressure 
 *  have mental health problems including major depression, schizophrenia or hallucinations (seeing or hearing things that are not there) 
 *  have a past or present drinking problem (alcoholism), or a family history of drinking problems 
 *  have a past or present drug abuse problem or addiction problem, or a family history of a drug abuse problem or addiction problem 
 *  have any other medical conditions 
 *  are pregnant or plan to become pregnant. SUBSYS may cause serious harm to your unborn baby. 
 *  are breastfeeding or plan to breastfeed. SUBSYS can pass into your breast milk. It can cause serious harm to your baby. You should not use SUBSYS while breastfeeding. 
      Tell your healthcare provider about all the medicines you take  , including prescription and non-prescription medicines, vitamins, and herbal supplements. Some medicines may cause serious or life-threatening side effects when taken with SUBSYS. Sometimes, the doses of certain medicines and SUBSYS may need to be changed if used together.
 

 *  Do not take any medicine while using SUBSYS until you have talked to your healthcare provider. Your healthcare provider will tell you if it is safe to take other medicines while you are using SUBSYS. 
 *  Be very careful about taking other medicines that may make you sleepy, such as other pain medicines, anti-depressants, sleeping pills, anti-anxiety medicines, antihistamines, muscle relaxants or tranquilizers. 
    Know the medicines you take. Keep a list of them to show your healthcare provider and pharmacist when you get a new medicine.
 

   How should I use SUBSYS?  



   Before you can begin to use SUBSYS:  



 *  Your healthcare provider will explain the TIRF REMS ACCESS program to you. 
 *  You will sign the TIRF REMS ACCESS program Patient-Prescriber Agreement form. 
 *  SUBSYS is only available at pharmacies that are part of the TIRF REMS ACCESS program. Your healthcare provider will let you know the pharmacy closest to your home where you can have your SUBSYS prescription filled. 
      Using SUBSYS:  
 

 *  Use SUBSYS exactly as prescribed. Do not use SUBSYS more often than prescribed. 
 *  See the "Instructions for Use" section at the end of this Medication Guide for detailed information about the right way to use and throw away (dispose of) SUBSYS. 
 *  SUBSYS comes in several strengths. When you are first prescribed SUBSYS, your healthcare provider will start you with the lowest strength medicine, and will change the dose until you and your healthcare provider find the right dose for you. Do not change your dose of SUBSYS unless your healthcare provider tells you to. Each SUBSYS unit contains enough medicine for 1 spray. 
 *  As your dose is adjusted, your healthcare provider will tell you whether your dose of SUBSYS is 1 or 2 sprays given underneath the tongue.If your dose of SUBSYS is 1 spray, then you will use 1 SUBSYS unit for each dose.If your dose of SUBSYS is 2 sprays, then you will use 2 SUBSYS units for each dose. 
 *  Take 1 dose of SUBSYS when you get an episode of breakthrough cancer pain. 
 *  Wait 30 minutes. If you are still in pain after 30 minutes, take 1 more dose of SUBSYS as instructed by your healthcare provider. 
 *  Do not take more than 2 doses of SUBSYS for an episode of breakthrough cancer pain. If your breakthrough pain does not get better after the second dose of SUBSYS, call your healthcare provider for instructions. Do not use another dose of SUBSYS at this time. 
 *  Wait at least 4 hours before treating a new episode of breakthrough cancer pain with SUBSYS. 
 *  Keep taking your around-the-clock opioid pain medicine while taking SUBSYS. 
 *  If you have more than 4 episodes of breakthrough cancer pain in a day, talk to your healthcare provider. The dose of your around-the-clock opioid pain medicine may need to be adjusted. 
 *  If you use too much SUBSYS or overdose, you or your caregiver should call for emergency medical help or have someone take you to the nearest hospital emergency room right away. 
      What should I avoid while using SUBSYS?  
 

 *  Do not drive, operate heavy machinery, or do other dangerous activities until you know how SUBSYS affects you. SUBSYS can make you sleepy. Ask your healthcare provider when it is okay to do these activities. 
 *  Do not drink alcohol while using SUBSYS. It can increase your chance of getting dangerous side effects. 
      What are the possible side effects of SUBSYS?   
 

   SUBSYS can cause serious side effects, including:  



 *  Breathing problems that can become life-threatening. See "What is the most important information I should know about SUBSYS?"Call your healthcare provider or get emergency medical help right away if you:have trouble breathinghave drowsiness with slowed breathinghave shallow breathing (little chest movement with breathing)feel faint, very dizzy, confused, or have other unusual symptomsThese symptoms can be a sign that you have used too much SUBSYS or the dose is too high for you. These symptoms may lead to serious problems or death if not treated right away. If you have any of these symptoms, do not use any more SUBSYS until you have talked to your healthcare provider. 
 *  Decreased blood pressure. This can make you feel dizzy or lightheaded if you get up too fast from sitting or lying down. 
 *  Physical dependence. Do not stop using SUBSYS or any other opioid, without talking to your healthcare provider. You could become sick with withdrawal symptoms because your body has become used to these medicines. Physical dependency is not the same as drug addiction. 
 *  A chance of abuse or addiction. This chance is higher if you are or have ever been addicted to or abused other medicines, street drugs, or alcohol, or if you have a history of mental health problems. 
    The most common side effects of SUBSYS are:
 

 *  nausea 
 *  vomiting 
 *  shortness of breath 
 *  sleepiness 
 *  dizziness 
 *  headache 
    Constipation (not often enough or hard bowel movements) is a very common side effect of pain medicines (opioids) including SUBSYS and is unlikely to go away without treatment. Talk to your healthcare provider about dietary changes, and the use of laxatives (medicines to treat constipation) and stool softeners to prevent or treat constipation while using SUBSYS.
 

 Tell your healthcare provider if you have any side effect that bothers you or that does not go away.



 These are not all the possible side effects of SUBSYS. For more information, ask your healthcare provider or pharmacist.



 Call your doctor for medical advice about side effects. You may report side effects to FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088.



   How should I store SUBSYS?  



 *  Always keep SUBSYS in a safe place away from children and from anyone for whom it has not been prescribed. Protect SUBSYS from theft. 
 *  Store SUBSYS at room temperature, 68 degrees F to 77 degrees F (20 degrees C to 25 degrees C) until ready to use. 
 *  Keep SUBSYS in the original blister package. Do not remove SUBSYS units from the blister packages for storage in a temporary container. 
 *  See the "Instructions for Use" section at the end of this Medication Guide for information about the right way to dispose of SUBSYS when no longer needed. 
 *  Use the SUBSYS Child Safety Kit to help you store SUBSYS and your other medicines out of the reach of children. It is very important that you use the items in the SUBSYS Child Safety Kit to help protect the children in your home or visiting your home. 
 *  Call Insys Therapeutics, Inc. at 1-877-978-2797 or visit www.subsysspray.com for a SUBSYS Child Safety Kit. 
    The SUBSYS Child Safety Kit contains important information on the storage and handling of SUBSYS.
 

 The SUBSYS Child Safety Kit includes:



 *  a portable carrying case (see Figure A) and lock (see Figure B) for you to keep a small supply of SUBSYS. Keep the rest of your SUBSYS in the locked storage space. 
   *  a package of cabinet and drawer child safety latches (see Figure C) to secure the storage space where SUBSYS is kept at home. 
   *  Keep the carrying case locked and away from children. (See Figure C) 
      General information about SUBSYS  
 

 Medicines are sometimes prescribed for purposes other than those listed in a Medication Guide.   Use SUBSYS only for the purpose for which it was prescribed. Do not give SUBSYS to other people, even if they have the same symptoms you have.   SUBSYS can harm other people and even cause death. Sharing SUBSYS is against the law.



 This Medication Guide summarizes the most important information about SUBSYS. If you would like more information, talk with your healthcare provider or pharmacist. You can ask your pharmacist or healthcare provider for information about SUBSYS that is written for healthcare professionals. 



 For more information about the TIRF REMS ACCESS program, go to www.TIRFREMSaccess.com or call 1-866-822-1483.



 What are the ingredients in SUBSYS?



 Active ingredient: fentanyl



 Inactive ingredients: dehydrated alcohol 63.6%, purified water, propylene glycol, xylitol, and L-menthol.



  Figure A  Figure B  Figure C 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   See  Boxed Warning    - WARNING RISK OF RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION, MEDICATION ERRORS, ABUSE POTENTIAL  



    EXCERPT:    *  Clinically significant respiratory and CNS depression can occur. Monitor patients accordingly. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Full and consumed SUBSYS units contain medicine that can be fatal to a child. Ensure proper storage and disposal. (  5.3  ,  16.2  ) 
 *  Use with other CNS depressants and moderate or strong CYP450 3A4 inhibitors may increase depressant effects including respiratory depression, hypotension, and profound sedation. Consider dosage adjustments if warranted. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Titrate SUBSYS cautiously in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or preexisting medical conditions predisposing them to respiratory depression and in patients susceptible to intracranial effects of CO2retention. (  5.6  ,  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Respiratory Depression



  Respiratory depression is the chief hazard of opioid agonists, including fentanyl, the active ingredient in SUBSYS. Respiratory depression is more likely to occur in patients with underlying respiratory disorders and elderly or debilitated patients, usually following large initial doses in opioid non-tolerant patients, or when opioids are given in conjunction with other drugs that depress respiration.



 Respiratory depression from opioids is manifested by a reduced urge to breathe and a decreased rate of respiration, often associated with the "sighing" pattern of breathing (deep breaths separated by abnormally long pauses). Carbon dioxide retention from opioid-induced respiratory depression can exacerbate the sedating effects of opioids. This makes overdoses involving drugs with sedative properties and opioids especially dangerous.



    5.2 Important Information Regarding Prescribing and Dispensing



   SUBSYS is not bioequivalent with other fentanyl products. Do not convert patients on a mcg per mcg basis from other fentanyl products.  



  When dispensing, DO NOT substitute a SUBSYS prescription for any other fentanyl product.  Substantial differences exist in the pharmacokinetic profile of SUBSYS compared to other fentanyl products that result in clinically important differences in the rate and extent of absorption of fentanyl. As a result of these differences, the substitution of the same dose of SUBSYS for the same dose of any other fentanyl product may result in a fatal overdose.  



  There are no conversion directions available for patients on any other fentanyl products. (Note: This includes oral, transdermal, or parenteral formulations of fentanyl.) All patients should be titrated from the 100 mcg dose.  Titrate each patient individually to provide adequate analgesia while minimizing side effects. [See  Dosage and Administration (2.1)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  



    5.3 Patient/Caregiver Instructions



   Patients and their caregivers must be instructed that SUBSYS contains a medicine in an amount which can be fatal to a child. Death has been reported in children who have accidentally ingested transmucosal immediate-release fentanyl products.  Patients and their caregivers must be instructed to keep both used and unused dosage units out of the reach of children. All used units should be disposed of immediately after use as they represent a special risk to children. [see  How Supplied/Storage and Handling (16.1  ,  16.2)  ,  Patient Counseling Information (17)  , and  Medication Guide  ]  .



 Physicians and dispensing pharmacists must specifically question patients or caregivers about the presence of children in the home (on a full time or visiting basis) and counsel them regarding the dangers to children from inadvertent exposure.



 SUBSYS could be fatal to individuals for whom it is not prescribed and for those who are not opioid-tolerant.



    5.4 Additive CNS Depressant Effects



  The concomitant use of SUBSYS with other CNS depressants, including other opioids, sedatives or hypnotics, general anesthetics, phenothiazines, tranquilizers, skeletal muscle relaxants, sedating antihistamines, and alcoholic beverages may produce increased depressant effects (e.g., respiratory depression, hypotension, and profound sedation). Concomitant use with strong and moderate inhibitors of CYP450 3A4 isoform (e.g., erythromycin, ketoconazole, and certain protease inhibitors) may increase fentanyl levels, resulting in increased depressant effects [see  Drug Interactions (7)  ]  .



 Patients on concomitant CNS depressants must be monitored for a change in opioid effects. Consideration should be given to adjusting the dose of SUBSYS if warranted.



    5.5 Effects on Ability to Drive and Use Machines



  Opioid analgesics impair the mental and/or physical ability required for the performance of potentially dangerous tasks (e.g., driving a car or operating machinery). Warn patients taking SUBSYS of these dangers and counsel them accordingly.



    5.6 Chronic Pulmonary Disease



  Because potent opioids can cause respiratory depression, titrate SUBSYS with caution in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or preexisting medical conditions predisposing them to respiratory depression. In such patients, even normal therapeutic doses of SUBSYS may further decrease respiratory drive to the point of respiratory failure.



    5.7 Head Injuries and Increased Intracranial Pressure



  Administer SUBSYS with extreme caution in patients who may be particularly susceptible to the intracranial effects of CO2retention such as those with evidence of increased intracranial pressure or impaired consciousness. Opioids may obscure the clinical course of a patient with a head injury and should be used only if clinically warranted.



    5.8 Cardiac Disease



  Intravenous fentanyl may produce bradycardia. Therefore, use SUBSYS with caution in patients with bradyarrhythmias.



    5.9 MAO Inhibitors



  SUBSYS is not recommended for use in patients who have received MAO inhibitors within 14 days, because severe and unpredictable potentiation by MAO inhibitors has been reported with opioid analgesics.



    5.10 Transmucosal Immediate Release Fentanyl (TIRF) Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS) ACCESS Program



  Because of the risk of misuse, abuse, addiction and overdose [see  Drug Abuse and Dependence (9)  ]  , SUBSYS is available only through a restricted program under a REMS called the TIRF REMS ACCESS program. Under the TIRF REMS ACCESS program, outpatients, prescribers who prescribe to outpatients, pharmacies, and distributors must enroll in the program. For inpatient administration (e.g. hospitals, hospices, and long-term care facilities that prescribe for inpatient use) of SUBSYS, patient and prescriber enrollment is not required.



 Required components of the TIRF REMS ACCESS program are:



 *  Healthcare professionals who prescribe SUBSYS must review the prescriber educational materials for the TIRF REMS ACCESS program, enroll in the program, and agree to comply with the REMS requirements. 
 *  To receive SUBSYS, patients must understand the risks and benefits and sign a Patient-Prescriber Agreement. 
 *  Pharmacies that dispense SUBSYS must enroll in the program and agree to comply with the REMS requirements. 
 *  Wholesalers and distributors that distribute SUBSYS must enroll in the program and distribute only to authorized pharmacies. 
    Further information, including a list of qualified pharmacies/distributors, is available at www.TIRFREMSaccess.com  or by calling 1-866-822-1483.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
