<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="suprep" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=3%) are: overall discomfort, abdominal fullness, nausea, abdominal cramping, and vomiting (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Braintree Laboratories, Inc. at 1-800-874-6756 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  .



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In a multicenter, controlled clinical trial comparing SUPREP Bowel Prep Kit with a bowel prep containing polyethylene glycol and electrolytes (PEG + E) that were administered in a split-dose (2-day) regimen, the most common adverse reactions after administration of SUPREP Bowel Prep Kit were overall discomfort, abdominal distention, abdominal pain, nausea, vomiting, and headache; see  Table 1  , below. Less common Adverse Reactions occurring were AV Block (1 case) and CK increase. In this study, patients receiving SUPREP Bowel Prep Kit were limited to a light breakfast followed by clear liquids; patients receiving the PEG + E bowel prep were allowed to have a normal breakfast and a light lunch, followed by clear liquids.



 Table 1: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions Observed in at Least 2% of Patients on the Split-Dose (2-Day) Regimen 
                                 Split-Dose (2-Day) Regimen          
   Symptom                     SUPREPN=190                          PEG + E productN=189                  
 Overall Discomfort            54%                                  67%                                   
 Abdominal Distension          40%                                  52%                                   
 Abdominal Pain                36%                                  43%                                   
 Nausea                        36%                                  33%                                   
 Vomiting                      8%                                   4%                                    
 Headache                      1.1%                                 0.5%                                  
           Table 2  shows the percentages of patients who developed new abnormalities of important electrolytes and uric acid after completing the bowel preparation with either SUPREP Bowel Prep Kit or PEG+E administered as a split-dose (2-day) regimen.
 

 Table 2: Patients with Normal Baseline Serum Chemistry with A Shift to an Abnormal Value While on the Split-Dose (2-Day) Regimen 
  *Percent (n/N) of patients where N=number of patients with normal baseline who had abnormal values at the timepoint(s) of interest.    
  Patients with normal bicarbonate at baseline who developed low bicarbonate (&lt;= 21 mEq/L) and high anion gap (&gt;= 13 mEq/L) on Day of Colonoscopy or Day 30.    
  
                                                        Day of Colonoscopy    n (%)*      Day 30    n (%)*          
 Anion gap (high)           SUPREP                    14 (8.9)                  3 (1.9)                     
                            PEG + Electrolytes        12 (7.6)                  2 (1.4)                     
 Bicarbonate (low)          SUPREP                    20 (12.7)                 7 (4.4)                     
                            PEG + Electrolytes        24 (15.2)                 4 (2.7)                     
 Bilirubin, total (high)    SUPREP                    14 (8.5)                  0 (0)                       
                            PEG + Electrolytes        20 (11.7)                 3 (1.9)                     
 BUN (high)                 SUPREP                    2 (1.6)                   14 (11.2)                   
                            PEG + Electrolytes        4 (2.9)                   19 (14.5)                   
 Calcium (high)             SUPREP                    16 (10.4)                 8 (5.2)                     
                            PEG + Electrolytes        6 (3.7)                   6 (3.9)                     
 Chloride (high)            SUPREP                    4 (2.4)                   6 (3.7)                     
                            PEG + Electrolytes        20 (12.2)                 6 (3.8)                     
 Creatinine (high)          SUPREP                    3 (1.9)                   5 (3.2)                     
                            PEG + Electrolytes        2 (1.2)                   8 (5.2)                     
 Osmolality (high)          SUPREP                    8 (5.8)                   NA                          
                            PEG + Electrolytes        19 (12.9)                 NA                          
 Osmolality (low)           SUPREP                    3 (2.2)                   NA                          
                            PEG + Electrolytes        2 (1.4)                   NA                          
 Potassium (high)           SUPREP                    3 (1.8)                   6 (3.7)                     
                            PEG + Electrolytes        5 (2.9)                   8 (4.9)                     
 Sodium (low)               SUPREP                    5 (3.1)                   1 (0.6)                     
                            PEG + Electrolytes        4 (2.3)                   2 (1.2)                     
 Uric acid (high)           SUPREP                    27 (23.5)                 13 (11.5)                   
                            PEG + Electrolytes        12 (9.5)                  20 (16.7)                   
          There were also 408 patients who participated in a study in which either SUPREP Bowel Prep Kit or PEG+E were administered in an evening-only (1-day) regimen. Higher rates of overall discomfort, abdominal distention, and nausea were observed with the evening-only (1-day) regimen compared to the split-dose (2-day) regimen for both preparations. Patients treated with SUPREP Bowel Prep Kit had increased rates of vomiting with the evening-only (1-day) regimen. An evening-only (1-day) dosing regimen was associated with higher rates of abnormal values for some electrolytes when compared to the split-dose (2-day) regimen for both preparations. For SUPREP Bowel Prep Kit, the evening-only (1-day) regimen was associated with higher rates of total bilirubin (high), BUN (high), creatinine (high), osmolality (high), potassium (high) and uric acid (high) than the SUPREP Bowel Prep Kit split-dose (2-day) regimen. Administration of SUPREP Bowel Prep Kit in an evening-only (1-day) dosing regimen is  not  recommended.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Risk of fluid and electrolyte abnormalities, arrhythmias, seizures and renal impairment - assess concurrent medications and consider testing in some patients (  5.1  ,  5.2  ,  5.3  ) 
 *  Patients with renal insufficiency - use caution, ensure adequate hydration and consider testing (  5.4  ) 
 *  Suspected GI obstruction or perforation - rule out the diagnosis before administration (  4  ,  5.6  ) 
 *  Patients at risk for aspiration - observe during administration (  5.7  ) 
 *  Not for direct ingestion - dilute and take with additional water (  5.8  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Serious Fluid and Serum Chemistry Abnormalities



  Advise all patients to hydrate adequately before, during, and after the use of SUPREP Bowel Prep Kit. If a patient develops significant vomiting or signs of dehydration after taking SUPREP Bowel Prep Kit, consider performing post-colonoscopy lab tests (electrolytes, creatinine, and BUN). Fluid and electrolyte disturbances can lead to serious adverse events including cardiac arrhythmias, seizures and renal impairment.



 Patients with electrolyte abnormalities should have them corrected before treatment with SUPREP Bowel Prep Kit. In addition, use caution when prescribing SUPREP Bowel Prep Kit for patients with conditions, or who are using medications, that increase the risk for fluid and electrolyte disturbances or may increase the risk of adverse events of seizure, arrhythmias, and renal impairment. [ see Drug Interactions (  7.1  )]  



 SUPREP Bowel Prep Kit can cause temporary elevations in uric acid. [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  . Uric acid fluctuations in patients with gout may precipitate an acute flare. The potential for uric acid elevation should be considered before administering SUPREP Bowel Prep Kit to patients with gout or other disorders of uric acid metabolism.



    5.2 Cardiac Arrhythmias



  There have been rare reports of serious arrhythmias associated with the use of ionic osmotic laxative products for bowel preparation. Use caution when prescribing SUPREP Bowel Prep Kit for patients at increased risk of arrhythmias (e.g., patients with a history of prolonged QT, uncontrolled arrhythmias, recent myocardial infarction, unstable angina, congestive heart failure, or cardiomyopathy). Pre-dose and post-colonoscopy ECGs should be considered in patients at increased risk of serious cardiac arrhythmias.



    5.3 Seizures



  There have been reports of generalized tonic-clonic seizures and/or loss of consciousness associated with use of bowel preparation products in patients with no prior history of seizures. The seizure cases were associated with electrolyteabnormalities (e.g., hyponatremia, hypokalemia, hypocalcemia, and hypomagnesemia) and low serum osmolality. The neurologic abnormalities resolved with correction of fluid and electrolyte abnormalities.



 Use caution when prescribing SUPREP Bowel Prep Kit for patients with a history of seizures and in patients at increased risk of seizure, such as patients taking medications that lower the seizure threshold (e.g., tricyclic antidepressants), patients withdrawing from alcohol or benzodiazepines, or patients with known or suspected hyponatremia.



    5.4 Renal Impairment



  Use caution when prescribing SUPREP Bowel Prep Kit for patients with impaired renal function or patients taking concomitant medications that may affect renal function (such as diuretics, angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors, angiotensin receptor blockers, or non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs). Advise these patients of the importance of adequate hydration, and consider performing baseline and post-colonoscopy laboratory tests (electrolytes, creatinine, and BUN) in these patients.



    5.5 Colonic Mucosal Ulcerations and Ischemic Colitis



  Administration of osmotic laxative products may produce colonic mucosal aphthous ulcerations, and there have been reports of more serious cases of ischemic colitis requiring hospitalization. Concurrent use of stimulant laxatives and SUPREP Bowel Prep Kit may increase these risks. The potential for mucosal ulcerations resulting from the bowel preparation should be considered when interpreting colonoscopy findings in patients with known or suspect inflammatory bowel disease (IBD).



    5.6 Use in Patients with Significant Gastrointestinal Disease



  If gastrointestinal obstruction or perforation is suspected, perform appropriate diagnostic studies to rule out these conditions before administering SUPREP Bowel Prep Kit.



 Use with caution in patients with severe active ulcerative colitis.



    5.7 Aspiration



  Use with caution in patients with impaired gag reflex and patients prone to regurgitation or aspiration. Such patients should be observed during administration of SUPREP Bowel Prep Kit solution.



    5.8 Not for Direct Ingestion



  Each bottle must be diluted with water to a final volume of 16 ounces and ingestion of additional water as recommended is important to patient tolerance. Direct ingestion of the undiluted solution may increase the risk of nausea, vomiting, dehydration, and electrolyte disturbances.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
