<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="suprax" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions are gastrointestinal such as diarrhea (16%), nausea (7%), loose stools (6%), abdominal pain (3%), dyspepsia (3%), and vomiting. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Lupin Pharma at 1-800-399-2561 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The most commonly seen adverse reactions in U.S. trials of the tablet formulation were gastrointestinal events, which were reported in 30% of adult patients on either the twice daily or the once daily regimen. Five percent (5%) of patients in the U.S. clinical trials discontinued therapy because of drug-related adverse reactions. Individual adverse reactions included diarrhea 16%, loose or frequent stools 6%, abdominal pain 3%, nausea 7%, dyspepsia 3%, and flatulence 4%. The incidence of gastrointestinal adverse reactions, including diarrhea and loose stools, in pediatric patients receiving the suspension was comparable to the incidence seen in adult patients receiving tablets.



   6.2 Post-marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been reported following the use of cefixime. Incidence rates were less than 1 in 50 (less than 2%).



     Gastrointestinal    



 Several cases of documented pseudomembranous colitis were identified in clinical trials. The onset of pseudomembranous colitis symptoms may occur during or after therapy.



     Hypersensitivity Reactions    



 Anaphylactic/anaphylactoid reactions (including shock and fatalities), skin rashes, urticaria, drug fever, pruritus, angioedema, and facial edema. Erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and serum sickness-like reactions have been reported.



     Hepatic    



 Transient elevations in SGPT, SGOT, alkaline phosphatase, hepatitis, jaundice.



     Renal    



 Transient elevations in BUN or creatinine, acute renal failure.



     Central Nervous System    



 Headaches, dizziness, seizures.



     Hemic and Lymphatic System    



 Transient thrombocytopenia, leukopenia, neutropenia, prolongation in prothrombin time, elevated LDH, pancytopenia, agranulocytosis, and eosinophilia.



     Abnormal Laboratory Tests    



 Hyperbilirubinemia.



     Other Adverse Reactions    



 Genital pruritus, vaginitis, candidiasis, toxic epidermal necrolysis.



     Adverse Reactions Reported for Cephalosporin-class Drugs    



 Allergic reactions, superinfection, renal dysfunction, toxic nephropathy, hepatic dysfunction including cholestasis, aplastic anemia, hemolytic anemia, hemorrhage, and colitis.



 Several cephalosporins have been implicated in triggering seizures, particularly in patients with renal impairment when the dosage was not reduced. [See  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION (  2  )  and  OVERDOSAGE (  10    )]. If seizures associated with drug therapy occur, the drug should be discontinued. Anticonvulsant therapy can be given if clinically indicated.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Hypersensitivity reactions including shock and fatalities have been reported with cefixime. Discontinue use if a reaction occurs. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Clostridium difficile associated diarrhea: Evaluate if diarrhea occurs. (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Anaphylactic/anaphylactoid reactions (including shock and fatalities) have been reported with the use of cefixime.



 Before therapy with Suprax is instituted, careful inquiry should be made to determine whether the patient has had previous hypersensitivity reactions to cephalosporins, penicillins, or other drugs. If this product is to be given to penicillin-sensitive patients, caution should be exercised because cross hypersensitivity among beta-lactam antibiotics has been clearly documented and may occur in up to 10% of patients with a history of penicillin allergy. If an allergic reaction to Suprax occurs, discontinue the drug.



    5.2 Clostridium difficile-Associated Diarrhea



   Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea (CDAD) has been reported with use of nearly all antibacterial agents, including Suprax, and may range in severity from mild diarrhea to fatal colitis. Treatment with antibacterial agents alters the normal flora of the colon leading to overgrowth of C. difficile.  



  C. difficile  produces toxins A and B which contribute to the development of CDAD. Hypertoxin producing isolates of C.    difficile  cause increased morbidity and mortality, as these infections can be refractory to antimicrobial therapy and may require colectomy. CDAD must be considered in all patients who present with diarrhea following antibiotic use. Careful medical history is necessary since CDAD has been reported to occur over two months after the administration of antibacterial agents.



 If CDAD is suspected or confirmed, ongoing antibiotic use not directed against C. difficile  may need to be discontinued. Appropriate fluid and electrolyte management, protein supplementation, antibiotic treatment of C. difficile,  and surgical evaluation should be instituted as clinically indicated.



    5.3 Dose Adjustment in Renal Impairment



  The dose of Suprax should be adjusted in patients with renal impairment as well as those undergoing continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis (CAPD) and hemodialysis (HD). Patients on dialysis should be monitored carefully [See DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION (  2  )  ].



    5.4 Coagulation Effects



  Cephalosporins, including Suprax, may be associated with a fall in prothrombin activity. Those at risk include patients with renal or hepatic impairment, or poor nutritional state, as well as patients receiving a protracted course of antimicrobial therapy, and patients previously stabilized on anticoagulant therapy. Prothrombin time should be monitored in patients at risk and exogenous vitamin K administered as indicated.



    5.5 Development of Drug-Resistant Bacteria



  Prescribing Suprax (cefixime) in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug-resistant bacteria.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
