<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="suprane" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence&gt; 10%) are coughing, breath holding, apnea, nausea, vomiting.  (6)  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Baxter Healthcare Corporation at 1-800-262-3784 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Adverse event information is derived from controlled clinical trials, the majority of which were conducted in the United States. The studies were conducted using a variety of premedications, other anesthetics, and surgical procedures of varying length. Most adverse events reported were mild and transient, and may reflect the surgical procedures, patient characteristics (including disease) and/or medications administered.



 Of the 2,143 patients exposed to SUPRANE in clinical trials, 370 adults and 152 children were induced with desflurane alone and 987 patients were maintained principally with desflurane. The frequencies given reflect the percent of patients with the event. Each patient was counted once for each type of adverse event. They are presented in alphabetical order according to body system.



 Table 2 
  Frequency of Events Occurring in Greater Than 1% of Clinical Trial Patients (in Reports Deemed "Probably Causally Related")    
  Induction (use as a mask inhalation agent)    
  Adult Patients (N=370):             Coughing 34%, breathholding 30%, apnea 15%, increased secretionsIncidence of events 3% - 10%, laryngospasm, oxyhemoglobin desaturation (SpO2 &lt; 90%), pharyngitis.    
  Maintenance or Recovery  Adult and Intubated Pediatric Patients (N=687):    
                                     Body as a Whole                    
                                                                          Headache                                                            
                                     Cardiovascular                     
                                                                          Bradycardia, hypertension, nodal arrhythmia, tachycardia            
                                     Digestive                          
                                                                          Nausea 27%, vomiting 16%                                            
                                     Nervous system                     
                                                                          Increased salivation                                                
                                     Respiratory                        
                                                                          Apnea, breathholding, cough increased, laryngospasm, pharyngitis    
                                     Special Senses                     
                                                                          Conjunctivitis (conjunctival hyperemia)                             
      
  Frequency of Events Occurring in Less Than 1% of Patients (in Reports Deemed "Probably Causally Related")  Reported in 3 or more patients, regardless of severity  Adverse reactions reported only from postmarketing experience or in the literature, not seen in clinical trials, are considered rare and are italicized.    
                                           Cardiovascular                         
                                                                                    Arrhythmia, bigeminy, abnormal electrocardiogram, myocardial ischemia, vasodilation    
                                           Digestive                              
                                                                                    Hepatitis                                                      
                                           Nervous System                         
                                                                                    Agitation, dizziness                                           
                                           Respiratory                            
                                                                                    Asthma, dyspnea, hypoxia                                       
  Frequency of Events Occurring in Less Than 1% of Clinical Trial Patients(in Reports Deemed "Causal Relationship Unknown")  Reported in 3 or more patients, regardless of severity    
                                           Body as a Whole                        
                                                                                    Fever                                                          
                                           Cardiovascular                         
                                                                                    Hemorrhage, myocardial infarction                              
                                           Metabolic and Nutrition                
                                                                                    Increased creatinine phosphokinase                             
                                           Musculoskeletal System                 
                                                                                    Myalgia                                                        
                                           Skin and Appendages                    
                                                                                    Pruritus                                                       
          6.2 Post-Marketing Experience
     The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of SUPRANE. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.  



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders  : Coagulopathy



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders  : Hyperkalemia, Hypokalemia, metabolic acidosis



   Nervous System Disorders  : Convulsion



   Eye Disorders:  Ocular icterus



   Cardiac Disorders:  Cardiac arrest, Torsade de pointes, ventricular failure, ventricular hypokinesia, atrial fibrillation



   Vascular Disorders:  Malignant hypertension, hemorrhage, hypotension, shock



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  Respiratory arrest, respiratory failure, respiratory distress, bronchospasm, hemoptysis



   Gastrointestinal Disorders  : Pancreatitis acute, abdominal pain



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:  Hepatic failure, hepatic necrosis, hepatitis, cytolytic hepatitis, cholestasis, jaundice, hepatic function abnormal, liver disorder



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorder  : Urticaria, erythema



   Musculoskeletal, Connective Tissue and Bone Disorders:  Rhabdomyolysis



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  Hyperthermia malignant, asthenia, malaise



   Investigations:  Electrocardiogram ST-T change, electrocardiogram T-wave inversion, tranaminases increased, alanine aminotransferase increased, aspartate aminotransferase increased, blood bilirubin increased, coagulation test abnormal, ammonia increased



   Injury, Poisoning, and Procedural Complications*:  Tachyarrhythmia, palpitations, eye burns, blindness transient, encephalopathy, ulcerative keratitis, ocular hyperemia, visual acuity reduced, eye irritation, eye pain, dizziness, migraine, fatigue, accidental exposure, skin burning sensation, drug administration error



 *All of reactions categorized within this SOC were accidental exposures to non-patients.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Malignant hyperthermia may occur.  (5.1)   
 *    Perioperative hyperkalemia may occur. Patients with latent or overt neuromuscular disease, particularly with Duchenne muscular dystrophy, appear to be most vulnerable.  (5.2)   
 *    SUPRANE may cause sensitivity hepatitis in patients sensitized by previous exposure to halogenated anesthetics. (  4  ,  5.5  ) 
 *    SUPRANE is not approved for maintenance of anesthesia in non-intubated children due to an increased incidence of respiratory adverse reactions. (  5.3  ,  8.4  ) 
 *    SUPRANE may cause airway narrowing and increased airway resistance in children with Bronchial hyperreactivity. (  5.3  ) 
 *    SUPRANE can react with desiccated CO2absorbents to produce carbon monoxide. (  5.4  ) 
 *    There are no adequate or well-controlled studies in pregnant or lactating women or during labor and delivery. SUPRANE is a uterine relaxant. (  8.1  ,  8.2  ,  8.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Malignant Hyperthermia



  In susceptible individuals, potent inhalation anesthetic agents may trigger a skeletal muscle hypermetabolic state leading to high oxygen demand and the clinical syndrome known as malignant hyperthermia. In genetically susceptible pigs, desflurane induced malignant hyperthermia. The clinical syndrome is signaled by hypercapnia, and may include muscle rigidity, tachycardia, tachypnea, cyanosis, arrhythmias, and/or unstable blood pressure. Some of these nonspecific signs may also appear during light anesthesia: acute hypoxia, hypercapnia, and hypovolemia.



 Treatment of malignant hyperthermia includes discontinuation of triggering agents, administration of intravenous dantrolene sodium, and application of supportive therapy. (Consult prescribing information for dantrolene sodium intravenous for additional information on patient management.) Renal failure may appear later, and urine flow should be monitored and sustained if possible.



 Fatal outcome of malignant hyperthermia has been reported with desflurane.



    5.2 Perioperative Hyperkalemia



  Use of inhaled anesthetic agents has been associated with rare increases in serum potassium levels that have resulted in cardiac arrhythmias and death in pediatric patients during the postoperative period. Patients with latent as well as overt neuromuscular disease, particularly Duchenne muscular dystrophy, appear to be most vulnerable. Concomitant use of succinylcholine has been associated with most, but not all, of these cases. These patients also experienced significant elevations in serum creatinine kinase levels and, in some cases, changes in urine consistent with myoglobinuria. Despite the similarity in presentation to malignant hyperthermia, none of these patients exhibited signs or symptoms of muscle rigidity or hypermetabolic state. Early and aggressive intervention to treat the hyperkalemia and resistant arrhythmias is recommended, as is subsequent evaluation for latent neuromuscular disease.



    5.3 Respiratory Adverse Reactions in Pediatric Patients



  SUPRANE is not approved for maintenance of anesthesia in non-intubated children due to an increased incidence of respiratory adverse reactions, including coughing, laryngospasm and secretions [see  Clinical Studies (14.5)  ].



 Children, particularly if 6 years old or younger, who are under an anesthetic maintenance of SUPRANE delivered via laryngeal mask airway (LMATM mask) are at increased risk for adverse respiratory reactions, e.g., coughing and laryngospasm, especially with removal of the laryngeal mask airway under deep anesthesia [see  Clinical Studies (14.5)  ]. Therefore, closely monitor these patients for signs and symptoms associated with laryngospasm and treat accordingly.



 When SUPRANE is used for maintenance of anesthesia in children with asthma or a history of recent upper airway infection, there is an increased risk for airway narrowing and increases in airway resistance. Therefore, closely monitor these patients for signs and symptoms associated with airway narrowing and treat accordingly .  



    5.4 Interactions with Desiccated Carbon Dioxide Absorbents



  Desflurane like some other inhalation anesthetics, can react with desiccated carbon dioxide (CO2) absorbents to produce carbon monoxide that may result in elevated levels of carboxyhemoglobin in some patients. Case reports suggest that barium hydroxide lime and soda lime become desiccated when fresh gases are passed through the CO2canister at high flow rates over many hours or days. When a clinician suspects that CO2absorbent may be desiccated, it should be replaced before the administration of SUPRANE.



    5.5 Hepatobiliary Disorders



  With the use of halogenated anesthetics, disruption of hepatic function, icterus and fatal liver necrosis have been reported; such reactions appear to indicate hypersensitivity. As with other halogenated anesthetic agents, SUPRANE may cause sensitivity hepatitis in patients who have been sensitized by previous exposure to halogenated anesthetics [see  Contraindications (4)  ]. Cirrhosis, viral hepatitis or other pre-existing hepatic disease may be a reason to select an anesthetic other than a halogenated anesthetic. As with all halogenated anesthetics, repeated anesthesia within a short period of time should be approached with caution.



    5.6 Laboratory Findings



  Transient elevations in glucose and white blood cell count may occur as with use of other anesthetic agents.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
