<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="survanta" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    Adverse Reactions

  The most commonly reported adverse experiences were associated with the dosing procedure. In the multiple-dose controlled clinical trials, each dose of SURVANTA was divided into four quarter-doses which were instilled through a catheter inserted into the endotracheal tube by briefly disconnecting the endotracheal tube from the ventilator. Transient bradycardia occurred with 11.9% of  doses  . Oxygen desaturation occurred with 9.8% of  doses  .



 Other reactions during the dosing procedure occurred with fewer than 1% of doses and included endotracheal tube reflux, pallor, vasoconstriction, hypotension, endotracheal tube blockage, hypertension, hypocarbia, hypercarbia, and apnea. No deaths occurred during the dosing procedure, and all reactions resolved with symptomatic treatment.



 The occurrence of concurrent illnesses common in premature infants was evaluated in the controlled trials. The rates in all controlled studies are in Table 3.



 Table 3. 
   All Controlled Studies              
 Concurrent Event                     SURVANTA (%)            Control      (%)        P  -Value  a          
 Patent ductus arteriosus             46.9                    47.1                  0.814                   
 Intracranial hemorrhage              48.1                    45.2                  0.241                   
 Severe intracranial hemorrhage       24.1                    23.3                  0.693                   
 Pulmonary air leaks                  10.9                    24.7                  &lt; 0.001                 
 Pulmonary interstitial emphysema     20.2                    38.4                  &lt; 0.001                 
 Necrotizing enterocolitis            6.1                     5.3                   0.427                   
 Apnea                                65.4                    59.6                  0.283                   
 Severe apnea                         46.1                    42.5                  0.114                   
 Post-treatment sepsis                20.7                    16.1                  0.019                   
 Post-treatment infection             10.2                    9.1                   0.345                   
 Pulmonary hemorrhage                 7.2                     5.3                   0.166                   
   a    P  -value comparing groups in controlled studies   
      When all controlled studies were pooled, there was no difference in intracranial hemorrhage. However, in one of the single-dose rescue studies and one of the multiple-dose prevention studies, the rate of intracranial hemorrhage was significantly higher in SURVANTA patients than control patients (63.3%  v  30.8%,  P  = 0.001; and 48.8%  v  34.2%,  P  = 0.047, respectively). The rate in a Treatment IND involving approximately 8100 infants was lower than in the controlled trials.
 

 In the controlled clinical trials, there was no effect of SURVANTA on results of common laboratory tests: white blood cell count and serum sodium, potassium, bilirubin, and creatinine.



 More than 4300 pretreatment and post-treatment serum samples from approximately 1500 patients were tested by Western Blot Immunoassay for antibodies to surfactant-associated proteins SP-B and SP-C. No IgG or IgM antibodies were detected.



 Several other complications are known to occur in premature infants. The following conditions were reported in the controlled clinical studies. The rates of the complications were not different in treated and control infants, and none of the complications were attributed to SURVANTA.



   Respiratory

  lung consolidation, blood from the endotracheal tube, deterioration after weaning, respiratory decompensation, subglottic stenosis, paralyzed diaphragm, respiratory failure.



   Cardiovascular

  hypotension, hypertension, tachycardia, ventricular tachycardia, aortic thrombosis, cardiac failure, cardio-respiratory arrest, increased apical pulse, persistent fetal circulation, air embolism, total anomalous pulmonary venous return.



   Gastrointestinal

  abdominal distention, hemorrhage, intestinal perforations, volvulus, bowel infarct, feeding intolerance, hepatic failure, stress ulcer.



   Renal

  renal failure, hematuria.



   Hematologic

  coagulopathy, thrombocytopenia, disseminated intravascular coagulation.



   Central Nervous System

  seizures



   Endocrine/Metabolic

  adrenal hemorrhage, inappropriate ADH secretion, hyperphosphatemia.



   Musculoskeletal

  inguinal hernia.



   Systemic

  fever, deterioration.



   Follow-Up Evaluations

  To date, no long-term complications or sequelae of SURVANTA therapy have been found.



   Single-Dose Studies

  Six-month adjusted-age follow-up evaluations of 232 infants (115 treated) demonstrated no clinically important differences between treatment groups in pulmonary and neurologic sequelae, incidence or severity of retinopathy of prematurity, rehospitalizations, growth, or allergic manifestations.



   Multiple-Dose Studies

  Six-month adjusted age follow-up evaluations have been completed in 631 (345 treated) of 916 surviving infants. There were significantly less cerebral palsy and need for supplemental oxygen in SURVANTA infants than controls. Wheezing at the time of examination was significantly more frequent among SURVANTA infants, although there was no difference in bronchodilator therapy.



 Final twelve-month follow-up data from the multiple-dose studies are available from 521 (272 treated) of 909 surviving infants. There was significantly less wheezing in SURVANTA infants than controls, in contrast to the six-month results. There was no difference in the incidence of cerebral palsy at twelve months.



 Twenty-four month adjusted age evaluations were completed in 429 (226 treated) of 906 surviving infants. There were significantly fewer SURVANTA infants with rhonchi, wheezing, and tachypnea at the time of examination. No other differences were found.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
