<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="sustiva1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;5%, moderate-severe) are impaired concentration, abnormal dreams, rash, dizziness, nausea, headache, fatigue, insomnia, and vomiting.  (5.5  ,  6)    To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Bristol-Myers Squibb at 1-800-721-5072 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch    .  



 

  The most significant adverse reactions observed in patients treated with SUSTIVA are:



 *    psychiatric symptoms [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   ], 
 *    nervous system symptoms [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)   ], 
 *    rash [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)   ]. 
      6.1 Clinical Trials Experience
   Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, the adverse reaction rates reported cannot be directly compared to rates in other clinical studies and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



   Adverse Reactions in Adults

  The most common (&gt;5% in either efavirenz treatment group) adverse reactions of at least moderate severity among patients in Study 006 treated with SUSTIVA in combination with zidovudine/lamivudine or indinavir were rash, dizziness, nausea, headache, fatigue, insomnia, and vomiting.



 Selected clinical adverse reactions of moderate or severe intensity observed in &gt;=2% of SUSTIVA-treated patients in two controlled clinical trials are presented in Table 2.



 Table 2: Selected Treatment-Emergenta Adverse Reactions of Moderate or Severe Intensity Reported in &gt;=2% of SUSTIVA-Treated Patients in Studies 006 and ACTG 364 
                              Study 006    LAM-, NNRTI-, and Protease Inhibitor-Naive Patients      Study ACTG 364    NRTI-experienced, NNRTI-, and Protease Inhibitor-Naive Patients     
                            SUSTIVA  b  +ZDV/LAM(n=412)  SUSTIVA  b  +Indinavir(n=415)  Indinavir+ZDV/LAM(n=401)  SUSTIVA  b  +Nelfinavir+ NRTIs(n=64)  SUSTIVA  b  +NRTIs(n=65)  Nelfinavir+NRTIs(n=66)   
   Adverse Reactions        180 weeks  c    102 weeks  c    76 weeks  c    71.1 weeks  c    70.9 weeks  c    62.7 weeks  c     
  
   a  Includes adverse events at least possibly related to study drug or of unknown relationship for Study 006. Includes all adverse events regardless of relationship to study drug for Study ACTG 364.  b  SUSTIVA provided as 600 mg once daily.  c  Median duration of treatment.  d  Includes erythema multiforme, rash, rash erythematous, rash follicular, rash maculopapular, rash petechial, rash pustular, and urticaria for Study 006 and macules, papules, rash, erythema, redness, inflammation, allergic rash, urticaria, welts, hives, itchy, and pruritus for ACTG 364.- = Not Specified.ZDV = zidovudine, LAM = lamivudine.   
  
  Body as a Whole            
    Fatigue                  8%             5%            9%            0             2%             3%            
    Pain                     1%             2%            8%            13%           6%             17%           
  Central and Peripheral Nervous System    
    Dizziness                9%             9%            2%            2%            6%             6%            
    Headache                 8%             5%            3%            5%            2%             3%            
    Insomnia                 7%             7%            2%            0             0              2%            
    Concentration impaired    5%             3%            &lt;1%           0             0              0             
    Abnormal dreams          3%             1%            0             -             -              -             
    Somnolence               2%             2%            &lt;1%           0             0              0             
    Anorexia                 1%             &lt;1%           &lt;1%           0             2%             2%            
  Gastrointestinal           
    Nausea                   10%            6%            24%           3%            2%             2%            
    Vomiting                 6%             3%            14%           -             -              -             
    Diarrhea                 3%             5%            6%            14%           3%             9%            
    Dyspepsia                4%             4%            6%            0             0              2%            
    Abdominal pain           2%             2%            5%            3%            3%             3%            
  Psychiatric                
    Anxiety                  2%             4%            &lt;1%           -             -              -             
    Depression               5%             4%            &lt;1%           3%            0              5%            
    Nervousness              2%             2%            0             2%            0              2%            
  Skin &amp; Appendages          
    Rashd                    11%            16%           5%            9%            5%             9%            
    Pruritus                 &lt;1%            1%            1%            9%            5%             9%            
             Pancreatitis has been reported, although a causal relationship with efavirenz has not been established. Asymptomatic increases in serum amylase levels were observed in a significantly higher number of patients treated with efavirenz 600 mg than in control patients (see    Laboratory Abnormalities    ).
 

   Nervous System Symptoms

  For 1008 patients treated with regimens containing SUSTIVA and 635 patients treated with a control regimen in controlled trials, Table 3 lists the frequency of symptoms of different degrees of severity and gives the discontinuation rates for one or more of the following nervous system symptoms: dizziness, insomnia, impaired concentration, somnolence, abnormal dreaming, euphoria, confusion, agitation, amnesia, hallucinations, stupor, abnormal thinking, and depersonalization [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)    ]. The frequencies of specific central and peripheral nervous system symptoms are provided in Table 2.



 Table 3: Percent of Patients with One or More Selected Nervous System Symptomsa,b 
   Percent of Patients with:           SUSTIVA 600 mg Once Daily    (n=1008)      Control Groups    (n=635)         
   %                                   %                                 
  
   a    Includes events reported regardless of causality.  b    Data from Study 006 and three Phase 2/3 studies.  c    "Mild" = Symptoms which do not interfere with patient's daily activities.  d    "Moderate" = Symptoms which may interfere with daily activities.  e    "Severe" = Events which interrupt patient's usual daily activities.   
  
  Symptoms of any severity            52.7                               24.6                               
  Mild symptomsc                      33.3                               15.6                               
  Moderate symptomsd                  17.4                               7.7                                
  Severe symptomse                    2.0                                1.3                                
  Treatment discontinuation as a result of symptoms    2.1                                1.1                                
           Psychiatric Symptoms
   Serious psychiatric adverse experiences have been reported in patients treated with SUSTIVA. In controlled trials, psychiatric symptoms observed at a frequency greater than 2% among patients treated with SUSTIVA or control regimens, respectively, were depression (19%, 16%), anxiety (13%, 9%), and nervousness (7%, 2%).



   Rash

  In controlled clinical trials, the frequency of rash (all grades, regardless of causality) was 26% for 1008 adults treated with regimens containing SUSTIVA and 17% for 635 adults treated with a control regimen. Most reports of rash were mild or moderate in severity. The frequency of Grade 3 rash was 0.8% for SUSTIVA-treated patients and 0.3% for control groups, and the frequency of Grade 4 rash was 0.1% for SUSTIVA and 0 for control groups. The discontinuation rates as a result of rash were 1.7% for SUSTIVA-treated patients and 0.3% for control groups [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)    ].



 Experience with SUSTIVA in patients who discontinued other antiretroviral agents of the NNRTI class is limited. Nineteen patients who discontinued nevirapine because of rash have been treated with SUSTIVA. Nine of these patients developed mild-to-moderate rash while receiving therapy with SUSTIVA, and two of these patients discontinued because of rash.



   Laboratory Abnormalities

  Selected Grade 3-4 laboratory abnormalities reported in &gt;=2% of SUSTIVA-treated patients in two clinical trials are presented in Table 4.



 Table 4: Selected Grade 3-4 Laboratory Abnormalities Reported in &gt;=2% of SUSTIVA-Treated Patients in Studies 006 and ACTG 364 
                    Study 006    LAM-, NNRTI-, and Protease    Inhibitor-Naive Patients      Study ACTG 364    NRTI-experienced, NNRTI-, and Protease Inhibitor-Naive Patients     
 Variable         Limit       SUSTIVA  a  +ZDV/LAM(n=412)  SUSTIVA  a  + Indinavir(n=415)  Indinavir+ZDV/LAM(n=401)  SUSTIVA  a  + Nelfinavir+ NRTIs(n=64)  SUSTIVA  a  + NRTIs(n=65)  Nelfinavir+ NRTIs(n=66)   
 180 weeks  b     102 weeks  b    76 weeks  b    71.1 weeks  b    70.9 weeks  b    62.7 weeks  b     
  
   a    SUSTIVA provided as 600 mg once daily.  b    Median duration of treatment.  c    Isolated elevations of GGT in patients receiving SUSTIVA may reflect enzyme induction not associated with liver toxicity.  d    Nonfasting.ZDV = zidovudine, LAM = lamivudine, ULN = upper limit of normal, ALT = alanine aminotransferase, AST = aspartate aminotransferase, GGT = gamma-glutamyltransferase.   
  
  Chemistry        
     ALT           &gt;5 * ULN    5%            8%            5%            2%            6%            3%            
     AST           &gt;5 * ULN    5%            6%            5%            6%            8%            8%            
     GGTc          &gt;5 * ULN    8%            7%            3%            5%            0             5%            
     Amylase       &gt;2 * ULN    4%            4%            1%            0             6%            2%            
     Glucose       &gt;250 mg/dL    3%            3%            3%            5%            2%            3%            
     Triglyceridesd    &gt;=751 mg/dL    9%            6%            6%            11%           8%            17%           
  Hematology       
     Neutrophils    &lt;750/mm3    10%           3%            5%            2%            3%            2%            
                Patients Coinfected with Hepatitis B or C
   Liver function tests should be monitored in patients with a history of hepatitis B and/or C. In the long-term data set from Study 006, 137 patients treated with SUSTIVA-containing regimens (median duration of therapy, 68 weeks) and 84 treated with a control regimen (median duration, 56 weeks) were seropositive at screening for hepatitis B (surface antigen positive) and/or C (hepatitis C antibody positive). Among these coinfected patients, elevations in AST to greater than five times ULN developed in 13% of patients in the SUSTIVA arms and 7% of those in the control arm, and elevations in ALT to greater than five times ULN developed in 20% of patients in the SUSTIVA arms and 7% of patients in the control arm. Among coinfected patients, 3% of those treated with SUSTIVA-containing regimens and 2% in the control arm discontinued from the study because of liver or biliary system disorders [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)    ].



   Lipids

  Increases from baseline in total cholesterol of 10-20% have been observed in some uninfected volunteers receiving SUSTIVA. In patients treated with SUSTIVA + zidovudine + lamivudine, increases from baseline in nonfasting total cholesterol and HDL of approximately 20% and 25%, respectively, were observed. In patients treated with SUSTIVA + indinavir, increases from baseline in nonfasting cholesterol and HDL of approximately 40% and 35%, respectively, were observed. Nonfasting total cholesterol levels &gt;=240 mg/dL and &gt;=300 mg/dL were reported in 34% and 9%, respectively, of patients treated with SUSTIVA + zidovudine + lamivudine; 54% and 20%, respectively, of patients treated with SUSTIVA + indinavir; and 28% and 4%, respectively, of patients treated with indinavir + zidovudine + lamivudine. The effects of SUSTIVA on triglycerides and LDL in this study were not well characterized since samples were taken from nonfasting patients. The clinical significance of these findings is unknown [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)    ].



   Adverse Reactions in Pediatric Patients

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, the adverse reaction rates reported cannot be directly compared to rates in other clinical studies and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 Assessment of adverse reactions is based on three clinical trials in 182 HIV-1 infected pediatric patients (3 months to 21 years of age) who received SUSTIVA in combination with other antiretroviral agents for a median of 123 weeks. The adverse reactions observed in the three trials were similar to those observed in clinical trials in adults except that rash was more common in pediatric patients (32% for all grades regardless of causality) and more often of higher grade (ie, more severe). Two (1.1%) pediatric patients experienced Grade 3 rash (confluent rash with fever, generalized rash), and four (2.2%) pediatric patients had Grade 4 rash (all erythema multiforme). Five pediatric patients (2.7%) discontinued from the study because of rash [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)    ].



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of SUSTIVA. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Body as a Whole:  allergic reactions, asthenia, redistribution/accumulation of body fat [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.12)    ]



   Central and Peripheral Nervous System:  abnormal coordination, ataxia, cerebellar coordination and balance disturbances, convulsions, hypoesthesia, paresthesia, neuropathy, tremor, vertigo



   Endocrine:  gynecomastia



   Gastrointestinal:  constipation, malabsorption



   Cardiovascular:  flushing, palpitations



   Liver and Biliary System:  hepatic enzyme increase, hepatic failure, hepatitis. A few of the postmarketing reports of hepatic failure, including cases in patients with no pre-existing hepatic disease or other identifiable risk factors, were characterized by a fulminant course, progressing in some cases to transplantation or death.



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  hypercholesterolemia, hypertriglyceridemia



   Musculoskeletal:  arthralgia, myalgia, myopathy



   Psychiatric:  aggressive reactions, agitation, delusions, emotional lability, mania, neurosis, paranoia, psychosis, suicide



   Respiratory:  dyspnea



   Skin and Appendages:  erythema multiforme, photoallergic dermatitis, Stevens-Johnson syndrome



   Special Senses:  abnormal vision, tinnitus
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *     Do not use as a single agent or add on as a sole agent to a failing regimen. Consider potential for cross-resistance when choosing other agents.  (5.2)   
 *    Not recommended with ATRIPLA, which contains efavirenz, emtricitabine, and tenofovir disoproxil fumarate, unless needed for dose adjustment when coadministered with rifampin.  (5.3)   
 *     Serious psychiatric symptoms: Immediate medical evaluation is recommended for serious psychiatric symptoms such as severe depression or suicidal ideation.  (5.4  ,  17)   
 *     Nervous system symptoms (NSS): NSS are frequent and usually begin 1-2 days after initiating therapy and resolve in 2-4 weeks. Dosing at bedtime may improve tolerability. NSS are not predictive of onset of psychiatric symptoms.  (5.5  ,  6.1  ,  17)   
 *     Embryo-Fetal Toxicity: Avoid administration in the first trimester of pregnancy as fetal harm may occur.  (5.6  ,  8.1)   
 *     Hepatotoxicity: Monitor liver function tests before and during treatment in patients with underlying hepatic disease, including hepatitis B or C coinfection, marked transaminase elevations, or who are taking medications associated with liver toxicity. Among reported cases of hepatic failure, a few occurred in patients with no pre-existing hepatic disease.  (5.8  ,  6.1  ,  8.6)   
 *     Rash: Rash usually begins within 1-2 weeks after initiating therapy and resolves within 4 weeks. Discontinue if severe rash develops.  (5.7  ,  6.1  ,  17)   
 *     Convulsions: Use caution in patients with a history of seizures.  (5.9)   
 *     Lipids: Total cholesterol and triglyceride elevations. Monitor before therapy and periodically thereafter.  (5.10)   
 *     Immune reconstitution syndrome: May necessitate further evaluation and treatment.  (5.11)   
 *     Redistribution/accumulation of body fat: Observed in patients receiving antiretroviral therapy.  (5.12  ,  17)   
    
 

   5.1 Drug Interactions



  Efavirenz plasma concentrations may be altered by substrates, inhibitors, or inducers of CYP3A. Likewise, efavirenz may alter plasma concentrations of drugs metabolized by CYP3A or CYP2B6. The most prominent effect of efavirenz at steady-state is induction of CYP3A and CYP2B6.  [ See  Dosage and Administration (2.1)    and   Drug Interactions (7.1)    .]



    5.2 Resistance



  SUSTIVA must not be used as a single agent to treat HIV-1 infection or added on as a sole agent to a failing regimen. Resistant virus emerges rapidly when efavirenz is administered as monotherapy. The choice of new antiretroviral agents to be used in combination with efavirenz should take into consideration the potential for viral cross-resistance.



    5.3 Coadministration with Related Products



  Coadministration of SUSTIVA with ATRIPLA (efavirenz 600 mg/emtricitabine 200 mg/tenofovir disoproxil fumarate 300 mg) is not recommended unless needed for dose adjustment (eg, with rifampin), since efavirenz is one of its active ingredients.



    5.4 Psychiatric Symptoms



  Serious psychiatric adverse experiences have been reported in patients treated with SUSTIVA. In controlled trials of 1008 patients treated with regimens containing SUSTIVA for a mean of 2.1 years and 635 patients treated with control regimens for a mean of 1.5 years, the frequency (regardless of causality) of specific serious psychiatric events among patients who received SUSTIVA or control regimens, respectively, were severe depression (2.4%, 0.9%), suicidal ideation (0.7%, 0.3%), nonfatal suicide attempts (0.5%, 0), aggressive behavior (0.4%, 0.5%), paranoid reactions (0.4%, 0.3%), and manic reactions (0.2%, 0.3%). When psychiatric symptoms similar to those noted above were combined and evaluated as a group in a multifactorial analysis of data from Study 006, treatment with efavirenz was associated with an increase in the occurrence of these selected psychiatric symptoms. Other factors associated with an increase in the occurrence of these psychiatric symptoms were history of injection drug use, psychiatric history, and receipt of psychiatric medication at study entry; similar associations were observed in both the SUSTIVA and control treatment groups. In Study 006, onset of new serious psychiatric symptoms occurred throughout the study for both SUSTIVA-treated and control-treated patients. One percent of SUSTIVA-treated patients discontinued or interrupted treatment because of one or more of these selected psychiatric symptoms. There have also been occasional postmarketing reports of death by suicide, delusions, and psychosis-like behavior, although a causal relationship to the use of SUSTIVA cannot be determined from these reports. Patients with serious psychiatric adverse experiences should seek immediate medical evaluation to assess the possibility that the symptoms may be related to the use of SUSTIVA, and if so, to determine whether the risks of continued therapy outweigh the benefits. [ See  Adverse Reactions (6.1)    .]



    5.5 Nervous System Symptoms



  Fifty-three percent (531/1008) of patients receiving SUSTIVA in controlled trials reported central nervous system symptoms (any grade, regardless of causality) compared to 25% (156/635) of patients receiving control regimens [ see     Adverse Reactions (6.1, Table 3)    ]. These symptoms included, but were not limited to, dizziness (28.1% of the 1008 patients), insomnia (16.3%), impaired concentration (8.3%), somnolence (7.0%), abnormal dreams (6.2%), and hallucinations (1.2%). These symptoms were severe in 2.0% of patients; and 2.1% of patients discontinued therapy as a result. These symptoms usually begin during the first or second day of therapy and generally resolve after the first 2-4 weeks of therapy. After 4 weeks of therapy, the prevalence of nervous system symptoms of at least moderate severity ranged from 5% to 9% in patients treated with regimens containing SUSTIVA and from 3% to 5% in patients treated with a control regimen. Patients should be informed that these common symptoms were likely to improve with continued therapy and were not predictive of subsequent onset of the less frequent psychiatric symptoms [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)    ]. Dosing at bedtime may improve the tolerability of these nervous system symptoms [ see  Dosage and Administration (2)    ].



 Analysis of long-term data from Study 006 (median follow-up 180 weeks, 102 weeks, and 76 weeks for patients treated with SUSTIVA + zidovudine + lamivudine, SUSTIVA + indinavir, and indinavir + zidovudine + lamivudine, respectively) showed that, beyond 24 weeks of therapy, the incidences of new-onset nervous system symptoms among SUSTIVA-treated patients were generally similar to those in the indinavir-containing control arm.



 Patients receiving SUSTIVA should be alerted to the potential for additive central nervous system effects when SUSTIVA is used concomitantly with alcohol or psychoactive drugs.



 Patients who experience central nervous system symptoms such as dizziness, impaired concentration, and/or drowsiness should avoid potentially hazardous tasks such as driving or operating machinery.



    5.6 Embryo-Fetal Toxicity



  Efavirenz may cause fetal harm when administered during the first trimester to a pregnant woman. Advise females of reproductive potential who are receiving SUSTIVA to avoid pregnancy. [ See  Use in Specific Populations (8.1  and     8.3)    .]



    5.7 Rash



  In controlled clinical trials, 26% (266/1008) of adult patients treated with 600 mg SUSTIVA experienced new-onset skin rash compared with 17% (111/635) of those treated in control groups [ see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ]. Rash associated with blistering, moist desquamation, or ulceration occurred in 0.9% (9/1008) of patients treated with SUSTIVA. The incidence of Grade 4 rash (eg, erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome) in adult patients treated with SUSTIVA in all studies and expanded access was 0.1%. Rashes are usually mild-to-moderate maculopapular skin eruptions that occur within the first 2 weeks of initiating therapy with efavirenz (median time to onset of rash in adults was 11 days) and, in most patients continuing therapy with efavirenz, rash resolves within 1 month (median duration, 16 days). The discontinuation rate for rash in adult clinical trials was 1.7% (17/1008).



 Rash was reported in 59 of 182 pediatric patients (32%) treated with SUSTIVA [ see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)    ]. Two pediatric patients experienced Grade 3 rash (confluent rash with fever, generalized rash), and four patients had Grade 4 rash (erythema multiforme). The median time to onset of rash in pediatric patients was 28 days (range 3-1642 days). Prophylaxis with appropriate antihistamines before initiating therapy with SUSTIVA in pediatric patients should be considered.



 SUSTIVA can generally be reinitiated in patients interrupting therapy because of rash. SUSTIVA should be discontinued in patients developing severe rash associated with blistering, desquamation, mucosal involvement, or fever. Appropriate antihistamines and/or corticosteroids may improve the tolerability and hasten the resolution of rash. For patients who have had a life-threatening cutaneous reaction (eg, Stevens-Johnson syndrome), alternative therapy should be considered [ see also  Contraindications (4.1)    ].



    5.8 Hepatotoxicity



  Monitoring of liver enzymes before and during treatment is recommended for patients with underlying hepatic disease, including hepatitis B or C infection; patients with marked transaminase elevations; and patients treated with other medications associated with liver toxicity [ see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)    and   Use in Specific Populations (8.6)    ]. A few of the postmarketing reports of hepatic failure occurred in patients with no pre-existing hepatic disease or other identifiable risk factors [ see     Adverse Reactions (6.2)    ]. Liver enzyme monitoring should also be considered for patients without pre-existing hepatic dysfunction or other risk factors. In patients with persistent elevations of serum transaminases to greater than five times the upper limit of the normal range, the benefit of continued therapy with SUSTIVA needs to be weighed against the unknown risks of significant liver toxicity.



    5.9 Convulsions



  Convulsions have been observed in adult and pediatric patients receiving efavirenz, generally in the presence of known medical history of seizures [ see  Nonclinical Toxicology (13.2)    ]. Caution should be taken in any patient with a history of seizures. Patients who are receiving concomitant anticonvulsant medications primarily metabolized by the liver, such as phenytoin and phenobarbital, may require periodic monitoring of plasma levels [ see  Drug Interactions (7.1)    ].



    5.10 Lipid Elevations



  Treatment with SUSTIVA has resulted in increases in the concentration of total cholesterol and triglycerides [ see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ]. Cholesterol and triglyceride testing should be performed before initiating SUSTIVA therapy and at periodic intervals during therapy.



    5.11 Immune Reconstitution Syndrome



  Immune reconstitution syndrome has been reported in patients treated with combination antiretroviral therapy, including SUSTIVA. During the initial phase of combination antiretroviral treatment, patients whose immune system responds may develop an inflammatory response to indolent or residual opportunistic infections [such as Mycobacterium avium  infection, cytomegalovirus, Pneumocystis jiroveci  pneumonia (PCP), or tuberculosis], which may necessitate further evaluation and treatment.



 Autoimmune disorders (such as Graves' disease, polymyositis, and Guillain-Barre syndrome) have also been reported to occur in the setting of immune reconstitution; however, the time to onset is more variable, and can occur many months after initiation of treatment.



    5.12 Fat Redistribution



  Redistribution/accumulation of body fat including central obesity, dorsocervical fat enlargement (buffalo hump), peripheral wasting, facial wasting, breast enlargement, and "cushingoid appearance" have been observed in patients receiving antiretroviral therapy. The mechanism and long-term consequences of these events are currently unknown. A causal relationship has not been established.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
