<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="sustol" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following clinically significant adverse reactions are described elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Injection Site Reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Gastrointestinal Disorders [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Hypersensitivity Reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *  Serotonin Syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 3%) are injection site reactions, constipation, fatigue, headache, diarrhea, abdominal pain, insomnia, dyspepsia, dizziness, asthenia, and gastroesophageal reflux. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Heron Therapeutics, Inc. at 844-HERON11 (1-844-437-6611) and  www.SUSTOL.com  or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch      



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   SUSTOL  



 The safety of a 10 mg subcutaneous dose of SUSTOL was evaluated in two double-blind, randomized, active-controlled studies, in which 210 patients (23%) received MEC and 467 patients (51%) received AC combination chemotherapy. The data described below reflect exposure to a single 10 mg dose of SUSTOL in 924 patients whose mean age was 56 years (range 19 to 91 years); 76% of patients were female; 70% of patients were Caucasian, 16% Asian, 10% Black, and 4% other races. Dexamethasone was co-administered with SUSTOL in Study 1 and Study 2 and an NK1receptor antagonist was co-administered with SUSTOL in Study 2.



   Table 1  lists the most common adverse reactions reported in at least 3% of patients following a single-dose of SUSTOL 10 mg in Study 1 and/or Study 2. Overall, injection site reactions (ISRs) were the most common group of adverse reactions in SUSTOL-treated patients. Specific types of ISRs reported by SUSTOL-treated patients are shown in  Table 2  .



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions Occurring in at Least 3% of Patients Treated with SUSTOL 10 mg in Study 1 and/or Study 2 
                                 Study 1              Study 2         
 Adverse Reaction          SUSTOL10 mgsubcutaneous(N=468)%  Palonosetronhydrochloride0.25 mgintravenous(N=463)%  SUSTOL10 mgsubcutaneous(N=456)%  Ondansetron0.15 mg/kgintravenous(N=459)%   
  
 Injection Site Reactions, any          37                   15                   62              See footnote       
 Constipation                      14                   11                   22                   15            
 Fatigue                           11                   10                   21                   24            
 Headache                           9                    9                   13                   19            
 Diarrhea                           8                    7                    9                    8            
 Abdominal Pain                     7                    7                    7                    4            
 Insomnia                           4                    2                    5                    6            
 Dyspepsia                          3                    3                    6                    7            
 Dizziness                          3                    2                    5                    5            
 Asthenia                           4                    6                    2                    2            
 Gastroesophageal Reflux            1                    1                    5                    4            
             Injection Site Reactions (ISRs)  
 

 Injection site reactions occurred in 37% (175/468) in Study 1, Cycle 1 only, and 62% (281/456) in Study 2 of SUSTOL-treated patients. The ISR manifestations included pain, erythema, mass/nodule, swelling/induration, and bleeding. The incidence of individual ISRs is shown in  Table 2  . Patients may have experienced one or more types of injection site reactions; a total of 213 of 924 patients had three or more.



 ISR reporting procedures included both investigator- and patient-reported outcomes in Study 2, while Study 1 used only investigator reporting.



 Table 2. Injection Site Adverse Reactions Following a Single 10 mg SUSTOL Dose 
 Injection Site Reaction         Study 1Treatment Arm (Subcutaneous Injection)  Study 2  ,  SUSTOL(N=456)%   
 SUSTOL(N=468)%                  Saline Control(N=463)%    
  
 Total Subjects with at least 1 ISR            37                       15                       62              
 Pain                                       3                        1                       20              
 Tenderness                                 4                        1                       27              
 Bruising/Hematoma                         22                       10                       45              
 Bleeding                                   2                        1                        4              
 Erythema/Redness                          11                        3                       17              
 Swelling/Induration                        1                        0                       10              
 Mass/Nodule                               11                        1                       18              
 Infection at injection site               &lt;1                        0                        1              
 Other                                      2                        1                        1              
          Less common adverse reactions reported in less than 3% of SUSTOL-treated patients in clinical trials are syncope, elevation of serum transaminase levels, pancreatitis, atrial fibrillation, somnolence, flushing, and hypersensitivity reactions (e.g., anaphylaxis, urticaria).
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of other formulations of granisetron. Because they are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.




   System Organ Class                                  Adverse Reactions                                  
  
     Cardiovascular                                    bradycardia, chest pain, palpitations, sick sinus syndrome   
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Injection site reactions (ISRs), including infection, bleeding, pain, nodules, swelling and induration: Monitor for ISRs following SUSTOL injection. Inform patients that some ISRs may occur 2 weeks or more after SUSTOL administration. In patients receiving antiplatelet agents or anticoagulants, consider the increased risk of bruising or severe hematoma prior to the use of SUSTOL. (  5.1  ) 
 *   Gastrointestinal disorders: Monitor for constipation and consider optimizing patients' current bowel regimens used for managing preexisting constipation. Also monitor for decreased bowel activity, particularly in patients with risk factors for gastrointestinal obstruction. Instruct patients to seek immediate medical care if signs and symptoms of ileus occur. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Hypersensitivity reactions: Serious reactions have been reported and may occur up to 7 days or longer following SUSTOL administration and may have an extended course. If a reaction occurs, administer appropriate treatment and monitor until signs and symptoms resolve. (  5.3  ) 
 *   Serotonin syndrome: Reported with 5-HT receptor antagonists alone but particularly with concomitant use of serotonergic drugs. If such symptoms occur, discontinue SUSTOL and initiate supportive treatment. If concomitant use of SUSTOL with other serotonergic drugs is clinically warranted, patients should be made aware of a potential increased risk for serotonin syndrome. (  5.4  ,  7.1  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Injection Site Reactions (ISRs)



   Infections  



 Infections at the injection site occurred in 0.4% (7 of 1814) of patients with cancer and 0.2% (1 of 412) of healthy subjects in clinical trials. Infections had a median onset of 9 days (range 7 to 16 days) following SUSTOL administration. One patient who was neutropenic at the time of the infection was hospitalized. All patients with infection were treated with antibiotics and had complete resolution.



  Bruising and/or hematomas  



 Bruising and/or hematomas at the injection site occurred in 426 of 1131 (38%) patients treated with SUSTOL 10 mg with a median time to onset of 2 days. Bruising and/or hematomas with a delayed onset (onset 5 or more days following SUSTOL administration) were reported in 175 (15%) patients. Severe bruising or hematoma (e.g., greater than 4 cm bruise or hematoma) occurred in 3% of patients. Patients receiving concomitant anticoagulant and antiplatelet medications were at greater risk for severe injection site bruising and hematomas.



  Bleeding  



 Bleeding at the injection site occurred in 70 of 1814 (4%) patients treated with SUSTOL. One patient required emergency management. Bleeding for longer than 5 days was reported in 23 (1%) patients.



  Pain and Tenderness  



 In a clinical trial that collected information about injection site pain and tenderness from patient diaries, pain with or without tenderness at the injection site was reported by 91 of 456 (20%) of patients treated with SUSTOL 10 mg, and an additional 50 of 456 (11%) of patients reported tenderness without pain. Pain and/or tenderness severe enough to require taking pain medication, interfere with patient activity level, or cause significant discomfort at rest was reported in 2% of patients. Among all patients who reported pain and/or tenderness with SUSTOL 10 mg in clinical trials, the median duration was 5 days, and pain lasting longer than 7 days occurred in 6% of patients.



  Nodules  



 Nodules at the injection site occurred in 203 of 1131 (18%) of patients treated with SUSTOL 10 mg. Nodules persisted for a median of 15 days and 73 patients (6%) had nodules with durations longer than 21 days.



  Management of ISRs  



 *  Monitor patients for ISRs following SUSTOL injection. Some ISRs (infections, bruising, and hematoma) may occur up to 2 weeks or more after SUSTOL administration. 
 *  In patients receiving antiplatelet agents or anticoagulants, consider the increased risk of bruising or severe hematoma prior to the use of SUSTOL. 
 *  In patients with ongoing or unresolved ISRs, administer SUSTOL at a site away from areas affected by ISRs [see Dosage and Administration (  2.1  )] . 
       5.2 Gastrointestinal Disorders
 

   Constipation  



 In clinical trials, 224 of 1131 (20%) of patients treated with SUSTOL 10 mg reported constipation compared to 13% to 15% in the 5-HT3receptor antagonist control arms. Hospitalization due to constipation or fecal impaction was reported in 5 SUSTOL-treated patients (0.3%). Monitor patients for the development of constipation while receiving treatment with SUSTOL taking into consideration the extended-release properties of the SUSTOL polymer formulation over at least 5 to 7 days, particularly in patients receiving opioid medications. Consider optimizing bowel regimens in patients using SUSTOL.



  Progressive Ileus and Gastric Distention  



 SUSTOL may mask a progressive ileus and/or gastric distention. This should be particularly considered before use of SUSTOL in patients who have had recent abdominal surgery. Monitor for decreased bowel activity, particularly in patients with risk factors for gastrointestinal obstruction.



    5.3 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis, have been reported in granisetron-treated patients who have exhibited hypersensitivity to other 5-HT3receptor antagonists [see Contraindications (  4  )]  . Avoid SUSTOL in patients who have had hypersensitivity reactions to other 5-HT3receptor antagonists [see Contraindications (  4  )]  .



 Due to the extended-release properties of the SUSTOL polymer formulation, exposure to granisetron may continue for 5 to 7 days following administration. Hypersensitivity reactions may occur up to 7 days or longer following SUSTOL administration and may have an extended course. Inform patients of the signs and symptoms of anaphylaxis, and instruct them to seek immediate medical care should signs and symptoms occur. If hypersensitivity reactions occur, administer appropriate treatment and monitor patients until signs and symptoms resolve.



    5.4 Serotonin Syndrome



  The development of serotonin syndrome has been reported with 5-HT3receptor antagonists. Most reports have been associated with concomitant use of serotonergic drugs (e.g., selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs), serotonin and norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs), monoamine oxidase inhibitors, mirtazapine, fentanyl, lithium, tramadol, and intravenous methylene blue). Some of the reported cases were fatal. Serotonin syndrome occurring with overdose of another 5-HT3receptor antagonist alone has also been reported. The majority of reports of serotonin syndrome related to 5-HT3receptor antagonist use occurred in a post-anesthesia care unit or an infusion center.



 Symptoms associated with serotonin syndrome may include the following combination of signs and symptoms: mental status changes (e.g., agitation, hallucinations, delirium, and coma), autonomic instability (e.g., tachycardia, labile blood pressure, dizziness, diaphoresis, flushing, hyperthermia), neuromuscular symptoms (e.g., tremor, rigidity, myoclonus, hyperreflexia, incoordination), seizures, with or without gastrointestinal symptoms (e.g., nausea, vomiting, diarrhea). Patients should be monitored for the emergence of serotonin syndrome, especially with concomitant use of SUSTOL and other serotonergic drugs. If symptoms of serotonin syndrome occur, discontinue SUSTOL and initiate supportive treatment. Patients should be informed of the increased risk of serotonin syndrome, especially if SUSTOL is used concomitantly with other serotonergic drugs [see Drug Interactions (  7.1  )]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
