<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="sutent" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The data described below reflect exposure to SUTENT in 660 patients who participated in the double-blind treatment phase of a placebo-controlled trial (n=202) for the treatment of GIST  [see  Clinical Studies (14.1)  ]  , an active-controlled trial (n=375) for the treatment of RCC  [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]  or a placebo-controlled trial (n=83) for the treatment of pNET  [see  Clinical Studies (14.3)  ]  . The GIST and RCC patients received a starting oral dose of 50 mg daily on Schedule 4/2 in repeated cycles, and the pNET patients received a starting oral dose of 37.5 mg daily without scheduled off-treatment periods.



 The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=20%) in patients with GIST, RCC or pNET are fatigue, asthenia, fever, diarrhea, nausea, mucositis/stomatitis, vomiting, dyspepsia, abdominal pain, constipation, hypertension, peripheral edema, rash, hand-foot syndrome, skin discoloration, dry skin, hair color changes, altered taste, headache, back pain, arthralgia, extremity pain, cough, dyspnea, anorexia, and bleeding. The potentially serious adverse reactions of hepatotoxicity, left ventricular dysfunction, QT interval prolongation, hemorrhage, hypertension, thyroid dysfunction, and adrenal function are discussed in    Warnings and Precautions (5)    . Other adverse reactions occurring in GIST, RCC and pNET studies are described below.



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



    EXCERPT:    *  The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=20%) are fatigue, asthenia, fever, diarrhea, nausea, mucositis/stomatitis, vomiting, dyspepsia, abdominal pain, constipation, hypertension, peripheral edema, rash, hand-foot syndrome, skin discoloration, dry skin, hair color changes, altered taste, headache, back pain, arthralgia, extremity pain, cough, dyspnea, anorexia, and bleeding. (  6  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer, Inc. at 1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    
 

 

  6.1 Adverse Reactions in GIST Study A

  Median duration of blinded study treatment was two cycles for patients on SUTENT (mean 3.0, range 1-9) and one cycle (mean 1.8, range 1-6) for patients on placebo at the time of the interim analysis. Dose reductions occurred in 23 patients (11%) on SUTENT and none on placebo. Dose interruptions occurred in 59 patients (29%) on SUTENT and 31 patients (30%) on placebo. The rates of treatment-emergent, non-fatal adverse reactions resulting in permanent discontinuation were 7% and 6% in the SUTENT and placebo groups, respectively.



 Most treatment-emergent adverse reactions in both study arms were Grade 1 or 2 in severity. Grade 3 or 4 treatment-emergent adverse reactions were reported in 56% versus 51% of patients on SUTENT versus placebo, respectively, in the double-blind treatment phase of the trial. Table 1 compares the incidence of common (&gt;=10%) treatment-emergent adverse reactions for patients receiving SUTENT and reported more commonly in patients receiving SUTENT than in patients receiving placebo.



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions Reported in Study A in at Least 10% of GIST Patients who Received SUTENT in the Double-Blind Treatment Phase and More Commonly Than in Patients Given PlaceboCommon Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE), Version 3.0 
 Adverse Reaction,n (%)               GIST          
 SUTENT (n=202)                 Placebo (n=102)     
 All Grades                        Grade 3/4           All Grades          Grade 3/4        
  
   Any                                                  114 (56)                                52 (51)         
   Gastrointestinal                                                                                             
   Diarrhea                         81 (40)              9 (4)              27 (27)              0 (0)          
   Mucositis/stomatitis             58 (29)              2 (1)              18 (18)              2 (2)          
   Constipation                     41 (20)              0 (0)              14 (14)              2 (2)          
   Cardiac                                                                                                      
   Hypertension                     31 (15)              9 (4)              11 (11)              0 (0)          
   Dermatology                                                                                                  
   Skin discoloration               61 (30)              0 (0)              23 (23)              0 (0)          
   Rash                             28 (14)              2 (1)               9 (9)               0 (0)          
   Hand-foot syndrome               28 (14)              9 (4)              10 (10)              3 (3)          
   Neurology                                                                                                    
   Altered taste                    42 (21)              0 (0)              12 (12)              0 (0)          
   Musculoskeletal                                                                                              
   Myalgia/limb pain                28 (14)              1 (1)               9 (9)               1 (1)          
   Metabolism/Nutrition                                                                                         
   Anorexia                         67 (33)              1 (1)              30 (29)              5 (5)          
   Asthenia                         45 (22)              10 (5)             11 (11)              3 (3)          
           In the double-blind treatment phase of GIST Study A, oral pain other than mucositis/stomatitis occurred in 12 patients (6%) on SUTENT versus 3 (3%) on placebo. Hair color changes occurred in 15 patients (7%) on SUTENT versus 4 (4%) on placebo. Alopecia was observed in 10 patients (5%) on SUTENT versus 2 (2%) on placebo.
 

 Table 2 provides common (&gt;=10%) treatment-emergent laboratory abnormalities.



 Table 2. Laboratory Abnormalities Reported in Study A in at Least 10% of GIST Patients Who Received SUTENT or Placebo in the Double-Blind Treatment PhaseCommon Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE), Version 3.0 
 Laboratory Parameter, n (%)          GIST          
 SUTENT (n=202)                 Placebo (n=102)     
 All Grades                        Grade 3/4           All Grades          Grade 3/4        
  
 LVEF=Left ventricular ejection fraction   
  
   Any                                                  68 (34)                                 22 (22)         
   Gastrointestinal                                                                                             
   AST / ALT                        78 (39)              3 (2)              23 (23)              1 (1)          
   Lipase                           50 (25)             20 (10)             17 (17)              7 (7)          
   Alkaline phosphatase             48 (24)              7 (4)              21 (21)              4 (4)          
   Amylase                          35 (17)              10 (5)             12 (12)              3 (3)          
   Total bilirubin                  32 (16)              2 (1)               8 (8)               0 (0)          
   Indirect bilirubin               20 (10)              0 (0)               4 (4)               0 (0)          
   Cardiac                                                                                                      
   Decreased LVEF                   22 (11)              2 (1)               3 (3)               0 (0)          
   Renal/Metabolic                                                                                              
   Creatinine                       25 (12)              1 (1)               7 (7)               0 (0)          
   Potassium decreased              24 (12)              1 (1)               4 (4)               0 (0)          
   Sodium increased                 20 (10)              0 (0)               4 (4)               1 (1)          
   Hematology                                                                                                   
   Neutrophils                      107 (53)            20 (10)              4 (4)               0 (0)          
   Lymphocytes                      76 (38)              0 (0)              16 (16)              0 (0)          
   Platelets                        76 (38)              10 (5)              4 (4)               0 (0)          
   Hemoglobin                       52 (26)              6 (3)              22 (22)              2 (2)          
           After an interim analysis  ,  the study was unblinded, and patients on the placebo arm were given the opportunity to receive open-label SUTENT treatment  [see  Clinical Studies (14.1)  ]  . For 241 patients randomized to the SUTENT arm, including 139 who received SUTENT in both the double-blind and open-label treatment phases, the median duration of SUTENT treatment was 6 cycles (mean 8.5, range 1 - 44). For the 255 patients who ultimately received open-label SUTENT treatment, median duration of study treatment was 6 cycles (mean 7.8, range 1 - 37) from the time of the unblinding. A total of 118 patients (46%) required dosing interruptions, and a total of 72 patients (28%) required dose reductions. The incidence of treatment-emergent adverse reactions resulting in permanent discontinuation was 20%. The most common Grade 3 or 4 treatment-related adverse reactions experienced by patients receiving SUTENT in the open-label treatment phase were fatigue (10%), hypertension (8%), asthenia (5%), diarrhea (5%), hand-foot syndrome (5%), nausea (4%), abdominal pain (3%), anorexia (3%), mucositis (2%), vomiting (2%), and hypothyroidism (2%).
 

   6.2 Adverse Reactions in the Treatment-Naive RCC Study

  The as-treated patient population for the treatment-naive RCC study included 735 patients, 375 randomized to SUTENT and 360 randomized to IFN-alpha. The median duration of treatment was 11.1 months (range: 0.4 - 46.1) for SUTENT treatment and 4.1 months (range: 0.1 - 45.6) for IFN-alpha treatment. Dose interruptions occurred in 202 patients (54%) on SUTENT and 141 patients (39%) on IFN-alpha. Dose reductions occurred in 194 patients (52%) on SUTENT and 98 patients (27%) on IFN-alpha. Discontinuation rates due to adverse reactions were 20% for SUTENT and 24% for IFN-alpha. Most treatment-emergent adverse reactions in both study arms were Grade 1 or 2 in severity. Grade 3 or 4 treatment-emergent adverse reactions were reported in 77% versus 55% of patients on SUTENT versus IFN-alpha, respectively.



 Table 3 compares the incidence of common (&gt;=10%) treatment-emergent adverse reactions for patients receiving SUTENT versus IFN-alpha.



 Table 3. Adverse Reactions Reported in at Least 10% of Patients with RCC Who Received SUTENT or IFN-alphaCommon Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE), Version 3.0 
 Adverse Reaction,n (%)        Treatment-Naive RCC   
 SUTENT (n=375)                IFN-alpha (n=360)    
 All Grades                        Grade 3/4           All Grades          Grade 3/4        
  
   Any                              372 (99)            290 (77)            355 (99)            197 (55)        
   Constitutional                                                                                               
   Fatigue                          233 (62)            55 (15)             202 (56)            54 (15)         
   Asthenia                         96 (26)             42 (11)             81 (22)              21 (6)         
   Fever                            84 (22)              3 (1)              134 (37)             1 (&lt;1)         
   Weight decreased                 60 (16)              1 (&lt;1)             60 (17)              3 (1)          
   Chills                           53 (14)              3 (1)              111 (31)             0 (0)          
   Chest Pain                       50 (13)              7 (2)               24 (7)              3 (1)          
   Influenza like illness            18 (5)              0 (0)              54 (15)              1 (&lt;1)         
   Gastrointestinal                                                                                             
   Diarrhea                         246 (66)            37 (10)             76 (21)              1 (&lt;1)         
   Nausea                           216 (58)             21 (6)             147 (41)             6 (2)          
   Mucositis/stomatitis             178 (47)             13 (3)              19 (5)              2 (&lt;1)         
   Vomiting                         148 (39)             19 (5)             62 (17)              4 (1)          
   Dyspepsia                        128 (34)             8 (2)               16 (4)              0 (0)          
   Abdominal pain                   113 (30)             20 (5)             42 (12)              5 (1)          
   Constipation                     85 (23)              4 (1)              49 (14)              1 (&lt;1)         
   Dry mouth                        50 (13)              0 (0)               27 (7)              1 (&lt;1)         
   GERD/reflux esophagitis          47 (12)              1 (&lt;1)              3 (1)                0(0)          
   Flatulence                       52 (14)              0 (0)               8 (2)               0 (0)          
   Oral pain                        54 (14)              2 (&lt;1)              2 (1)               0 (0)          
   Glossodynia                      40 (11)              0 (0)               2 (1)               0 (0)          
   Hemorrhoids                      38 (10)              0 (0)               6 (2)               0 (0)          
   Cardiac                                                                                                      
   Hypertension                     127 (34)            50 (13)              13 (4)              1 (&lt;1)         
   Edema, peripheral                91 (24)              7 (2)               17 (5)              2 (1)          
   Ejection fraction decreased       61 (16)              10 (3)              19 (5)              6 (2)          
   Dermatology                                                                                                  
   Rash                             109 (29)             6 (2)              39 (11)              1 (&lt;1)         
   Hand-foot syndrome               108 (29)             32 (8)              3 (1)               0 (0)          
   Skin discoloration/ yellow skin       94 (25)              1 (&lt;1)              0 (0)               0 (0)          
   Dry skin                         85 (23)              1 (&lt;1)              26 (7)              0 (0)          
   Hair color changes               75 (20)              0 (0)               1 (&lt;1)              0 (0)          
   Alopecia                         51 (14)              0 (0)               34 (9)              0 (0)          
   Erythema                         46 (12)              2 (&lt;1)              5 (1)               0 (0)          
   Pruritus                         44 (12)              1 (&lt;1)              24 (7)              1 (&lt;1)         
   Neurology                                                                                                    
   Altered taste                    178 (47)             1 (&lt;1)             54 (15)              0 (0)          
   Headache                         86 (23)              4 (1)              69 (19)              0 (0)          
   Dizziness                        43 (11)              2 (&lt;1)             50 (14)              2 (1)          
   Musculoskeletal                                                                                              
   Back pain                        105 (28)             19 (5)             52 (14)              7 (2)          
   Arthralgia                       111 (30)             10 (3)             69 (19)              4 (1)          
   Pain in extremity/ limb discomfort       150 (40)             19 (5)             107 (30)             7 (2)          
   Endocrine                                                                                                    
   Hypothyroidism                   61 (16)              6 (2)               3 (1)               0 (0)          
   Respiratory                                                                                                  
   Cough                            100 (27)             3 (1)              51 (14)              1 (&lt;1)         
   Dyspnea                          99 (26)              24 (6)             71 (20)              15 (4)         
   Nasopharyngitis                  54 (14)              0 (0)               8 (2)               0 (0)          
   Oropharyngeal Pain               51 (14)              2 (&lt;1)              9 (2)               0 (0)          
   Upper respiratory tract infection       43 (11)              2 (&lt;1)              9 (2)               0 (0)          
   Metabolism/Nutrition                                                                                         
   Anorexia                         182 (48)             11 (3)             153 (42)             7 (2)          
   Hemorrhage/Bleeding                                                                                          
   Bleeding, all sites              140 (37)             16 (4)             35 (10)              3 (1)          
   Psychiatric                                                                                                  
   Insomnia                         57 (15)              3 (&lt;1)             37 (10)              0 (0)          
   Depression                       40 (11)              0 (0)              51 (14)              5 (1)          
           Treatment-emergent Grade 3/4 laboratory abnormalities are presented in Table 4.
 

 Table 4. Laboratory Abnormalities Reported in at Least 10% of Treatment-Naive RCC Patients Who Received SUTENT or IFN-alpha 
 Laboratory Parameter, n (%)   Treatment-Naive RCC   
 SUTENT (n=375)                IFN-alpha (n=360)    
 All Grades                        Grade 3/4           All Grades          Grade 3/4        
  
   Gastrointestinal                                                                                             
   AST                              211 (56)             6 (2)              136 (38)             8 (2)          
   ALT                              192 (51)             10 (3)             144 (40)             9 (2)          
   Lipase                           211 (56)            69 (18)             165 (46)             29 (8)         
   Alkaline phosphatase             171 (46)             7 (2)              132 (37)             6 (2)          
   Amylase                          130 (35)             22 (6)             114 (32)             12 (3)         
   Total bilirubin                  75 (20)              3 (1)               8 (2)               0 (0)          
   Indirect bilirubin               49 (13)              4 (1)               3 (1)               0 (0)          
   Renal/Metabolic                                                                                              
   Creatinine                       262 (70)             2 (&lt;1)             183 (51)             1 (&lt;1)         
   Creatine kinase                  183 (49)             9 (2)              40 (11)              4 (1)          
   Uric acid                        173 (46)            54 (14)             119 (33)             29 (8)         
   Calcium decreased                156 (42)             4 (1)              145 (40)             4 (1)          
   Phosphorus                       116 (31)             22 (6)             87 (24)              23 (6)         
   Albumin                          106 (28)             4 (1)              72 (20)              0 (0)          
   Glucose increased                86 (23)              21 (6)             55 (15)              22 (6)         
   Sodium decreased                 75 (20)              31 (8)             55 (15)              13 (4)         
   Glucose decreased                65 (17)              0 (0)              43 (12)              1 (&lt;1)         
   Potassium increased              61 (16)              13 (3)             61 (17)              15 (4)         
   Calcium increased                50 (13)              2 (&lt;1)             35 (10)              5 (1)          
   Potassium decreased              49 (13)              3 (1)               7 (2)               1 (&lt;1)         
   Sodium increased                 48 (13)              0 (0)              38 (10)              0 (0)          
   Hematology                                                                                                   
   Neutrophils                      289 (77)            65 (17)             178 (49)             31 (9)         
   Hemoglobin                       298 (79)             29 (8)             250 (69)             18 (5)         
   Platelets                        255 (68)             35 (9)             85 (24)              2 (1)          
   Lymphocytes                      256 (68)            66 (18)             245 (68)            93 (26)         
   Leukocytes                       293 (78)             29 (8)             202 (56)             8 (2)          
             6.3 Adverse Reactions in the Phase 3 pNET Study
   The median number of days on treatment was 139 days (range 13-532 days) for patients on SUTENT and 113 days (range 1-614 days) for patients on placebo. Nineteen patients (23%) on SUTENT and 4 patients (5%) on placebo were on study for &gt;1 year. Dose interruptions occurred in 25 patients (30%) on SUTENT and 10 patients (12%) on placebo. Dose reductions occurred in 26 patients (31%) on SUTENT and 9 patients (11%) on placebo. Discontinuation rates due to adverse reactions were 22% for SUTENT and 17% for placebo.



 Most treatment-emergent adverse reactions in both study arms were Grade 1 or 2 in severity. Grade 3 or 4 treatment-emergent adverse reactions were reported in 54% versus 50% of patients on SUTENT versus placebo, respectively. Table 5 compares the incidence of common (&gt;=10%) treatment-emergent adverse reactions for patients receiving SUTENT and reported more commonly in patients receiving SUTENT than in patients receiving placebo.



 Table 5. Adverse Reactions Reported in the Phase 3 pNET Study in at Least 10% of Patients who Received SUTENT and More Commonly Than in Patients Given PlaceboCommon Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE), Version 3.0 
 Adverse Reaction,n (%)               pNET          
 SUTENT (n=83)                   Placebo (n=82)     
 All Grades                        Grade 3/4           All Grades          Grade 3/4        
  
   Any                              82 (99)             45 (54)             78 (95)             41 (50)         
   Constitutional                                                                                               
   Asthenia                         28 (34)              4 (5)              22 (27)              3 (4)          
   Fatigue                          27 (33)              4 (5)              22 (27)              7 (9)          
   Weight decreased                 13 (16)               1(1)               9 (11)              0 (0)          
   Gastrointestinal                                                                                             
   Diarrhea                         49 (59)              4 (5)              32 (39)              2 (2)          
   Stomatitis/oral Syndromes        40 (48)              5 (6)              15 (18)              0 (0)          
   Nausea                           37 (45)              1 (1)              24 (29)              1 (1)          
   Abdominal pain                   32 (39)              4 (5)              28 (34)              8 (10)         
   Vomiting                         28 (34)              0 (0)              25 (31)              2 (2)          
   Dyspepsia                        12 (15)              0 (0)               5 (6)               0 (0)          
   Cardiac                                                                                                      
   Hypertension                     22 (27)              8 (10)              4 (5)               1 (1)          
   Dermatology                                                                                                  
   Hair color changes               24 (29)              1 (1)               1 (1)               0 (0)          
   Hand-foot syndrome               19 (23)              5 (6)               2 (2)               0 (0)          
   Rash                             15 (18)              0 (0)               4 (5)               0 (0)          
   Dry skin                         12 (15)              0 (0)               9 (11)              0 (0)          
   Neurology                                                                                                    
   Dysgeusia                        17 (21)              0 (0)               4 (5)               0 (0)          
   Headache                         15 (18)              0 (0)              11 (13)              1 (1)          
   Musculoskeletal                                                                                              
   Arthralgia                       12 (15)              0 (0)               5 (6)               0 (0)          
   Psychiatric                                                                                                  
   Insomnia                         15 (18)              0 (0)              10 (12)              0 (0)          
   Hemorrhage/Bleeding                                                                                          
   Bleeding events                  18 (22)              0 (0)               8 (10)              3 (4)          
   Epistaxis                        17 (21)              1 (1)               4 (5)               0 (0)          
           Table 6 provides common (&gt;=10%) treatment-emergent laboratory abnormalities.
 

 Table 6. Laboratory Abnormalities Reported in the Phase 3 pNET Study in at Least 10% of Patients Who Received SUTENT 
 Laboratory Parameter, n (%)     pNET    
 SUTENT                          Placebo   
 N                               All Grades     Grade 3/4            N         All Grades     Grade 3/4      
  
   Gastrointestinal                                                                                                 
   AST increased                  82        59 (72)           4 (5)        80        56 (70)           2 (3)        
   ALT increased                  82        50 (61)           3 (4)        80        44 (55)           2 (3)        
   Alkaline phosphatase increased   82        52 (63)          8 (10)        80        56 (70)          9 (11)        
   Total bilirubin increased      82        30 (37)           1 (1)        80        22 (28)           3 (4)        
   Amylase increased              74        15 (20)           3 (4)        74        7 (10)            1 (1)        
   Lipase increased               75        13 (17)           4 (5)        72        8 (11)            3 (4)        
   Renal/Metabolic                                                                                                  
   Glucose increased              82        58 (71)          10 (12)       80        62 (78)          14 (18)       
   Albumin decreased              81        33 (41)           1 (1)        79        29 (37)           1 (1)        
   Phosphorus decreased           81        29 (36)           6 (7)        77        17 (22)           4 (5)        
   Calcium decreased              82        28 (34)           0 (0)        80        15 (19)           0 (0)        
   Sodium decreased               82        24 (29)           2 (2)        80        27 (34)           2 (3)        
   Creatinine increased           82        22 (27)           4 (5)        80        22 (28)           4 (5)        
   Glucose decreased              82        18 (22)           2 (2)        80        12 (15)           3 (4)        
   Potassium decreased            82        17 (21)           3 (4)        80        11 (14)           0 (0)        
   Magnesium decreased            52        10 (19)           0 (0)        39        4 (10)            0 (0)        
   Potassium increased            82        15 (18)           1 (1)        80        9 (11)            1 (1)        
   Hematology                                                                                                       
   Neutrophils decreased          82        58 (71)          13 (16)       80        13 (16)           0 (0)        
   Hemoglobin decreased           82        53 (65)           0 (0)        80        44 (55)           1 (1)        
   Platelets decreased            82        49 (60)           4 (5)        80        12 (15)           0 (0)        
   Lymphocytes decreased          82        46 (56)           6 (7)        80        28 (35)           3 (4)        
               6.4 Venous Thromboembolic Events
   Seven patients (3%) on SUTENT and none on placebo in the double-blind treatment phase of GIST Study A experienced venous thromboembolic events; five of the seven were Grade 3 deep venous thrombosis (DVT), and two were Grade 1 or 2. Four of these seven GIST patients discontinued treatment following first observation of DVT.



 Thirteen (3%) patients receiving SUTENT for treatment-naive RCC had venous thromboembolic events reported. Seven (2%) of these patients had pulmonary embolism, one was Grade 2 and six were Grade 4, and six (2%) patients had DVT, including three Grade 3. One patient was permanently withdrawn from SUTENT due to pulmonary embolism; dose interruption occurred in two patients with pulmonary embolism and one with DVT. In treatment-naive RCC patients receiving IFN-alpha, six (2%) venous thromboembolic events occurred; one patient (&lt;1%) experienced a Grade 3 DVT and five patients (1%) had pulmonary embolism, all Grade 4. One patient (1%) receiving SUTENT for pNET had a venous thromboembolic event reported compared to 5 patients (6%) receiving placebo. The SUTENT patient had Grade 2 thrombosis. Two placebo patients had DVT, one was Grade 3, two placebo patients had pulmonary embolism, one was Grade 3 and one was Grade 4, and one placebo patient had Grade 3 jugular thrombosis.



   6.5 Reversible Posterior Leukoencephalopathy Syndrome

  There have been reports (&lt;1%), some fatal, of subjects presenting with seizures and radiological evidence of reversible posterior leukoencephalopathy syndrome (RPLS). Patients with seizures and signs/symptoms consistent with RPLS, such as hypertension, headache, decreased alertness, altered mental functioning, and visual loss, including cortical blindness should be controlled with medical management including control of hypertension. Temporary suspension of SUTENT is recommended; following resolution, treatment may be resumed at the discretion of the treating physician.



   6.6 Pancreatic and Hepatic Function

  If symptoms of pancreatitis or hepatic failure are present, patients should have SUTENT discontinued. Pancreatitis was observed in 5 (1%) patients receiving SUTENT for treatment-naive RCC compared to 1 (&lt;1%) patient receiving IFN-alpha. Pancreatitis was observed in 1 (1%) patient receiving SUTENT for pNET and 1 (1%) patient receiving placebo. Hepatotoxicity was observed in patients receiving SUTENT  [See  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .



   6.7 Post-marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of SUTENT. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



    Blood and lymphatic system disorders:  thrombotic microangiopathy; hemorrhage associated with thrombocytopenia (including some fatalities) . Suspension of SUTENT is recommended; following resolution, treatment may be resumed at the discretion of the treating physician.
 

   Gastrointestinal disorders:  esophagitis.



   Hepatobiliary disorders:  cholecystitis, particularly acalculous cholecystitis.



   Immune system disorders:  hypersensitivity reactions, including angioedema.



   Infections and infestations:  serious infection (with or without neutropenia). The infections most commonly observed with sunitinib treatment include respiratory, urinary tract, skin infections, sepsis/septic shock.



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  fistula formation, sometimes associated with tumor necrosis and/or regression; myopathy and/or rhabdomyolysis with or without acute renal failure. Patients with signs or symptoms of muscle toxicity should be managed as per standard medical practice.



   Renal and urinary disorders:  renal impairment and/or failure.



   Respiratory disorders:  pulmonary embolism.



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  pyoderma gangrenosum, including positive dechallenges.



   Vascular disorders:  arterial thromboembolic events. The most frequent events included cerebrovascular accident, transient ischemic attack and cerebral infarction.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: HEPATOTOXICITY

    WARNING: HEPATOTOXICITY  

    Hepatotoxicity has been observed in clinical trials and post-marketing experience. This hepatotoxicity may be severe, and deaths have been reported.   [See   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]    



   EXCERPT:   WARNING:  HEPATOTOXICITY



    See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



   Hepatotoxicity has been observed in clinical trials and post-marketing experience. This hepatotoxicity may be severe, and deaths have been reported.   [See   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]    
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hepatotoxicity, including liver failure, has been observed. Monitor liver function tests before initiation of treatment, during each cycle of treatment, and as clinically indicated. SUTENT should be interrupted for Grade 3 or 4 drug-related hepatic adverse events and discontinued if there is no resolution. Do not restart SUTENT if patients subsequently experience severe changes in liver function tests or have other signs and symptoms of liver failure. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Women of childbearing potential should be advised of the potential hazard to the fetus and to avoid becoming pregnant. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Cardiac toxicity including left ventricular ejection fraction declines to below the lower limit of normal and cardiac failure including death have occurred. Monitor patients for signs and symptoms of congestive heart failure. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Prolonged QT intervals and Torsade de Pointes have been observed. Use with caution in patients at higher risk for developing QT interval prolongation. When using SUTENT, monitoring with on-treatment electrocardiograms and electrolytes should be considered. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Hypertension may occur. Monitor blood pressure and treat as needed. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Hemorrhagic events including tumor-related hemorrhage have occurred. Perform serial complete blood counts and physical examinations. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Osteonecrosis of the jaw has been reported. Consider preventive dentistry prior to treatment with SUTENT. If possible, avoid invasive dental procedures, particularly in patients receiving intravenous bisphosphonate therapy. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Cases of Tumor Lysis Syndrome (TLS) have been reported primarily in patients with RCC and GIST with high tumor burden. Monitor these patients closely and treat as clinically indicated. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Thyroid dysfunction may occur. Patients with signs and/or symptoms suggestive of hypothyroidism or hyperthyroidism should have laboratory monitoring of thyroid function performed and be treated as per standard medical practice. (  5.9  ) 
 *  Hypoglycemia may occur. Check blood glucose levels regularly and assess if anti-diabetic drug dose modifications are required. (  5.10  ) 
 *  Wound Healing: Impaired wound healing has occurred with SUTENT. Temporary interruption of therapy with SUTENT is recommended in patients undergoing major surgical procedures. (  5.11  ) 
 *  Proteinuria: Monitor urine protein. Interrupt treatment for 24-hour urine protein &gt;=3 grams. Discontinue for repeat episodes of protein &gt;=3 grams despite dose reductions or nephrotic syndrome. (  5.12  ) 
 *  Discontinue SUTENT if necrotizing fasciitis, erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome or toxic epidermal necrolysis occurs. (  5.13  ). 
 *  Adrenal hemorrhage was observed in animal studies. Monitor adrenal function in case of stress such as surgery, trauma or severe infection. (  5.14  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hepatotoxicity



  SUTENT has been associated with hepatotoxicity, which may result in liver failure or death. Liver failure has been observed in clinical trials (7/2281 [0.3%]) and post-marketing experience. Liver failure signs include jaundice, elevated transaminases and/or hyperbilirubinemia in conjunction with encephalopathy, coagulopathy, and/or renal failure. Monitor liver function tests (ALT, AST, bilirubin) before initiation of treatment, during each cycle of treatment, and as clinically indicated. SUTENT should be interrupted for Grade 3 or 4 drug-related hepatic adverse events and discontinued if there is no resolution. Do not restart SUTENT if patients subsequently experience severe changes in liver function tests or have other signs and symptoms of liver failure.



 Safety in patients with ALT or AST &gt;2.5 * ULN or, if due to liver metastases, &gt;5.0 * ULN has not been established.



    5.2 Pregnancy



  SUTENT can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. As angiogenesis is a critical component of embryonic and fetal development, inhibition of angiogenesis following administration of SUTENT should be expected to result in adverse effects on pregnancy. In animal reproductive studies in rats and rabbits, sunitinib was teratogenic, embryotoxic, and fetotoxic. There are no adequate and well-controlled studies of SUTENT in pregnant women. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to a fetus. Women of childbearing potential should be advised to avoid becoming pregnant while receiving treatment with SUTENT.



    5.3 Left Ventricular Dysfunction



   In the presence of clinical manifestations of congestive heart failure (CHF), discontinuation of SUTENT is recommended.  The dose of SUTENT should be interrupted and/or reduced in patients without clinical evidence of CHF but with an ejection fraction &lt;50% and &gt;20% below baseline.



 Cardiovascular events, including heart failure, myocardial disorders and cardiomyopathy, some of which were fatal, have been reported through post-marketing experience. For GIST and RCC, more patients treated with SUTENT experienced decline in left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) than patients receiving either placebo or interferon-alpha (IFN-alpha). In the double-blind treatment phase of GIST Study A, 22/209 patients (11%) on SUTENT and 3/102 patients (3%) on placebo had treatment-emergent LVEF values below the lower limit of normal (LLN). Nine of 22 GIST patients on SUTENT with LVEF changes recovered without intervention. Five patients had documented LVEF recovery following intervention (dose reduction: one patient; addition of antihypertensive or diuretic medications: four patients). Six patients went off study without documented recovery. Additionally, three patients on SUTENT had Grade 3 reductions in left ventricular systolic function to LVEF &lt;40%; two of these patients died without receiving further study drug. No GIST patients on placebo had Grade 3 decreased LVEF. In the double-blind treatment phase of GIST Study A, 1 patient on SUTENT and 1 patient on placebo died of diagnosed heart failure; 2 patients on SUTENT and 2 patients on placebo died of treatment-emergent cardiac arrest.



 In the treatment-naive RCC study, 103/375 (27%) and 54/360 (15%) patients on SUTENT and IFN-alpha, respectively, had an LVEF value below the LLN. Twenty-six patients on SUTENT (7%) and seven on IFN-alpha (2%) experienced declines in LVEF to &gt;20% below baseline and to below 50%. Left ventricular dysfunction was reported in four patients (1%) and CHF in two patients (&lt;1%) who received SUTENT.



 In the Phase 3 pNET study, cardiac failure leading to death was reported in 2/83 (2%) patients on SUTENT and no patients on placebo.



 Patients who presented with cardiac events within 12 months prior to SUTENT administration, such as myocardial infarction (including severe/unstable angina), coronary/peripheral artery bypass graft, symptomatic CHF, cerebrovascular accident or transient ischemic attack, or pulmonary embolism were excluded from SUTENT clinical studies. It is unknown whether patients with these concomitant conditions may be at a higher risk of developing drug-related left ventricular dysfunction. Physicians are advised to weigh this risk against the potential benefits of the drug. These patients should be carefully monitored for clinical signs and symptoms of CHF while receiving SUTENT. Baseline and periodic evaluations of LVEF should also be considered while these patients are receiving SUTENT. In patients without cardiac risk factors, a baseline evaluation of ejection fraction should be considered.  



    5.4 QT Interval Prolongation and Torsade de Pointes



  SUTENT has been shown to prolong the QT interval in a dose dependent manner, which may lead to an increased risk for ventricular arrhythmias including Torsade de Pointes. Torsade de Pointes has been observed in &lt;0.1% of SUTENT-exposed patients.



 SUTENT should be used with caution in patients with a history of QT interval prolongation, patients who are taking antiarrhythmics, or patients with relevant pre-existing cardiac disease, bradycardia, or electrolyte disturbances. When using SUTENT, periodic monitoring with on-treatment electrocardiograms and electrolytes (magnesium, potassium) should be considered. Concomitant treatment with strong CYP3A4 inhibitors, which may increase sunitinib plasma concentrations, should be used with caution and dose reduction of SUTENT should be considered [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ]  .



    5.5 Hypertension



  Patients should be monitored for hypertension and treated as needed with standard anti-hypertensive therapy. In cases of severe hypertension, temporary suspension of SUTENT is recommended until hypertension is controlled.



 Of patients receiving SUTENT for treatment-naive RCC, 127/375 patients (34%) receiving SUTENT compared with 13/360 patients (4%) on IFN-alpha experienced hypertension. Grade 3 hypertension was observed in 50/375 treatment-naive RCC patients (13%) on SUTENT compared to 1/360 patients (&lt;1%) on IFN-alpha. While all-grade hypertension was similar in GIST patients on SUTENT compared to placebo, Grade 3 hypertension was reported in 9/202 GIST patients on SUTENT (4%), and none of the GIST patients on placebo. Of patients receiving SUTENT in the Phase 3 pNET study, 22/83 patients (27%) on SUTENT and 4/82 patients (5%) on placebo experienced hypertension. Grade 3 hypertension was reported in 8/83 pNET patients (10%) on SUTENT, and 1/82 patient (1%) on placebo. No Grade 4 hypertension was reported. SUTENT dosing was reduced or temporarily delayed for hypertension in 21/375 patients (6%) on the treatment-naive RCC study and 7/83 pNET patients (8%). Four treatment-naive RCC patients, including one with malignant hypertension, one patient with pNET, and no GIST patients discontinued treatment due to hypertension. Severe hypertension (&gt;200 mmHg systolic or 110 mmHg diastolic) occurred in 8/202 GIST patients on SUTENT (4%), 1/102 GIST patients on placebo (1%), in 32/375 treatment-naive RCC patients (9%) on SUTENT, in 3/360 patients (1%) on IFN-alpha, and in 8/80 pNET patients (10%) on SUTENT and 2/76 pNET patients (3%) on placebo.



    5.6 Hemorrhagic Events



  Hemorrhagic events reported through post-marketing experience, some of which were fatal, have included GI, respiratory, tumor, urinary tract and brain hemorrhages. In patients receiving SUTENT in a clinical trial for treatment-naive RCC, 140/375 patients (37%) had bleeding events compared with 35/360 patients (10%) receiving IFN-alpha. Bleeding events occurred in 37/202 patients (18%) receiving SUTENT in the double-blind treatment phase of GIST Study A, compared to 17/102 patients (17%) receiving placebo. Epistaxis was the most common hemorrhagic adverse event reported. Bleeding events, excluding epistaxis, occurred in 18/83 patients (22%) receiving SUTENT in the Phase 3 pNET study, compared to 8/82 patients (10%) receiving placebo. Epistaxis was reported in 17/83 patients (20%) receiving SUTENT for pNET and 4 patients (5%) receiving placebo. Less common bleeding events in GIST, RCC and pNET patients included rectal, gingival, upper gastrointestinal, genital, and wound bleeding. In the double-blind treatment phase of GIST Study A, 14/202 patients (7%) receiving SUTENT and 9/102 patients (9%) on placebo had Grade 3 or 4 bleeding events. In addition, one patient in GIST Study A taking placebo had a fatal gastrointestinal bleeding event during Cycle 2. Most events in RCC patients were Grade 1 or 2; there was one Grade 5 event of gastric bleed in a treatment-naive patient. In the pNET study, 1/83 patients (1%) receiving SUTENT had Grade 3 epistaxis, and no patients had other Grade 3 or 4 bleeding events. In pNET patients receiving placebo, 3/82 patients (4%) had Grade 3 or 4 bleeding events.



 Tumor-related hemorrhage has been observed in patients treated with SUTENT. These events may occur suddenly, and in the case of pulmonary tumors may present as severe and life-threatening hemoptysis or pulmonary hemorrhage. Cases of pulmonary hemorrhage, some with a fatal outcome, have been observed in clinical trials and have been reported in post-marketing experience in patients treated with SUTENT for MRCC, GIST and metastatic lung cancer. SUTENT is not approved for use in patients with lung cancer. Treatment-emergent Grade 3 and 4 tumor hemorrhage occurred in 5/202 patients (3%) with GIST receiving SUTENT on Study A. Tumor hemorrhages were observed as early as Cycle 1 and as late as Cycle 6. One of these five patients received no further drug following tumor hemorrhage. None of the other four patients discontinued treatment or experienced dose delay due to tumor hemorrhage. No patients with GIST in the Study A placebo arm were observed to undergo intratumoral hemorrhage. Clinical assessment of these events should include serial complete blood counts (CBCs) and physical examinations.



 Serious, sometimes fatal gastrointestinal complications including gastrointestinal perforation, have occurred rarely in patients with intra-abdominal malignancies treated with SUTENT.



    5.7 Osteonecrosis of the Jaw (ONJ)



  ONJ has been observed in clinical trials and has been reported in post-marketing experience in patients treated with sunitinib. Concomitant exposure to other risk factors, such as bisphosphonates or dental disease, may increase the risk of osteonecrosis of the jaw.



    5.8 Tumor Lysis Syndrome (TLS)



  Cases of TLS, some fatal, have been observed in clinical trials and have been reported in post-marketing experience, primarily in patients with RCC or GIST treated with SUTENT. Patients generally at risk of TLS are those with high tumor burden prior to treatment. These patients should be monitored closely and treated as clinically indicated.



    5.9 Thyroid Dysfunction



  Baseline laboratory measurement of thyroid function is recommended and patients with hypothyroidism or hyperthyroidism should be treated as per standard medical practice prior to the start of SUTENT treatment. All patients should be observed closely for signs and symptoms of thyroid dysfunction, including hypothyroidism, hyperthyroidism, and thyroiditis, on SUTENT treatment. Patients with signs and/or symptoms suggestive of thyroid dysfunction should have laboratory monitoring of thyroid function performed and be treated as per standard medical practice.



 Treatment-emergent acquired hypothyroidism was noted in eight GIST patients (4%) on SUTENT versus one (1%) on placebo. Hypothyroidism was reported as an adverse reaction in sixty-one patients (16%) on SUTENT in the treatment-naive RCC study and in three patients (1%) in the IFN-alpha arm. Hypothyroidism was reported as an adverse reaction in 6/83 patients (7%) on SUTENT in the Phase 3 pNET study and in 1/82 patients (1%) in the placebo arm.



 Cases of hyperthyroidism, some followed by hypothyroidism, have been reported in clinical trials and through post-marketing experience.



    5.10 Hypoglycemia



   SUTENT has been associated with symptomatic hypoglycemia, which may result in loss of consciousness, or require hospitalization. Hypoglycemia has occurred in clinical trials in 2% of the patients treated with SUTENT for RCC and GIST and in approximately 10% of the patients treated with SUTENT for pNET. For patients being treated with SUTENT for pNET, pre-existing abnormalities in glucose homeostasis were not present in all patients who experienced hypoglycemia. Reductions in blood glucose levels may be worse in diabetic patients. Check blood glucose levels regularly during and after discontinuation of treatment with SUTENT. Assess if anti-diabetic drug dosage needs to be adjusted to minimize the risk of hypoglycemia.  



    5.11 Wound Healing



  Cases of impaired wound healing have been reported during SUTENT therapy. Temporary interruption of SUTENT therapy is recommended for precautionary reasons in patients undergoing major surgical procedures. There is limited clinical experience regarding the timing of reinitiation of therapy following major surgical intervention. Therefore, the decision to resume SUTENT therapy following a major surgical intervention should be based upon clinical judgment of recovery from surgery.



    5.12 Proteinuria



   Proteinuria and nephrotic syndrome have been reported. Some of these cases have resulted in renal failure and fatal outcomes. Monitor patients for the development or worsening of proteinuria. Perform baseline and periodic urinalyses during treatment, with follow up measurement of 24-hour urine protein as clinically indicated. Interrupt SUTENT and dose reduce for 24-hour urine protein &gt;= 3 grams. Discontinue SUTENT for patients with nephrotic syndrome or repeat episodes of urine protein &gt;= 3 grams despite dose reductions. The safety of continued SUTENT treatment in patients with moderate to severe proteinuria has not been systematically evaluated.  



    5.13 Dermatologic Toxicities



   Severe cutaneous reactions have been reported, including cases of erythema multiforme (EM), Stevens-Johnson syndrome (SJS), and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), some of which were fatal. If signs or symptoms of SJS, TEN, or EM (e.g., progressive skin rash often with blisters or mucosal lesions) are present, SUTENT treatment should be discontinued. If a diagnosis of SJS or TEN is suspected, SUTENT treatment must not be re-started.  



  Necrotizing fasciitis, including fatal cases, has been reported in patients treated with Sutent, including of the perineum and secondary to fistula formation. Discontinue Sutent in patients who develop necrotizing fasciitis.  



    5.14 Adrenal Function



  Physicians prescribing SUTENT are advised to monitor for adrenal insufficiency in patients who experience stress such as surgery, trauma or severe infection.



 Adrenal toxicity was noted in non-clinical repeat dose studies of 14 days to 9 months in rats and monkeys at plasma exposures as low as 0.7 times the AUC observed in clinical studies. Histological changes of the adrenal gland were characterized as hemorrhage, necrosis, congestion, hypertrophy and inflammation. In clinical studies, CT/MRI obtained in 336 patients after exposure to one or more cycles of SUTENT demonstrated no evidence of adrenal hemorrhage or necrosis. ACTH stimulation testing was performed in approximately 400 patients across multiple clinical trials of SUTENT. Among patients with normal baseline ACTH stimulation testing, one patient developed consistently abnormal test results during treatment that are unexplained and may be related to treatment with SUTENT. Eleven additional patients with normal baseline testing had abnormalities in the final test performed, with peak cortisol levels of 12-16.4 mcg/dL (normal &gt;18 mcg/dL) following stimulation. None of these patients were reported to have clinical evidence of adrenal insufficiency.



    5.15 Laboratory Tests



  CBCs with platelet count and serum chemistries including phosphate should be performed at the beginning of each treatment cycle for patients receiving treatment with SUTENT.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
