<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="synjardy" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6  ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following important adverse reactions are described below and elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Lactic Acidosis [see Boxed Warning and Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ,  5.3  ,  5.4  ,  5.9  ,  5.10  )]  
 *  Hypotension [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Impairment in Renal Function [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *  Impaired Hepatic Function [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  Hypoglycemia with Concomitant Use with Insulin and Insulin Secretagogues [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *  Genital Mycotic Infections [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *  Urinary Tract Infections [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
 *  Vitamin B12Deficiency [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  
 *  Increased Low-Density Lipoprotein Cholesterol (LDL-C) [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.11  )]  
   *  Most common adverse reactions associated with empagliflozin (5% or greater incidence) were urinary tract infection and female genital mycotic infections. (  6.1  ) 
 *  Most common adverse reactions associated with metformin (&gt;5%) are diarrhea, nausea/vomiting, flatulence, abdominal discomfort, indigestion, asthenia, and headache. (  6.1  ) 
      EXCERPT:     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Boehringer Ingelheim Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-800-542-6257 or 1-800-459-9906 TTY, or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of concomitantly administered empagliflozin (daily dose 10 mg and 25 mg) and metformin (mean daily dose of approximately 1800 mg) has been evaluated in 3456 patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus treated for 16 to 24 weeks, of which 926 patients received placebo, 1271 patients received a daily dose of empagliflozin 10 mg, and 1259 patients received a daily dose of empagliflozin 25 mg. Discontinuation of therapy due to adverse events across treatment groups was 3.0%, 2.8%, and 2.9% for placebo, empagliflozin 10 mg, and empagliflozin 25 mg, respectively.



   Empagliflozin Add-On Combination Therapy with Metformin  In a 24-week placebo-controlled trial of empagliflozin 10 mg and 25 mg administered once daily added to metformin, there were no adverse reactions reported regardless of investigator assessment of causality in &gt;=5% of patients and more commonly than in patients given placebo.



   Empagliflozin Add-On Combination Therapy with Metformin and Sulfonylurea  In a 24-week placebo-controlled trial of empagliflozin 10 mg and 25 mg administered once daily added to metformin and sulfonylurea, adverse reactions reported regardless of investigator assessment of causality in &gt;=5% of patients and more commonly than in patients given placebo are presented in Table 1 (see also Table 4).



 Table 1  Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=5% of Patients Treated with Empagliflozin added on to Metformin plus Sulfonylurea and Greater than with Placebo in a 24-week Placebo Controlled Clinical Study 
                              Number (%) of Patients     
                                  Placebon=225           Empagliflozin 10 mgn=224      Empagliflozin 25 mgn=217     
 Hypoglycemia                       22 (9.8)                   35 (15.6)                  28 (12.9)           
 Urinary tract infection            15 (6.7)                   21 (9.4)                   15 (6.9)            
 Nasopharyngitis                    11 (4.9)                   18 (8.0)                   13 (6.0)            
        Empagliflozin  The data in Table 2 are derived from a pool of four 24-week placebo-controlled trials and 18-week data from a placebo-controlled trial with basal insulin. Empagliflozin was used as monotherapy in one trial and as add-on therapy in four trials  [see Clinical Studies (  14  )]  .
 

 These data reflect exposure of 1976 patients to empagliflozin with a mean exposure duration of approximately 23 weeks. Patients received placebo (N=995), empagliflozin 10 mg (N=999), or empagliflozin 25 mg (N=977) once daily. The mean age of the population was 56 years and 3% were older than 75 years of age. More than half (55%) of the population was male; 46% were White, 50% were Asian, and 3% were Black or African American. At baseline, 57% of the population had diabetes more than 5 years and had a mean hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c) of 8%. Established microvascular complications of diabetes at baseline included diabetic nephropathy (7%), retinopathy (8%), or neuropathy (16%). Baseline renal function was normal or mildly impaired in 91% of patients and moderately impaired in 9% of patients (mean eGFR 86.8 mL/min/1.73 m  2  ).



 Table 2 shows common adverse reactions (excluding hypoglycemia) associated with the use of empagliflozin. The adverse reactions were not present at baseline, occurred more commonly on empagliflozin than on placebo and occurred in greater than or equal to 2% of patients treated with empagliflozin 10 mg or empagliflozin 25 mg.



 Table 2  Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=2% of Patients Treated with Empagliflozin and Greater than Placebo in Pooled Placebo-Controlled Clinical Studies of Empagliflozin Monotherapy or Combination Therapy 
   a  Predefined adverse event grouping, including, but not limited to, urinary tract infection, asymptomatic bacteriuria, cystitis  b  Female genital mycotic infections include the following adverse reactions: vulvovaginal mycotic infection, vaginal infection, vulvitis, vulvovaginal candidiasis, genital infection, genital candidiasis, genital infection fungal, genitourinary tract infection, vulvovaginitis, cervicitis, urogenital infection fungal, vaginitis bacterial. Percentages calculated with the number of female subjects in each group as denominator: placebo (N=481), empagliflozin 10 mg (N=443), empagliflozin 25 mg (N=420).  c  Predefined adverse event grouping, including, but not limited to, polyuria, pollakiuria, and nocturia  d  Male genital mycotic infections include the following adverse reactions: balanoposthitis, balanitis, genital infections fungal, genitourinary tract infection, balanitis candida, scrotal abscess, penile infection. Percentages calculated with the number of male subjects in each group as denominator: placebo (N=514), empagliflozin 10 mg (N=556), empagliflozin 25 mg (N=557).   
  
                                             Number (%) of Patients     
                                             PlaceboN=995          Empagliflozin 10 mgN=999      Empagliflozin 25 mgN=977     
 Urinary tract infection  a                7.6%                  9.3%                  7.6%                   
 Female genital mycotic infections  b      1.5%                  5.4%                  6.4%                   
 Upper respiratory tract infection         3.8%                  3.1%                  4.0%                   
 Increased urination  c                    1.0%                  3.4%                  3.2%                   
 Dyslipidemia                              3.4%                  3.9%                  2.9%                   
 Arthralgia                                2.2%                  2.4%                  2.3%                   
 Male genital mycotic infections  d        0.4%                  3.1%                  1.6%                   
 Nausea                                    1.4%                  2.3%                  1.1%                   
      Thirst (including polydipsia) was reported in 0%, 1.7%, and 1.5% for placebo, empagliflozin 10 mg, and empagliflozin 25 mg, respectively.
 

   Volume Depletion  Empagliflozin causes an osmotic diuresis, which may lead to intravascular volume contraction and adverse reactions related to volume depletion. In the pool of five placebo-controlled clinical trials, adverse reactions related to volume depletion (e.g., blood pressure (ambulatory) decreased, blood pressure systolic decreased, dehydration, hypotension, hypovolemia, orthostatic hypotension, and syncope) were reported by 0.3%, 0.5%, and 0.3% of patients treated with placebo, empagliflozin 10 mg, and empagliflozin 25 mg, respectively. Empagliflozin may increase the risk of hypotension in patients at risk for volume contraction  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  ) and Use in Specific Populations (  8.5  ,  8.6  )].  



   Increased Urination  In the pool of five placebo-controlled clinical trials, adverse reactions of increased urination (e.g., polyuria, pollakiuria, and nocturia) occurred more frequently on empagliflozin than on placebo (see Table 3). Specifically, nocturia was reported by 0.4%, 0.3%, and 0.8% of patients treated with placebo, empagliflozin 10 mg, and empagliflozin 25 mg, respectively.



   Impairment in Renal Function  Use of empagliflozin was associated with increases in serum creatinine and decreases in eGFR (see Table 3). Patients with moderate renal impairment at baseline had larger mean changes  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  ) and Use in Specific Populations (  8.5  ,  8.6  )]  .



 Table 3  Changes from Baseline in Serum Creatinine and eGFR in the Pool of Four 24-week Placebo-Controlled Studies and Renal Impairment Study 
   a  Subset of patients from renal impairment study with eGFR 30 to less than 60 mL/min/1.73 m  2  .  b  Approximately 3 weeks after end of treatment.   
  
                         Pool of 24-Week Placebo-Controlled Studies     
   Placebo               Empagliflozin 10 mg      Empagliflozin 25 mg     
 Baseline Mean         N                     825                   830                   822                    
 Creatinine (mg/dL)    0.84                  0.85                  0.85                   
 eGFR (mL/min/1.73 m  2  )  87.3                  87.1                  87.8                   
 Week 12 Change        N                     771                   797                   783                    
 Creatinine (mg/dL)    0.00                  0.02                  0.01                   
 eGFR (mL/min/1.73 m  2  )  -0.3                  -1.3                  -1.4                   
 Week 24 Change        N                     708                   769                   754                    
 Creatinine (mg/dL)    0.00                  0.01                  0.01                   
 eGFR (mL/min/1.73 m  2  )  -0.3                  -0.6                  -1.4                   
                         Moderate Renal Impairment  a       
   Placebo                                     Empagliflozin 25 mg     
 Baseline              N                     187                   --                    187                    
 Creatinine (mg/dL)    1.49                  --                    1.46                   
 eGFR (mL/min/1.73 m  2  )  44.3                  --                    45.4                   
 Week 12 Change        N                     176                   --                    179                    
 Creatinine (mg/dL)    0.01                  --                    0.12                   
 eGFR (mL/min/1.73 m  2  )  0.1                   --                    -3.8                   
 Week 24 Change        N                     170                   --                    171                    
 Creatinine (mg/dL)    0.01                  --                    0.10                   
 eGFR (mL/min/1.73 m  2  )  0.2                   --                    -3.2                   
 Week 52 Change        N                     164                   --                    162                    
 Creatinine (mg/dL)    0.02                  --                    0.11                   
 eGFR (mL/min/1.73 m  2  )  -0.3                  --                    -2.8                   
 Post-treatment Change  b    N                     98                    --                    103                    
 Creatinine (mg/dL)    0.03                  --                    0.02                   
 eGFR (mL/min/1.73 m  2  )  0.16                  --                    1.48                   
        Hypoglycemia  The incidence of hypoglycemia by study is shown in Table 4. The incidence of hypoglycemia increased when empagliflozin was administered with insulin or sulfonylurea  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  .
 

 Table 4  Incidence of Overalla and Severeb Hypoglycemic Events in Placebo-Controlled Clinical Studies 
   a  Overall hypoglycemic events: plasma or capillary glucose of less than or equal to 70 mg/dL  b  Severe hypoglycemic events: requiring assistance regardless of blood glucose  c  Insulin dose could not be adjusted during the initial 18 week treatment period   
  
   Monotherapy(24 weeks)     
 Overall (%)       
 Severe (%)        
   In Combination withMetformin(24 weeks)     
 Overall (%)       
 Severe (%)        
   In Combination withMetformin + Sulfonylurea(24 weeks)     
 Overall (%)       
 Severe (%)        
   In Combination withPioglitazone +/- Metformin(24 weeks)     
 Overall (%)       
 Severe (%)        
   In Combination with Basal Insulin(18 weeks  c  )     
 Overall (%)       
 Severe (%)        
   In Combination with MDI Insulin +/-Metformin(18 weeks  c  )     
 Overall (%)       
 Severe (%)        
        Genital Mycotic Infections  In the pool of five placebo-controlled clinical trials, the incidence of genital mycotic infections (e.g., vaginal mycotic infection, vaginal infection, genital infection fungal, vulvovaginal candidiasis, and vulvitis) was increased in patients treated with empagliflozin compared to placebo, occurring in 0.9%, 4.1%, and 3.7% of patients randomized to placebo, empagliflozin 10 mg, and empagliflozin 25 mg, respectively. Discontinuation from study due to genital infection occurred in 0% of placebo-treated patients and 0.2% of patients treated with either empagliflozin 10 or 25 mg.
 

 Genital mycotic infections occurred more frequently in female than male patients (see Table 2).



 Phimosis occurred more frequently in male patients treated with empagliflozin 10 mg (less than 0.1%) and empagliflozin 25 mg (0.1%) than placebo (0%).



   Urinary Tract Infections  In the pool of five placebo-controlled clinical trials, the incidence of urinary tract infections (e.g., urinary tract infection, asymptomatic bacteriuria, and cystitis) was increased in patients treated with empagliflozin compared to placebo (see Table 2). Patients with a history of chronic or recurrent urinary tract infections were more likely to experience a urinary tract infection. The rate of treatment discontinuation due to urinary tract infections was 0.1%, 0.2%, and 0.1% for placebo, empagliflozin 10 mg, and empagliflozin 25 mg, respectively.



 Urinary tract infections occurred more frequently in female patients. The incidence of urinary tract infections in female patients randomized to placebo, empagliflozin 10 mg, and empagliflozin 25 mg was 16.6%, 18.4%, and 17.0%, respectively. The incidence of urinary tract infections in male patients randomized to placebo, empagliflozin 10 mg, and empagliflozin 25 mg was 3.2%, 3.6%, and 4.1%, respectively  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  ) and Use in Specific Populations (  8.5  )]  .



   Metformin hydrochloride  The most common (&gt;5%) established adverse reactions due to initiation of metformin therapy are diarrhea, nausea/vomiting, flatulence, abdominal discomfort, indigestion, asthenia, and headache.



 Long-term treatment with metformin has been associated with a decrease in vitamin B12absorption which may very rarely result in clinically significant vitamin B12deficiency (e.g., megaloblastic anemia)  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )].  



   Laboratory Tests    Empagliflozin    Increase in Low-Density Lipoprotein Cholesterol (LDL-C):  Dose-related increases in low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL-C) were observed in patients treated with empagliflozin. LDL-C increased by 2.3%, 4.6%, and 6.5% in patients treated with placebo, empagliflozin 10 mg, and empagliflozin 25 mg, respectively  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.11  )]  . The range of mean baseline LDL-C levels was 90.3 to 90.6 mg/dL across treatment groups.



   Increase in Hematocrit:  In a pool of four placebo-controlled studies, median hematocrit decreased by 1.3% in placebo and increased by 2.8% in empagliflozin 10 mg and 2.8% in empagliflozin 25 mg treated patients. At the end of treatment, 0.6%, 2.7%, and 3.5% of patients with hematocrits initially within the reference range had values above the upper limit of the reference range with placebo, empagliflozin 10 mg, and empagliflozin 25 mg, respectively.



   Metformin hydrochloride  In controlled clinical trials of metformin of 29 weeks' duration, a decrease to subnormal levels of previously normal serum Vitamin B12levels, without clinical manifestations, was observed in approximately 7% of patients. Such decrease, possibly due to interference with B12absorption from the B12-intrinsic factor complex, is, however, very rarely associated with anemia and appears to be rapidly reversible with discontinuation of metformin or Vitamin B12supplementation  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: RISK OF LACTIC ACIDOSIS

  WARNING: RISK OF LACTIC ACIDOSIS

    Lactic acidosis is a rare, but serious,

complication that can occur due to metformin accumulation.  The risk

increases with conditions such as renal impairment, sepsis, dehydration,

excess alcohol intake, hepatic impairment, and acute congestive heart

failure.  



   The onset is often subtle, accompanied only by nonspecific symptoms

such as malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence,

and nonspecific abdominal distress.  



   Laboratory abnormalities include low

pH, increased anion gap, and elevated blood lactate.  



   If acidosis is suspected,

SYNJARDY should be discontinued and the patient hospitalized immediately   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].    



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: RISK OF LACTIC ACIDOSIS



   See full prescribing information

for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Lactic acidosis can occur due to metformin accumulation. The risk increases with conditions such as renal impairment, sepsis, dehydration, excess alcohol intake, hepatic impairment, and acute congestive heart failure. (5.1) 
 *  Symptoms include malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence, and nonspecific abdominal distress. Laboratory abnormalities include low pH, increased anion gap, and elevated blood lactate. (5.1) 
 *  If acidosis is suspected, discontinue SYNJARDY and hospitalize the patient immediately (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Lactic acidosis: Warn against excessive alcohol use. SYNJARDY is not recommended in hepatic impairment or hypoxic states and is contraindicated in renal impairment. Ensure normal renal function before initiating and at least annually thereafter. (  5.1  ,  5.3  ,  5.4  ,  5.9  ,  5.10  ) 
 *   Hypotension: Before initiating SYNJARDY assess and correct volume status in patients with renal impairment, the elderly, in patients with low systolic blood pressure, and in patients on diuretics. Monitor for signs and symptoms during therapy. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Impairment in renal function: Monitor renal function during therapy. (  5.3  ) 
 *   Radiological studies and surgical procedures: Temporarily discontinue SYNJARDY in patients undergoing radiologic studies with intravascular administration of iodinated contrast materials or any surgical procedures necessitating restricted intake of food and fluids. (  5.3  ) 
 *   Hypoglycemia: Consider lowering the dose of insulin secretagogue or insulin to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia when initiating SYNJARDY (  5.5  ) 
 *   Genital mycotic infections: Monitor and treat as appropriate (  5.6  ) 
 *   Urinary tract infections: Monitor and treat as appropriate (  5.7  ) 
 *   Vitamin B12deficiency: Metformin may lower vitamin B12levels. Monitor hematologic parameters annually. (  5.8  ) 
 *   Increased LDL-C: Monitor and treat as appropriate (  5.11  ) 
 *   Macrovascular outcomes: There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with SYNJARDY. (  5.12  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Lactic Acidosis



  Lactic acidosis is a serious, metabolic complication that can occur due to metformin accumulation during treatment with SYNJARDY and is fatal in approximately 50% of cases. Lactic acidosis may also occur in association with a number of pathophysiologic conditions, including diabetes mellitus, and whenever there is significant tissue hypoperfusion and hypoxemia. Lactic acidosis is characterized by elevated blood lactate levels (&gt;5 mmol/L), decreased blood pH, electrolyte disturbances with an increased anion gap, and an increased lactate/pyruvate ratio. When metformin is implicated as the cause of lactic acidosis, metformin plasma levels of &gt;5 ug/mL are generally found.



 The reported incidence of lactic acidosis in patients receiving metformin is approximately 0.03 cases/1000 patient-years, (with approximately 0.015 fatal cases/1000 patient-years). In more than 20,000 patient-years exposure to metformin in clinical trials, there were no reports of lactic acidosis. Reported cases have occurred primarily in diabetic patients with significant renal impairment, including both intrinsic renal disease and renal hypoperfusion, often in the setting of multiple concomitant medical/surgical problems and multiple concomitant medications. Patients with congestive heart failure requiring pharmacologic management, particularly when accompanied by hypoperfusion and hypoxemia due to unstable or acute failure, are at increased risk of lactic acidosis. The risk of lactic acidosis increases with the degree of renal impairment and the patient's age. The risk of lactic acidosis may, therefore, be significantly decreased by regular monitoring of renal function in patients taking metformin. In particular, treatment of the elderly should be accompanied by careful monitoring of renal function. Metformin treatment should not be initiated in any patient unless measurement of creatinine clearance demonstrates that renal function is not reduced. In addition, metformin should be promptly withheld in the presence of any condition associated with hypoxemia, dehydration, or sepsis. Because impaired hepatic function may significantly limit the ability to clear lactate, metformin should be avoided in patients with clinical or laboratory evidence of hepatic impairment. Patients should be cautioned against excessive alcohol intake when taking metformin, since alcohol potentiates the effects of metformin on lactate metabolism. In addition, metformin should be temporarily discontinued prior to any intravascular radiocontrast study and for any surgical procedure necessitating restricted intake of food or fluids. Use of topiramate, a carbonic anhydrase inhibitor, in epilepsy and migraine prophylaxis may cause dose-dependent metabolic acidosis and may exacerbate the risk of metformin-induced lactic acidosis [see Drug Interactions (  7.2  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  .



 The onset of lactic acidosis is often subtle, and accompanied by nonspecific symptoms such as malaise, myalgias, respiratory distress, increasing somnolence, and nonspecific abdominal distress. More severe acidosis may be associated with signs such as hypothermia, hypotension, and resistant bradyarrhythmias. Patients should be educated to recognize and promptly report these symptoms. If present, SYNJARDY should be discontinued until lactic acidosis is ruled out. Gastrointestinal symptoms, which are commonly reported during initiation of metformin therapy are less frequently observed in subjects on a chronic, stable, dose of metformin. Gastrointestinal symptoms in subjects on chronic, stable, dose of metformin could be caused by lactic acidosis or other serious disease.



 To rule out lactic acidosis, serum electrolytes, ketones, blood glucose, blood pH, lactate levels, and blood metformin levels may be useful. Levels of fasting venous plasma lactate above the upper limit of normal but less than 5 mmol/L in patients taking metformin do not necessarily indicate impending lactic acidosis and may be due to other mechanisms, such as poorly-controlled diabetes or obesity, vigorous physical activity, or technical problems in sample handling.



 Lactic acidosis should be suspected in any diabetic patient with metabolic acidosis lacking evidence of ketoacidosis (ketonuria and ketonemia). Lactic acidosis is a medical emergency that must be treated in a hospital setting. In a patient with lactic acidosis who is taking metformin, the drug should be discontinued immediately and supportive measures promptly instituted. Metformin is dialyzable (clearance of up to 170 mL/min under good hemodynamic conditions) and prompt hemodialysis is recommended to remove the accumulated metformin and correct the metabolic acidosis. Such management often results in prompt reversal of symptoms and recovery [see Boxed Warning and Contraindications (  4  )].  



    5.2 Hypotension



  Empagliflozin causes intravascular volume contraction. Symptomatic hypotension may occur after initiating empagliflozin [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  particularly in patients with renal impairment, the elderly, in patients with low systolic blood pressure, and in patients on diuretics. Before initiating SYNJARDY, assess for volume contraction and correct volume status if indicated. Monitor for signs and symptoms of hypotension after initiating therapy and increase monitoring in clinical situations where volume contraction is expected [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.5  )]  .



    5.3 Impairment in Renal Function



  Empagliflozin increases serum creatinine and decreases eGFR [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  . The risk of impaired renal function with empagliflozin is increased in elderly patients and patients with moderate renal impairment.



 Metformin is known to be substantially excreted by the kidney. The risk of metformin accumulation and lactic acidosis increases with the degree of renal impairment. Therefore, SYNJARDY is contraindicated in patients with renal impairment (serum creatinine levels greater than or equal to 1.5 mg/dL for males or 1.4 mg/dL for females, or eGFR less than 45 mL/min/1.73 m  2  ) [see Contraindications (  4  ), Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ), and Use in Specific Populations (  8.6  )]  .



 Before initiation of therapy with SYNJARDY and at least annually thereafter, renal function should be assessed and verified to be normal. In patients in whom development of renal impairment is anticipated (e.g., elderly), renal function should be assessed more frequently and SYNJARDY discontinued if evidence of renal impairment is present (serum creatinine levels greater than or equal to 1.5 mg/dL for males or 1.4 mg/dL for females, or eGFR less than 45 mL/min/1.73 m  2  ).



    Use of concomitant medications that may affect renal function or metformin disposition:      Concomitant medication(s) that may affect renal function or result in significant hemodynamic change or interfere with the disposition of metformin should be used with caution [see Drug Interactions (  7.2  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  .
 

    Radiological studies and surgical procedures:      Radiologic studies involving the use of intravascular iodinated contrast materials (e.g., intravenous urogram, intravenous cholangiography, angiography, and computed tomography) can lead to acute alteration of renal function and have been associated with lactic acidosis in patients receiving metformin. Therefore, in patients in whom any such study is planned, SYNJARDY should be temporarily discontinued at the time of or prior to the procedure, and withheld for 48 hours subsequent to the procedure and reinstituted only after renal function has been confirmed to be normal.
 

 SYNJARDY should be temporarily discontinued for any surgical procedure (except minor procedures not associated with restricted intake of food and fluids) and should not be restarted until the patient's oral intake has resumed and renal function has been evaluated as normal.



    5.4 Impaired Hepatic Function



  Because impaired hepatic function has been associated with some cases of lactic acidosis with metformin therapy, SYNJARDY should generally be avoided in patients with clinical or laboratory evidence of hepatic disease [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].  



    5.5 Hypoglycemia with Concomitant Use with Insulin and Insulin Secretagogues



    Empagliflozin    Insulin and insulin secretagogues are known to cause hypoglycemia. The risk of hypoglycemia is increased when empagliflozin is used in combination with insulin secretagogues (e.g., sulfonylurea) or insulin [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  . Therefore, a lower dose of the insulin secretagogue or insulin may be required to reduce the risk of hypoglycemia when used in combination with SYNJARDY.
 

   Metformin hydrochloride    Hypoglycemia does not occur in patients receiving metformin alone under usual circumstances of use, but could occur when caloric intake is deficient, when strenuous exercise is not compensated by caloric supplementation, or during concomitant use with other glucose-lowering agents (such as SUs and insulin) or ethanol. Elderly, debilitated, or malnourished patients, and those with adrenal or pituitary insufficiency or alcohol intoxication are particularly susceptible to hypoglycemic effects. Hypoglycemia may be difficult to recognize in the elderly, and in people who are taking beta-adrenergic blocking drugs. Monitor for a need to lower the dose of SYNJARDY to minimize the risk of hypoglycemia in these patients.
 

    5.6 Genital Mycotic Infections



  Empagliflozin increases the risk for genital mycotic infections [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  . Patients with a history of chronic or recurrent genital mycotic infections were more likely to develop mycotic genital infections. Monitor and treat as appropriate.



    5.7 Urinary Tract Infections



  Empagliflozin increases the risk for urinary tract infections [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  . Monitor and treat as appropriate.



    5.8 Vitamin B12Levels



  In controlled, 29-week clinical trials of metformin, a decrease to subnormal levels of previously normal serum vitamin B12levels, without clinical manifestations, was observed in approximately 7% of metformin-treated patients. Such decrease, possibly due to interference with B12absorption from the B12-intrinsic factor complex, is, however, very rarely associated with anemia or neurologic manifestations due to the short duration (&lt;1 year) of the clinical trials. This risk may be more relevant to patients receiving long-term treatment with metformin, and adverse hematologic and neurologic reactions have been reported postmarketing. The decrease in vitamin B12levels appears to be rapidly reversible with discontinuation of metformin or vitamin B12supplementation. Measurement of hematologic parameters on an annual basis is advised in patients on SYNJARDY and any apparent abnormalities should be appropriately investigated and managed. Certain individuals (those with inadequate vitamin B12or calcium intake or absorption) appear to be predisposed to developing subnormal vitamin B12levels. In these patients, routine serum vitamin B12measurement at 2- to 3-year intervals may be useful.



    5.9 Alcohol Intake



  Alcohol is known to potentiate the effect of metformin on lactate metabolism. Patients, therefore, should be warned against excessive alcohol intake while receiving SYNJARDY [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].  



    5.10 Hypoxic States



  Cardiovascular collapse (shock) from whatever cause (e.g., acute congestive heart failure, acute myocardial infarction, and other conditions characterized by hypoxemia) have been associated with lactic acidosis and may also cause prerenal azotemia. When such events occur in patients on SYNJARDY therapy, the drug should be promptly discontinued [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].  



    5.11 Increased Low-Density Lipoprotein Cholesterol (LDL-C)



  Increases in LDL-C can occur with empagliflozin. Monitor and treat as appropriate.



    5.12 Macrovascular Outcomes



  There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with SYNJARDY, or any other antidiabetic drug.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
