<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="talwin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most commonly occurring reactions are: nausea, dizziness or lightheadedness, vomiting, euphoria.



     Dermatologic Reactions:    Soft tissue induration, nodules, and cutaneous depression can occur at injection sites. Ulceration (sloughing) and severe sclerosis of the skin and subcutaneous tissues (and, rarely, underlying muscle) have been reported after multiple doses. Other reported dermatologic reactions include diaphoresis, sting on injection, flushed skin including plethora, dermatitis including pruritus.



 Infrequently occurring reactions are-    respiratory    : respiratory depression, dyspnea, transient apnea in a small number of newborn infants whose mothers received TALWIN during labor;    cardiovascular    : circulatory depression, shock, hypertension;    CNS effects    : dizziness, lightheadedness, hallucinations, sedation, euphoria, headache, confusion, disorientation; infrequently weakness, disturbed dreams, insomnia, syncope, visual blurring and focusing difficulty, depression; and rarely tremor, irritability, excitement, tinnitus;    gastrointestinal    : constipation, dry mouth;    other    : urinary retention, headache, paresthesia, alterations in rate or strength of uterine contractions during labor.



 Rarely reported reactions include-    neuromuscular    and    psychiatric    : muscle tremor, insomnia, disorientation, hallucinations;    gastrointestinal    : taste alteration, diarrhea and cramps;    ophthalmic    : blurred vision, nystagmus, diplopia, miosis;    hematologic    : depression of white blood cells (especially granulocytes), which is usually reversible, moderate transient eosinophilia;    other    : tachycardia, weakness or faintness, chills; allergic reactions including edema of the face, toxic epidermal necrolysis. (See    Acute CNS Manifestations    and    Drug Dependence    under    WARNINGS    .)
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
