<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tamiflu0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed below and elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Serious skin and hypersensitivity reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Neuropsychiatric events [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
    The most common adverse reactions are nausea and vomiting.
 

   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;1% and more common than with placebo):



 *  Treatment studies - Nausea, vomiting (  6.1  ) 
 *  Prophylaxis studies - Nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, abdominal pain (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Genentech at 1-888-835-2555 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Treatment Studies in Adult Subjects  



 A total of 1171 subjects who participated in adult controlled clinical trials for the treatment of influenza were treated with TAMIFLU. The most frequently reported adverse events in these studies were nausea and vomiting. These events were generally of mild to moderate severity and usually occurred on the first 2 days of administration. Less than 1% of subjects discontinued prematurely from clinical trials due to nausea and vomiting.



 Adverse events that occurred with an incidence of &gt;=1% in 1440 subjects taking placebo or TAMIFLU 75 mg twice daily in adult treatment studies are shown in  Table 4  . This summary includes 945 healthy young adults and 495 "at risk" subjects (elderly patients and patients with chronic cardiac or respiratory disease). Those events reported numerically more frequently in subjects taking TAMIFLU compared with placebo were nausea, vomiting, bronchitis, insomnia, and vertigo.



     Prophylaxis Studies in Adult Subjects  



 A total of 4187 subjects (adolescents, healthy adults, and elderly) participated in prophylaxis studies, of whom 1790 received the recommended dose of 75 mg once daily for up to 6 weeks. Adverse events were qualitatively very similar to those seen in the treatment studies, despite a longer duration of dosing (see  Table 4  ). Events reported more frequently in subjects receiving TAMIFLU compared to subjects receiving placebo in prophylaxis studies, and more commonly than in treatment studies, were aches and pains, rhinorrhea, dyspepsia and upper respiratory tract infections. However, the difference in incidence between TAMIFLU and placebo for these events was less than 1%. There were no clinically relevant differences in the safety profile of the 942 elderly subjects who received TAMIFLU or placebo, compared with the younger population.



 Table 4 Most Frequent Adverse Events in Studies in Naturally Acquired Influenza in Subjects 13 Years of Age and Older 
                                       Treatment  Prophylaxis   
 Adverse Event                         PlaceboN=716  TAMIFLU75 mg twice dailyN=724  Placebo/No ProphylaxisN=1688  TAMIFLU75 mg once dailyN=1790   
  
 Nausea (without vomiting)                40       (6%)       72      (10%)       56       (3%)      129       (7%)     
 Vomiting                                 21       (3%)       68       (9%)       16       (1%)       39       (2%)     
 Diarrhea                                 70      (10%)       48       (7%)       40       (2%)       50       (3%)     
 Bronchitis                               15       (2%)       17       (2%)       22       (1%)       15       (1%)     
 Abdominal pain                           16       (2%)       16       (2%)       25       (1%)       37       (2%)     
 Dizziness                                25       (3%)       15       (2%)       21       (1%)       24       (1%)     
 Headache                                 14       (2%)       13       (2%)      306      (18%)      326      (18%)     
 Cough                                    12       (2%)       9        (1%)      119       (7%)       94       (5%)     
 Insomnia                                 6        (1%)       8        (1%)       15       (1%)       22       (1%)     
 Vertigo                                  4        (1%)       7        (1%)       4       (&lt;1%)       4       (&lt;1%)     
 Fatigue                                  7        (1%)       7        (1%)      163      (10%)      139       (8%)     
               Additional adverse events occurring in &lt;1% of patients receiving TAMIFLU for treatment included unstable angina, anemia, pseudomembranous colitis, humerus fracture, pneumonia, pyrexia, and peritonsillar abscess.
 

     Treatment Studies in Pediatric Subjects  



 A total of 1032 pediatric subjects aged 1 to 12 years (including 698 otherwise healthy pediatric subjects aged 1 to 12 years and 334 asthmatic pediatric subjects aged 6 to 12 years) participated in controlled clinical trials of TAMIFLU given for the treatment of influenza. A total of 515 pediatric subjects received treatment with TAMIFLU for oral suspension.



 Adverse events occurring in &gt;=1% of pediatric subjects receiving TAMIFLU treatment are listed in  Table 5  . The most frequently reported adverse event was vomiting. Other events reported more frequently by pediatric subjects treated with TAMIFLU included abdominal pain, epistaxis, ear disorder, and conjunctivitis. These events generally occurred once and resolved despite continued dosing resulting in discontinuation of drug in 8 out of 515 (2%) cases.



 The adverse event profile in adolescents is similar to that described for adult subjects and pediatric subjects aged 1 to 12 years.



     Prophylaxis Studies in Pediatric Subjects  



 Pediatric subjects aged 1 to 12 years participated in a postexposure prophylaxis study in households, both as index cases (n=134) and as contacts (n=222). Gastrointestinal events were the most frequent, particularly vomiting. In a separate 6-week, uncontrolled, pediatric seasonal prophylaxis study (n=49), the adverse events noted were consistent with those previously observed (see  Table 5  ).



 Table 5 Most Frequent Adverse Events Occurring in Children Aged 1 to 12 Years in Studies in Naturally Acquired Influenza 
                                   Treatment Trials  Household Prophylaxis Trial   
 Adverse Event                     PlaceboN=517  TAMIFLU2 mg/kg twice dailyN=515  No ProphylaxisN=87  Prophylaxis with TAMIFLUonce dailyN=99   
  
 Vomiting                             48       (9%)       77       (15%)       2         (2%)        10       (10%)     
 Diarrhea                             55      (11%)       49       (10%)       -                     1        (1%)      
 Otitis media                         58      (11%)       45       (9%)        2         (2%)        2        (2%)      
 Abdominal pain                       20       (4%)       24       (5%)        -                     3        (3%)      
 Asthma (including aggravated)        19       (4%)       18       (3%)        1         (1%)        1        (1%)      
 Nausea                               22       (4%)       17       (3%)        1         (1%)        4        (4%)      
 Epistaxis                            13       (3%)       16       (3%)        -                     1        (1%)      
 Pneumonia                            17       (3%)       10       (2%)        2         (2%)        -                  
 Ear disorder                         6        (1%)       9        (2%)        -                     -                  
 Sinusitis                            13       (3%)       9        (2%)        -                     -                  
 Bronchitis                           11       (2%)       8        (2%)        2         (2%)        -                  
 Conjunctivitis                       2       (&lt;1%)       5        (1%)        -                     -                  
 Dermatitis                           10       (2%)       5        (1%)        -                     -                  
 Lymphadenopathy                      8        (2%)       5        (1%)        -                     -                  
 Tympanic membrane disorder           6        (1%)       5        (1%)        -                     -                  
                   Prophylaxis Study in Immunocompromised Subjects  
 

 In a 12-week seasonal prophylaxis study in 475 immunocompromised subjects, including 18 pediatric subjects 1 to 12 years of age, the safety profile in the 238 subjects receiving TAMIFLU was consistent with that previously observed in other TAMIFLU prophylaxis clinical trials.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of TAMIFLU. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to TAMIFLU exposure.



 Body as a Whole: Swelling of the face or tongue, allergy, anaphylactic/anaphylactoid reactions, hypothermia



 Dermatologic: Rash, dermatitis, urticaria, eczema, toxic epidermal necrolysis, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome, erythema multiforme  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  



 Digestive: Hepatitis, liver function tests abnormal



 Cardiac: Arrhythmia



 Gastrointestinal disorders: Gastrointestinal bleeding, hemorrhagic colitis



 Neurologic: Seizure



 Metabolic: Aggravation of diabetes



 Psychiatric: Abnormal behavior, delirium, including symptoms such as hallucinations, agitation, anxiety, altered level of consciousness, confusion, nightmares, delusions  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Serious skin/hypersensitivity reactions: Discontinue TAMIFLU and initiate appropriate treatment if allergic-like reactions occur or are suspected. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Neuropsychiatric events: Patients with influenza, including those receiving TAMIFLU, particularly pediatric patients, may be at an increased risk of confusion or abnormal behavior early in their illness. Monitor for signs of abnormal behavior. (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Serious Skin/Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Cases of anaphylaxis and serious skin reactions including toxic epidermal necrolysis, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome, and erythema multiforme have been reported in postmarketing experience with TAMIFLU. TAMIFLU should be stopped and appropriate treatment instituted if an allergic-like reaction occurs or is suspected.



    5.2 Neuropsychiatric Events



  Influenza can be associated with a variety of neurologic and behavioral symptoms that can include events such as hallucinations, delirium, and abnormal behavior, in some cases resulting in fatal outcomes. These events may occur in the setting of encephalitis or encephalopathy but can occur without obvious severe disease.



 There have been postmarketing reports (mostly from Japan) of delirium and abnormal behavior leading to injury, and in some cases resulting in fatal outcomes, in patients with influenza who were receiving TAMIFLU. Because these events were reported voluntarily during clinical practice, estimates of frequency cannot be made but they appear to be uncommon based on TAMIFLU usage data. These events were reported primarily among pediatric patients and often had an abrupt onset and rapid resolution. The contribution of TAMIFLU to these events has not been established. Closely monitor patients with influenza for signs of abnormal behavior. If neuropsychiatric symptoms occur, evaluate the risks and benefits of continuing treatment for each patient.



    5.3 Bacterial Infections



  Serious bacterial infections may begin with influenza-like symptoms or may coexist with or occur as complications during the course of influenza. TAMIFLU has not been shown to prevent such complications.



    5.4 Limitations of Populations Studied



  Efficacy of TAMIFLU in the treatment of influenza in patients with chronic cardiac disease and/or respiratory disease has not been established. No difference in the incidence of complications was observed between the treatment and placebo groups in this population. No information is available regarding treatment of influenza in patients with any medical condition sufficiently severe or unstable to be considered at imminent risk of requiring hospitalization.



 Efficacy of TAMIFLU for treatment or prophylaxis of influenza has not been established in immunocompromised patients.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
