<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="targretin1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The safety of Targretin  (r)  gel has been assessed in clinical studies of 117 patients with CTCL who received Targretin  (r)  gel for up to 172 weeks. In the multicenter open-label study, 50 patients with CTCL received Targretin  (r)  gel for up to 98 weeks. The mean duration of therapy for these 50 patients was 199 days. The most common adverse events reported with an incidence at the application site of at least 10% in patients with CTCL were rash, pruritus, skin disorder, and pain.



 Adverse events leading to dose reduction or study drug discontinuation in at least two patients were rash, contact dermatitis, and pruritus.



 Of the 49 patients (98%) who experienced any adverse event, most experienced events categorized as mild (9 patients, 18%) or moderate (27 patients, 54%). There were 12 patients (24%) who experienced at least one moderately severe adverse event. The most common moderately severe events were rash (7 patients, 14%) and pruritus (3 patients, 6%). Only one patient (2%) experienced a severe adverse event (rash).



 In the patients with CTCL receiving Targretin  (r)  gel, adverse events reported regardless of relationship to study drug at an incidence of &gt;=5% are presented in Table 1.



 A similar safety profile for Targretin  (r)  gel was demonstrated in the Phase I-II program. For the 67 patients enrolled in the Phase I-II program, the mean duration of treatment was 436 days (range 12-1203 days). As in the multicenter study, the most common adverse events regardless of relationship to study drug in the Phase I-II program were rash (78%), pain (40%), and pruritus (40%).



 Table 1. Incidence of All Adverse Events* and Application Site Adverse Events with Incidence &gt;= 5% for All Application Frequencies of Targretin(r) Gel in the Multicenter CTCL Study 
 * Regardless of association with treatmentIncludes Investigator terms such as:  1  Contact dermatitis, irritant contact dermatitis, irritant dermatitis  2  Pruritus, itching, itching of lesion  3  Erythema, scaling, irritation, redness, rash, dermatitis  4  Skin inflammation, excoriation, sticky or tacky sensation of skin; NOS = Not Otherwise Specified   
  
                                                      All Adverse Events         Application Site Adverse Events    
  COSTART 5Body System/Preferred Term                 N = 50n (%)                N = 50n (%)                
  Skin and Appendages                                 
     Contact Dermatitis1                              7 (14)                     4 (8)                      
     Exfoliative Dermatitis                           3 (6)                      0                          
     Pruritus2                                        18 (36)                    9 (18)                     
     Rash3                                            36 (72)                    28 (56)                    
     Maculopapular Rash                               3 (6)                      0                          
     Skin Disorder (NOS)4                             13 (26)                    9 (18)                     
     Sweating                                         3 (6)                      0                          
  Body as a Whole                                     
     Asthenia                                         3 (6)                      0                          
     Headache                                         7 (14)                     0                          
     Infection                                        9 (18)                     0                          
     Pain                                             15 (30)                    9 (18)                     
  Cardiovascular                                      
     Edema                                            5 (10)                     0                          
     Peripheral Edema                                 3 (6)                      0                          
  Hemic and Lymphatic                                 
     Leukopenia                                       3 (6)                      0                          
     Lymphadenopathy                                  3 (6)                      0                          
     WBC Abnormal                                     3 (6)                      0                          
  Metabolic and Nutritional                           
     Hyperlipemia                                     5 (10)                     0                          
     Nervous                                          
     Paresthesia                                      3 (6)                      3 (6)                      
  Respiratory                                         
     Cough Increased                                  3 (6)                      0                          
     Pharyngitis                                      3 (6)                      0                          
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
