<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="targretin0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the prescribing information:



 *    Hyperlipidemia [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *    Pancreatitis [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
 *    Hepatotoxicity, cholestasis, and hepatic failure [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ] 
 *    Hypothyroidism [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   ] 
 *    Neutropenia [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)   ] 
 *    Cataracts [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)   ] 
 *    Vitamin A Supplementation Hazard [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)   ] 
 *    Hypoglycemia Risk in Patients with Diabetes Mellitus [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)   ] 
 *    Photosensitivity [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)   ] 
 *    Laboratory Tests [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)   ] 
 *    Drug/Laboratory Test Interactions [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.11)   ] 
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (greater than 10%) include: hyperlipidemia, hypercholesteremia, headache, hypothyroidism, asthenia, leukopenia, rash, nausea, infection, peripheral edema, abdominal pain, and dry skin. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Valeant Pharmaceuticals North America LLC at 1-800-321-4576 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of TARGRETIN has been evaluated in two clinical trials of 152 patients with CTCL who received TARGRETIN for up to 97 weeks and in 352 patients in other trials. The mean duration of therapy for the 152 patients with CTCL was 166 days. The most common adverse events reported with an incidence of at least 10% in patients with CTCL treated at an initial dose of 300 mg/m  2  /day of TARGRETIN are shown in Table 2. The events at least possibly related to treatment are lipid abnormalities (elevated triglycerides, elevated total and LDL cholesterol and decreased HDL cholesterol), hypothyroidism, headache, asthenia, rash, leukopenia, anemia, nausea, infection, peripheral edema, abdominal pain, and dry skin. Most adverse events occurred at a greater incidence in patients treated at starting doses of greater than 300 mg/m  2  /day (see Table 2).



 Adverse reactions leading to TARGRETIN dose reduction or discontinuation in at least two patients were hyperlipemia, neutropenia/leukopenia, diarrhea, fatigue/lethargy, hypothyroidism, headache, liver function test abnormalities, rash, pancreatitis, nausea, anemia, allergic reaction, muscle spasm, pneumonia, and confusion.



 The NCI Grade 3 and NCI Grade 4 adverse reactions reported in two or more patients with CTCL treated at an initial dose of 300 mg/m  2  /day of TARGRETIN (see Table 3) were hypertriglyceridemia, pruritus, headache, peripheral edema, leukopenia, rash, and hypercholesteremia. Most of these moderately severe or severe adverse events occurred at a higher rate in patients treated at starting doses of greater than 300 mg/m  2  /day than in patients treated at a starting dose of 300 mg/m  2  /day.



 In patients with CTCL receiving an initial dose of 300 mg/m  2  /day, the incidence of NCI Grade 3 or 4 elevations in triglycerides and total cholesterol was 28% and 25%, respectively (Table 4). In contrast, in patients with CTCL receiving greater than 300 mg/m  2  /day, the incidence of NCI Grade 3 or 4 elevated triglycerides and total cholesterol was 45% and 45%, respectively. Other Grade 3 and 4 laboratory abnormalities are shown in Table 3.



 In addition to the 152 patients enrolled in the two CTCL trials, 352 patients received TARGRETIN as monotherapy for various advanced malignancies at doses from 5 mg/m  2  /day to 1000 mg/m  2  /day. The common adverse reactions (incidence greater than 10%) were similar to those seen in patients with CTCL.



 In the 504 patients (CTCL and non-CTCL) who received TARGRETIN as monotherapy, drug-related serious adverse reactions that were fatal, in one patient each, were acute pancreatitis, subdural hematoma, and liver failure.



 In the patients with CTCL receiving an initial dose of 300 mg/m  2  /day of TARGRETIN, adverse reactions reported at an incidence of less than 10% and not included in Tables 2-4 or discussed in other parts of labeling and possibly related to treatment were as follows:



   Body as a Whole:  chills, cellulitis, chest pain, breast pain, sepsis, and monilia infection.



   Cardiovascular:  hemorrhage, hypertension, angina pectoris, right heart failure, syncope, and tachycardia.



   Digestive:  constipation, dry mouth, flatulence, colitis, dyspepsia, cheilitis, gastroenteritis, gingivitis, liver failure, and melena.



   Hemic and Lymphatic:  eosinophilia, thrombocythemia, coagulation time increased, lymphocytosis, and thrombocytopenia.



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  LDH increased, creatinine increased, hypoproteinemia, hyperglycemia, weight decreased, weight increased, and amylase increased.



   Musculoskeletal:  arthralgia, myalgia, bone pain, myasthenia, and arthrosis.



   Nervous:  depression, agitation, ataxia, cerebrovascular accident, confusion, dizziness, hyperesthesia, hypesthesia, and neuropathy.



   Respiratory  : pharyngitis, rhinitis, dyspnea, pleural effusion, bronchitis, cough increased, lung edema, hemoptysis, and hypoxia.



   Skin and Appendages:  skin ulcer, acne, alopecia, skin nodule, macular papular rash, pustular rash, serous drainage, and vesicular bullous rash.



   Special Senses:  dry eyes, conjunctivitis, ear pain, blepharitis, corneal lesion, keratitis, otitis externa, and visual field defect.



   Urogenital:  albuminuria, hematuria, urinary incontinence, urinary tract infection, urinary urgency, dysuria, and kidney function abnormal.



 Table 2: Adverse Events with Incidence &gt;=10% in CTCL Trials 
                                     Initial Assigned Dose Group  (mg/m2/day)    
                                     300                                &gt;300                               
  Body System                        N = 84                             N = 53                             
  Adverse EventPreferred English term coded according to Ligand-modified COSTART 5 Dictionary.,Patients are counted at most once in each AE category.    N (%)                              N (%)                              
                                                                                                           
  METABOLIC AND NUTRITIONAL DISORDERS                                                                          
  Hyperlipemia                       66 (79)                            42 (79)                            
  Hypercholesteremia                 27 (32)                            33 (62)                            
  Lactic dehydrogenase increased     6 (7)                              7 (13)                             
                                                                                                           
  BODY AS A WHOLE                                                                                          
  Headache                           25 (30)                            22 (42)                            
  Asthenia                           17 (20)                            24 (45)                            
  Infection                          11 (13)                            12 (23)                            
  Abdominal pain                     9 (11)                             2 (4)                              
  Chills                             8 (10)                             7 (13)                             
  Fever                              4 (5)                              9 (17)                             
  Flu syndrome                       3 (4)                              7 (13)                             
  Back pain                          2 (2)                              6 (11)                             
  Infection bacterial                1 (1)                              7 (13)                             
                                                                                                           
  ENDOCRINE                                                                                                
  Hypothyroidism                     24 (29)                            28 (53)                            
                                                                                                           
  SKIN AND APPENDAGES                                                                                      
  Rash                               14 (17)                            12 (23)                            
  Dry skin                           9 (17)                             5 (9)                              
  Exfoliative dermatitis             8 (10)                             15 (28)                            
  Alopecia                           3 (4)                              6 (11)                             
                                                                                                           
  HEMIC AND LYMPHATIC SYSTEM                                                                               
  Leukopenia                         14 (17)                            25 (47)                            
  Anemia                             5 (6)                              13 (25)                            
  Hypochromic anemia                 3 (4)                              7 (13)                             
                                                                                                           
  DIGESTIVE SYSTEM                                                                                         
  Nausea                             13 (16)                            4 (8)                              
  Diarrhea                           6 (7)                              22 (42)                            
  Vomiting                           3 (4)                              7 (13)                             
  Anorexia                           2 (2)                              12 (23)                            
                                                                                                           
  CARDIOVASCULAR SYSTEM                                                                                    
  Peripheral edema                   11 (13)                            6 (11)                             
                                                                                                           
  NERVOUS SYSTEM                                                                                           
  Insomnia                           4 (5)                              6 (11)                             
         Table  3  : Incidence of Moderately Severe and Severe Adverse Events Reported in at Least Two Patients (CTCL Trials)
 


                                     Initial Assigned Dose Group (mg/m2/day)    
                                     300 (N = 84)       &gt;300 (N = 53)      
                                     Mod Sev            Severe             Mod Sev            Severe             
  Body System                                                              
  Adverse EventPreferred English term coded according to Ligand-modified COSTART 5 Dictionary.,Patients are counted at most once in each AE category. Patients are classified by the highest severity within each row.    N (%)              N (%)              N (%)              N (%)              
                                                                           
  BODY AS A WHOLE                                                          
  Asthenia                           1 (1)              0 (0)              11 (21)            0 (0)              
  Headache                           3 (4)              0 (0)              5 (9)              1 (2)              
  Infection bacterial                1 (1)              0 (0)              0 (0)              2 (4)              
                                                                           
  CARDIOVASCULAR SYS.                                                      
  Peripheral edema                   2 (2)              1 (1)              0 (0)              0 (0)              
                                                                           
  DIGESTIVE SYSTEM                                                         
  Anorexia                           0 (0)              0 (0)              3 (6)              0 (0)              
  Diarrhea                           1 (1)              1 (1)              2 (4)              1 (2)              
  Pancreatitis                       1 (1)              0 (0)              3 (6)              0 (0)              
  Vomiting                           0 (0)              0 (0)              2 (4)              0 (0)              
                                                                           
  ENDOCRINE                                                                
  Hypothyroidism                     1 (1)              1 (1)              2 (4)              0 (0)              
                                                                           
  HEM. &amp; LYMPH. SYS.                                                       
  Leukopenia                         3 (4)              0 (0)              6 (11)             1 (2)              
                                                                           
  META. AND NUTR. DIS.                                                     
  Bilirubinemia                      0 (0)              1 (1)              2 (4)              0 (0)              
  Hypercholesteremia                 2 (2)              0 (0)              5 (9)              0 (0)              
  Hyperlipemia                       16 (19             6 (7)              17 (32)            5 (9)              
  SGOT/AST increased                 0 (0)              0 (0)              2 (4)              0 (0)              
  SGPT/ALT increased                 0 (0)              0 (0)              2 (4)              0 (0)              
                                                                           
  RESPIRATORY SYSTEM                                                       
  Pneumonia                          0 (0)              0 (0)              2 (4)              2 (4)              
                                                                           
  SKIN AND APPENDAGES                                                      
  Exfoliative dermatitis             0 (0)              1 (1)              3 (6)              1 (2)              
  Rash                               1 (1)              2 (2)              1 (2)              0 (0)              
           Table  4  : Treatment-Emergent Abnormal Laboratory Values in CTCL Trials
 


                                     Initial Assigned Dose (mg/m2/day)    
                                     300                &gt;300               
                                     N = 83Number of patients with at least one analyte value post-baseline.    N = 53             
  Analyte                            Grade 3Adapted from NCI Common Toxicity Criteria, Grade 3 and 4, Version 2.0. Patients are considered to have had a Grade 3 or 4 value if either of the following occurred: a) Value becomes Grade 3 or 4 during the study; b) Value is abnormal at baseline and worsens to Grade 3 or 4 on study, including all values beyond study drug discontinuation, as defined in data handling conventions.  (%)    Grade 4  (%)       Grade 3  (%)       Grade 4  (%)       
                                                                           
  TriglyceridesThe denominator used to calculate the incidence rates for fasting Total Cholesterol and Triglycerides were N=75 for the 300 mg/m2/day initial dose group and N=44 for the &gt;300 mg/m2/day initial dose group.    21                 7                  32                 14                 
  Total Cholesterol                  19                 7                  16                 30                 
                                                                           
  Alkaline Phosphatase               1                  0                  0                  2                  
  Hyperglycemia                      1                  0                  6                  0                  
  Hypocalcemia                       1                  0                  0                  0                  
  Hyponatremia                       1                  0                  9                  0                  
  SGPT/ALT                           1                  0                  2                  2                  
  Hyperkalemia                       0                  0                  2                  0                  
  Hypernatremia                      0                  1                  0                  0                  
  SGOT/AST                           0                  0                  2                  2                  
  Total Bilirubin                    0                  0                  0                  2                  
                                                                           
  ANC decreased                      12                 4                  19                 8                  
  ALC decreased                      7                  0                  15                 0                  
  WBC decreased                      4                  0                  11                 0                  
  Hemoglobin decreased               0                  0                  2                  0                  
           The safety profile from the one post-approval trial with 59 subjects was generally comparable to that of the pivotal trials with the exception of serious adverse events hypertriglyceridemia, neutropenia and bone marrow failure which were observed more frequently in the TARGRETIN 300 mg/m  2  /day group than in the TARGRETIN 150 mg/m  2  /day group.
 

 Severe hypertriglyceridemia (  &gt;  800 mg/dL) was not seen in any subject in the lower dosage arm.



 The most common AEs by preferred term in either the TARGRETIN 300 or 150 mg/m  2  /day treatment group were as follows: hypertriglyceridemia (18 subjects [62.1%] and 17 subjects [56.7%], respectively); hypothyroidism (15 subjects [51.7%] and 13 subjects [43.3%], respectively); headache (9 subjects [31.0%] and 7 subjects [23.3%], respectively); hypercholesterolemia (8 subjects [27.6%] and 7 subjects [23.3%], respectively); neutropenia (7 subjects [24.1%] and 2 subjects [6.7%], respectively); and skin exfoliation (5 subjects [17.2%] and 5 subjects [16.7%], respectively).



 Higher percentage of subjects in the TARGRETIN 300 mg/m  2  /day group than in TARGRETIN 150 mg/m  2  /day group experienced SAEs (13 subjects [44.8%] vs 11 subjects [36.7%], respectively.



 Of the SAEs of special interest, there were more events in the TARGRETIN 300 mg/m  2  /day group than in the TARGRETIN 150 mg/m  2  /day group of bone marrow failure (3 [10.3%] vs 1 [3.3%, respectively]), neutropenia (3 [10.3%] vs 0 [0%], respectively), and of hypertriglyceridemia (9 [31%] vs 2 [6.7%], respectively).
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: BIRTH DEFECTS

  WARNING: BIRTH DEFECTS

    TARGRETIN is a member of the retinoid class of drugs that is associated with birth defects in humans.  Bexarotene also caused birth defects when administered orally to pregnant rats.  TARGRETIN must not be administered to a pregnant woman. (  8.1  )  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: BIRTH DEFECTS



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



   TARGRETIN is a member of the retinoid class of drugs that is associated with birth defects in humans. Bexarotene also caused birth defects when administered orally to pregnant rats.  TARGRETIN must not be administered to a pregnant woman.  (  8.1  )  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Hyperlipidemia: TARGRETIN causes elevations in blood lipids. Obtain baseline values, monitor, and manage elevations during therapy by dose reduction, interruption, discontinuation and/or lipid lowering therapy. (  5.1  ,  5.11  ) 
 *    Pancreatitis: Interrupt TARGRETIN and evaluate if suspected. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Hepatotoxicity, cholestasis, and hepatic failure: Interrupt or discontinue TARGRETIN and evaluate if liver chemistry tests exceed three times the upper limit of normal values. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Hypothyroidism: TARGRETIN therapy can cause hypothyroidism. monitor and replace thyroid hormone if needed (  5.5  ) 
 *    Neutropenia: Monitor for neutropenia. Reduce TARGRETIN dose or interrupt as indicated. (  5.6  ) 
 *    Photosensitivity: Minimize exposure to sunlight and artificial ultraviolet light during treatment. (  5.10  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hyperlipidemia



  TARGRETIN induces substantial elevations in lipids in most patients. About 70% of patients with CTCL who received an initial dose of &gt;  300 mg/m2/day of TARGRETIN had fasting triglyceride levels greater than 2.5 times the upper limit of normal. About 55% had values over 800 mg/dL with a median of about 1200 mg/dL in those patients. Cholesterol elevations above 300 mg/dL occurred in approximately 60% and 75% of patients with CTCL who received an initial dose of 300 mg/m  2  /day or greater than 300 mg/m  2  /day, respectively. Decreases in high density lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol to less than 25 mg/dL were seen in about 55% and 90% of patients receiving an initial dose of 300 mg/m  2  /day or greater than 300 mg/m  2  /day, respectively, of TARGRETIN. Monitor lipid changes and treat abnormalities during therapy. The effects on triglycerides, HDL cholesterol, and total cholesterol were reversible with cessation of therapy, and could generally be mitigated by dose reduction and/or concomitant antilipemic therapy.



 Perform fasting blood lipid determinations before TARGRETIN therapy is initiated and weekly until the lipid response to TARGRETIN is established, which usually occurs within two to four weeks, and monitor at eight week intervals thereafter. Fasting triglycerides should be normal or normalized with appropriate intervention prior to initiating TARGRETIN therapy. Maintain triglyceride levels below 400 mg/dL to reduce the risk of clinical sequelae [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ]. If fasting triglycerides are elevated or become elevated during treatment, institute antilipemic therapy, and if necessary, reduce or interrupt the dose of TARGRETIN. In the 300 mg/m  2  /day initial dose group, 60% of patients were given lipid lowering drugs. Atorvastatin was used in 48% (73/152) of patients with CTCL. Because of a potential drug-drug interaction, avoid gemfibrozil use with TARGRETIN [ see  Drug Interactions (7)    ].



    5.2 Pancreatitis



  Acute pancreatitis, including a fatal case, has been reported in four patients with CTCL and in six patients with non-CTCL cancers treated with TARGRETIN; the cases were associated with marked elevations of fasting serum triglycerides, the lowest being 770 mg/dL in one patient. One patient with advanced non-CTCL cancer died of pancreatitis. Interrupt TARGRETIN and evaluate if pancreatitis is suspected. Patients with CTCL who have risk factors for pancreatitis (e.g., prior pancreatitis, uncontrolled hyperlipidemia, excessive alcohol consumption, uncontrolled diabetes mellitus, biliary tract disease, and medications known to increase triglyceride levels or to be associated with pancreatic toxicity) may be at greater risk for pancreatitis associated with TARGRETIN [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)    ].



    5.3 Hepatotoxicity, cholestasis, and hepatic failure



  TARGRETIN caused elevations in liver chemistry tests (LFTs) in 5% (AST), 2% (ALT), and 0% (bilirubin) in patients with CTCL receiving an initial dose of 300 mg/m  2  /day. In contrast, with an initial dose greater than 300 mg/m  2  /day of TARGRETIN, the incidence of LFT elevations was higher at 7% (SGOT/AST), 9% (SGPT/ALT), and 6% (bilirubin). Two patients developed cholestasis, including one patient who died of liver failure. In clinical trials, elevated LFTs resolved within one month in 80% of patients following a decrease in dose or discontinuation of therapy. Obtain baseline LFTs and monitor LFTs after one, two and four weeks of treatment initiation, and if stable, at least every eight weeks thereafter during treatment. Interrupt or discontinue TARGRETIN if test results exceed three times the upper limit of normal values for AST, ALT, or bilirubin.



    5.4 Hypothyroidism



  TARGRETIN induces hypothyroidism in about half of all patients treated by causing a reversible reduction in levels of thyroid hormone (total thyroxine [total T4]) and thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH). The incidence of decreases in TSH and total T4 were about 60% and 45%, respectively, in patients with CTCL receiving an initial dose of 300 mg/m  2  /day. Hypothyroidism was reported as an adverse event in 29% of patients. Consider treatment with thyroid hormone supplementation in patients with hypothyroidism. In the 300 mg/m  2  /day initial dose group, 37% of patients were treated with thyroid hormone replacement. Obtain baseline thyroid function tests and patients monitor during treatment.



    5.5 Neutropenia



  Leukopenia in the range of 1000 to &lt;3000 WBC x 10  6  /L occurred in 18% of patients with CTCL receiving an initial dose of 300 mg/m  2  /day of TARGRETIN. Patients receiving an initial dose greater than 300 mg/m  2  /day of TARGRETIN had an incidence of leukopenia of 43%. No patient with CTCL treated with TARGRETIN developed leukopenia of less than 1000 WBC x 10  6  /L. The usual time to onset of leukopenia was four to eight weeks after initiating TARGRETIN. The leukopenia observed in most patients was predominately neutropenia. In the 300 mg/m  2  /day initial dose group, the incidence of NCI Grade 3 and Grade 4 neutropenia, respectively, was 12% and 4%. The leukopenia and neutropenia experienced during TARGRETIN therapy resolved after dose reduction or discontinuation of treatment, on average within 30 days in 93% of the patients with CTCL and 82% of patients with non-CTCL cancers. Leukopenia and neutropenia were rarely associated with severe sequelae or serious adverse events. Obtain complete blood counts (CBC) at baseline and periodically during treatment.



    5.6 Cataracts



  Posterior subcapsular cataracts occurred in preclinical toxicity studies in rats and dogs administered bexarotene daily for 6 months. New cataracts or worsening of previous cataracts occurred in 15 of 79 patients who were monitored with serial slit lamp examinations. Because of the high prevalence and rate of cataract formation in older patient populations, the relationship of TARGRETIN and cataracts cannot be determined in the absence of an appropriate control group. Patients treated with TARGRETIN who experience visual difficulties should have an appropriate ophthalmologic evaluation.



    5.7 Vitamin A Supplementation Hazard



  In clinical studies, patients were advised to limit vitamin A intake to &lt;  15,000 IU/day. Because of the relationship of bexarotene to vitamin A, patients should be advised to limit vitamin A supplements to avoid potential additive toxic effects.



    5.8 Hypoglycemia Risk in Patients with Diabetes Mellitus



  In patients using insulin, agents enhancing insulin secretion (e.g., sulfonylureas), or insulin-sensitizers (e.g., thiazolidinedione class), based on the mechanism of action, TARGRETIN could enhance the action of these agents, resulting in hypoglycemia. Hypoglycemia has not been associated with the use of TARGRETIN as monotherapy.



    5.9 Photosensitivity



  Retinoids as a class have been associated with photosensitivity. In vitro  assays indicate that bexarotene is a potential photosensitizing agent. Phototoxicity manifested as sunburn and skin sensitivity to sunlight occurred in patients who were exposed to direct sunlight while receiving TARGRETIN. Advise patients to minimize exposure to sunlight and artificial ultraviolet light while receiving TARGRETIN.



    5.10 Laboratory Tests



  Before initiating TARGRETIN therapy, obtain a CBC, fasting lipid profile, liver function tests, and a thyroid profile. Fasting triglycerides should be normal or normalized with appropriate intervention prior to therapy. Monitor lab tests during TARGRETIN therapy as described above.



 Hyperlipidemia usually occurs within the initial two to four weeks. Therefore, weekly lipid determinations are recommended during this interval. Subsequently, in patients not hyperlipidemic, determinations can be performed less frequently [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)    ].



 A white blood cell count with differential should be obtained at baseline and periodically during treatment. Baseline liver function tests should be obtained and should be carefully monitored after one, two and four weeks of treatment initiation, and if stable, periodically thereafter during treatment. Baseline thyroid function tests should be obtained and then monitored during treatment as indicated [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  ,  5.4  ,  5.5  ,  5.6  )]  .



    5.11 Drug/Laboratory Test Interactions



  CA125 assay values in patients with ovarian cancer may be increased by TARGRETIN therapy.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
