<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tarka" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  TARKA has been evaluated in over 1,957 subjects and patients. Of these, 541 patients, including 23% elderly patients, participated in U.S. controlled clinical trials, and 251 were studied in foreign controlled clinical trials. In clinical trials with TARKA, no adverse experiences peculiar to this combination drug have been observed. Adverse experiences that have occurred have been limited to those that have been previously reported with verapamil or trandolapril. TARKA has been evaluated for long-term safety in 272 patients treated for 1 year or more. Adverse experiences were usually mild and transient.



 Discontinuation of therapy because of adverse events in U.S. placebo-controlled hypertension studies was required in 2.6% and 1.9% of patients treated with TARKA and placebo, respectively.



 Adverse experiences occurring in 1% or more of the 541 patients in placebo-controlled hypertension trials who were treated with a range of trandolapril (0.5-8 mg) and verapamil (120-240 mg) combinations are shown below.



 ADVERSE EVENTS OCCURRING in &gt;= 1% of TARKA PATIENTS IN U.S. PLACEBO-CONTROLLED TRIALS 
                                     TARKA(N = 541)% Incidence(% Discontinuance)      PLACEBO    (N = 206)% Incidence(% Discontinuance)     
 AV Block First Degree             3.9 (0.2)                           0.5 (0.0)                          
 Bradycardia                       1.8 (0.0)                           0.0 (0.0)                          
 Bronchitis                        1.5 (0.0)                           0.5 (0.0)                          
 Chest Pain                        2.2 (0.0)                           1.0 (0.0)                          
 Constipation                      3.3 (0.0)                           1.0 (0.0)                          
 Cough                             4.6 (0.0)                           2.4 (0.0)                          
 Diarrhea                          1.5 (0.2)                           1.0 (0.0)                          
 Dizziness                         3.1 (0.0)                           1.9 (0.5)                          
 Dyspnea                           1.3 (0.4)                           0.0 (0.0)                          
 Edema                             1.3 (0.0)                           2.4 (0.0)                          
 Fatigue                           2.8 (0.4)                           2.4 (0.0)                          
 Headache(s)  +                    8.9 (0.0)                           9.7 (0.5)                          
 Increased Liver Enzymes*          2.8 (0.2)                           1.0 (0.0)                          
 Nausea                            1.5 (0.2)                           0.5 (0.0)                          
 Pain Extremity(ies)               1.1 (0.2)                           0.5 (0.0)                          
 Pain Back  +                      2.2 (0.0)                           2.4 (0.0)                          
 Pain Joint(s)                     1.7 (0.0)                           1.0 (0.0)                          
 Upper Respiratory Tract Infection(s)  +    5.4 (0.0)                           7.8 (0.0)                          
 Upper Respiratory Tract Congestion  +    2.4 (0.0)                           3.4 (0.0)                          
 *   Also includes increase in SGPT, SGOT, Alkaline Phosphatase+   Incidence of adverse events is higher in Placebo group than TARKA patients   
      Other clinical adverse experiences possibly, probably, or definitely related to drug treatment occurring in 0.3% or more of patients treated with trandolapril/verapamil combinations with or without concomitant diuretic in controlled or uncontrolled trials (N = 990) and less frequent, clinically significant events (in italics) include the following:
 

   Cardiovascular

  Angina, AV block second degree, bundle branch block, edema, flushing, hypotension, myocardial infarction , palpitations, premature ventricular contractions, nonspecific ST-T changes, near syncope, tachycardia.



   Central Nervous System

  Drowsiness, hypesthesia, insomnia, loss of balance, paresthesia, vertigo.



   Dermatologic

  Pruritus, rash.



   Emotional, Mental, Sexual States

  Anxiety, impotence, abnormal mentation.



   Eye, Ear, Nose, Throat

  Epistaxis, tinnitus, upper respiratory tract infection, blurred vision.



   Gastrointestinal

  Diarrhea, dyspepsia, dry mouth, nausea.



   General Body Function

  Chest pain, malaise, weakness.



   Genitourinary

  Endometriosis, hematuria, nocturia, polyuria, proteinuria.



   Hemopoietic

  Decreased leukocytes, decreased neutrophils.



   Musculoskeletal System

  Arthralgias/myalgias, gout (increased uric acid).



   Pulmonary

  Dyspnea.



   Angioedema

  Angioedema has been reported in 3 (0.15%) patients receiving TARKA in U.S. and foreign studies (N = 1,957). Angioedema associated with laryngeal edema may be fatal. If angioedema of the face, extremities, lips, tongue, glottis, and/or larynx occurs, treatment with TARKA should be discontinued and appropriate therapy instituted immediately (see  WARNINGS  ).



   Hypotension

  (See  WARNINGS  .) In hypertensive patients, hypotension occurred in 0.6% and near syncope occurred in 0.1%. Hypotension or syncope was a cause for discontinuation of therapy in 0.4% of hypertensive patients.



   Treatment of Acute Cardiovascular Adverse Reactions

  The frequency of cardiovascular adverse reactions which require therapy is rare, hence, experience with their treatment is limited. Whenever severe hypotension or complete AV block occur following oral administration of TARKA (verapamil component), the appropriate emergency measures should be applied immediately, e.g., intravenously administered isoproterenol HCl, levarterenol bitartrate, atropine (all in the usual doses), or calcium gluconate (10% solution). In patients with hypertrophic cardiomyopathy (IHSS), alpha-adrenergic agents (phenylephrine, metaraminol bitartrate or methoxamine) should be used to maintain blood pressure, and isoproterenol and levarterenol should be avoided. If further support is necessary, inotropic agents (dopamine or dobutamine) may be administered. Actual treatment and dosage should depend on the severity and the clinical situation and the judgment and experience of the treating physician.



   

  Other adverse experiences (in addition to those in table and listed above) that have been reported with the individual components are listed below.



   Verapamil Component

  Cardiovascular

  (See  WARNINGS  .) CHF/pulmonary edema, AV block 3 degrees , atrioventricular dissociation, claudication, purpura (vasculitis), syncope.



   Digestive System

  Gingival hyperplasia. Reversible, (upon discontinuation of verapamil) nonobstructive, paralytic ileus has been infrequently reported in association with the use of verapamil.



   Hemic and Lymphatic

  Ecchymosis or bruising.



   Nervous System

  Cerebrovascular accident, confusion, psychotic symptoms, shakiness, somnolence.



   Skin

  Exanthema, hair loss, hyperkeratosis, maculae, sweating, urticaria, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, erythema multiform.



   Urogenital

  Gynecomastia, galactorrhea/hyperprolactinemia, increased urination, spotty menstruation.



   Trandolapril Component

  Emotional, Mental, Sexual States

  Decreased libido.



   Gastrointestinal

  Pancreatitis.



   Clinical Laboratory Test Findings

  Hematology

  (See  WARNINGS  ). Low white blood cells, low neutrophils, low lymphocytes, low platelets.



   Serum Electrolytes

  Hyperkalemia (see  PRECAUTIONS  ), hyponatremia.



   Renal Function Tests

  Increases in creatinine and blood urea nitrogen levels occurred in 1.1 percent and 0.3 percent, respectively, of patients receiving TARKA with or without hydrochlorothiazide therapy. None of these increases required discontinuation of treatment. Increases in these laboratory values are more likely to occur in patients with renal insufficiency or those pretreated with a diuretic and, based on experience with other ACE inhibitors, would be expected to be especially likely in patients with renal artery stenosis (see  PRECAUTIONS  and  WARNINGS  ).



   Liver Function Tests

  Elevations of liver enzymes (SGOT, SGPT, LDH, and alkaline phosphatase) and/or serum bilirubin occurred. Discontinuation for elevated liver enzymes occurred in 0.9 percent of patients (see  WARNINGS  ).



   Post Marketing Experience

  There has been a single postmarketing report of paralysis (tetraparesis) associated with the combined use of verapamil and colchicine. This may have been caused by colchicine crossing the blood-brain barrier due to CYP3A4 and P-gp inhibition by verapamil. Combined use of verapamil and colchicine is not recommended (see  PRECAUTIONS-Drug Interactions  ).
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY

    WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY  

    *  When pregnancy is detected, discontinue TARKA as soon as possible. 
 *  Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus (see WARNINGS: Fetal Toxicity). 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
