<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tasigna" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6     ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  The following serious adverse reactions can occur with Tasigna and are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the package insert  [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5)]  .



 *  Myelosuppression [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  
 *  QT Prolongation [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  
 *  Sudden Deaths [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]  
 *  Cardiac and Arterial Vascular Occlusive Events [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)]  
 *  Pancreatitis and Elevated Serum Lipase [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)]  
 *  Hepatotoxicity [see Warnings and Precautions (5.6)]  
 *  Electrolyte Abnormalities [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.7)]  
 *  Hemorrhage [see Warnings and Precautions (5.12)]  
 *  Fluid Retention [see Warnings and Precautions (5.17)]  
      EXCERPT:   The most commonly reported non-hematologic adverse reactions (&gt;=20% in patients with newly diagnosed Ph+ CML-CP, resistant or intolerant Ph+ CML-CP, or resistant or intolerant Ph+ CML-AP) were nausea, rash, headache, fatigue, pruritus, vomiting, diarrhea, cough, constipation, arthralgia, nasopharyngitis, pyrexia, and night sweats. Hematologic adverse drug reactions include myelosuppression: thrombocytopenia, neutropenia and anemia. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact NOVARTIS Pharmaceuticals Corporation at 1-888-669-6682 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1     Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   In Patients with Newly Diagnosed Ph+ CML-CP  



 The data below reflect exposure to Tasigna from a randomized trial in patients with newly diagnosed Ph+ CML in chronic phase treated at the recommended dose of 300 mg twice-daily (n=279). The median time on treatment in the nilotinib 300 mg twice-daily group was 61 months (range 0.1 to 71 months). The median actual dose intensity was 593 mg/day in the nilotinib 300 mg twice-daily group.



 The most common (&gt;10%) non-hematologic adverse drug reactions were rash, pruritus, headache, nausea, fatigue, alopecia, myalgia, and upper abdominal pain. Constipation, diarrhea, dry skin, muscle spasms, arthralgia, abdominal pain, peripheral edema, vomiting, and asthenia were observed less commonly (&lt;=10% and &gt;5%) and have been of mild to moderate severity, manageable and generally did not require dose reduction.



 Increase in QTcF &gt;60 msec from baseline was observed in 1 patient (0.4%) in the 300 mg twice-daily treatment group. No patient had an absolute QTcF of &gt;500 msec while on study drug.



 The most common hematologic adverse drug reactions (all grades) were myelosuppression including: thrombocytopenia (18%), neutropenia (15%) and anemia (8%). See Table 7 for Grade 3/4 laboratory abnormalities.



 Discontinuation due to adverse reactions, regardless of relationship to study drug, was observed in 10% of patients.



   In Patients with Resistant or Intolerant Ph+ CML-CP and CML-AP  



 In the single open-label multicenter clinical trial, a total of 458 patients with Ph+ CML-CP and CML-AP resistant to or intolerant to at least one prior therapy including imatinib were treated (CML-CP=321; CML-AP=137) at the recommended dose of 400 mg twice-daily.



 The median duration of exposure in days for CML-CP and CML-AP patients is 561 (range 1 to 1096) and 264 (range 2 to 1160), respectively. The median dose intensity for patients with CML-CP and CML-AP is 789 mg/day (range 151 to 1110) and 780 mg/day (range 150 to 1149), respectively and corresponded to the planned 400 mg twice-daily dosing.



 The median cumulative duration in days of dose interruptions for the CML-CP patients was 20 (range 1 to 345), and the median duration in days of dose interruptions for the CML-AP patients was 23 (range 1 to 234).



 In patients with CML-CP, the most commonly reported non-hematologic adverse drug reactions (&gt;=10%) were rash, pruritus, nausea, fatigue, headache, constipation, diarrhea, vomiting and myalgia. The common serious drug-related adverse reactions (&gt;=1% and &lt;10%) were thrombocytopenia, neutropenia and anemia.



 In patients with CML-AP, the most commonly reported non-hematologic adverse drug reactions (&gt;=10%) were rash, pruritus and fatigue. The common serious adverse drug reactions (&gt;=1% and &lt;10%) were thrombocytopenia, neutropenia, febrile neutropenia, pneumonia, leukopenia, intracranial hemorrhage, elevated lipase and pyrexia.



 Sudden deaths and QT prolongation were reported. The maximum mean QTcF change from baseline at steady-state was 10 msec. Increase in QTcF &gt;60 msec from baseline was observed in 4.1% of the patients and QTcF of &gt;500 msec was observed in 4 patients (&lt;1%)  [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.2, 5.3), Clinical Pharmacology (12.6)]  .



 Discontinuation due to adverse drug reactions was observed in 16% of CML-CP and 10% of CML-AP patients.



   Most Frequently Reported Adverse Reactions  



 Tables 5 and 6 show the percentage of patients experiencing non-hematologic adverse reactions (excluding laboratory abnormalities) regardless of relationship to study drug. Adverse reactions reported in greater than 10% of patients who received at least 1 dose of Tasigna are listed.



 Table 5: Most Frequently Reported Non-hematologic Adverse Reactions (Regardless of Relationship to Study Drug) in Patients with Newly Diagnosed Ph+ CML-CP (&gt;=10% in Tasigna 300 mg Twice-Daily or Imatinib 400 mg Once-Daily Groups) 60-Month Analysisa 
   a  Excluding laboratory abnormalities  b  NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events, Version 3.0   
  
                    Patients with Newly Diagnosed Ph+ CML-CP     
                                    
                    TASIGNA    300 mg    twice-daily      Imatinib    400 mg    once-daily      TASIGNA    300 mg    twice-daily      Imatinib    400 mg    once-daily     
                    N=279            N=280            N=279            N=280           
   Body System and Preferred Term      All Grades    (%)      CTC Grades      b      3/4 (%)     
 Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders  Rash             38               19               &lt;1               2                 
                  Pruritus         21               7                &lt;1               0                 
                  Alopecia         13               7                0                0                 
                  Dry skin         12               6                0                0                 
 Gastrointestinal disorders  Nausea           22               41               2                2                 
                  Constipation     20               8                &lt;1               0                 
                  Diarrhea         19               46               1                4                 
                  Vomiting         15               27               &lt;1               &lt;1                
                  Abdominal pain upper  18               14               1                &lt;1                
                  Abdominal pain   15               12               2                0                 
                  Dyspepsia        10               12               0                0                 
 Nervous system disorders  Headache         32               23               3                &lt;1                
                  Dizziness        12               11               &lt;1               &lt;1                
 General disorders and administration site conditions  Fatigue          23               20               1                1                 
                  Pyrexia          14               13               &lt;1               0                 
                  Asthenia         14               12               &lt;1               0                 
                  Peripheral edema  9                20               &lt;1               0                 
                  Face edema       &lt;1               14               0                &lt;1                
 Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders  Myalgia          19               19               &lt;1               &lt;1                
                  Arthralgia       22               17               &lt;1               &lt;1                
                  Muscle spasms    12               34               0                1                 
                  Pain in extremity  15               16               &lt;1               &lt;1                
                  Back pain        19               17               1                1                 
 Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders  Cough            17               13               0                0                 
                  Oropharyngeal pain  12               6                0                0                 
                  Dyspnea          11               6                2                &lt;1                
 Infections and infestations  Nasopharyngitis  27               21               0                0                 
                  Upper respiratory tract infection  17               14               &lt;1               0                 
                  Influenza        13               9                0                0                 
                  Gastroenteritis  7                10               0                &lt;1                
 Eye disorders    Eyelid edema     1                19               0                &lt;1                
                  Periorbital edema  &lt;1               15               0                0                 
 Psychiatric disorders  Insomnia         11               9                0                0                 
 Vascular disorder  Hypertension     10               4                1                &lt;1                
           Table 6: Most Frequently Reported Non-hematologic Adverse Reactions in Patients with Resistant or Intolerant Ph+ CML Receiving Tasigna 400 mg Twice-Daily (Regardless of Relationship to Study Drug) (&gt;=10% in any Group) 24-Month Analysisa 
   a  Excluding laboratory abnormalities  b  NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events, Version 3.0  c  Also includes preferred term anorexia   
  
   Body System and Preferred Term      CML-CP           CML-AP          
                    N=321            N=    137       
                    All Grades (%)      CTC Grades      b      3/4 (%)      All Grades (%)      CTC Grades      b      3/4 (%)     
 Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders  Rash             36               2                29               0                 
                  Pruritus         32               &lt;1               20               0                 
                  Night sweat      12               &lt;1               27               0                 
                  Alopecia         11               0                12               0                 
 Gastrointestinal disorders  Nausea           37               1                22               &lt;1                
                  Constipation     26               &lt;1               19               0                 
                  Diarrhea         28               3                24               2                 
                  Vomiting         29               &lt;1               13               0                 
                  Abdominal pain   15               2                16               3                 
                  Abdominal pain upper  14               &lt;1               12               &lt;1                
                  Dyspepsia        10               &lt;1               4                0                 
 Nervous system disorders  Headache         35               2                20               1                 
 General disorders and administration site conditions  Fatigue          32               3                23               &lt;1                
                  Pyrexia          22               &lt;1               28               2                 
                  Asthenia         16               0                14               1                 
                  Peripheral edema  15               &lt;1               12               0                 
 Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders  Myalgia          19               2                16               &lt;1                
                  Arthralgia       26               2                16               0                 
                  Muscle spasms    13               &lt;1               15               0                 
                  Bone pain        14               &lt;1               15               2                 
                  Pain in extremity  20               2                18               1                 
                  Back pain        17               2                15               &lt;1                
                  Musculoskeletal pain  11               &lt;1               12               1                 
 Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders  Cough            27               &lt;1               18               0                 
                  Dyspnea          15               2                9                2                 
                  Oropharyngeal pain  11               0                7                0                 
 Infections and infestations  Nasopharyngitis  24               &lt;1               15               0                 
                  Upper respiratory tract infection  12               0                10               0                 
 Metabolism and nutrition disorders  Decreased appetite  c    15               &lt;1               17               &lt;1                
 Psychiatric disorders  Insomnia         12               1                7                0                 
 Vascular disorders  Hypertension     10               2                11               &lt;1                
              Laboratory Abnormalities  
 

 Table 7 shows the percentage of patients experiencing treatment-emergent Grade 3/4 laboratory abnormalities in patients who received at least one dose of Tasigna.



 Table 7: Percent Incidence of Clinically Relevant Grade 3/4* Laboratory Abnormalities 
   *  NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events, version 3.0  1  CML-CP: Thrombocytopenia: 12% were Grade 3, 18% were Grade 4  2  CML-CP: Neutropenia: 16% were Grade 3, 15% were Grade 4  3  CML-AP: Thrombocytopenia: 11% were Grade 3, 32% were Grade 4  4  CML-AP: Neutropenia: 16% were Grade 3, 26% were Grade 4   
  
                    Patient Population     
                    Newly    D    iagnosed Ph+ CML-CP      Resistant or Intolerant Ph+     
                                     CML-CP           CML-AP          
                    TASIGNA 300 mg    twice-daily    N=279    (%)      Imatinib    400 mg    once-daily    N=280    (%)      TASIGNA 400 mg    twice-daily    N=3    21    (%)      TASIGNA 400 mg    twice-daily    N=1    37    (%)     
   Hematologic Parameters                                                                         
 Thrombocytopenia  10               9                30  1            42  3             
 Neutropenia      12               22               31  2            42  4             
 Anemia           4                6                11               27                
   Biochemistry Parameters                                                                         
 Elevated lipase  9                4                18               18                
 Hyperglycemia    7                &lt;1               12               6                 
 Hypophosphatemia  8                10               17               15                
 Elevated bilirubin (total)  4                &lt;1               7                9                 
 Elevated SGPT (ALT)  4                3                4                4                 
 Hyperkalemia     2                1                6                4                 
 Hyponatremia     1                &lt;1               7                7                 
 Hypokalemia      &lt;1               2                2                9                 
 Elevated SGOT (AST)  1                1                3                2                 
 Decreased albumin  0                &lt;1               4                3                 
 Hypocalcemia     &lt;1               &lt;1               2                5                 
 Elevated alkaline phosphatase  0                &lt;1               &lt;1               1                 
 Elevated creatinine  0                &lt;1               &lt;1               &lt;1                
           Elevated total cholesterol (all grades) occurred in 28% (Tasigna 300 mg bid) and 4% (imatinib). Elevated triglycerides (all grades) occurred in12% and 8% of patients in the Tasigna and imatinib arms, respectively. Hyperglycemia (all grades) occurred in 50% and 31% of patients in the Tasigna and imatinib arms, respectively.
 

 Most common biochemistry laboratory abnormalities (all grades) were alanine aminotransferase increased (72%), blood bilirubin increased (59%), aspartate aminotransferase increased (47%), lipase increased (28%), blood glucose increased (50%), blood cholesterol increased (28%), and blood triglyceride increased (12%).



   6.2     Additional Data from Clinical Trials

  The following adverse drug reactions were reported in patients in the Tasigna clinical studies at the recommended doses. These adverse drug reactions are ranked under a heading of frequency, the most frequent first using the following convention: common (&gt;=1% and &lt;10%), uncommon (&gt;=0.1% and &lt;1%), and unknown frequency (single events). For laboratory abnormalities, very common events (&gt;=10%), which were not included in Tables 5 and 6, are also reported. These adverse reactions are included based on clinical relevance and ranked in order of decreasing seriousness within each category, obtained from 2 clinical studies:



 *  Newly diagnosed Ph+ CML-CP 60 month analysis and, 
 *  Resistant or intolerant Ph+ CML-CP and CMP-AP 24 months' analysis. 
      Infections and Infestations:   Common: folliculitis. Uncommon: pneumonia, bronchitis, urinary tract infection, candidiasis (including oral candidiasis). Unknown frequency: sepsis, subcutaneous abscess, anal abscess, furuncle, tinea pedis.
 

   Neoplasms Benign, Malignant, and Unspecified  : Common: skin papilloma. Unknown frequency: oral papilloma, paraproteinemia.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  Common: leukopenia, eosinophilia, febrile neutropenia, pancytopenia, lymphopenia. Unknown frequency: thrombocythemia, leukocytosis.



   Immune System Disorders:  Unknown frequency: hypersensitivity.



   Endocrine Disorders:  Uncommon: hyperthyroidism, hypothyroidism. Unknown frequency: hyperparathyroidism secondary, thyroiditis.



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  Very Common: hypophosphatemia. Common: electrolyte imbalance (including hypomagnesemia, hyperkalemia, hypokalemia, hyponatremia, hypocalcemia, hypercalcemia, hyperphosphatemia), diabetes mellitus, hyperglycemia, hypercholesterolemia, hyperlipidemia, hypertriglyceridemia. Uncommon: gout, dehydration, increased appetite. Unknown frequency: hyperuricemia, hypoglycemia.



   Psychiatric Disorders:  Common: depression, anxiety. Unknown frequency: disorientation, confusional state, amnesia, dysphoria.



   Nervous System Disorders:  Common: peripheral neuropathy, hypoesthesia, paresthesia. Uncommon: intracranial hemorrhage, ischemic stroke, transient ischemic attack, cerebral infarction, migraine, loss of consciousness (including syncope), tremor, disturbance in attention, hyperesthesia. Unknown frequency: basilar artery stenosis, brain edema, optic neuritis, lethargy, dysesthesia, restless legs syndrome.



   Eye Disorders:   Common: eye hemorrhage, eye pruritus, conjunctivitis, dry eye (including xerophthalmia). Uncommon: vision impairment, vision blurred, visual acuity reduced, photopsia, hyperemia (scleral, conjunctival, ocular), eye irritation, conjunctival hemorrhage. Unknown frequency: papilloedema, diplopia, photophobia, eye swelling, blepharitis, eye pain, chorioretinopathy, conjunctivitis allergic, ocular surface disease.



   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders:  Common: vertigo. Unknown frequency: hearing impaired, ear pain, tinnitus.



   Cardiac Disorders:  Common: angina pectoris, arrhythmia (including atrioventricular block, cardiac flutter, extrasystoles, atrial fibrillation, tachycardia, bradycardia), palpitations, electrocardiogram QT prolonged. Uncommon: cardiac failure, myocardial infarction, coronary artery disease, cardiac murmur, coronary artery stenosis, myocardial ischemia, pericardial effusion, cyanosis. Unknown frequency: ventricular dysfunction, pericarditis, ejection fraction decrease.



   Vascular Disorders:  Common: flushing. Uncommon: hypertensive crisis, peripheral arterial occlusive disease, intermittent claudication, arterial stenosis limb, hematoma, arteriosclerosis. Unknown frequency: shock hemorrhagic, hypotension, thrombosis, peripheral artery stenosis.



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  Common: dyspnea exertional, epistaxis, dysphonia. Uncommon: pulmonary edema, pleural effusion, interstitial lung disease, pleuritic pain, pleurisy, pharyngolaryngeal pain, throat irritation. Unknown frequency: pulmonary hypertension, wheezing.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  Common: pancreatitis, abdominal discomfort, abdominal distension, dysgeusia, flatulence. Uncommon: gastrointestinal hemorrhage, melena, mouth ulceration, gastroesophageal reflux, stomatitis, esophageal pain, dry mouth, gastritis, sensitivity of teeth. Unknown frequency: gastrointestinal ulcer perforation, retroperitoneal hemorrhage, hematemesis, gastric ulcer, esophagitis ulcerative, subileus, enterocolitis, hemorrhoids, hiatus hernia, rectal hemorrhage, gingivitis.



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:  Very Common: hyperbilirubinemia. Common: hepatic function abnormal. Uncommon: hepatotoxicity, toxic hepatitis, jaundice. Unknown frequency: cholestasis, hepatomegaly.



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  Common: eczema, urticaria, erythema, hyperhidrosis, contusion, acne, dermatitis (including allergic, exfoliative and acneiform). Uncommon: exfoliative rash, drug eruption, pain of skin, ecchymosis. Unknown frequency: psoriasis, erythema multiforme, erythema nodosum, skin ulcer, palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia syndrome, petechiae, photosensitivity, blister, dermal cyst, sebaceous hyperplasia, skin atrophy, skin discoloration, skin exfoliation, skin hyperpigmentation, skin hypertrophy, hyperkeratosis.



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  Common: bone pain, musculoskeletal chest pain, musculoskeletal pain, back pain, neck pain, flank pain, muscular weakness. Uncommon: musculoskeletal stiffness, joint swelling. Unknown frequency: arthritis.



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:   Common: pollakiuria. Uncommon: dysuria, micturition urgency, nocturia. Unknown frequency: renal failure, hematuria, urinary incontinence, chromaturia.



   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders:  Uncommon: breast pain, gynecomastia, erectile dysfunction. Unknown frequency: breast induration, menorrhagia, nipple swelling.



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  Common: pyrexia, chest pain (including non-cardiac chest pain), pain, chest discomfort, malaise. Uncommon: gravitational edema, influenza-like illness, chills, feeling body temperature change (including feeling hot, feeling cold). Unknown frequency: localized edema.



   Investigations:  Very Common: alanine aminotransferase increased, aspartate aminotransferase increased, lipase increased, lipoprotein cholesterol (including very low density and high density) increased, total cholesterol increased, blood triglycerides increased. Common: hemoglobin decreased, blood amylase increased, gamma-glutamyltransferase increased, blood creatinine phosphokinase increased, blood alkaline phosphatase increased, weight decreased, weight increased, globulins decreased. Uncommon: blood lactate dehydrogenase increased, blood urea increased. Unknown frequency: troponin increased, blood bilirubin unconjugated increased, insulin C-peptide decreased, blood parathyroid hormone increased.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: QT PROLONGATION AND SUDDEN DEATHS 

    WARNING: QT PROLONGATION AND SUDDEN DEATHS   

    *  Tasigna prolongs the QT interval. Prior to Tasigna administration and periodically, monitor for hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia and correct deficiencies (5.2). Obtain ECGs to monitor the QTc at baseline, seven days after initiation, and periodically thereafter, and following any dose adjustments (5.2, 5.3, 5.7, 5.15). 
 *  Sudden deaths have been reported in patients receiving nilotinib (5.3). Do not administer Tasigna to patients with hypokalemia, hypomagnesemia, or long QT syndrome (4, 5.2). 
 *  Avoid use of concomitant drugs known to prolong the QT interval and strong CYP3A4 inhibitors (5.8). 
 *  Avoid food 2 hours before and 1 hour after taking the dose (5.9). 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING: QT PROLONGATION AND SUDDEN DEATHS  
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Tasigna prolongs the QT interval. Prior to Tasigna administration and periodically, monitor for hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia and correct deficiencies (5.2). Obtain ECGs to monitor the QTc at baseline, seven days after initiation, and periodically thereafter, and following any dose adjustments (5.2, 5.3, 5.7, 5.15). 
 *  Sudden deaths have been reported in patients receiving nilotinib (5.3). Do not administer Tasigna to patients with hypokalemia, hypomagnesemia, or long QT syndrome (4, 5.2). 
 *  Avoid use of concomitant drugs known to prolong the QT interval and strong CYP3A4 inhibitors (5.8). 
 *  Avoid food 2 hours before and 1 hour after taking the dose (5.9). 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">     5     WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *  Myelosuppression: Associated with neutropenia, thrombocytopenia and anemia. CBC should be done every 2 weeks for the first 2 months, then monthly. Reversible by withholding dose. Dose reduction may be required. (  5.1  ) 
 *  QT Prolongation: Tasigna prolongs the QT interval. Correct hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia prior to administration and monitor periodically. (  5.2  ) Avoid drugs known to prolong the QT interval and strong CYP3A4 inhibitors. (  5.8  )  Use with caution in patients with hepatic impairment (  5.10  ). Obtain ECGs at baseline, seven days after initiation, and periodically thereafter, as well as following any dose adjustments. (  5.2  ,  5.3  ,  5.7  ,  5.14  ) 
 *  Sudden deaths: Sudden deaths have been reported in patients with resistant or intolerant Ph+ CML receiving Tasigna. Ventricular repolarization abnormalities may have contributed to their occurrence. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Cardiac and Arterial Vascular Occlusive Events: Cardiovascular events including ischemic heart disease, peripheral arterial occlusive disease and ischemic cerebrovascular events have been reported in patients with newly diagnosed Ph+ CML receiving Tasigna. Cardiovascular status should be evaluated and cardiovascular risk factors monitored and managed during Tasigna therapy. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Pancreatitis and elevated serum lipase: Monitor serum lipase monthly or as clinically indicated. In case lipase elevations are accompanied by abdominal symptoms, interrupt doses and consider appropriate diagnostics to exclude pancreatitis. (  5.5  )  
 *  Hepatotoxicity: Tasigna may result in elevations in bilirubin, AST/ALT, and alkaline phosphatase. Monitor hepatic function tests monthly or as clinically indicated. (  5.6  )  
 *  Electrolyte abnormalities: Tasigna can cause hypophosphatemia, hypokalemia, hyperkalemia, hypocalcemia, and hyponatremia. Correct electrolyte abnormalities prior to initiating Tasigna and monitor periodically during therapy. (  5.7  ,  5.15  ) 
 *  Hepatic impairment: Tasigna exposure is increased in patients with impaired hepatic function (at baseline). A dose reduction is recommended in these patients and QT interval should be monitored closely. (  5.10  ) 
 *  Tumor lysis syndrome: Tumor lysis syndrome cases have been reported in Tasigna treated patients with resistant or intolerant CML. Due to potential for tumor lysis syndrome, maintain adequate hydration and correct uric acid levels prior to initiating therapy with Tasigna. (  5.11  ) 
 *  Hemorrhage: Hemorrhage from various sites was reported in patients with newly diagnosed CML and observed in the postmarketing reports of patients receiving Tasigna therapy. (  5.12  ) 
 *  Drug interactions: Avoid concomitant use of strong inhibitors or inducers of CYP3A4. If patients must be coadministered a strong CYP3A4 inhibitor, dose reduction should be considered and the QT interval should be monitored closely. (  5.8  )  
 *  Food effects: Food increases blood levels of Tasigna. Avoid food 2 hours before and 1 hour after a dose. (  5.9  ) 
 *  Total gastrectomy: More frequent follow-up of these patients should be considered. If necessary, dose increase may be considered. (  5.13  ) 
 *  Embryo-fetal toxicity: Fetal harm can occur when administered to a pregnant woman. Women should be advised not to become pregnant when taking Tasigna. (  5.16  ) 
 *  Fluid retention: Pericardial effusion, pleural effusion, and severe fluid retention have occurred in patients receiving Tasigna. Monitor patients for signs and symptoms such as unexpected rapid weight gain, swelling, and shortness of breath. (  5.17  ) 
    
 

   5.1     Myelosuppression



  Treatment with Tasigna can cause Grade 3/4 thrombocytopenia, neutropenia and anemia .  Perform complete blood counts every 2 weeks for the first 2 months and then monthly thereafter, or as clinically indicated. Myelosuppression was generally reversible and usually managed by withholding Tasigna temporarily or dose reduction [see Dosage and Administration (2.2)]  .



    5.2     QT Prolongation



  Tasigna has been shown to prolong cardiac ventricular repolarization as measured by the QT interval on the surface ECG in a concentration-dependent manner [see Adverse Reactions (6.1), Clinical Pharmacology (12.6)].   Prolongation of the QT interval can result in a type of ventricular tachycardia called torsade de pointes, which may result in syncope, seizure, and/or death. ECGs should be performed at baseline, 7 days after initiation of Tasigna, and periodically as clinically indicated and following dose adjustments [see Warnings and Precautions (5.15)]  .



 Tasigna should not be used in patients who have hypokalemia, hypomagnesemia or long QT syndrome. Before initiating Tasigna and periodically, test electrolyte, calcium and magnesium blood levels. Hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia must be corrected prior to initiating Tasigna and these electrolytes should be monitored periodically during therapy [see Warnings and Precautions (5.15)]  .



 Significant prolongation of the QT interval may occur when Tasigna is inappropriately taken with food and/or strong CYP3A4 inhibitors and/or medicinal products with a known potential to prolong QT. Therefore, coadministration with food must be avoided and concomitant use with strong CYP3A4 inhibitors and/or medicinal products with a known potential to prolong QT should be avoided [see Warnings and Precautions (5.8, 5.9)]  . The presence of hypokalemia and hypomagnesemia may further prolong the QT interval [see Warnings and Precautions (5.7, 5.15)]  .



    5.3     Sudden Deaths



  Sudden deaths have been reported in 0.3% of patients with CML treated with nilotinib in clinical studies of 5,661 patients. The relative early occurrence of some of these deaths relative to the initiation of nilotinib suggests the possibility that ventricular repolarization abnormalities may have contributed to their occurrence.



    5.4     Cardiac and Arterial Vascular Occlusive Events



   Cardiovascular events, including arterial vascular occlusive events, were reported in a randomized, clinical trial in newly diagnosed CML patients and observed in the postmarketing reports of patients receiving nilotinib therapy. With a median time on therapy of 60 months in the clinical trial, cardiovascular events, including arterial vascular occlusive events, occurred in 9.3% and 15.2% of patients in the Tasigna 300 and 400 mg bid arms, respectively, and in 3.2% in the imatinib arm. These included cases of cardiovascular events including ischemic heart disease-related cardiac events (5.0% and 9.4% in the Tasigna 300 mg and 400 mg bid arms respectively, and 2.5% in the imatinib arm), peripheral arterial occlusive disease (3.6% and 2.9% in the Tasigna 300 mg and 400 mg bid arms respectively, and 0% in the imatinib arm), and ischemic cerebrovascular events (1.4% and 3.2% in the Tasigna 300 mg and 400 mg bid arms respectively, and 0.7% in the imatinib arm). If acute signs or symptoms of cardiovascular events occur, advise patients to seek immediate medical attention. The cardiovascular status of patients should be evaluated and cardiovascular risk factors should be monitored and actively managed during Tasigna therapy according to standard guidelines [see Dosage and Administration (2.2)]  .  



    5.5     Pancreatitis and Elevated Serum Lipase



  Tasigna can cause increases in serum lipase. Patients with a previous history of pancreatitis may be at greater risk of elevated serum lipase. If lipase elevations are accompanied by abdominal symptoms, interrupt dosing and consider appropriate diagnostics to exclude pancreatitis. Test serum lipase levels monthly or as clinically indicated.



    5.6     Hepatotoxicity



  Tasigna may result in hepatotoxicity as measured by elevations in bilirubin, AST/ALT, and alkaline phosphatase. Monitor hepatic function tests monthly or as clinically indicated [see Warnings and Precautions (5.15)]  .



    5.7     Electrolyte Abnormalities



  The use of Tasigna can cause hypophosphatemia, hypokalemia, hyperkalemia, hypocalcemia, and hyponatremia. Correct electrolyte abnormalities prior to initiating Tasigna and during therapy. Monitor these electrolytes periodically during therapy [see Warnings and Precautions (5.15)]  .



    5.8     Drug Interactions



  Avoid administration of Tasigna with agents that may increase nilotinib exposure (e.g., strong CYP3A4 inhibitors) or anti-arrhythmic drugs (including, but not limited to amiodarone, disopyramide, procainamide, quinidine and sotalol) and other drugs that may prolong QT interval (including, but not limited to chloroquine, clarithromycin, haloperidol, methadone, moxifloxacin and pimozide). Should treatment with any of these agents be required, interrupt therapy with Tasigna. If interruption of treatment with Tasigna is not possible, patients who require treatment with a drug that prolongs QT or strongly inhibits CYP3A4 should be closely monitored for prolongation of the QT interval [see Boxed Warning, Dosage and Administration (2.2), Drug Interactions (7.2)]  .



    5.9     Food Effects



  The bioavailability of nilotinib is increased with food, thus Tasigna must not be taken with food. No food should be consumed for at least 2 hours before and for at least 1 hour after the dose is taken. Also avoid grapefruit products and other foods that are known to inhibit CYP3A4 [see Boxed Warning, Drug Interactions (7.2) and Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)]  .



    5.10     Hepatic Impairment



  Nilotinib exposure is increased in patients with impaired hepatic function. Use a lower starting dose for patients with mild to severe hepatic impairment (at baseline) and monitor the QT interval frequently [see Dosage and Administration (2.2) and Use in Specific Populations (8.7)]  .



    5.11     Tumor Lysis Syndrome



  Tumor lysis syndrome cases have been reported in Tasigna treated patients with resistant or intolerant CML. Malignant disease progression, high WBC counts and/or dehydration were present in the majority of these cases. Due to potential for tumor lysis syndrome, maintain adequate hydration and correct uric acid levels prior to initiating therapy with Tasigna.



    5.12     Hemorrhage



   In a randomized trial in patients with newly diagnosed Ph+ CML in chronic phase comparing Tasigna and imatinib, Grade 3 or 4 hemorrhage occurred in 1.1% of patients in the Tasigna 300 mg bid arm, in 1.8% patients in the Tasigna 400 mg bid arm, and 0.4% of patients in the imatinib arm. GI hemorrhage occurred in 2.9% and 5.1% of patients in the Tasigna 300 mg bid and 400 mg bid arms and in 1.4% of patients in the imatinib arm, respectively. Grade 3 or 4 events occurred in 0.7% and 1.4% of patients in the Tasigna 300 mg bid and 400 mg bid arms, respectively, and in no patients in the imatinib arm.  



    5.13     Total Gastrectomy



  Since the exposure of nilotinib is reduced in patients with total gastrectomy, perform more frequent monitoring of these patients. Consider dose increase or alternative therapy in patients with total gastrectomy [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)]  .



    5.14     Lactose



  Since the capsules contain lactose, Tasigna is not recommended for patients with rare hereditary problems of galactose intolerance, severe lactase deficiency with a severe degree of intolerance to lactose-containing products, or of glucose-galactose malabsorption.



    5.15     Monitoring Laboratory Tests



   Complete blood counts should be performed every 2 weeks for the first 2 months and then monthly thereafter. Perform chemistry panels, including electrolytes, calcium, magnesium, liver enzymes, lipid profile, and glucose prior to therapy and periodically. ECGs should be obtained at baseline, 7 days after initiation and periodically thereafter, as well as following dose adjustments [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  . Monitor lipid profiles and glucose periodically during the first year of Tasigna therapy and at least yearly during chronic therapy. Should treatment with any HMG-CoA reductase inhibitor (a lipid lowering agent) be needed to treat lipid elevations, evaluate the potential for a drug-drug interaction before initiating therapy as certain HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors are metabolized by the CYP3A4 pathway [see Drug Interactions (7.1)]  . Assess glucose levels before initiating treatment with Tasigna and monitor during treatment as clinically indicated. If test results warrant therapy, physician should follow their local standards of practice and treatment guidelines.  



    5.16     Embryo-Fetal Toxicity



  There are no adequate and well controlled studies of Tasigna in pregnant women. However, Tasigna may cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Nilotinib caused embryo-fetal toxicities in animals at maternal exposures that were lower than the expected human exposure at the recommended doses of nilotinib. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus. Women of child-bearing potential should avoid becoming pregnant while taking Tasigna [see Use in Specific Populations (8.1)]  .



    5.17     Fluid Retention



   In the randomized trial in patients with newly diagnosed Ph+ CML in chronic phase, severe (Grade 3 or 4) fluid retention occurred in 3.9% and 2.9% of patients receiving Tasigna 300 mg bid and 400 mg bid, respectively, and in 2.5% of patients receiving imatinib. Effusions (including pleural effusion, pericardial effusion, ascites) or pulmonary edema, were observed in 2.2% and 1.1% of patients receiving Tasigna 300 mg bid and 400 mg bid, respectively, and in 2.1% of patients receiving imatinib. Effusions were severe (Grade 3 or 4) in 0.7% and 0.4% of patients receiving Tasigna 300 mg bid and 400 mg bid, respectively, and in no patients receiving imatinib. Similar events were also observed in postmarketing reports. Monitor patients for signs of severe fluid retention (e.g., unexpected rapid weight gain or swelling) and for symptoms of respiratory or cardiac compromise (e.g., shortness of breath) during Tasigna treatment; evaluate etiology and treat patients accordingly.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
