<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tasmar" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

    Cases of severe hepatocellular injury, including fulminant liver failure resulting in death, have been reported in postmarketing use. As of May 2005, 3 cases of fatal fulminant hepatic failure have been reported from more than 40,000 patient years of worldwide use. This incidence may be 10- to 100-fold higher than the background incidence in the general population. All 3 cases were reported within the first six months of initiation of treatment with TASMAR. Analysis of the laboratory monitoring data in over 3,400 TASMAR-treated patients participating in clinical trials indicated that increases in SGPT/ALT or SGOT/AST, when present, generally occurred within the first 6 months of treatment with TASMAR.  



 The imprecision of the estimated increase is due to uncertainties about the base rate and the actual number of cases occurring in association with TASMAR. The incidence of idiopathic potentially fatal fulminant hepatic failure (i.e., not due to viral hepatitis or alcohol) is low. One estimate, based upon transplant registry data, is approximately 3/1,000,000 patients per year in the United States. Whether this estimate is an appropriate basis for estimating the increased risk of liver failure among TASMAR users is uncertain. TASMAR users, for example, differ in age and general health status from candidates for liver transplantation. Similarly, underreporting of cases may lead to significant underestimation of the increased risk associated with the use of TASMAR.



 During the premarketing development of tolcapone, two distinct patient populations were studied, patients with end-of-dose wearing-off phenomena and patients with stable responses to levodopa therapy. All patients received concomitant treatment with levodopa preparations, however, and were similar in other clinical aspects. Adverse reactions are shown for these two populations combined.



 The most commonly observed adverse reactions in the double-blind, placebo-controlled trials (N=892), with a difference in incidence (TASMAR minus Placebo) of at least 5% or greater in the 100 mg or 200 mg TASMAR- treated groups compared to placebo, were dyskinesia, nausea, diarrhea, anorexia, sleep disorder, vomiting, urine discoloration, somnolence, hallucination, dystonia, and sweating.



 Approximately 16% of the 592 patients who participated in the double-blind, placebo-controlled trials discontinued treatment due to adverse reactions compared to 10% of the 298 patients who received placebo. Diarrhea was by far the most frequent cause of discontinuation (approximately 6% in tolcapone patients vs. 1% on placebo).



   Adverse Reaction Incidence in Controlled Clinical Studies

  Table 4 lists treatment emergent adverse reactions that occurred in at least 1% of patients treated with tolcapone participating in the double-blind, placebo-controlled studies and were numerically more common in at least one of the tolcapone groups. In these studies, either tolcapone or placebo was added to levodopa/carbidopa (or benserazide).



 The prescriber should be aware that these figures cannot be used to predict the incidence of adverse reactions in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors differ from those that prevailed in the clinical studies. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be compared with figures obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatments, uses, and investigators. However, the cited figures do provide the prescriber with some basis for estimating the relative contribution of drug and nondrug factors to the adverse reactions incidence rate in the population studied.



 Table 4. Summary of Patients With Adverse Reactions After Start of Trial Drug Administration (At Least 1% in TASMAR Group and at Least One TASMAR Dose Group greater than Placebo) 
                                             Placebo               Tolcapone tid        
                                                                   100 mg                200 mg               
                                             N = 298               N = 296               N = 298              
   Adverse Reactions                         (%)                   (%)                   (%)                  
  
  Dyskinesia                                20                    42                    51                    
  Nausea                                    18                    30                    35                    
  Sleep Disorder                            18                    24                    25                    
  Dystonia                                  17                    19                    22                    
  Dreaming Excessive                        17                    21                    16                    
  Anorexia                                  13                    19                    23                    
  Cramps Muscle                             17                    17                    18                    
  Orthostatic Complaints                    14                    17                    17                    
  Somnolence                                13                    18                    14                    
  Diarrhea                                  8                     16                    18                    
  Confusion                                 9                     11                    10                    
  Dizziness                                 10                    13                    6                     
  Headache                                  7                     10                    11                    
  Hallucination                             5                     8                     10                    
  Vomiting                                  4                     8                     10                    
  Constipation                              5                     6                     8                     
  Fatigue                                   6                     7                     3                     
  Upper Respiratory Tract Infection         3                     5                     7                     
  Falling                                   4                     4                     6                     
  Sweating Increased                        2                     4                     7                     
  Urinary Tract Infection                   4                     5                     5                     
  Xerostomia                                2                     5                     6                     
  Abdominal Pain                            3                     5                     6                     
  Syncope                                   3                     4                     5                     
  Urine Discoloration                       1                     2                     7                     
  Dyspepsia                                 2                     4                     3                     
  Influenza                                 2                     3                     4                     
  Dyspnea                                   2                     3                     3                     
  Balance Loss                              2                     3                     2                     
  Flatulence                                2                     2                     4                     
  Hyperkinesia                              1                     3                     2                     
  Chest Pain                                1                     3                     1                     
  Hypotension                               1                     2                     2                     
  Paresthesia                               2                     3                     1                     
  Stiffness                                 1                     2                     2                     
  Arthritis                                 1                     2                     1                     
  Chest Discomfort                          1                     1                     2                     
  Hypokinesia                               1                     1                     3                     
  Micturition Disorder                      1                     2                     1                     
  Pain Neck                                 1                     2                     2                     
  Burning                                   0                     2                     1                     
  Sinus Congestion                          0                     2                     1                     
  Agitation                                 0                     1                     1                     
  Bleeding Dermal                           0                     1                     1                     
  Irritability                              0                     1                     1                     
  Mental Deficiency                         0                     1                     1                     
  Hyperactivity                             0                     1                     1                     
  Malaise                                   0                     1                     0                     
  Panic Reaction                            0                     1                     0                     
  Tumor Skin                                0                     1                     0                     
  Cataract                                  0                     1                     0                     
  Euphoria                                  0                     1                     0                     
  Fever                                     0                     0                     1                     
  Alopecia                                  0                     1                     0                     
  Eye Inflamed                              0                     1                     0                     
  Hypertonia                                0                     0                     1                     
  Tumor Uterus                              0                     1                     0                     
            Effects of Gender on Adverse Reactions
   Female patients may be more likely to develop somnolence than males.



   Other Adverse Events Observed During All Trials in Patients With Parkinson's Disease

  During these trials, all adverse events were recorded by the clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. To provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals having adverse events, similar types of adverse events were grouped into a smaller number of standardized categories using COSTART dictionary terminology. These categories are used in the listing below.



 All reported events that occurred at least twice (or once for serious or potentially serious events), except those already listed above, trivial events and terms too vague to be meaningful are included, without regard to determination of a causal relationship to TASMAR.



 Events are further classified within body system categories and enumerated in order of decreasing frequency using the following definitions: frequent adverse events are defined as those occurring in at least 1/100 patients; infrequent adverse events are defined as those occurring in between 1/100 and 1/1000 patients; and rare adverse events are defined as those occurring in fewer than 1/1000 patients.



   Nervous System  -  frequent:  depression, hypesthesia, tremor, speech disorder, vertigo, emotional lability;  infrequent:  neuralgia, amnesia, extrapyramidal syndrome, hostility, libido increased, manic reaction, nervousness, paranoid reaction, cerebral ischemia, cerebrovascular accident, delusions, libido decreased, neuropathy, apathy, choreoathetosis, myoclonus, psychosis, thinking abnormal, twitching;  rare:  antisocial reaction, delirium, encephalopathy, hemiplegia, meningitis.



   Digestive System  -  frequent:  tooth disorder;  infrequent:  dysphagia, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, gastroenteritis, mouth ulceration, increased salivation, abnormal stools, esophagitis, cholelithiasis, colitis, tongue disorder, rectal disorder;  rare:  cholecystitis, duodenal ulcer, gastrointestinal carcinoma, stomach atony.



   Body as a Whole  -  frequent:  flank pain, accidental injury, abdominal pain, infection;  infrequent:  hernia, pain, allergic reaction, cellulitis, infection fungal, viral infection, carcinoma, chills, infection bacterial, neoplasm, abscess, face edema;  rare:  death.



   Cardiovascular System  -  frequent:  palpitation;  infrequent:  hypertension, vasodilation, angina pectoris, heart failure, atrial fibrillation, tachycardia, migraine, aortic stenosis, arrhythmia, arteriospasm, bradycardia, cerebral hemorrhage, coronary artery disorder, heart arrest, myocardial infarct, myocardial ischemia, pulmonary embolus;  rare:  arteriosclerosis, cardiovascular disorder, pericardial effusion, thrombosis.



   Musculoskeletal System  -  frequent:  myalgia;  infrequent:  tenosynovitis, arthrosis, joint disorder.



   Urogenital System  -  frequent:  urinary incontinence, impotence;  infrequent:  prostatic disorder, dysuria, nocturia, polyuria, urinary retention, urinary tract disorder, hematuria, kidney calculus, prostatic carcinoma, breast neoplasm, oliguria, uterine atony, uterine disorder, vaginitis;  rare:  bladder calculus, ovarian carcinoma, uterine hemorrhage.



   Respiratory System  -  frequent:  bronchitis, pharyngitis;  infrequent:  cough increased, rhinitis, asthma, epistaxis, hyperventilation, laryngitis, hiccup;  rare:  apnea, hypoxia, lung edema.



   Skin and Appendages  -  frequent:  rash;  infrequent:  herpes zoster, pruritus, seborrhea, skin discoloration, eczema, erythema multiforme, skin disorder, furunculosis, herpes simplex, urticaria.



   Special Senses  -  frequent:  tinnitus;  infrequent:  diplopia, ear pain, eye hemorrhage, eye pain, lacrimation disorder, otitis media, parosmia;  rare:  glaucoma.



   Metabolic and Nutritional  -  infrequent:  edema, hypercholesteremia, thirst, dehydration.



   Hemic and Lymphatic System  -  infrequent:  anemia;  rare:  leukemia, thrombocytopenia.



   Endocrine System  -  infrequent:  diabetes mellitus.



   Unclassified  -  infrequent:  surgical procedure.



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Valeant Pharmaceuticals North America LLC at 1-800-321-4576 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING

  WARNING

    Because of the risk of potentially fatal, acute fulminant liver failure, TASMAR (tolcapone) should ordinarily be used in patients with Parkinson's disease on l-dopa/carbidopa who are experiencing symptom fluctuations and are not responding satisfactorily to or are not appropriate candidates for other adjunctive therapies (see   INDICATIONS   and   DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION   sections).  



   Because of the risk of liver injury and because TASMAR, when it is effective, provides an observable symptomatic benefit, the patient who fails to show substantial clinical benefit within 3 weeks of initiation of treatment, should be withdrawn from TASMAR.  



   TASMAR therapy should not be initiated if the patient exhibits clinical evidence of liver disease or two SGPT/ALT or SGOT/AST values greater than the upper limit of normal. Patients with severe dyskinesia or dystonia should be treated with caution (see   PRECAUTIONS: Rhabdomyolysis  ).  



   PATIENTS WHO DEVELOP EVIDENCE OF HEPATOCELLULAR INJURY WHILE ON TASMAR AND ARE WITHDRAWN FROM THE DRUG FOR ANY REASON MAY BE AT INCREASED RISK FOR LIVER INJURY IF TASMAR IS REINTRODUCED. ACCORDINGLY, SUCH PATIENTS SHOULD NOT ORDINARILY BE CONSIDERED FOR RETREATMENT.  



   Cases of severe hepatocellular injury, including fulminant liver failure resulting in death, have been reported in postmarketing use. As of May 2005, 3 cases of fatal fulminant hepatic failure have been reported from more than 40,000 patient years of worldwide use. This incidence may be 10- to 100-fold higher than the background incidence in the general population. Underreporting of cases may lead to significant underestimation of the increased risk associated with the use of TASMAR. All 3 cases were reported within the first six months of initiation of treatment with TASMAR. Analysis of the laboratory monitoring data in over 3,400 TASMAR-treated patients participating in clinical trials indicated that increases in SGPT/ALT or SGOT/AST, when present, generally occurred within the first 6 months of treatment with TASMAR.  



   A prescriber who elects to use TASMAR in face of the increased risk of liver injury is strongly advised to monitor patients for evidence of emergent liver injury. Patients should be advised of the need for self-monitoring for both the classical signs of liver disease (e.g., clay colored stools, jaundice) and the nonspecific ones (eg, fatigue, loss of appetite, lethargy).  



   Although a program of periodic laboratory monitoring for evidence of hepatocellular injury is recommended, it is not clear that periodic monitoring of liver enzymes will prevent the occurrence of fulminant liver failure. However, it is generally believed that early detection of drug-induced hepatic injury along with immediate withdrawal of the suspect drug enhances the likelihood for recovery. Accordingly, the following liver monitoring program is recommended.  



   Before starting treatment with TASMAR, the physician should conduct appropriate tests to exclude the presence of liver disease. In patients determined to be appropriate candidates for treatment with TASMAR, serum glutamic-pyruvic transaminase (SGPT/ALT) and serum glutamic-oxaloacetic transaminase (SGOT/AST) levels should be determined at baseline and periodically (i.e. every 2 to 4 weeks) for the first 6 months of therapy. After the first six months, periodic monitoring is recommended at intervals deemed clinically relevant. Although more frequent monitoring increases the chances of early detection, the precise schedule for monitoring is a matter of clinical judgment. If the dose is increased to 200 mg tid (see   DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION   section), liver enzyme monitoring should take place before increasing the dose and then be conducted every 2 to 4 weeks for the following 6 months of therapy. After six months, periodic monitoring is recommended at intervals deemed clinically relevant.  



   TASMAR should be discontinued if SGPT/ALT or SGOT/AST levels exceed 2 times the upper limit of normal or if clinical signs and symptoms suggest the onset of hepatic dysfunction (persistent nausea, fatigue, lethargy, anorexia, jaundice, dark urine, pruritus, and right upper quadrant tenderness).  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
