<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tazorac" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  In human dermal safety studies, tazarotene 0.05% and 0.1% gels did not induce allergic contact sensitization, phototoxicity or photoallergy.



     Psoriasis:  The most frequent adverse events reported with  TAZORAC    (r)  Gel 0.05% and 0.1% were limited to the skin. Those occurring in 10 to 30% of patients, in descending order, included pruritus, burning/stinging, erythema, worsening of psoriasis, irritation, and skin pain. Events occurring in 1 to 10% of patients included rash, desquamation, irritant contact dermatitis, skin inflammation, fissuring, bleeding, and dry skin. Increases in "psoriasis worsening" and "sun-induced erythema" were noted in some patients over the 4th to 12th months as compared to the first three months of a 1 year study. In general, the incidence of adverse events with  TAZORAC    (r)  Gel 0.05% was 2 to 5% lower than that seen with  TAZORAC    (r)  Gel 0.1%.



     Acne:  The most frequent adverse events reported with  TAZORAC    (r)  Gel 0.1% in the treatment of acne occurring in 10 to 30% of patients, in descending order, included desquamation, burning/stinging, dry skin, erythema and pruritus. Events occurring in 1 to 10% of patients included irritation, skin pain, fissuring, localized edema and skin discoloration.



     Postmarketing Experience  



 The following adverse reactions have been identified during postmarketing use of  TAZORAC    (r)  Gel 0.05% and 0.1% in clinical practice. Because they are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to  TAZORAC    (r)  Gel. The reactions include: blister, rash, skin discoloration (including skin hyperpigmentation or skin hypopigmentation), and pain.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
