<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="telmisartan" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6  ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reaction is described elsewhere in labeling:



         Renal dysfunction upon use with ramipril  [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.6)  ]  



    EXCERPT:    *    Hypertension:  The most common adverse events (&gt;=1%) reported in hypertension trials are back pain, sinusitis, and diarrhea  (6.1)   
 *    Cardiovascular risk reduction:  The serious adverse events (&gt;=1%) reported in cardiovascular risk reduction trials were intermittent claudication and skin ulcer  (6.1)   
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Boehringer Ingelheim Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at (800) 542-6257 or (800) 459-9906 TTY, or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1  Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reactions rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Hypertension  Telmisartan has been evaluated for safety in more than 3700 patients, including 1900 treated for over 6 months and more than 1300 for over one year.  Adverse experiences have generally been mild and transient in nature and have infrequently required discontinuation of therapy.



 In placebo-controlled trials involving 1041 patients treated with various doses of telmisartan (20 to 160 mg) monotherapy for up to 12 weeks, the overall incidence of adverse events was similar to that in patients treated with placebo.



 Adverse events occurring at an incidence of &gt;=1% in patients treated with telmisartan and at a greater rate than in patients treated with placebo, irrespective of their causal association, are presented in Table 1.



   Table 1 Adverse Events Occurring at an Incidence of &gt;=1% in Patients Treated with Telmisartan and at a Greater Rate Than Patients Treated with Placebo  




                                     Telmisartann=1455%                 Placebon=380%                      
  Upper respiratory tract infection    7                                  6                                  
  Back pain                          3                                  1                                  
  Sinusitis                          3                                  2                                  
  Diarrhea                           3                                  2                                  
  Pharyngitis                        1                                  0                                  
         In addition to the adverse events in the table, the following events occurred at a rate of &gt;=1% but were at least as frequent in the placebo group:  influenza-like symptoms, dyspepsia, myalgia, urinary tract infection, abdominal pain, headache, dizziness, pain, fatigue, coughing, hypertension, chest pain, nausea, and peripheral edema. Discontinuation of therapy because of adverse events was required in 2.8% of 1455 patients treated with telmisartan tablets and 6.1% of 380 placebo patients in placebo-controlled clinical trials.
 

 The incidence of adverse events was not dose-related and did not correlate with gender, age, or race of patients.



 The incidence of cough occurring with telmisartan in 6 placebo-controlled trials was identical to that noted for placebo-treated patients (1.6%).



 In addition to those listed above, adverse events that occurred in more than 0.3% of 3500 patients treated with telmisartan monotherapy in controlled or open trials are listed below.  It cannot be determined whether these events were causally related to telmisartan tablets:



   Autonomic Nervous System  :  impotence, increased sweating, flushing;  Body as a Whole  : allergy, fever, leg pain, malaise;  Cardiovascular  :  palpitation, dependent edema, angina pectoris, tachycardia, leg edema, abnormal ECG;  CNS  :  insomnia, somnolence, migraine, vertigo, paresthesia, involuntary muscle contractions, hypoesthesia;  Gastrointestinal  :  flatulence, constipation, gastritis, vomiting, dry mouth, hemorrhoids, gastroenteritis, enteritis, gastroesophageal reflux, toothache, non-specific gastrointestinal disorders;  Metabolic  :  gout, hypercholesterolemia, diabetes mellitus;  Musculoskeletal  :  arthritis, arthralgia, leg cramps;  Psychiatric  :  anxiety, depression, nervousness;  Resistance Mechanism  :  infection, fungal infection, abscess, otitis media;  Respiratory  :  asthma, bronchitis, rhinitis, dyspnea, epistaxis;  Skin  :  dermatitis, rash, eczema, pruritus;  Urinary  :  micturition frequency, cystitis;  Vascular  : cerebrovascular disorder; and  Special Senses  :  abnormal vision, conjunctivitis, tinnitus, earache.



 During initial clinical studies, a single case of angioedema was reported (among a total of 3781 patients treated).



   Clinical Laboratory Findings  



 In placebo-controlled clinical trials, clinically relevant changes in standard laboratory test parameters were rarely associated with administration of telmisartan tablets.



   Hemoglobin  :  A greater than 2 g/dL decrease in hemoglobin was observed in 0.8% telmisartan patients compared with 0.3% placebo patients.  No patients discontinued therapy because of anemia.



   Creatinine  :  A 0.5 mg/dL rise or greater in creatinine was observed in 0.4% telmisartan patients compared with 0.3% placebo patients.  One telmisartan-treated patient discontinued therapy because of increases in creatinine and blood urea nitrogen.



   Liver Enzymes  :  Occasional elevations of liver chemistries occurred in patients treated with telmisartan; all marked elevations occurred at a higher frequency with placebo.  No telmisartan-treated patients discontinued therapy because of abnormal hepatic function.



   Cardiovascular Risk Reduction  



 Because common adverse reactions were well characterized in studies of telmisartan in hypertension, only adverse events leading to discontinuation and serious adverse events were recorded in subsequent studies of telmisartan for cardiovascular risk reduction. In TRANSCEND (N=5926, 4 years and 8 months of follow-up), discontinuations for adverse events were 8.4% on telmisartan and 7.6% on placebo. The only serious adverse events at least 1% more common on telmisartan than placebo were intermittent claudication (7% vs 6%) and skin ulcer (3% vs 2%).



   6.2  Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of telmisartan. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to estimate reliably their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. Decisions to include these reactions in labeling are typically based on one or more of the following factors:  (1) seriousness of the reaction, (2) frequency of reporting, or (3) strength of causal connection to telmisartan.



 The most frequent spontaneously reported events include: headache, dizziness, asthenia, coughing, nausea, fatigue, weakness, edema, face edema, lower limb edema, angioneurotic edema, urticaria, hypersensitivity, sweating increased, erythema, chest pain, atrial fibrillation, congestive heart failure, myocardial infarction, blood pressure increased, hypertension aggravated, hypotension (including postural hypotension), hyperkalemia, syncope, dyspepsia, diarrhea, pain, urinary tract infection, erectile dysfunction, back pain, abdominal pain, muscle cramps (including leg cramps), myalgia, bradycardia, eosinophilia, thrombocytopenia, uric acid increased, abnormal hepatic function/liver disorder, renal impairment including acute renal failure, anemia, increased CPK, anaphylactic reaction, tendon pain (including tendonitis, tenosynovitis), drug eruption (toxic skin eruption mostly reported as toxicoderma, rash, and urticaria), hypoglycemia (in diabetic patients), and angioedema (with fatal outcome).



 Rare cases of rhabdomyolysis have been reported in patients receiving angiotensin II receptor blockers, including telmisartan.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING:  FETAL TOXICITY

  WARNING:  FETAL TOXICITY

    *  When pregnancy is detected, discontinue Telmisartan Tablets USP as soon as possible [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING:  FETAL TOXICITY
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  .



 *  When pregnancy is detected, discontinue Telmisartan Tablets USP as soon as possible (5.1) 
 *  Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Avoid fetal or neonatal exposure  (5.1)   
 *    Hypotension: Correct any volume or salt depletion before initiating therapy. Observe for signs and symptoms of hypotension  (5.2)   
 *    Monitor carefully in patients with impaired hepatic  (5.4)  or renal function  (5.5)   
 *    Avoid concomitant use of an ACE inhibitor and angiotensin receptor blocker  (5.6)   
    
 

   5.1  Fetal Toxicity



   Pregnancy Category D  



 Use of drugs that act on the renin-angiotensin system during the second and third trimesters of pregnancy reduces fetal renal function and increases fetal and neonatal morbidity and death. Resulting oligohydramnios can be associated with fetal lung hypoplasia and skeletal deformations. Potential neonatal adverse effects include skull hypoplasia, anuria, hypotension, renal failure, and death. When pregnancy is detected, discontinue telmisartan as soon as possible [see Use in Specific Populations  (8.1)  ]  .



    5.2  Hypotension



  In patients with an activated renin-angiotensin system, such as volume- or salt-depleted patients (e.g., those being treated with high doses of diuretics), symptomatic hypotension may occur after initiation of therapy with telmisartan. Either correct this condition prior to administration of telmisartan, or start treatment under close medical supervision with a reduced dose.



 If hypotension does occur, the patient should be placed in the supine position and, if necessary, given an intravenous infusion of normal saline.  A transient hypotensive response is not a contraindication to further treatment, which usually can be continued without difficulty once the blood pressure has stabilized.



    5.3  Hyperkalemia



  Hyperkalemia may occur in patients on ARBs, particularly in patients with advanced renal impairment, heart failure, on renal replacement therapy, or on potassium supplements, potassium-sparing diuretics, potassium-containing salt substitutes or other drugs that increase potassium levels. Consider periodic determinations of serum electrolytes to detect possible electrolyte imbalances, particularly in patients at risk.



    5.4  Impaired Hepatic Function



  As the majority of telmisartan is eliminated by biliary excretion, patients with biliary obstructive disorders or hepatic insufficiency can be expected to have reduced clearance.  Initiate telmisartan at low doses and titrate slowly in these patients [see Use in Specific Populations  (8.6)  and Clinical Pharmacology  (12.3)  ]  .



    5.5  Impaired Renal Function



  As a consequence of inhibiting the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, anticipate changes in renal function in susceptible individuals.  In patients whose renal function may depend on the activity of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (e.g., patients with severe congestive heart failure or renal dysfunction), treatment with angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors and angiotensin receptor antagonists has been associated with oliguria and/or progressive azotemia and (rarely) with acute renal failure and/or death. Similar results have been reported with telmisartan [see Clinical Pharmacology  (12.3)  ]  .



 In studies of ACE inhibitors in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, increases in serum creatinine or blood urea nitrogen were observed.  There has been no long term use of telmisartan in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, but anticipate an effect similar to that seen with ACE inhibitors.



    5.6  Dual Blockade of the Renin-Angiotensin-Aldosterone System



   Dual blockade of the RAS with angiotensin-receptor blockers, ACE inhibitors, or aliskiren is associated with increased risks of hypotension, hyperkalemia, and changes in renal function (including acute renal failure) compared to monotherapy.  



  The ONTARGET trial enrolled 25,620 patients &gt;=55 years old with atherosclerotic disease or diabetes with end-organ damage, randomizing them to telmisartan only, ramipril only, or the combination, and followed them for a median of 56 months. Patients receiving the combination of telmisartan and ramipril did not obtain any additional benefit compared to monotherapy, but experienced an increased incidence of renal dysfunction (e.g., acute renal failure) compared with groups receiving telmisartan alone or ramipril alone.  



  In most patients no benefit has been associated with using two RAS inhibitors concomitantly. In general, avoid combined use of RAS inhibitors. Closely monitor blood pressure, renal function, and electrolytes in patients on telmisartan and other agents that affect the RAS.  



  Do not co-administer aliskiren with telmisartan in patients with diabetes. Avoid concomitant use of aliskiren with telmisartan in patients with renal impairment (GFR &lt;60 mL/min/1.73 m  2  ).  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
