<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="temodar" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=10% incidence) are: alopecia, fatigue, nausea, vomiting, headache, constipation, anorexia, convulsions, rash, hemiparesis, diarrhea, asthenia, fever, dizziness, coordination abnormal, viral infection, amnesia, and insomnia. (  6.1  ) 
 *  The most common Grade 3 to 4 hematologic laboratory abnormalities (&gt;=10% incidence) that have developed during treatment with temozolomide are: lymphopenia, thrombocytopenia, neutropenia, and leukopenia. (  6.1  ) 
 *  Allergic reactions have also been reported. (  6  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   

    Newly Diagnosed Glioblastoma Multiforme:  



 During the concomitant phase (TEMODAR+radiotherapy), adverse reactions including thrombocytopenia, nausea, vomiting, anorexia, and constipation were more frequent in the TEMODAR+RT arm. The incidence of other adverse reactions was comparable in the two arms. The most common adverse reactions across the cumulative TEMODAR experience were alopecia, nausea, vomiting, anorexia, headache, and constipation (see    Table 7    ). Forty-nine percent (49%) of patients treated with TEMODAR reported one or more severe or life-threatening reactions, most commonly fatigue (13%), convulsions (6%), headache (5%), and thrombocytopenia (5%). Overall, the pattern of reactions during the maintenance phase was consistent with the known safety profile of TEMODAR.



 TABLE 7: Number (%) of Patients with Adverse Reactions: All and Severe/Life Threatening (Incidence of 5% or Greater) 
                               Concomitant PhaseRT Alone(n=285)  Concomitant PhaseRT+TMZ(n=288)  Maintenance PhaseTMZ(n=224)   
                                  All  Grade &gt;=3     All  Grade &gt;=3     All  Grade &gt;=3   
  
 RT+TMZ=radiotherapy plus temozolomide; NOS=not otherwise specified.   
   Note:  Grade 5 (fatal) adverse reactions are included in the Grade &gt;=3 column.   
  
   Subjects Reporting any Adverse Reaction      258       (91)      74       (26)      266       (92)      80       (28)      206       (92)      82       (37)     
   Body as a Whole - General Disorders                                                                                                     
 Anorexia                         25   (9)         1   (&lt;1)       56   (19)        2   (1)        61   (27)        3   (1)      
 Dizziness                        10   (4)         0              12   (4)         2   (1)        12   (5)         0            
 Fatigue                         139   (49)       15   (5)       156   (54)       19   (7)       137   (61)       20   (9)      
 Headache                         49   (17)       11   (4)        56   (19)        5   (2)        51   (23)        9   (4)      
 Weakness                          9   (3)         3   (1)        10   (3)         5   (2)        16   (7)         4   (2)      
   Central and Peripheral Nervous System Disorders                                                                                                     
 Confusion                        12   (4)         6   (2)        11   (4)         4   (1)        12   (5)         4   (2)      
 Convulsions                      20   (7)         9   (3)        17   (6)        10   (3)        25   (11)        7   (3)      
 Memory Impairment                12   (4)         1   (&lt;1)        8   (3)         1   (&lt;1)       16   (7)         2   (1)      
   Disorders of the Eye                                                                                                         
 Vision Blurred                   25   (9)         4   (1)        26   (9)         2   (1)        17   (8)         0            
   Disorders of the Immune System                                                                                                     
 Allergic Reaction                 7   (2)         1   (&lt;1)       13   (5)         0               6   (3)         0            
   Gastrointestinal System Disorders                                                                                                     
 Abdominal Pain                    2   (1)         0               7   (2)         1   (&lt;1)       11   (5)         1   (&lt;1)     
 Constipation                     18   (6)         0              53   (18)        3   (1)        49   (22)        0            
 Diarrhea                          9   (3)         0              18   (6)         0              23   (10)        2   (1)      
 Nausea                           45   (16)        1   (&lt;1)      105   (36)        2   (1)       110   (49)        3   (1)      
 Stomatitis                       14   (5)         1   (&lt;1)       19   (7)         0              20   (9)         3   (1)      
 Vomiting                         16   (6)         1   (&lt;1)       57   (20)        1   (&lt;1)       66   (29)        4   (2)      
   Injury and Poisoning                                                                                                         
 Radiation Injury NOS             11   (4)         1   (&lt;1)       20   (7)         0               5   (2)         0            
   Musculoskeletal System Disorders                                                                                                     
 Arthralgia                        2   (1)         0               7   (2)         1   (&lt;1)       14   (6)         0            
   Platelet, Bleeding and Clotting Disorders                                                                                                     
 Thrombocytopenia                  3   (1)         0              11   (4)         8   (3)        19   (8)         8   (4)      
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                                        
 Insomnia                          9   (3)         1   (&lt;1)       14   (5)         0               9   (4)         0            
   Respiratory System Disorders                                                                                                     
 Coughing                          3   (1)         0              15   (5)         2   (1)        19   (8)         1   (&lt;1)     
 Dyspnea                           9   (3)         4   (1)        11   (4)         5   (2)        12   (5)         1   (&lt;1)     
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                                                                                                     
 Alopecia                        179   (63)        0             199   (69)        0             124   (55)        0            
 Dry Skin                          6   (2)         0               7   (2)         0              11   (5)         1   (&lt;1)     
 Erythema                         15   (5)         0              14   (5)         0               2   (1)         0            
 Pruritus                          4   (1)         0              11   (4)         0              11   (5)         0            
 Rash                             42   (15)        0              56   (19)        3   (1)        29   (13)        3   (1)      
   Special Senses Other, Disorders                                                                                                     
 Taste Perversion                  6   (2)         0              18   (6)         0              11   (5)         0            
                   Myelosuppression (neutropenia and thrombocytopenia), which is a known dose-limiting toxicity for most cytotoxic agents, including TEMODAR, was observed. When laboratory abnormalities and adverse reactions were combined, Grade 3 or Grade 4 neutrophil abnormalities including neutropenic reactions were observed in 8% of the patients, and Grade 3 or Grade 4 platelet abnormalities, including thrombocytopenic reactions, were observed in 14% of the patients treated with TEMODAR.
 

   

    Refractory Anaplastic Astrocytoma:  



     Tables 8    and    9    show the incidence of adverse reactions in the 158 patients in the anaplastic astrocytoma study for whom data are available. In the absence of a control group, it is not clear in many cases whether these reactions should be attributed to temozolomide or the patients' underlying conditions, but nausea, vomiting, fatigue, and hematologic effects appear to be clearly drug-related. The most frequently occurring adverse reactions were nausea, vomiting, headache, and fatigue. The adverse reactions were usually NCI Common Toxicity Criteria (CTC) Grade 1 or 2 (mild to moderate in severity) and were self-limiting, with nausea and vomiting readily controlled with antiemetics. The incidence of severe nausea and vomiting (CTC Grade 3 or 4) was 10% and 6%, respectively. Myelosuppression (thrombocytopenia and neutropenia) was the dose-limiting adverse reaction. It usually occurred within the first few cycles of therapy and was not cumulative.



 Myelosuppression occurred late in the treatment cycle and returned to normal, on average, within 14 days of nadir counts. The median nadirs occurred at 26 days for platelets (range: 21-40 days) and 28 days for neutrophils (range: 1-44 days). Only 14% (22/158) of patients had a neutrophil nadir and 20% (32/158) of patients had a platelet nadir, which may have delayed the start of the next cycle. Less than 10% of patients required hospitalization, blood transfusion, or discontinuation of therapy due to myelosuppression.



 In clinical trial experience with 110 to 111 women and 169 to 174 men (depending on measurements), there were higher rates of Grade 4 neutropenia (ANC less than 500 cells/uL) and thrombocytopenia (less than 20,000 cells/uL) in women than men in the first cycle of therapy (12% vs. 5% and 9% vs. 3%, respectively).



 In the entire safety database for which hematologic data exist (N=932), 7% (4/61) and 9.5% (6/63) of patients over age 70 experienced Grade 4 neutropenia or thrombocytopenia in the first cycle, respectively. For patients less than or equal to age 70, 7% (62/871) and 5.5% (48/879) experienced Grade 4 neutropenia or thrombocytopenia in the first cycle, respectively. Pancytopenia, leukopenia, and anemia have also been reported.



 TABLE 8: Adverse Reactions in the Anaplastic Astrocytoma Trial in Adults (&gt;=5%) 
                                           No. (%) of TEMODAR Patients (N=158)   
                                                   All Reactions                     Grade 3/4              
 Any Adverse Reaction                                 153 (97)                        79 (50)               
  
   Body as a Whole                                                                                          
 Headache                                             65 (41)                          10 (6)               
 Fatigue                                              54 (34)                          7 (4)                
 Asthenia                                             20 (13)                          9 (6)                
 Fever                                                21 (13)                          3 (2)                
 Back pain                                             12 (8)                          4 (3)                
   Cardiovascular                                                                                           
 Edema peripheral                                     17 (11)                          1 (1)                
   Central and Peripheral Nervous System                                                                     
 Convulsions                                          36 (23)                          8 (5)                
 Hemiparesis                                          29 (18)                          10 (6)               
 Dizziness                                            19 (12)                          1 (1)                
 Coordination abnormal                                17 (11)                          2 (1)                
 Amnesia                                              16 (10)                          6 (4)                
 Insomnia                                             16 (10)                            0                  
 Paresthesia                                           15 (9)                          1 (1)                
 Somnolence                                            15 (9)                          5 (3)                
 Paresis                                               13 (8)                          4 (3)                
 Urinary incontinence                                  13 (8)                          3 (2)                
 Ataxia                                                12 (8)                          3 (2)                
 Dysphasia                                             11 (7)                          1 (1)                
 Convulsions local                                     9 (6)                             0                  
 Gait abnormal                                         9 (6)                           1 (1)                
 Confusion                                             8 (5)                             0                  
   Endocrine                                                                                                
 Adrenal hypercorticism                                13 (8)                            0                  
   Gastrointestinal System                                                                                  
 Nausea                                               84 (53)                         16 (10)               
 Vomiting                                             66 (42)                          10 (6)               
 Constipation                                         52 (33)                          1 (1)                
 Diarrhea                                             25 (16)                          3 (2)                
 Abdominal pain                                        14 (9)                          2 (1)                
 Anorexia                                              14 (9)                          1 (1)                
   Metabolic                                                                                                
 Weight increase                                       8 (5)                             0                  
   Musculoskeletal System                                                                                   
 Myalgia                                               8 (5)                                                
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                    
 Anxiety                                               11 (7)                          1 (1)                
 Depression                                            10 (6)                            0                  
   Reproductive Disorders                                                                                   
 Breast pain, female                                   4 (6)                                                
   Resistance Mechanism Disorders                                                                           
 Infection viral                                      17 (11)                            0                  
   Respiratory System                                                                                       
 Upper respiratory tract infection                     13 (8)                            0                  
 Pharyngitis                                           12 (8)                            0                  
 Sinusitis                                             10 (6)                            0                  
 Coughing                                              8 (5)                             0                  
   Skin and Appendages                                                                                      
 Rash                                                  13 (8)                            0                  
 Pruritus                                              12 (8)                          2 (1)                
   Urinary System                                                                                           
 Urinary tract infection                               12 (8)                            0                  
 Micturition increased frequency                       9 (6)                             0                  
   Vision                                                                                                   
 Diplopia                                              8 (5)                             0                  
 Vision abnormal                                       8 (5)                                                
        TABLE 9: Adverse Hematologic Effects (Grade 3 to 4) in the Anaplastic Astrocytoma Trial in Adults 
                                                                          TEMODAR                         
  
 Hemoglobin                                                              7/158 (4%)                       
 Lymphopenia                                                            83/152 (55%)                      
 Neutrophils                                                            20/142 (14%)                      
 Platelets                                                              29/156 (19%)                      
 WBC                                                                    18/158 (11%)                      
        TEMODAR for injection delivers equivalent temozolomide dose and exposure to both temozolomide and 5-(3-methyltriazen-1-yl)-imidazole-4-carboxamide (MTIC) as the corresponding TEMODAR capsules. Adverse reactions probably related to treatment that were reported from the 2 studies with the intravenous formulation (n=35) that were not reported in studies using the TEMODAR capsules were: pain, irritation, pruritus, warmth, swelling, and erythema at infusion site as well as the following adverse reactions: petechiae and hematoma.
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of TEMODAR. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to the drug exposure.



   Dermatologic disorders  : Toxic epidermal necrolysis and Stevens-Johnson syndrome



   Immune system disorders  : Allergic reactions, including anaphylaxis. Erythema multiforme, which resolved after discontinuation of TEMODAR and, in some cases, recurred upon rechallenge.



   Hematopoietic disorders  : Prolonged pancytopenia, which may result in aplastic anemia and fatal outcomes  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .



   Hepatobiliary disorders  : Fatal and severe hepatotoxicity, elevation of liver enzymes, hyperbilirubinemia, cholestasis, and hepatitis  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  .



   Infections and infestations  : Opportunistic infections including  Pneumocystis  pneumonia (PCP)  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  and primary and reactivated cytomegalovirus  ,  reactivation of hepatitis B infections, including some cases with fatal outcomes  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  .



   Pulmonary disorders  : Interstitial pneumonitis, pneumonitis, alveolitis, and pulmonary fibrosis.



   Endocrine disorders  : Diabetes insipidus
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

    TEMODAR  (r)   (temozolomide) Capsules  



   PHARMACIST:  



 Dispense enclosed Patient Package Insert to each patient.



   PHARMACIST INFORMATION SHEET  



     IMPORTANT DISPENSING INFORMATION  



   For every patient, TEMODAR must be dispensed in a separate vial or in its original package making sure each container lists the strength per capsule and that patients take the appropriate number of capsules from each package or vial.  



   Please see the dispensing instructions below for more information.  



   

    What is TEMODAR?  



 TEMODAR  (r)   (temozolomide) is an oral alkylating agent for the treatment of newly diagnosed glioblastoma multiforme and refractory anaplastic astrocytoma.



   How is TEMODAR dosed?  



 The daily dose of TEMODAR Capsules for a given patient is calculated by the physician, based on the patient's body surface area (BSA). The resulting dose is then rounded off to the nearest 5 mg. An example of the dosing may be as follows: the initial daily dose of TEMODAR in milligrams is the BSA multiplied by mg/m  2  /day, (a patient with a BSA of 1.84 is 1.84 * 75 mg = 138, or 140 mg/day). The dose for subsequent cycles may be adjusted according to nadir neutrophil and platelet counts in the previous cycle and at the time of initiating the next cycle.



   How might the dose of TEMODAR be modified for Refractory Anaplastic Astrocytoma?  



 Dosage of TEMODAR must be adjusted according to nadir neutrophil and platelet counts in the previous cycle and neutrophil and platelet counts at the time of initiating the next cycle. The initial dose is 150 mg/m  2   orally once daily for 5 consecutive days per 28-day treatment cycle. If both the nadir and day of dosing (Day 29, Day 1 of next cycle) absolute neutrophil counts (ANC) are greater than or equal to 1.5 * 10  9  /L (1500/uL) and both the nadir and Day 29, Day 1 of next cycle platelet counts are greater than or equal to 100 * 10  9  /L (100,000/uL), the TEMODAR dose may be increased to 200 mg/m  2  /day for 5 consecutive days per 28-day treatment cycle. During treatment, a complete blood count should be obtained on Day 22 (21 days after the first dose) or within 48 hours of that day, and weekly until the ANC is above 1.5 * 10  9  /L (1500/uL) and the platelet count exceeds 100 * 10  9  /L (100,000/uL). The next cycle of TEMODAR should not be started until the ANC and platelet count exceed these levels. If the ANC falls to less than 1.0 * 10  9  /L (1000/uL) or the platelet count is less than 50 * 10  9  /L (50,000/uL) during any cycle, the next cycle should be reduced by 50 mg/m  2  , but not below 100 mg/m  2  , the lowest recommended dose (see     Table 1     below).



 TABLE 1: Dosing Modification Table for Refractory Anaplastic Astrocytoma 
                                                                                                        
         What is the TEMODAR Capsules treatment regimen?  
 

 TEMODAR is given for 5 consecutive days on a 28-day cycle. Patients should continue taking TEMODAR until their physician determines that their disease has progressed, up to 2 years, or until unacceptable side effects or toxicities occur. Physicians may alter the treatment regimen for a given patient.



   Newly Diagnosed Concomitant Phase Treatment Schedule  



 TEMODAR is administered orally at 75 mg/m  2   daily for 42 days concomitant with focal radiotherapy (60 Gy administered in 30 fractions), followed by maintenance TEMODAR for 6 cycles. No dose reductions are recommended; however, dose interruptions may occur based on patient tolerance. The TEMODAR dose can be continued throughout the 42-day concomitant period up to 49 days if all of the following conditions are met: absolute neutrophil count greater than or equal to 1.5 * 10  9  /L, platelet count greater than or equal to 100 *10  9  /L, common toxicity criteria (CTC) nonhematological toxicity less than or equal to Grade 1 (except for alopecia, nausea and vomiting). During treatment a complete blood count should be obtained weekly. Temozolomide dosing should be interrupted or discontinued during concomitant phase according to the hematological and nonhematological toxicity criteria as noted in     Table 2.       Pneumocystis   pneumonia (PCP) prophylaxis is required during the concomitant administration of TEMODAR and radiotherapy, and should be continued in patients who develop lymphocytopenia until recovery from lymphocytopenia (CTC grade less than or equal to 1).



 TABLE 2: Temozolomide Dosing Interruption or Discontinuation During Concomitant Radiotherapy and Temozolomide 
 Toxicity                                  TMZ InterruptionTreatment with concomitant TMZ could be continued when all of the following conditions were met: absolute neutrophil count greater than or equal to 1.5 * 109/L; platelet count greater than or equal to 100 * 109/L; CTC nonhematological toxicity less than or equal to Grade 1 (except for alopecia, nausea, vomiting).       TMZ Discontinuation         
  
 TMZ = temozolomide; CTC = Common Toxicity Criteria.   
  
 Absolute Neutrophil Count                 greater than or equal to 0.5 and less than 1.5 * 109/L      less than 0.5 * 109/L        
 Platelet Count                            greater than or equal to 10 and less than 100 * 109/L       less than 10 * 109/L        
 CTC Nonhematological Toxicity (except for alopecia, nausea, vomiting)           CTC Grade 2                   CTC Grade 3 or 4          
           Maintenance Phase Treatment Schedule   
 

 Four weeks after completing the TEMODAR + RT phase, TEMODAR is administered for an additional 6 cycles of maintenance treatment. Dosage in Cycle 1 (maintenance) is 150 mg/m  2   once daily for 5 days followed by 23 days without treatment. At the start of Cycle 2, the dose is escalated to 200 mg/m  2  , if the CTC nonhematologic toxicity for Cycle 1 is Grade less than or equal to 2 (except for alopecia, nausea and vomiting), absolute neutrophil count (ANC) is greater than or equal to 1.5 * 10  9  /L, and the platelet count is greater than or equal to 100 * 10  9  /L. If the dose was not escalated at Cycle 2, escalation should not be done in subsequent cycles. The dose remains at 200 mg/m  2   per day for the first 5 days of each subsequent cycle except if toxicity occurs.



 During treatment a complete blood count should be obtained on Day 22 (21 days after the first dose) or within 48 hours of that day, and weekly until the ANC is above 1.5 * 10  9  /L (1500/uL) and the platelet count exceeds 100 * 10  9  /L (100,000/uL). The next cycle of TEMODAR should not be started until the ANC and platelet count exceed these levels. Dose reductions during the next cycle should be based on the lowest blood counts and worst nonhematologic toxicity during the previous cycle. Dose reductions or discontinuations during the maintenance phase should be applied according to   Tables   3     and     4    .



 TABLE 3: Temozolomide Dose Levels for Maintenance Treatment 
      Dose Level              Dose (mg/m2/day)                              Remarks                         
  
          -1                        100                           Reduction for prior toxicity              
          0                         150                               Dose during Cycle 1                   
          1                         200                  Dose during Cycles 2-6 in absence of toxicity      
        TABLE 4: Temozolomide Dose Reduction or Discontinuation During Maintenance Treatment 
 Toxicity                                  Reduce TMZ by 1 Dose LevelTMZ dose levels are listed in Table 3.         Discontinue TMZ           
  
 TMZ = temozolomide; CTC = Common Toxicity Criteria.   
  
 Absolute Neutrophil Count                     less than 1.0 * 109/L       See footnoteTMZ is to be discontinued if dose reduction to less than 100 mg/m2 is required or if the same Grade 3 nonhematological toxicity (except for alopecia, nausea, vomiting) recurs after dose reduction.   
 Platelet Count                                 less than 50 * 109/L                See footnote            
 CTC Nonhematological Toxicity (except for alopecia, nausea, vomiting)           CTC Grade 3                     CTC Grade 4             
           How is TEMODAR taken?  
 

 Patients should take each day's dose with a full glass of water at the same time each day. Taking the medication on an empty stomach or at bedtime may help ease nausea. If patients are also taking antinausea or other medications to relieve the side effects associated with TEMODAR, they should be advised to take these medications 30 minutes before they take TEMODAR. Temozolomide causes the rapid appearance of malignant tumors in rats. Patients   SHOULD NOT   open or split the capsules. If capsules are accidentally opened or damaged, rigorous precautions should be taken with the capsule contents to avoid inhalation or contact with the skin or mucous membranes. The medication should be kept away from children and pets. The TEMODAR capsules should be swallowed whole and   NEVER CHEWED  .



   What should the patient avoid during treatment with TEMODAR?  



 There are no dietary restrictions for patients taking TEMODAR. TEMODAR may affect testicular function, so male patients should exercise adequate birth control measures. TEMODAR may cause birth defects. Female patients should avoid becoming pregnant while receiving this drug. Women who are nursing prior to receiving TEMODAR should discontinue nursing. It is not known whether TEMODAR is excreted into breast milk.



 Because many drugs are excreted in human milk, and because of the potential for serious adverse reactions in nursing infants and tumorigenicity shown for temozolomide in animal studies, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or to discontinue the drug, taking into account the importance of TEMODAR to the mother.



   What are the side effects of TEMODAR?  



 Nausea and vomiting are the most common side effects associated with TEMODAR. Noncumulative myelosuppression is the dose-limiting toxicity. Patients should be evaluated periodically by their physician to monitor blood counts.



   Other commonly reported side effects reported by patients taking TEMODAR   are fatigue, constipation, alopecia, anorexia, and headache.



   How is TEMODAR supplied?  



 TEMODAR Capsules are available in 5-mg, 20-mg, 100-mg, 140-mg, 180-mg, and 250-mg strengths. The capsules contain a white capsule body with a color cap, and the colors vary based on the dosage strength.




                   TEMODAR Capsule Strength                    Color                                      
  
                             5 mg                              Green Cap                                  
                            20 mg                              Yellow Cap                                 
                            100 mg                             Pink Cap                                   
                            140 mg                             Blue Cap                                   
                            180 mg                             Orange Cap                                 
                            250 mg                             White Cap                                  
        The 5-mg, 20-mg, 100-mg, 140-mg, and 180-mg capsule strengths are available in 5-count and 14-count packages. The 250-mg capsule strength is available in a 5-count package. 
 

   How is TEMODAR dispensed?  



 Each strength of TEMODAR must be dispensed in a separate vial or in its original package (one strength per one container). Follow the instructions below:



 Based on the dose prescribed, determine the number of each strength of TEMODAR capsules needed for the full 42- or 5-day cycle as prescribed by the physician. For example, in a 5-day cycle, 275 mg/day would be dispensed as five 250-mg capsules, five 20-mg capsules and five 5-mg capsules. Label each container with the appropriate number of capsules to be taken each day. Dispense to the patient, making sure each container lists the strength (mg) per capsule and that he or she understands to take the appropriate number of capsules of TEMODAR from each package or vial to equal the total daily dose prescribed by the physician.



   How can TEMODAR be ordered?  



 TEMODAR can be ordered from your wholesaler. It is important to understand if TEMODAR is being used as part of a 42-day regimen or as part of a 5-day course. Remember to order enough TEMODAR for the appropriate cycle.



 For example:



 *  a 5-day course of 360 mg/day would require the following to be ordered: two 5-count packages of 180-mg capsules. 
 *  a 42-day course of 140 mg/day would require the following to be ordered: three 14-count packages of 140-mg capsules. 
    For examples of other dosing regimens, please refer to the full   Prescribing Information (Table 6)  .
 


 TEMODAR Product                                                              NDC Number                  
  
 Sachets:                                                                                                 
 5-mg capsules (5 count)                                                     0085-3004-03                 
 5-mg capsules (14 count)                                                    0085-3004-04                 
 20-mg capsules (5 count)                                                    0085-1519-03                 
 20-mg capsules (14 count)                                                   0085-1519-04                 
 100-mg capsules (5 count)                                                   0085-1366-03                 
 100-mg capsules (14 count)                                                  0085-1366-04                 
 140-mg capsules (5 count)                                                   0085-1425-03                 
 140-mg capsules (14 count)                                                  0085-1425-04                 
 180-mg capsules (5 count)                                                   0085-1430-03                 
 180-mg capsules (14 count)                                                  0085-1430-04                 
 250-mg capsules (5 count)                                                   0085-1417-02                 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Myelosuppression - monitor Absolute Neutrophil Count (ANC) and platelet count prior to dosing and throughout treatment. Geriatric patients and women have a higher risk of developing myelosuppression. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Cases of myelodysplastic syndrome and secondary malignancies, including myeloid leukemia, have been observed. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Pneumocystis pneumonia (PCP) - PCP prophylaxis required for all patients receiving concomitant TEMODAR and radiotherapy for the 42-day regimen for the treatment of newly diagnosed glioblastoma multiforme. (  5.3  ) 
 *  All patients, particularly those receiving steroids, should be observed closely for the development of lymphopenia and PCP. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Complete blood counts should be obtained throughout the treatment course as specified. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Hepatotoxicity - fatal and severe hepatotoxicity have been reported. Perform liver function tests at baseline, midway through the first cycle, prior to each subsequent cycle, and approximately two to four weeks after the last dose of TEMODAR. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Hepatitis B virus (HBV) reactivation - fatal hepatitis due to HBV reactivation has been reported. Screen patients for HBV infection before treatment initiation. Monitor patients during and after treatment with TEMODAR. Discontinue therapy for patients with evidence of active HBV infection (  5.5  ) 
 *  Fetal harm can occur when administered to a pregnant woman. Women should be advised to avoid becoming pregnant when receiving TEMODAR. (  5.6  ) 
 *  As bioequivalence has been established only when given over 90 minutes, infusion over a shorter or longer period of time may result in suboptimal dosing; the possibility of an increase in infusion-related adverse reactions cannot be ruled out. (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Myelosuppression



  Patients treated with TEMODAR may experience myelosuppression, including prolonged pancytopenia, which may result in aplastic anemia, which in some cases has resulted in a fatal outcome. In some cases, exposure to concomitant medications associated with aplastic anemia, including carbamazepine, phenytoin, and sulfamethoxazole/trimethoprim, complicates assessment. Prior to dosing, patients must have an absolute neutrophil count (ANC) greater than or equal to 1.5 * 10  9  /L and a platelet count greater than or equal to 100 * 10  9  /L. A complete blood count should be obtained on Day 22 (21 days after the first dose) or within 48 hours of that day, and weekly until the ANC is above 1.5 * 10  9  /L and platelet count exceeds 100 * 10  9  /L. Geriatric patients and women have been shown in clinical trials to have a higher risk of developing myelosuppression.



    5.2 Myelodysplastic Syndrome



  Cases of myelodysplastic syndrome and secondary malignancies, including myeloid leukemia, have been observed.



    5.3 Pneumocystis  Pneumonia



  For treatment of newly diagnosed glioblastoma multiforme: Prophylaxis against Pneumocystis  pneumonia (PCP) is required for all patients receiving concomitant TEMODAR and radiotherapy for the 42-day regimen.



 There may be a higher occurrence of PCP when temozolomide is administered during a longer dosing regimen. However, all patients receiving temozolomide, particularly patients receiving steroids, should be observed closely for the development of PCP regardless of the regimen.



    5.4 Laboratory Tests



  For the concomitant treatment phase with RT, a complete blood count should be obtained prior to initiation of treatment and weekly during treatment.



 For the 28-day treatment cycles, a complete blood count should be obtained prior to treatment on Day 1 and on Day 22 (21 days after the first dose) of each cycle. Blood counts should be performed weekly until recovery if the ANC falls below 1.5 * 10  9  /L and the platelet count falls below 100 * 10  9  /L [see  Recommended Dosing and Dose Modification Guidelines (2.1)  ].  



    5.5 Hepatotoxicity



   Fatal and severe hepatotoxicity have been reported in patients receiving TEMODAR. Perform liver function tests at baseline, midway through the first cycle, prior to each subsequent cycle, and approximately two to four weeks after the last dose of TEMODAR.  



  Additionally, hepatitis due to hepatitis B virus (HBV) reactivation, in some cases resulting in death, has been reported. Screen patients for HBV infection before treatment initiation. Monitor patients with evidence of prior HBV infection for clinical and laboratory signs of hepatitis or HBV reactivation during and for several months following treatment with TEMODAR. Discontinue therapy for patients with evidence of active hepatitis B infection.  



    5.6 Use in Pregnancy



  TEMODAR can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Administration of TEMODAR to rats and rabbits during organogenesis at 0.38 and 0.75 times the maximum recommended human dose (75 and 150 mg/m  2  ), respectively, caused numerous fetal malformations of the external organs, soft tissues, and skeleton in both species [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ].  



    5.7 Infusion Time



  As bioequivalence has been established only when TEMODAR for Injection was given over 90 minutes, infusion over a shorter or longer period of time may result in suboptimal dosing. Additionally, the possibility of an increase in infusion-related adverse reactions cannot be ruled out.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
