<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tenex" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Adverse reactions noted with Tenex (guanfacine hydrochloride) are similar to those of other drugs of the central alpha2-adrenoreceptor agonist class: dry mouth, sedation (somnolence), weakness (asthenia), dizziness, constipation, and impotence. While the reactions are common, most are mild and tend to disappear on continued dosing.



 Skin rash with exfoliation has been reported in a few cases; although clear cause and effect relationships to Tenex could not be established, should a rash occur, Tenex should be discontinued and the patient monitored appropriately.



 In the dose-response monotherapy study described under    CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY    , the frequency of the most commonly observed adverse reactions showed a dose relationship from 0.5 to 3 mg as follows:




 AdverseReaction              Placebon=59      0.5 mgn=60        1 mgn=61         2 mgn=60         3 mgn=59       
  
 Dry Mouth                        0%               10%              10%              42%              54%         
 Somnolence                       8%               5%               10%              13%              39%         
 Asthenia                         0%               2%               3%               7%               3%          
 Dizziness                        8%               12%              2%               8%               15%         
 Headache                         8%               13%              7%               5%               3%          
 Impotence                        0%               0%               0%               7%               3%          
 Constipation                     0%               2%               0%               5%               15%         
 Fatigue                          2%               2%               5%               8%               10%         
            The percent of patients who dropped out because of adverse reactions are shown below for each dosage group.
 


                                Placebo          0.5 mg            1 mg             2 mg             3 mg         
  
 Percent dropouts                 0%              2.0%             5.0%              13%              32%         
            The most common reasons for dropouts among patients who received guanfacine were dry mouth, somnolence, dizziness, fatigue, weakness, and constipation.
 

 In the 12-week, placebo-controlled, dose-response study of guanfacine administered with 25 mg chlorthalidone at bedtime, the frequency of the most commonly observed adverse reactions showed a clear dose relationship from 0.5 to 3 mg as follows:




 AdverseReaction              Placebon=73      0.5 mgn=72        1 mgn=72         2 mgn=72         3 mgn=72       
  
 Dry Mouth                      5 (7%)           4 (5%)           6 (8%)           8 (11%)         20 (28%)       
 Somnolence                     1 (1%)           3 (4%)           0 (0%)           1 (1%)          10 (14%)       
 Asthenia                       0 (0%)           2 (3%)           0 (0%)           2 (2%)           7 (10%)       
 Dizziness                      2 (2%)           1 (1%)           3 (4%)           6 (8%)           3 (4%)        
 Headache                       3 (4%)           4 (3%)           3 (4%)           1 (1%)           2 (2%)        
 Impotence                      1 (1%)           1 (0%)           0 (0%)           1 (1%)           3 (4%)        
 Constipation                   0 (0%)           0 (0%)           0 (0%)           1 (1%)           1 (1%)        
 Fatigue                        3 (3%)           2 (3%)           2 (3%)           5 (6%)           3 (4%)        
            There were 41 premature terminations because of adverse reactions in this study. The percent of patients who dropped out and the dose at which the dropout occurred were as follows:
 


 Dose                           Placebo          0.5 mg            1 mg             2 mg             3 mg         
  
 Percent dropouts                6.9%             4.2%             3.2%             6.9%             8.3%         
            Reasons for dropouts among patients who received guanfacine were: somnolence, headache, weakness, dry mouth, dizziness, impotence, insomnia, constipation, syncope, urinary incontinence, conjunctivitis, paresthesia, and dermatitis.
 

 In a second 12-week placebo-controlled combination therapy study in which the dose could be adjusted upward to 3 mg per day in 1-mg increments at 3-week intervals, i.e., a setting more similar to ordinary clinical use, the most commonly recorded reactions were: dry mouth, 47%; constipation, 16%; fatigue, 12%; somnolence, 10%; asthenia, 6%; dizziness, 6%; headache, 4%; and insomnia, 4%.



 Reasons for dropouts among patients who received guanfacine were: somnolence, dry mouth, dizziness, impotence, constipation, confusion, depression, and palpitations.



 In the clonidine/guanfacine comparison described in    CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY    , the most common adverse reactions noted were as follows:




 AdverseReactions                            Guanfacine(n=279)                  Clonidine(n=278)            
  
 Dry Mouth                                          30%                                37%                  
 Somnolence                                         21%                                35%                  
 Dizziness                                          11%                                8%                   
 Constipation                                       10%                                5%                   
 Fatigue                                            9%                                 8%                   
 Headache                                           4%                                 4%                   
 Insomnia                                           4%                                 3%                   
         Adverse reactions occurring in 3% or less of patients in the three controlled trials of Tenex (guanfacine hydrochloride) with a diuretic were:
 

 Cardiovascular- bradycardia, palpitations, substernal pain



 Gastrointestinal- abdominal pain, diarrhea, dyspepsia, dysphagia, nausea



 CNS- amnesia, confusion, depression, insomnia, libido decrease



 ENT disorders- rhinitis, taste perversion, tinnitus



 Eye disorders- conjunctivitis, iritis, vision disturbance



 Musculoskeletal- leg cramps, hypokinesia



 Respiratory- dyspnea



 Dermatologic- dermatitis, pruritus, purpura, sweating



 Urogenital- testicular disorder, urinary incontinence



 Other- malaise, paresthesia, paresis



 Adverse reaction reports tend to decrease over time. In an open-label trial of one year's duration, 580 hypertensive subjects were given guanfacine, titrated to achieve goal blood pressure, alone (51%), with diuretic (38%), with beta blocker (3%), with diuretic plus beta blocker (6%), or with diuretic plus vasodilator (2%). The mean daily dose of guanfacine reached was 4.7 mg.




 AdverseReaction                     Incidence of adverse reactions at any time during the study  Incidence of adverse reactions at end of one year   
                                                  n = 580                            n = 580                
  
 Dry Mouth                                          60%                                15%                  
 Drowsiness                                         33%                                6%                   
 Dizziness                                          15%                                1%                   
 Constipation                                       14%                                3%                   
 Weakness                                           5%                                 1%                   
 Headache                                           4%                                0.2%                  
 Insomnia                                           5%                                 0%                   
         There were 52 (8.9%) dropouts due to adverse effects in this 1-year trial. The causes were: dry mouth (n = 20), weakness (n = 12), constipation (n = 7), somnolence (n = 3), nausea (n = 3), orthostatic hypotension (n = 2), insomnia (n = 1), rash (n = 1), nightmares (n = 1), headache (n = 1), and depression (n = 1).
 

  Postmarketing Experience   An open-label postmarketing study involving 21,718 patients was conducted to assess the safety of Tenex (guanfacine hydrochloride) 1 mg/day given at bedtime for 28 days. Tenex was administered with or without other antihypertensive agents. Adverse events reported in the postmarketing study at an incidence greater than 1% included dry mouth, dizziness, somnolence, fatigue, headache and nausea. The most commonly reported adverse events in this study were the same as those observed in controlled clinical trials.



 Less frequent, possibly Tenex-related events observed in the postmarketing study and/or reported spontaneously include:



 BODY AS A WHOLE asthenia, chest pain, edema, malaise, tremor



 CARDIOVASCULAR bradycardia, palpitations, syncope, tachycardia



 CENTRAL NERVOUS SYSTEM paresthesias, vertigo



 EYE DISORDERS blurred vision



 GASTROINTESTINAL SYSTEM abdominal pain, constipation, diarrhea, dyspepsia



 LIVER AND BILLIARY SYSTEM abnormal liver function tests



 MUSCULO-SKELETAL SYSTEM arthralgia, leg cramps, leg pain, myalgia



 PSYCHIATRIC agitation, anxiety, confusion, depression, insomnia, nervousness



 RREPRODUCTIVE SYSTEM, Male- impotence



 RESPIRATORY SYSTEM dyspnea



 SKIN AND APPENDAGES alopecia, dermatitis, exfoliative dermatitis, pruritus, rash



 SPECIAL SENSES alterations in taste



 URINARY SYSTEM nocturia, urinary frequency



 Rare, serious disorders with no definitive cause and effect relationship to Tenex have been reported spontaneously and/or in the postmarketing study. These events include acute renal failure, cardiac fibrillation, cerebrovascular accident, congestive heart failure, heart block, and myocardial infarction.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
