<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tenivac" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  The most frequent solicited injection site reaction within 0-3 days following TENIVAC was pain, reported in 78.3% of study participants 11-59 years of age and 35.3% of participants &gt;=60 years of age. (  6.1  ) 
 *  The most frequent solicited systemic reaction within 0-3 days following TENIVAC was headache, reported in 17.9% of participants, overall. (  6.1  ) 
 *  Other common (&gt;=10%) solicited adverse reactions within 0-3 days following TENIVAC were injection site redness, injection site swelling, malaise, muscle weakness and pain in joints. (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Sanofi Pasteur Inc. at 1-800-822-2463 (1-800-VACCINE) or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or http://vaers.hhs.gov  
 

 

  6.1 Data from Clinical Studies

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. The adverse reaction information from clinical trials does, however, provide a basis for identifying the adverse events that appear to be related to vaccine use and for approximating rates of those events.



 In a primary immunization study conducted in Canada, 18 participants, 8 of whom were 6 to 9 years of age and 10 of whom were 17 to 56 years of age, received three doses of TENIVAC vaccine. In four booster immunization studies conducted in either the US or Canada, TENIVAC vaccine was administered to 3,723 participants overall, ranging in age from 11 to 93 years.



 In one of these studies, a US multi-center booster immunization study (TDC01), 2,250 adolescents and adults ages 11-59 years of age received TENIVAC vaccine in an open-label design and adults 60 years of age and over were randomized to receive either TENIVAC vaccine (N = 700) or DECAVAC vaccine (US licensed Td manufactured by Sanofi Pasteur Inc.) (N = 701). Vaccine assignment for participants &gt;=60 years of age was unblinded to pharmacists and vaccination nurses, but was blinded to other study personnel and participants. Among participants who received TENIVAC vaccine, overall, 80.4% were Caucasian, 3.3% Black, 5.1% Hispanic, 4.5% Asian and 6.6% other races. Among participants &gt;=60 years of age, the racial distribution was similar for the TENIVAC vaccine and DECAVAC vaccine groups. Among participants who received TENIVAC vaccine, the proportion of participants who were female varied by age group (44.4% of participants 11-18 years of age, 70.1% of participants 19-59 years of age and 62.4% of participants &gt;=60 years of age). Among participants &gt;=60 years of age who received DECAVAC vaccine, 57.6% were female. Nearly all (99.8%) enrolled participants and all participants in the per-protocol immunogenicity population had a reported or documented history of previous immunization against tetanus and diphtheria and, by report, had not received a vaccine containing tetanus or diphtheria toxoid within 5 years prior to enrollment.



 In the US multi-center booster immunization study, solicited injection site reactions and systemic adverse events were monitored on diary cards for a subset of participants 11-59 years of age and for all participants &gt;=60 years of age. The incidence and severity of solicited injection site reactions and selected solicited systemic adverse events that occurred within 3 days following vaccination are shown in Table 2.



 Table 2: Frequency and Severity of Selected Solicited Adverse Events Within 0-3 Days Following TENIVAC Vaccine or DECAVAC Vaccine in a US Study 
                           TENIVAC Vaccine      DECAVAC Vaccine     
                         Adolescents11 to 18 yearsN = 491-492%  Adults19 to 59 yearsN = 247%  Adults&gt;=60 yearsN = 688-695%  Adults&gt;=60 yearsN = 686-693%   
  
   Injection Site Adverse Reactions     
   Pain                   
   Any                          80.1                 74.9                  35.3                  29.4           
   Moderate                     15.0                 18.2                   2.9                   2.3           
   Severe                         0.2                  0.4                  0.6                   0.7           
   Redness                
   Any                          25.6                 15.8                  18.1                  18.0           
   &gt;=35 mm to &lt;50 mm              1.2                  2.4                  0.7                   1.3           
   &gt;=50 mm                        0.4                  0.4                  2.3                   1.9           
   Swelling               
   Any                           15.0                 17.0                  12.1                  13.0          
   &gt;=35 mm to &lt;50 mm              1.2                  2.8                  1.0                   1.3           
   &gt;=50 mm                        1.8                  2.8                  1.7                   1.3           
   Systemic Adverse Events     
   Fever                  
   &gt;=37.5 degrees C               4.3                  5.7                  2.5                   3.8           
   &gt;=38.0 degrees C to &lt;39 degrees C           0.8                  1.6                  0.6                   0.9           
   &gt;=39 degrees C                 0.0                  0.0                  0.1                   0.1           
   Headache               
   Any                          23.0                 25.1                  11.7                  10.8           
   Moderate                       4.3                  7.3                  1.6                   1.4           
   Severe                         0.6                  0.8                  0.0                   0.3           
   Muscle Weakness        
   Any                          32.3                 17.4                   4.9                   5.9           
   Moderate                       7.3                  3.2                  1.3                   1.0           
   Severe                         0.6                  0.4                  0.1                   0.1           
   Malaise                
   Any                          14.5                 17.0                   8.9                   8.8           
   Moderate                       3.5                  3.2                  2.4                   1.2           
   Severe                         0.8                  0.4                  0.1                   0.4           
   Pain in Joints         
   Any                          15.7                 10.9                   8.5                   7.4           
   Moderate                       2.8                  1.6                  2.2                   1.4           
   Severe                         0.6                  0.4                  0.1                   0.0           
           In the US booster immunization study, among participants &gt;=60 years of age, 7 (1.0%) participants in the TENIVAC vaccine group and 10 (1.4%) participants in the DECAVAC vaccine group experienced a serious adverse event within 30 days following vaccination. During this period, 2 (0.3%) participants 19-59 years of age and no participants 11-18 years of age experienced a serious adverse event following TENIVAC vaccine. Serious adverse events within 30 days following TENIVAC vaccine included localized infection, asthma, colonic polyp, cellulitis, angina pectoris, hip and wrist fracture, cholecystitis, chest pain and cerebrovascular accident.
 

 There were five deaths reported during the study. All of the reported deaths were in participants &gt;=60 years of age and occurred &gt;30 days post-vaccination: three in the TENIVAC vaccine group (cardiopulmonary arrest; myocardial infarction and septic shock; and unknown cause) and two in the DECAVAC vaccine group (myocardial infarction and congestive heart failure; and liver cancer).



 In the primary immunization study (N = 18) in which serious adverse events were monitored for 3 days following each vaccination and in three other booster immunization studies in which serious adverse events were monitored for either four days (N = 347) or one month (N = 426) following vaccination, no serious adverse events were reported.



   6.2 Data from Post-marketing Experience

  The following adverse events have been spontaneously reported during the post-marketing use of TENIVAC vaccine. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to vaccine exposure.



 The following adverse events were included based on severity, frequency of reporting or the strength of causal association to TENIVAC vaccine:



 *   Blood and lymphatic system disorders Lymphadenopathy 
 *   Immune system disorders Allergic reactions (such as erythematous rash, maculopapular rash, urticaria and pruritus);anaphylactic reaction (bronchopasm and angioedema). 
 *   Nervous system disorders Paresthesia, dizziness, syncopeGuillain Barre syndrome 
 *   Gastrointestinal disorders Vomiting 
 *   Musculoskeletal, connective tissue and bone disorders Myalgia, pain in extremities 
 *   General disorders and administration site conditions Injection site reactions (including inflammation, mass, edema, induration, warmth, pruritus, cellulitis, discomfort)Fatigue, edema peripheral 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  The tip caps of the prefilled syringes may contain natural rubber latex which may cause allergic reactions in latex sensitive individuals. (  5.2  ) 
 *  More frequent administration of TENIVAC than described in Dosage and Administration (  2.1  ,  2.2  ,  2.3  ,  2.4  ) may be associated with increased incidence and severity of adverse reactions. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Persons who experienced an Arthus-type hypersensitivity reaction following a prior dose of a tetanus toxoid-containing vaccine should not receive TENIVAC more frequently than every 10 years, even for tetanus prophylaxis as part of wound management. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Carefully consider benefits and risks before administering TENIVAC to persons with a history of Guillain-Barre syndrome within 6 weeks of a previous tetanus toxoid-containing vaccine. (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Management of Acute Allergic Reactions



  Epinephrine hydrochloride solution (1:1,000) and other appropriate agents and equipment must be available for immediate use in case an anaphylactic or acute hypersensitivity reaction occurs.



    5.2 Latex



   The tip caps of the TENIVAC prefilled syringes may contain natural rubber latex, which may cause allergic reactions in latex sensitive individuals.  



    5.3 Frequency of Administration



  More frequent doses of TENIVAC vaccine than described in Section 2, Dosage and Administration, may be associated with increased incidence and severity of adverse reactions. [See   Dosage and Administration (2.1  ,  2.2  ,  2.3  ,  2.4)    .]



    5.4 Arthus Reactions



  Persons who experienced an Arthus-type hypersensitivity reaction following a prior dose of a tetanus toxoid-containing vaccine usually have high serum tetanus antitoxin levels and should not receive TENIVAC vaccine more frequently than every 10 years, even for tetanus prophylaxis as part of wound management.



    5.5 Guillain-Barre Syndrome and Brachial Neuritis



  A review by the Institute of Medicine found evidence for a causal relation between tetanus toxoid and both brachial neuritis and Guillian-Barre syndrome. (  2  ) If Guillain-Barre syndrome occurred within 6 weeks of receipt of prior vaccine containing tetanus toxoid, the decision to give TENIVAC vaccine or any vaccine containing tetanus toxoid should be based on careful consideration of the potential benefits and possible risks.



    5.6 Limitations of Vaccine Effectiveness



  Vaccination with TENIVAC vaccine may not protect all individuals.



    5.7 Altered Immunocompetence



  If TENIVAC vaccine is administered to immunocompromised persons, including persons receiving immunosuppressive therapy, the expected immune response may not be obtained. [See   Drug Interactions (7.3)    .]
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
