<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="teruflex" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S1">       5.   WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  
 

 5.1.   Rx ONLY



 5.2.   Do not use unless solutions are clear and free from particulates.



 5.3.   Always inspect the blood bag set for leaks before use.



 5.4.   Avoid excessive heat and direct sunlight. Protect from freezing.



 5.5.   Recommended storage conditions: Room Temperature (15-30  o  C/59-86  o  F).



 5.6.   It is normal to have condensation in the blister packaging. If the amount of moisture is greater than expected, check for leaks from the fluid-filled components of the blood bag set.



 5.7.   Use aseptic techniques.



 5.8.   Do not use a dielectric tube sealer to seal the tubing while the needle is connected to the donor's body unless it is approved for such a purpose.



 5.9.   Do not touch needle after removing the needle cover.



  5.10.   Assure that the White Clamp below the pouch is closed prior to initiating phlebotomy.  
 

 5.11    Do not collect donor test samples until the tubing between the "Y" and the diversion pouch is permanently sealed.



 5.12    Discard the Diversion Blood Sampling Arm and phlebotomy needle/donor tubing according to institutional procedures.



 5.13.   The AGELESS (oxygen absorber packet, Mitsubishi Gas Chemical) contained in this package absorbs oxygen and generates heat on removal. Do not open and handle it with care.



 5.14.   Dispose of the AGELESS packet with the blister tray.



 5.15.   Do not dispose the AGELESS packet with wastes containing volatile or flammable materials.



 5.16.   Due to possible exposure to infectious agents in the handling of blood, take adequate precautions at all times to prevent exposure to and transmission of such agents. Follow your institution's standard operating procedures.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
