<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tetracycline" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      ADVERSE REACTIONS  

    Gastrointestinal:  anorexia, nausea, epigastric distress, vomiting, diarrhea, glossitis, black hairy tongue, dysphagia, enterocolitis, and inflammatory lesions (with monilial overgrowth) in the anogenital region.



 Rare instances of esophagitis and esophageal ulceration have been reported in patients receiving particularly the capsule and also the tablet forms of tetracyclines.



 Most of the patients were reported to have taken medication immediately before going to bed (see    DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION    ).



   Teeth:  permanent discoloration of teeth may be caused during tooth development. Enamel hypoplasia has also been reported (see    WARNINGS    ).



   Skin:  maculopapular and erythrematous rashes. Exfoliative dermatitis has been reported but is uncommon. Onycholysis and discoloration of the nails have been reported rarely. Photosensitivity is discussed in    WARNINGS    .



   Renal Toxicity:  rise in BUN has been reported and is apparently dose related.



   Liver:  hepatotoxicity and liver failure have been observed in patients receiving large doses of tetracycline and in tetracycline-treated patients with renal impairment.



   Hypersensitivity Reactions:  urticaria, angioneurotic edema, anaphylaxis, anaphylactoid purpura, pericarditis, exacerbation of systemic lupus erythematosus, and serum sickness-like reactions, as fever, rash, and arthralgia.



   Blood:  hemolytic anemia, thrombocytopenia, thrombocytopenic purpura, neutropenia and eosinophilia have been reported.



   Other:  bulging fontanels in infants and intracranial pressure in adults (see    PRECAUTIONS-General    ).



 When given over prolonged periods, tetracyclines have been reported to produce brown-black microscopic discoloration of thyroid glands. No abnormalities of thyroid function studies are known to occur.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
