<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tetrabenazine" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following risks are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *    Depression and suicidality [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *    Akathisia, restlessness and agitation [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *    Parkinsonism [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
 *    Dysphagia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]  
 *    Sedation and somnolence [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions are (&gt;10% and at least 5% greater than placebo): Sedation/somnolence, fatigue, insomnia, depression, akathisia, anxiety, nausea. (  6  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Valeant Pharmaceuticals North America LLC at 1-800-321-4576 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Commonly Observed Adverse Reactions in Controlled Clinical Trials

  The most common adverse reactions from Table 1 occurring in over 10% of tetrabenazine-treated patients, and at least 5% greater than placebo, were sedation/somnolence (31%), fatigue (22%), insomnia (22%), depression (19%), akathisia (19%), and nausea (13%).



   6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 During its development, tetrabenazine tablets were administered to 773 unique subjects and patients. The conditions and duration of exposure to tetrabenazine tablets varied greatly, and included single and multiple dose clinical pharmacology studies in healthy volunteers (n=259) and open-label (n=529) and double-blind studies (n=84) in patients.



 In a randomized, 12-week, placebo-controlled clinical trial of HD subjects, adverse reactions (ARs) were more common in the tetrabenazine tablets group than in the placebo group. Forty-nine of 54 (91%) patients who received tetrabenazine tablets experienced one or more ARs at any time during the study. The ARs most commonly reported (over 10%, and at least 5% greater than placebo) were sedation/somnolence (31% vs. 3% on placebo), fatigue (22% vs. 13% on placebo), insomnia (22% vs. 0% on placebo), depression (19% vs. 0% on placebo), akathisia (19% vs. 0% on placebo), and nausea (13% vs. 7% on placebo).



     Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=4% Patients  



 The number and percentage of the most commonly reported AEs that occurred at any time during the study in &gt;=4% of tetrabenazine-treated patients, and with a greater frequency than in placebo-treated patients, are presented in Table 1 in decreasing order of frequency within body systems for the tetrabenazine tablets group.



 Table 1. Treatment Emergent Adverse Reactions in Patients Treated with Tetrabenazine Tablets and with a Greater Frequency than Placebo in the 12-Week, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trial of Tetrabenazine Tablets 
   Body System                   AE Term                         Tetrabenazine Tablets    n = 54    n (%)      Placebo    n = 30    n (%)     
  
  PSYCHIATRIC DISODERS          Sedation/somnolence             17 (31%)                  1 (3%)            
  Insomnia                      12 (22%)                        -                         
  Depression                    10 (19%)                        -                         
  Anxiety/anxiety aggravated    8 (15%)                         1 (3%)                    
  Irritability                  5 (9%)                          1 (3%)                    
  Appetite decreased            2 (4%)                          -                         
  Obsessive reaction            2 (4%)                          -                         
  CENTRAL &amp; PERIPHERAL NERVOUS SYSTEM    Akathisia                       10 (19%)                  -                 
  Balance difficulty            5 (9%)                          -                         
  Parkinsonism/bradykinesia     5 (9%)                          -                         
  Dizziness                     2 (4%)                          -                         
  Dysarthria                    2 (4%)                          -                         
  Gait unsteady                 2 (4%)                          -                         
  Headache                      2 (4%)                          1 (3%)                    
  GASTROINTESTINAL SYSTEM DISORDERS    Nausea                          7 (13%)                   2 (7%)            
  Vomiting                      3 (6%)                          1 (3%)                    
  BODY AS A WHOLE - GENERAL     Fatigue                         12 (22%)                  4 (13%)           
  Fall                          8 (15%)                         4 (13%)                   
  Laceration (head)             3 (6%)                          -                         
  Ecchymosis                    3 (6%)                          -                         
  RESPIRATORY SYSTEM DISORDERS    Upper respiratory tract infection    6 (11%)                   2 (7%)            
  Shortness of breath           2 (4%)                          -                         
  Bronchitis                    2 (4%)                          -                         
  URINARY SYSTEM DISORDERS      Dysuria                         2 (4%)                    -                 
          Dose escalation was discontinued or dosage of study drug was reduced because of one or more ARs in 28 of 54 (52%) patients randomized to tetrabenazine tablets. These ARs consisted of sedation (15), akathisia (7), parkinsonism (4), depression (3), anxiety (2), fatigue (1) and diarrhea (1). Some patients had more than one AR and are, therefore, counted more than once.
 

     Adverse Reactions Due to Extrapyramidal Symptoms (EPS)  



 The following table describes the incidence of events considered to be extrapyramidal adverse reactions.



 Table 2. Treatment Emergent EPS in Patients Treated with Tetrabenazine Tablets Occurring with a Greater Frequency than Placebo in the 12-Week, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trial of Tetrabenazine Tablets 
   Event                       Patient (%) reporting event     
   Tetrabenazine Tablets    n = 54      Placebo    n = 30          
  
  AkathisiaPatients with the following adverse event preferred terms were counted in this category: akathisia, hyperkinesia, restlessness.    10 (19%)                    0                        
  Extrapyramidal eventPatients with the following adverse event preferred terms were counted in this category: bradykinesia, parkinsonism, extrapyramidal disorder, hypertonia.    8 (15%)                     0                        
  Any extrapyramidal event    18 (33%)                    0                        
         Patients may have had events in more than one category.
 

   6.3 Laboratory Tests

  No clinically significant changes in laboratory parameters were reported in clinical trials with tetrabenazine tablets. In controlled clinical trials, tetrabenazine tablets caused a small mean increase in alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST), laboratory values as compared to placebo.



   6.4 Vital Signs

  In controlled clinical trials, tetrabenazine tablets did not affect blood pressure, pulse, and body weight. Orthostatic blood pressure was not consistently measured in the tetrabenazine tablets clinical trials.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING:  DEPRESSION AND SUICIDALITY

    WARNING:  DEPRESSION AND SUICIDALITY  

    Tetrabenazine tablets can increase the risk of depression and suicidal thoughts and behavior (suicidality) in patients with Huntington's disease. Anyone considering the use of tetrabenazine tablets must balance the risks of depression and suicidality with the clinical need for control of choreiform movements. Close observation of patients for the emergence or worsening of depression, suicidality, or unusual changes in behavior should accompany therapy. Patients, their caregivers, and families should be informed of the risk of depression and suicidality and should be instructed to report behaviors of concern promptly to the treating physician.   



   Particular caution should be exercised in treating patients with a history of depression or prior suicide attempts or ideation, which are increased in frequency in Huntington's disease. Tetrabenazine tablets are contraindicated in patients who are actively suicidal, and in patients with untreated or inadequately treated depression   [see   Contraindications (4)  , and   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  .  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: DEPRESSION AND SUICIDALITY    



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  .  



 *   Increases the risk of depression and suicidal thoughts and behavior (suicidality) in patients with Huntington's disease. (5.3) 
 *   Balance risks of depression and suicidality with the clinical need for control of choreiform movements when considering the use of tetrabenazine tablets. (5.1) 
 *   Monitor patients for the emergence or worsening of depression, suicidality, or unusual changes in behavior. (5.3) 
 *   Inform patients, caregivers and families of the risk of depression and suicidality and instruct to report behaviors of concern promptly to the treating physician. (5.3) 
 *   Exercise caution when treating patients with a history of depression or prior suicide attempts or ideation. (5.3) 
 *   Tetrabenazine tablets are contraindicated in patients who are actively suicidal, and in patients with untreated or inadequately treated depression. (4, 5.3) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Periodically reevaluate the benefit of tetrabenazine tablets and potential for adverse effects such as worsening mood, cognition, rigidity, and functional capacity. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Do not exceed 50 mg/day and the maximum single dose should not exceed 25 mg if administered in conjunction with a strong CYP2D6 inhibitor (e.g., fluoxetine, paroxetine) (  5.3  ,  7.1  ) 
 *    Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS). (  5.5  ,  7.6  ) Discontinue tetrabenazine tablets if this occurs. (  5.5  ,  7.6  ) 
 *    Restlessness, agitation, akathisia and parkinsonism. Reduce dose or discontinue tetrabenazine tablets if this occurs. (  5.6  ,  5.7  ) 
 *    Dysphagia and aspiration pneumonia. Monitor for dysphagia. (  5.8  ) 
 *    Sedation/Somnolence. May impair the patient's ability to drive or operate complex machinery. (  5.9  ) 
 *    Alcohol or other sedating drugs can worsen sedation and somnolence. (  5.10  ,  7.4  ) 
 *    QTc prolongation. Do not prescribe in combination with other drugs that prolong QTc. (  5.11  ,  7.5  ,  7.6  ,  12.2  ) 
 *    Exaggerates extrapyramidal disorders when used with drugs that reduce or antagonize dopamine. Discontinue tetrabenazine tablets if this occurs. (  5.15  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Clinical Worsening and Adverse Effects



  Huntington's disease is a progressive disorder characterized by changes in mood, cognition, chorea, rigidity, and functional capacity over time. In a 12-week controlled trial, tetrabenazine tablets were also shown to cause slight worsening in mood, cognition, rigidity, and functional capacity. Whether these effects persist, resolve, or worsen with continued treatment is unknown. Therefore, proper use of the drug requires attention to all facets of the underlying disease process over time.



 Prescribers should periodically re-evaluate the need for tetrabenazine tablets in their patients by assessing the beneficial effect on chorea and possible adverse effects, including depression, cognitive decline, parkinsonism, dysphagia, sedation/somnolence, akathisia, restlessness and disability. It may be difficult to distinguish between drug-induced side-effects and progression of the underlying disease; decreasing the dose or stopping the drug may help the clinician distinguish between the two possibilities. In some patients, underlying chorea itself may improve over time, decreasing the need for tetrabenazine tablets.



    5.2 Dosing of Tetrabenazine Tablets



  Proper dosing of tetrabenazine tablets involves titration of therapy to determine an individualized dose for each patient. When first prescribed, tetrabenazine tablets therapy should be titrated slowly over several weeks to allow the identification of a dose that both reduces chorea and is tolerated [see  Dosage and Administration (2.1)  ].  Some adverse effects such as depression, fatigue, insomnia, sedation/somnolence, parkinsonism and akathisia may be dose-dependent and may resolve or lessen with dosage adjustment or specific treatment. If the adverse effect does not resolve or decrease, consider discontinuing tetrabenazine tablets.



 Doses above 50 mg should not be given without CYP2D6 genotyping patients to determine if they are poor metabolizers [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ,  Use in Specific Populations (8.8)  , and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ].  



    5.3 Risk of Depression and Suicidality



  Patients with Huntington's disease are at increased risk for depression, suicidal ideation or behaviors (suicidality). Tetrabenazine tablets increase the risk for suicidality in patients with HD. All patients treated with tetrabenazine tablets should be observed for new or worsening depression or suicidality. If depression or suicidality does not resolve, consider discontinuing treatment with tetrabenazine tablets.



 In a 12-week, double-blind placebo-controlled study in patients with chorea associated with Huntington's disease, 10 of 54 patients (19%) treated with tetrabenazine tablets were reported to have an adverse event of depression or worsening depression compared to none of the 30 placebo-treated patients. In two open-label studies (in one study, 29 patients received tetrabenazine tablets for up to 48 weeks; in the second study, 75 patients received tetrabenazine tablets for up to 80 weeks), the rate of depression/worsening depression was 35%.



 In all of the HD chorea studies of tetrabenazine tablets (n=187), one patient committed suicide, one attempted suicide, and six had suicidal ideation.



 Clinicians should be alert to the heightened risk of suicide in patients with Huntington's disease regardless of depression indices. Reported rates of completed suicide among individuals with Huntington's disease ranged from 3-13% and over 25% of patients attempt suicide at some point in their illness.



 Patients, their caregivers, and families should be informed of the risks of depression, worsening depression, and suicidality associated with tetrabenazine tablets and should be instructed to report behaviors of concern promptly to the treating physician. Patients with HD who express suicidal ideation should be evaluated immediately.



    5.4 Laboratory Tests



  Before prescribing a daily dose of tetrabenazine tablets that is greater than 50 mg per day, patients should be genotyped to determine if they express the drug metabolizing enzyme, CYP2D6. CYP2D6 testing is necessary to determine whether patients are poor metabolizers (PMs), extensive (EMs) or intermediate metabolizers (IMs) of tetrabenazine tablets.



 Patients who are PMs of tetrabenazine tablets will have substantially higher levels of the primary drug metabolites (about 3-fold for alpha-HTBZ and 9-fold for beta-HTBZ) than patients who are EMs. The dosage should be adjusted according to a patient's CYP2D6 metabolizer status. In patients who are identified as CYP2D6 PMs, the maximum recommended total daily dose is 50 mg and the maximum recommended single dose is 25 mg [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ,  Use in Specific Populations (8.8)  , and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ].  



    5.5 Risk of Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS)



  A potentially fatal symptom complex sometimes referred to as Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS) has been reported in association with tetrabenazine tablets and other drugs that reduce dopaminergic transmission [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.12)  ,  Drug Interactions (7.6)  ].  Clinical manifestations of NMS are hyperpyrexia, muscle rigidity, altered mental status, and evidence of autonomic instability (irregular pulse or blood pressure, tachycardia, diaphoresis, and cardiac dysrhythmia). Additional signs may include elevated creatinine phosphokinase, myoglobinuria, rhabdomyolysis, and acute renal failure. The diagnosis of NMS can be complicated; other serious medical illness (e.g., pneumonia, systemic infection), and untreated or inadequately treated extrapyramidal disorders can present with similar signs and symptoms. Other important considerations in the differential diagnosis include central anticholinergic toxicity, heat stroke, drug fever, and primary central nervous system pathology.



 The management of NMS should include (1) immediate discontinuation of tetrabenazine tablets and other drugs not essential to concurrent therapy; (2) intensive symptomatic treatment and medical monitoring; and (3) treatment of any concomitant serious medical problems for which specific treatments are available. There is no general agreement about specific pharmacological treatment regimens for NMS.



 Recurrence of NMS has been reported. If treatment with tetrabenazine tablets is needed after recovery from NMS, patients should be monitored for signs of recurrence.



    5.6 Risk of Akathisia, Restlessness, and Agitation



  In a 12-week, double-blind, placebo-controlled study in patients with chorea associated with HD, akathisia was observed in 10 (19%) of tetrabenazine-treated patients and 0% of placebo-treated patients. In an 80-week open-label study, akathisia was observed in 20% of tetrabenazine-treated patients. Akathisia was not observed in a 48-week open-label study. Patients receiving tetrabenazine tablets should be monitored for the presence of akathisia. Patients receiving tetrabenazine tablets should also be monitored for signs and symptoms of restlessness and agitation, as these may be indicators of developing akathisia. If a patient develops akathisia, the tetrabenazine tablets dose should be reduced; however, some patients may require discontinuation of therapy.



    5.7 Risk of Parkinsonism



  Tetrabenazine tablets can cause parkinsonism. In a 12-week double-blind, placebo-controlled study in patients with chorea associated with HD, symptoms suggestive of parkinsonism (i.e., bradykinesia, hypertonia and rigidity) were observed in 15% of tetrabenazine-treated patients compared to 0% of placebo-treated patients. In 48-week and 80-week open-label studies, symptoms suggestive of parkinsonism were observed in 10% and 3% of tetrabenazine-treated patients, respectively. Because rigidity can develop as part of the underlying disease process in Huntington's disease, it may be difficult to distinguish between this drug-induced side-effect and progression of the underlying disease process. Drug-induced parkinsonism has the potential to cause more functional disability than untreated chorea for some patients with Huntington's disease. If a patient develops parkinsonism during treatment with tetrabenazine tablets, dose reduction should be considered; in some patients, discontinuation of therapy may be necessary.



    5.8 Risk of Dysphagia



  Dysphagia is a component of HD. However, drugs that reduce dopaminergic transmission have been associated with esophageal dysmotility and dysphagia. Dysphagia may be associated with aspiration pneumonia. In a 12-week, double-blind, placebo-controlled study in patients with chorea associated with HD, dysphagia was observed in 4% of tetrabenazine-treated patients and 3% of placebo-treated patients. In 48-week and 80-week open-label studies, dysphagia was observed in 10% and 8% of tetrabenazine-treated patients, respectively. Some of the cases of dysphagia were associated with aspiration pneumonia. Whether these events were related to treatment is unknown.



    5.9 Risk of Sedation and Somnolence



  Sedation is the most common dose-limiting adverse effect of tetrabenazine tablets. In a 12-week, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial in patients with chorea associated with HD, sedation/somnolence occurred in 17/54 (31%) tetrabenazine-treated patients and in 1 (3%) placebo-treated patient. Sedation was the reason upward titration of tetrabenazine tablets was stopped and/or the dose of tetrabenazine tablets was decreased in 15/54 (28%) patients. In all but one case, decreasing the dose of tetrabenazine tablets resulted in decreased sedation. In 48-week and 80-week open-label studies, sedation/somnolence occurred in 17% and 57% of tetrabenazine-treated patients, respectively. In some patients, sedation occurred at doses that were lower than recommended doses.



 Patients should not perform activities requiring mental alertness to maintain the safety of themselves or others, such as operating a motor vehicle or operating hazardous machinery, until they are on a maintenance dose of tetrabenazine tablets and know how the drug affects them.



    5.10 Interaction with Alcohol



  Patients should be advised that the concomitant use of alcohol or other sedating drugs may have additive effects and worsen sedation and somnolence [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  and  Drug Interactions (7.4)  ].  



    5.11 Risk of QTc Prolongation



  Tetrabenazine tablets causes a small increase (about 8 msec) in the corrected QT (QTc) interval. QT prolongation can lead to development of torsade de pointes-type ventricular tachycardia with the risk increasing as the degree of prolongation increases [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)  ].  The use of tetrabenazine tablets should be avoided in combination with other drugs that are known to prolong QTc, including antipsychotic medications (e.g., chlorpromazine, haloperidol, thioridazine, ziprasidone), antibiotics (e.g., moxifloxacin), Class 1A (e.g., quinidine, procainamide), and Class III (e.g., amiodarone, sotalol) antiarrhythmic medications or any other medications known to prolong the QTc interval [see Drug Interactions (  7.5  ,  7.6  ) and  Use in Specific Populations (8.9)  ].  



 Tetrabenazine tablets should also be avoided in patients with congenital long QT syndrome and in patients with a history of cardiac arrhythmias. Certain circumstances may increase the risk of the occurrence of torsade de pointes and/or sudden death in association with the use of drugs that prolong the QTc interval, including (1) bradycardia; (2) hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia; (3) concomitant use of other drugs that prolong the QTc interval; and (4) presence of congenital prolongation of the QT interval [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.9)  ].  



    5.12 Concomitant Use of Neuroleptic Drugs, Reserpine and MAOIs



   Neuroleptic Drugs  



 Patients taking neuroleptic (antipsychotic) drugs (e.g., chlorpromazine, haloperidol, olanzapine, risperidone, thioridazine, ziprasidone) were excluded from clinical studies during the tetrabenazine tablets development program. Adverse reactions associated with tetrabenazine tablets, such as QTc prolongation, NMS, and extrapyramidal disorders, may be exaggerated by concomitant use of dopamine antagonists [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  ,  5.11  ), Drug Interactions (  7.5  ,  7.6  ), and  Use in Specific Populations (8.9)  ].  



  Reserpine  



 Reserpine binds irreversibly to VMAT2, and the duration of its effect is several days. The physician should wait for chorea to reemerge before administering tetrabenazine tablets to avoid overdosage and major depletion of serotonin and norepinephrine in the CNS. At least 20 days should elapse after stopping reserpine before starting tetrabenazine tablets. Tetrabenazine tablets and reserpine should not be used concomitantly [see  Contraindications (4)  and  Drug Interactions (7.2)  ].  



  Monoamine Oxidase Inhibitors (MAOIs)  



 Tetrabenazine tablets are contraindicated in patients taking MAOIs. Tetrabenazine tablets should not be used in combination with an MAOI, or within a minimum of 14 days of discontinuing therapy with an MAOI [see  Contraindications (4)  and  Drug Interactions (7.3)  ].  



    5.13 Risk of Hypotension and Orthostatic Hypotension



  Tetrabenazine tablets induced postural dizziness in healthy volunteers receiving single doses of 25 or 50 mg. One subject had syncope and one subject with postural dizziness had documented orthostasis. Dizziness occurred in 4% of tetrabenazine-treated patients (vs. none on placebo) in the 12-week controlled trial; however, blood pressure was not measured during these events. Monitoring of vital signs on standing should be considered in patients who are vulnerable to hypotension.



    5.14 Risk of Hyperprolactinemia



  Tetrabenazine tablets elevates serum prolactin concentrations in humans. Following administration of 25 mg to healthy volunteers, peak plasma prolactin levels increased 4- to 5-fold. Tissue culture experiments indicate that approximately one third of human breast cancers are prolactin-dependent in vitro  , a factor of potential importance if tetrabenazine tablets are being considered for a patient with previously detected breast cancer. Although amenorrhea, galactorrhea, gynecomastia and impotence can be caused by elevated serum prolactin concentrations, the clinical significance of elevated serum prolactin concentrations for most patients is unknown. Chronic increase in serum prolactin levels (although not evaluated in the tetrabenazine tablets development program) has been associated with low levels of estrogen and increased risk of osteoporosis. If there is a clinical suspicion of symptomatic hyperprolactinemia, appropriate laboratory testing should be done and consideration should be given to discontinuation of tetrabenazine tablets.



    5.15 Risk of Tardive Dyskinesia (TD)



  A potentially irreversible syndrome of involuntary, dyskinetic movements may develop in patients treated with neuroleptic drugs. In an animal model of orofacial dyskinesias, acute administration of reserpine, a monoamine depletor, has been shown to produce vacuous chewing in rats. Although the pathophysiology of tardive dyskinesia remains incompletely understood, the most commonly accepted hypothesis of the mechanism is that prolonged post-synaptic dopamine receptor blockade leads to supersensitivity to dopamine. Neither reserpine nor tetrabenazine tablets, which are dopamine depletors, have been reported to cause clear tardive dyskinesia in humans, but as pre-synaptic dopamine depletion could theoretically lead to supersensitivity to dopamine, and tetrabenazine tablets can cause the extrapyramidal symptoms also known to be associated with neuroleptics (e.g., parkinsonism and akathisia), physicians should be aware of the possible risk of tardive dyskinesia. If signs and symptoms of TD appear in a patient treated with tetrabenazine tablets, drug discontinuation should be considered.



    5.16 Use in Patients with Concomitant Illnesses



  Clinical experience with tetrabenazine tablets in patients with systemic illnesses is limited.



  Depression and Suicidality  



 Tetrabenazine tablets may increase the risk for depression or suicidality in patients with a history of depression or suicidal behavior or in patients with diseases, conditions, or treatments that cause depression or suicidality. Tetrabenazine tablets are contraindicated in patients with untreated or inadequately treated depression or who are actively suicidal [see  Contraindications (4)  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  , and  Use in Specific Populations (8.7)  ].  



  Hepatic Disease  



 Tetrabenazine tablets are contraindicated in patients with hepatic impairment [see  Dosage and Administration (2.4)  ,  Contraindications (4)  ,  Use in Specific Populations (8.6)  , and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ].  



  Heart Disease  



 Tetrabenazine tablets have not been evaluated in patients with a recent history of myocardial infarction or unstable heart disease. Patients with these diagnoses were excluded from premarketing clinical trials.



    5.17 Binding to Melanin-Containing Tissues



  Since tetrabenazine tablets or its metabolites bind to melanin-containing tissues, it could accumulate in these tissues over time. This raises the possibility that tetrabenazine tablets may cause toxicity in these tissues after extended use. Neither ophthalmologic nor microscopic examination of the eye was conducted in the chronic toxicity study in dogs. Ophthalmologic monitoring in humans was inadequate to exclude the possibility of injury occurring after long-term exposure.



 The clinical relevance of tetrabenazine binding to melanin-containing tissues is unknown. Although there are no specific recommendations for periodic ophthalmologic monitoring, prescribers should be aware of the possibility of long-term ophthalmologic effects [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)  ].  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
