<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tetracaine" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious ocular adverse reactions are described elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Corneal injury with Intracameral Use [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Corneal Toxicity [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Corneal Injury due to Insensitivity [  See Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
    The following adverse reactions have been identified following use of Tetracaine Hydrochloride Ophthalmic Solution 0.5%.  Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.
 

   Ocular Adverse Reactions  Transient stinging, burning, and conjunctival redness, eye irritation, eye pain, ocular discomfort.



   EXCERPT:   Ocular adverse events: stinging, burning, conjunctival redness (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Alcon Laboratories, Inc., at 1-800-757-9195 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.   
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



     EXCERPT:    *  Do not use intracamerally since use may damage corneal endothelial cells (  5.1  ) 
 *  Prolonged use or abuse may lead to corneal epithelial toxicity and may manifest as epithelial defects which may progress to permanent corneal damage. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Patients should not touch the eye for at least 10-20 minutes after using anesthetic as accidental injuries can occur due to insensitivity of the eye. (  5.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Corneal injury with Intracameral Use



  Not for injection or intraocular use. Do not use intracamerally because use of Tetracaine   Hydrochloride Ophthalmic Solution 0.5% may lead to damage of the corneal endothelial cells.



    5.2 Corneal Toxicity



  Prolonged use or abuse may lead to corneal epithelial toxicity and may manifest as epithelial defects which may progress to permanent corneal damage.



    5.3 Corneal Injury due to Insensitivity



  Patients should not touch the eye for at least 10-20 minutes after using anesthetic as accidental injuries can occur due to insensitivity of the eye.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
