<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="theracys" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The most common adverse reactions observed with TheraCys treatment at a rate &gt; 10% were transient dysuria, urinary frequency and urgency, malaise, hematuria, fever, chills, cystitis, and mild nausea.



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions observed with TheraCys treatment at a rate &gt; 10% were transient dysuria, urinary frequency and urgency, malaise, hematuria, fever, chills, cystitis, and mild nausea.



 Symptoms of bladder irritability were reported in approximately 50% of patients receiving TheraCys, typically beginning 4-6 hours after instillation and lasting 24-72 hours. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pharmacovigilance Department, Sanofi Pasteur Inc. at 1-800-822-2463 (1-800-VACCINE) or MEDWATCH at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a medicinal product cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another medicinal product and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Administration of TheraCys causes an inflammatory response in the bladder, thus requiring careful patient monitoring. Symptoms of bladder irritability are reported in approximately 50% of patients receiving TheraCys and typically begin 4-6 hours after instillation and last 24-72 hours. The irritative reactions usually are seen following the third instillation and tend to increase in severity after each administration. There is no evidence that dose reduction or antituberculous drug therapy can prevent or lessen the irritative symptoms of TheraCys.



 In a clinical trial conducted in the United States, patients with stage Ta or T1 papillary tumor with 2 or more recurrences within the last 12 months, with carcinoma  in situ  (CIS), or with both of these conditions, were randomized to receive treatment with intravesical TheraCys or doxorubicin. Prior therapy with either BCG or doxorubicin was not allowed. Patients with muscle-invasive cancers or incomplete resection of papillary tumors were not eligible. One-hundred and twelve patients received TheraCys in 6 weekly instillations, followed by single instillations at 3, 6, 12, 18, and 24 months after enrollment, and were included in safety analyses. In the control group, 119 patients received doxorubicin in 5 weekly treatments, followed by 11 monthly treatments. Safety information was collected prior to each treatment dose.



 Table 1 shows the frequency of adverse reactions observed in this trial. Local irritative symptoms were more common with TheraCys than with doxorubicin; however, grade &gt;= 3 irritative toxicity was similar, occurring in approximately 2-7% of patients. Systemic symptoms (fever, chills, malaise, anorexia) were also more common with TheraCys. Overall, grade &gt;= 3 toxicities were seen in 26 patients (23%) treated with TheraCys and 25 patients (21%) treated with doxorubicin. TheraCys treatment was discontinued in twelve patients due to toxicity.



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions Reported in Patients Treated with TheraCys in a Trial Conducted in the United States 
                                   Study Arm        
      System/Organ Class        TheraCys (N=112)   Doxorubicin (N=119)   
       Adverse reaction           All Grades%          Grade &gt;=3%         All Grades%          Grade &gt;=3%       
  
   Infections and Infestations     
           Cystitis                   29.5                 0                  19.3                0.8           
   Urinary tract infection            17.9                 0                  17.6                 0            
     Pulmonary infection              2.7                  0                  4.2                 0.8           
      Systemic infection              2.7                 1.8                 0.8                  0            
          Infection                   0.9                 0.9                 0.8                  0            
   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders     
            Anemia                    20.5                 0                  24.4                 0            
          Leukopenia                  5.4                  0                  5.9                  0            
 Coagulopathy/ Thrombocytopenia         0.9                  0                  0.8                  0            
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders     
           Anorexia                   10.7                 0                  5.0                  0            
   Nervous System Disorders     
           Headache                   1.8                  0                  3.4                  0            
          Dizziness                   0.9                  0                  0.8                  0            
      Cardiac Disorders         
    Cardiac (unclassified)            2.7                  0                  3.4                 0.8           
   Gastrointestinal Disorders     
       Nausea/Vomiting                16.1                 0                  8.4                 0.8           
           Diarrhea                   6.3                  0                  1.7                  0            
        Abdominal pain                2.7                  0                  2.5                  0            
         Constipation                 0.9                  0                  0.8                  0            
   Hepatobiliary Disorders      
      Liver involvement               2.7                  0                  0.8                  0            
   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders     
          Skin rash                   1.8                  0                  2.5                  0            
   Musculoskeletal, Connective Tissue, and Bone Disorders     
 Arthralgia/Myalgia/ Arthritis         7.1                 0.9                 4.2                  0            
          Flank pain                  0.9                  0                  0.8                  0            
   Renal and Urinary Disorders     
           Dysuria                    51.8                3.6                 40.3                5.9           
      Urinary frequency               40.2                1.8                 28.6                4.2           
          Hematuria                   39.3                7.1                 27.7                6.7           
       Urinary urgency                17.9                0.9                 11.8                2.5           
     Renal toxicity (NOS)             9.8                 1.8                 9.2                 0.8           
     Urinary incontinence             6.3                  0                  0.8                 0.8           
     Bladder cramps/pain              6.3                  0                  5.0                 1.7           
      Contracted bladder              5.4                 0.9                 5.0                 0.8           
       Tissue in urine                0.9                  0                  1.7                  0            
     Ureteral obstruction             0.9                 0.9                  0                   0            
   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders     
         Genital pain                 9.8                  0                  13.4                1.7           
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions     
           Malaise                    40.2                1.8                 14.3                 0            
    Fever (&gt;38 degrees C)             38.4                2.7                 9.2                  0            
            Chills                    33.9                2.7                 5.9                  0            
           Fatigue                    0.9                  0                   0                   0            
             6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following additional adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of TheraCys. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



     Infections and Infestations  



 BCG Infection: BCG is capable of dissemination when administered by the intravesical route. Serious infections, including sepsis with associated mortality, have been reported. BCG infections have also been reported in eye, lung, liver, bone, bone marrow, kidney, regional lymph nodes, peritoneum, genitourinary tract (orchitis/epididymitis), and prostate (e.g., Granulomatous prostatitis). BCG infection of aneurysms and prosthetic devices (including arterial grafts, cardiac devices and artificial joints) has also been reported.



 Joint symptoms (arthritis, arthralgia), ocular symptoms (including conjunctivitis, uveitis, iritis, keratitis, granulomatous choreoretinitis), urinary symptoms (including urethritis), skin rash, alone or in combination (Reiter's syndrome), have been reported following administration of TheraCys. For the reports of Reiter's syndrome, the risk seems to be more elevated among patients who are positive for HLA-B27.



 Renal abscess



     Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders  



 Pneumonia, interstitial lung disease



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders



 Erythema nodosum



     Renal and Urinary Disorders  



 Renal failure, pyelonephritis, nephritis (including tubulointerstitial nephritis, interstitial nephritis and glomerulonephritis)



 Urinary retention (including bladder tamponade and feeling of residual urine)



     General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions  



 Flu-like symptoms



     Investigations (Laboratory Tests)  



 Abnormal/increased blood creatinine or blood urea nitrogen (BUN)
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: RISK OF TRANSMISSION AND INFECTION

    WARNING: RISK OF TRANSMISSION AND INFECTION  

    *  TheraCys(r), BCG Live (Intravesical) contains live, attenuated mycobacteria. Because of the potential risk for transmission, prepare, handle, and dispose of TheraCys as a biohazard material. (2, 5) 
 *  BCG is capable of dissemination when administered by the intravesical route. Serious infections, including fatal infections, have been reported in patients receiving Intravesical BCG. (5, 6) 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING - RISK OF TRANSMISSION AND INFECTION
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  TheraCys(r), BCG Live (Intravesical) contains live, attenuated mycobacteria. Because of the potential risk for transmission, prepare, handle, and dispose of TheraCys as a biohazard material. (2, 5) 
 *  BCG is capable of dissemination when administered by the intravesical route. Serious infections, including fatal infections, have been reported in patients receiving Intravesical BCG. (5, 6) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  If TheraCys is administered within two weeks of either biopsy, TUR or traumatic bladder catheterization (associated with hematuria), a systemic BCG reaction is much more likely to occur. (  5.1  ) 
 *  If a bacterial urinary tract infection (UTI) occurs during the course of TheraCys treatment, withhold TheraCys instillation until complete resolution of the bacterial UTI. (  5.3  ) 
 *  If a patient develops persistent fever or experiences an acute febrile illness consistent with BCG infection, permanently discontinue BCG instillations. Initiate treatment with 2 or more antimycobacterial agents promptly while conducting diagnostic evaluation, including cultures. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Prepare and handle TheraCys using aseptic technique. Avoid needle stick injuries during the handling and mixing of TheraCys. (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Systemic BCG Reaction



  A systemic BCG reaction is a systemic granulomatous illness, which may occur subsequent to exposure to TheraCys. Because it is usually difficult to isolate BCG organisms from affected organs, the extent such a reaction is caused by an infectious process versus an inflammatory hypersensitivity reaction often is unclear. "Systemic BCG reaction" may be defined as the presence of any of the following signs, if no other etiologies for such signs are detectable: fever &gt;=39.5 degrees C (&gt;=103.1 degrees F) for &gt;=12 hours; fever &gt;=38.5 degrees C (&gt;=101.3 degrees F) for &gt;=48 hours; pneumonitis; hepatitis; other organ dysfunction outside of the genitourinary tract with granulomatous inflammation on biopsy; or the classical signs of sepsis, including circulatory collapse, acute respiratory distress, and disseminated intravascular coagulation. If TheraCys is administered within two weeks of either biopsy, TUR or traumatic bladder catheterization (associated with hematuria), a systemic BCG reaction is much more likely to occur. Death has been reported with the use of TheraCys in association with systemic BCG reaction in post-marketing experience.



    5.2 BCG infection



  To help prevent serious infections, avoid trauma and/or introduction of contaminants to the urinary tract. Wait a minimum of 14 days after traumatic catheterization before administering TheraCys. Resume TheraCys treatment according to the original schedule.



 BCG infections of aneurysms and prosthetic devices (including arterial grafts, cardiac devices, and artificial joints) have been reported following intravesical administration of BCG. The risk of these ectopic BCG infections has not been determined. The benefits of TheraCys therapy must be carefully weighed against the possibility of an ectopic BCG infection in patients with pre-existing arterial aneurysms or prosthetic devices of any kind.



 Some male genitourinary tract infections (orchitis/epididymitis) have been refractory to multiple drug antituberculous therapy and required orchiectomy.



 Monitor patients for the presence of symptoms and signs of toxicity after each intravesical treatment. If a patient develops persistent fever or experiences an acute febrile illness consistent with BCG infection, permanently discontinue BCG instillations, evaluate and treat the patient immediately for BCG infection, and seek an infectious diseases consultation. As standard therapy for BCG infection, promptly initiate treatment with 2 or more antimycobacterial agents while conducting diagnostic evaluation, including cultures. Do not use single antibiotic therapy. Negative cultures do not rule out infection.



 TheraCys is not sensitive to pyrazinamide.



    5.3 Bacterial Urinary Tract Infection (UTI)



  If a bacterial urinary tract infection (UTI) occurs during the course of TheraCys treatment, withhold TheraCys instillation until complete resolution of the bacterial UTI.



    5.4 Antimicrobial Therapy



  Do not use antimycobacterial drugs (e.g., isoniazid) prophylactically to prevent the local, irritative side effects of TheraCys. They may affect the effectiveness of TheraCys and there are no data to suggest that the acute, local urinary tract symptoms common with intravesical BCG are due to mycobacterial infection.



    5.5 Handling Precautions



  Because TheraCys contains live mycobacteria, prepare, handle and dispose of TheraCys, and all equipment, supplies and receptacles in contact with TheraCys, as biohazardous waste (or material). Use aseptic techniques, wear gloves and eye protection, and take precautions to avoid contact of TheraCys with broken skin. Avoid needle stick injuries during the handling and mixing of TheraCys.



 BCG infections have been reported in health care workers preparing BCG for administration. Nosocomial infections have been reported in immunosuppressed patients receiving parenteral drugs that were prepared in areas in which BCG was prepared.



    5.6 Latex



  The stopper of the vial for this product contains natural rubber latex, which may cause allergic reactions.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
