<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="thymoglobulin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Clinical Trials

      US Phase 3 Study    



 Thymoglobulin adverse events are generally manageable or reversible. In the US Phase 3 controlled clinical trial (n=163) comparing the efficacy and safety of Thymoglobulin and Atgam, there were no significant differences in clinically significant adverse events between the two treatment groups (  Table 2  ). Malignancies were reported in 3 patients who received Thymoglobulin and in 3 patients who received Atgam during the one-year follow-up period. These included two post-transplant lymphoproliferative diseases (PTLDs) in the Thymoglobulin group and two PTLDs in the Atgam group.



 Table 2. Frequently Reported and Significant Adverse EventsTreatment Emergent Adverse Events (TEAE) are summarized. Frequently reported adverse events are those reported by more than 25% of patients in a treatment group; significant adverse events are those where the incidence rate differed between treatment groups by a significance level of &lt;=0.05.   
     Preferred Term           Thymoglobulin        n=82          Atgam        n=81          p Value          
     No. of    Patients        (%)            No. of    Patients        (%)         
  
     Frequently Reported Events        
   Fever                52             (63.4)             51          
   Chills               47             (57.3)             35          
   Leukopenia           47             (57.3)             24          
   Pain                 38             (46.3)             35          
   Headache             33             (40.2)             28          
   Abdominal pain         31             (37.8)             22          
   Diarrhea             30             (36.6)             26          
   Hypertension         30             (36.6)             23          
   Nausea               30             (36.6)             23          
   Thrombocytopenia         30             (36.6)             36          
   Peripheral edema         28             (34.1)             28          
   Dyspnea              23             (28.0)             16          
   Asthenia             22             (26.8)             26          
   Hyperkalemia         22             (26.8)             15          
   Tachycardia          22             (26.8)             19          
     Significant Events                                                          
   Leukopenia           47             (57.3)             24          
   Malaise              11             (13.4)              3          
   Dizziness             7              (8.5)             20          
      Infections occurring in both treatment groups during the 3-month follow-up are summarized in  Table 3  . No significant differences were seen between the Thymoglobulin and Atgam groups for all types of infections, and the incidence of cytomegalovirus (CMV) infection was equivalent in both groups. (Viral prophylaxis was by the center's discretion during antibody treatment, but all centers used gancyclovir infusion during treatment.)
 

 Table 3. Infections 
     BODY SYSTEM        Preferred Term           Thymoglobulin        n=82           Atgam        n=81         p Value                   
         No. of     Patients              (%)                        Total    Reports          No. of    Patients         (%)                        Total    Reports        
  
 BODY AS A WHOLE            30                         (36.6)                     36                         22                         (27.2)                     29                         0.240                       
   Infection                25                         (30.5)                     26                         19                         (23.5)                     21                         0.378                       
     Other                  14                         (17.1)                     15                         11                         (13.6)                     12                         0.665                       
     CMV                    11                         (13.4)                     11                         9                          (11.1)                     9                          0.812                       
   Sepsis                   10                         (12.2)                     10                         7                          (9.6)                      7                          0.610                       
   Moniliasis               0                          (0.0)                      0                          1                          (1.2)                      1                          0.497                       
 DIGESTIVE                  5                          (6.1)                      5                          3                          (3.7)                      3                          0.720                       
    Gastrointestinal moniliasis    4                          (4.9)                      4                          1                          (1.2)                      1                          0.367                       
   Oral moniliasis          3                          (3.7)                      0                          2                          (2.5)                      1                          0.497                       
   Gastritis                1                          (1.2)                      1                          0                          (0.0)                      0                          1.000                       
 RESPIRATORY                0                          (0.0)                      0                          1                          (1.2)                      1                          0.497                       
   Pneumonia                0                          (0.0)                      0                          1                          (1.2)                      1                          0.497                       
 SKIN                       4                          (4.9)                      4                          0                          (0.0)                      0                          0.120                       
   Herpes simplex           4                          (4.9)                      4                          0                          (0.0)                      0                          0.120                       
 UROGENITAL                 15                         (18.3)                     15                         22                         (29.2)                     22                         0.195                       
   Urinary tract infection   15                         (18.3)                     15                         21                         (25.9)                     21                         0.262                       
   Vaginitis                0                          (0.0)                      0                          1                          (1.2)                      1                          0.497                       
 NOT SPECIFIED              0                          (0.0)                      0                          2                          (2.5)                      2                          0.245                       
        Post-marketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of Thymoglobulin. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



     Infusion-Associated Reactions and Immune System Disorders    



 IARs may occur following the administration of Thymoglobulin and may occur as soon as the first or second infusion during a single course of Thymoglobulin treatment. Clinical manifestations of infusion-associated reactions IARs have included some of the following signs and symptoms: fever, chills/rigors, dyspnea, nausea/vomiting, diarrhea, hypotension or hypertension, malaise, rash, urticaria, and/or headache. IARs with Thymoglobulin are generally manageable with a reduction in infusion rates and/or with medications. Transient reversible elevations in transaminases without any clinical signs or symptoms have also been reported during Thymoglobulin administration. (See      PRECAUTIONS      ). Serious and fatal anaphylactic reactions have been reported (See      WARNINGS      ). The fatalities occurred in patients who did not receive epinephrine during the event.



 IARs consistent with cytokine release syndrome (CRS) have been reported. Severe and potentially life-threatening CRS have also been reported. Post-marketing reports of severe CRS have included cardiorespiratory dysfunction (including hypotension, acute respiratory distress syndrome, pulmonary edema, myocardial infarction, tachycardia, and/or death).



 During post-marketing surveillance, reactions such as fever, rash, urticaria, arthralgia, and/or myalgia, indicating possible serum sickness, have been reported. Serum sickness tends to occur 5 to 15 days after onset of Thymoglobulin therapy. Symptoms are manageable with corticosteroid treatment. 



     Adverse Events Due to Immunosuppression    



 Infections, reactivation of infection, febrile neutropenia and sepsis have been reported after Thymoglobulin administration in combination with multiple immunosuppressive agents, These infections can be fatal. (See      WARNINGS       and      PRECAUTIONS      ). Malignancies including, but not limited to lymphoproliferative disorders (LPD) and other lymphomas (which may be virally mediated) as well as solid tumors have been reported. These events have sometimes been associated with fatal outcome. (See      PRECAUTIONS      ). These adverse events were reported with use of a combination of multiple immunosuppressive agents.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING

  WARNING

   Thymoglobulin  (r)   should only be used by physicians experienced in immunosuppressive therapy for the management of renal transplant patients. 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
