<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tindamax" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6 ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions for a single 2 g dose of tinidazole (incidence &gt;1%) are metallic/bitter taste, nausea, weakness/fatigue/malaise, dyspepsia/cramps/epigastric discomfort, vomiting, anorexia, headache, dizziness and constipation (  6.1  )



 To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Mission Pharmacal Company at 1-855-778-0177or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Among 3669 patients treated with a single 2 g dose of tinidazole, in both controlled and uncontrolled trichomoniasis and giardiasis clinical studies, adverse reactions were reported by 11.0% of patients. For multi-day dosing in controlled and uncontrolled amebiasis studies, adverse reactions were reported by 13.8% of 1765 patients. Common (&gt;= 1% incidence) adverse reactions reported by body system are as follows. (Note: Data described in Table 1 below are pooled from studies with variable designs and safety evaluations.)



   Other adverse reactions reported with tinidazole include:  



 Central Nervous System: Two serious adverse reactions reported include convulsions and transient peripheral neuropathy including numbness and paresthesia  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].  Other CNS reports include vertigo, ataxia, giddiness, insomnia, drowsiness.



 Gastrointestinal: tongue discoloration, stomatitis, diarrhea



 Hypersensitivity: urticaria, pruritis, rash, flushing, sweating, dryness of mouth, fever, burning sensation, thirst, salivation, angioedema



 Renal: darkened urine



 Cardiovascular: palpitations



 Hematopoietic: transient neutropenia, transient leukopenia



 Other:  Candida  overgrowth, increased vaginal discharge, oral candidiasis, hepatic abnormalities including raised transaminase level, arthralgias, myalgias, and arthritis.



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions Summary of Published Reports           
                                                                 2 g single dose        Multi-day dose      
  GI:      Metallic/bitter taste                                       3.7%                  6.3%           
            Nausea                                                     3.2%                  4.5%           
            Anorexia                                                   1.5%                  2.5%           
            Dyspepsia/cramps/epigastric discomfort                     1.8%                  1.4%           
            Vomiting                                                   1.5%                  0.9%           
            Constipation                                               0.4%                  1.4%           
  CNS:  Weakness/fatigue/malaise                                       2.1%                  1.1%           
            Dizziness                                                  1.1%                  0.5%           
  Other: Headache                                                      1.3%                  0.7%           
  Total patients with adverse reactions                          11.0%(403/3669)       13.8%(244/1765)      
         Rare reported adverse reactions include bronchospasm, dyspnea, coma, confusion, depression, furry tongue, pharyngitis and reversible thrombocytopenia.
 

   Adverse Reactions in Pediatric Patients:  In pooled pediatric studies, adverse reactions reported in pediatric patients taking tinidazole were similar in nature and frequency to adult findings including nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, taste change, anorexia, and abdominal pain.



   Bacterial vaginosis:  The most common adverse reactions in treated patients (incidence &gt;2%), which were not identified in the trichomoniasis, giardiasis and amebiasis studies, are gastrointestinal: decreased appetite, and flatulence; renal: urinary tract infection, painful urination, and urine abnormality; and other reactions including pelvic pain, vulvo-vaginal discomfort, vaginal odor, menorrhagia, and upper respiratory tract infection  [See Clinical Studies (  14.5  )].  



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified and reported during post-approval use of Tindamax. Because the reports of these reactions are voluntary and the population is of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate the frequency of the reaction or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Severe acute hypersensitivity reactions have been reported on initial or subsequent exposure to tinidazole. Hypersensitivity reactions may include urticaria, pruritis, angioedema, Stevens-Johnson syndrome and erythema multiforme.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: POTENTIAL RISK FOR CARCINOGENICITY

    WARNING: POTENTIAL RISK FOR CARCINOGENICITY  

  Carcinogenicity has been seen in mice and rats treated chronically with metronidazole, another nitroimidazole agent (  13.1  ). Although such data have not been reported for tinidazole, the two drugs are structurally related and have similar biologic effects.    Its use should be reserved for the conditions described in INDICATIONS AND USAGE (  1  ).  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: POTENTIAL RISK FOR CARCINOGENICITY  



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



   Carcinogenicity has been seen in mice and rats treated chronically with metronidazole, another nitroimidazole agent (  13.1  ). Although such data have not been reported for tinidazole, the two drugs are structurally related and have similar biologic effects.  Use should be limited to approved indications only.  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">     5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *  Seizures and neuropathy have been reported. Discontinue Tindamax if abnormal neurologic signs develop (  5.1  ) 
 *  Vaginal candidiasis may develop with Tindamax and require treatment with an antifungal agent (  5.2  ) 
 *  Use Tindamax with caution in patients with blood dyscrasias. Tindamax may produce transient leukopenia and neutropenia (  5.3,    7.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Neurological Adverse Reactions



  Convulsive seizures and peripheral neuropathy, the latter characterized mainly by numbness or paresthesia of an extremity, have been reported in patients treated with tinidazole. The appearance of abnormal neurologic signs demands the prompt discontinuation of tinidazole therapy.



    5.2 Vaginal Candidiasis



  The use of tinidazole may result in Candida  vaginitis. In a clinical study of 235 women who received tinidazole for bacterial vaginosis, a vaginal fungal infection developed in 11 (4.7%) of all study subjects [see Clinical Studies (  14.5  )].  



    5.3 Blood Dyscrasia



  Tinidazole should be used with caution in patients with evidence of or history of blood dyscrasia [see Drug Interactions (  7.3  )].  



    5.4 Drug Resistance



  Prescribing Tindamax in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection or a prophylactic indication is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug-resistant bacteria.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
