<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tirosint" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Common adverse reactions with levothyroxine therapy are primarily those of hyperthyroidism due to therapeutic overdosage  [See  Overdosage (10)  ].  They include the following:



 *   General: fatigue, increased appetite, weight loss, heat intolerance, fever, excessive sweating 
 *   Central nervous system: headache, hyperactivity, nervousness, anxiety, irritability, emotional lability, insomnia 
 *   Musculoskeletal: tremors, muscle weakness 
 *   Cardiovascular: palpitations, tachycardia, arrhythmias, increased pulse and blood pressure, heart failure, angina, myocardial infarction, cardiac arrest 
 *   Respiratory : dyspnea 
 *   Gastrointestinal (GI): diarrhea, vomiting, abdominal cramps, elevations in liver function tests 
 *   Dermatologic: hair loss, flushing 
 *   Endocrine: decreased bone mineral density 
 *   Reproductive: menstrual irregularities, impaired fertility 
      EXCERPT:   Common adverse reactions for levothyroxine are primarily those of hyperthyroidism due to therapeutic overdosage including: irregular heartbeat, chest pain, shortness of breath, leg cramps, headache, nervousness, irritability, insomnia, tremors, muscle weakness, change in appetite, weight change, diarrhea, heat intolerance, changes in menstrual periods, and skin rash (  6  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Akrimax Pharmaceuticals at 1-888-383-1733, or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  .    



 

    Adverse Reactions in Children  



 Pseudotumor cerebri and slipped capital femoral epiphysis have been reported in children receiving levothyroxine therapy. Overtreatment may result in craniosynostosis in infants and premature closure of the epiphyses in children with resultant compromised adult height. Seizures have been reported rarely with the institution of levothyroxine therapy.



     Hypersensitivity Reactions  



 Hypersensitivity reactions to inactive ingredients (in this product or other levothyroxine products) have occurred in patients treated with thyroid hormone products. These include urticaria, pruritus, skin rash, flushing, angioedema, various GI symptoms (abdominal pain, nausea, vomiting and diarrhea), fever, arthralgia, serum sickness and wheezing. Hypersensitivity to levothyroxine itself is not known to occur.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: NOT FOR TREATMENT OF OBESITY OR FOR WEIGHT LOSS

    WARNING: NOT FOR TREATMENT OF OBESITY OR FOR WEIGHT LOSS  

    *  Thyroid hormones, including TIROSINT, either alone or with other therapeutic agents, should not be used for the treatment of obesity or for weight loss. 
 *  In euthyroid patients, doses within the range of daily hormonal requirements are ineffective for weight reduction. 
 *  Larger doses may produce serious or even life threatening manifestations of toxicity, particularly when given in association with sympathomimetic amines such as those used for their anorectic effects [See Adverse Reactions (6), Drug Interactions (7.7), and Overdosage (10)]. 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING: NOT FOR TREATMENT OF OBESITY OR FOR WEIGHT LOSS  
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



 *  Thyroid hormones, including TIROSINT, should not be used for the treatment of obesity or for weight loss. 
 *  Doses beyond the range of daily hormonal requirements may produce serious or even life threatening manifestations of toxicity (6, 10). 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Proper dose titration is critical to prevent the persistence of hypothyroidism or the development of hyperthyroidism (  5.1  ) 
 *  Elderly and patients with cardiovascular disease: Initiate levothyroxine at less than the full replacement dose because of the increased risk of cardiac adverse reactions, including atrial fibrillation (  2.3  ,  5.2  ,  8.5  ) 
 *  Suppression of thyroid nodules with levothyroxine is generally not recommended (  5.3  ) 
 *  Patients with concomitant adrenal insufficiency: Treat with replacement glucocorticoids prior to initiation of treatment with levothyroxine (  5.4  ) 
 *  Long-term levothyroxine therapy can decrease bone mineral density. Give the lowest effective dose, particularly in patients with compromised bone mineral density (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Importance of Proper Dose Titration to Prevent Hyperthyroidism or Incomplete Treatment of Hypothyroidism



  Levothyroxine has a narrow therapeutic index. Regardless of the indication for use, careful dosage titration is necessary to avoid hyperthyroidism or incomplete treatment of hypothyroidism. These consequences include, among others, adverse effects on cardiovascular function, growth and development, bone metabolism, reproductive function, cognitive function, emotional state, gastrointestinal function, and on glucose and lipid metabolism. Periodic clinical and thyroid function monitoring is recommended [See  Dosage and Administration (2.4)  ]  . In addition, many drugs interact with levothyroxine sodium necessitating adjustments in dosing to maintain therapeutic response [See  Drug Interactions (7)  ].  



    5.2 Risk of Cardiac Adverse Reactions in the Elderly and in Patients with Underlying Cardiovascular Disease



  In the elderly and in patients with cardiovascular disorders, levothyroxine therapy should be initiated at lower doses than those recommended in younger individuals or in patients without cardiac disease and it should be noted that unlike levothyroxine sodium tablets, TIROSINT capsules cannot be cut in half [See  Dosage and Administration (2.3)  and  Use in Specific Populations (8.5)  ].  If cardiac symptoms develop or worsen, the levothyroxine sodium dose should be reduced or withheld for one week and then cautiously restarted at a lower dose. Overtreatment with levothyroxine sodium may have adverse cardiovascular effects such as an increase in heart rate, cardiac wall thickness, and cardiac contractility and may precipitate angina or arrhythmias. Patients with coronary artery disease who are receiving levothyroxine therapy should be monitored closely during surgical procedures because of the possibility of precipitating cardiac arrhythmias, including atrial fibrillation. Concomitant administration of levothyroxine and sympathomimetic agents to patients with coronary artery disease may precipitate coronary insufficiency [See  Drug Interactions (7.7)  ].  



    5.3 Patients with Nontoxic Diffuse Goiter or Nodular Thyroid Disease



  Suppression of thyroid nodules with levothyroxine is a controversial issue. Routine suppression of benign thyroid nodules is generally not recommended in iodine-sufficient patients. If the serum thyrotropin-stimulating hormone (TSH) is already suppressed, levothyroxine sodium should not be administered. If the serum TSH level is not suppressed, TIROSINT should not be used without frequent laboratory monitoring of thyroid function for evidence of hyperthyroidism and clinical monitoring for potential associated adverse cardiovascular signs and symptoms of hyperthyroidism.



    5.4 Patients with Concomitant Adrenal Insufficiency



  Occasionally, chronic autoimmune thyroiditis may occur in association with other autoimmune disorders such as adrenal insufficiency, pernicious anemia, and insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus. Patients with concomitant adrenal insufficiency should be treated with replacement glucocorticoids prior to initiation of treatment with levothyroxine sodium [See  Contraindications (4)  ].  Failure to do so may precipitate an acute adrenal crisis when thyroid hormone therapy is initiated, due to increased metabolic clearance of glucocorticoids by thyroid hormone.



    5.5 Thyroid Hormone Over-replacement Associated with Decreased Bone Mineral Density



  Over-replacement with levothyroxine therapy has been associated with decreased bone mineral density, especially in post-menopausal women. The increased bone resorption may be associated with increased serum levels and urinary excretion of calcium and phosphorous, elevations in bone alkaline phosphatase, and suppressed serum parathyroid hormone levels. Therefore, it is recommended that patients receiving levothyroxine sodium be given the minimum dose necessary to achieve the desired clinical and biochemical response, unless TSH suppression is the goal of therapy, as in patients with well-differentiated thyroid cancer.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
