<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tisseel" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Anaphylactic and hypersensitivity reactions have been reported. No adverse events of this type were reported during clinical trials (  5.1  ,  6.1  ,  6.3  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Baxter Healthcare Corporation at 1-866-888-2472 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Overall Adverse Reactions

    Hypersensitivity/Allergic/Anaphylactic Reactions:  Hypersensitivity or allergic/anaphylactoid reactions may occur. In isolated cases, these reactions have progressed to severe anaphylaxis (  see  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS, Hypersensitivity/Allergic/Anaphylactic Reactions (5.1)    ). No adverse events of this type were reported during clinical trials.



   6.2 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Increased D-Dimer levels have been observed during a clinical study in cardiovascular surgery  (see  CLINICAL STUDIES (14)  ),  but did not exceed values reported in the literature occurring after this type of surgery. Postoperatively increased D-Dimers may result at least partly from the degradation of Fibrin Sealant.



   6.3 Post Marketing

  Because adverse reactions are reported voluntarily and the population is of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate the frequency of these reactions.



 Manifestations of hypersensitivity or allergic reactions associated with the class of fibrin sealant/hemostatic products include: application site irritation, chest discomfort, chills, headache, lethargy, restlessness, vomiting, paresthesia and wheezing. There have been no reports of these reactions related to the specific use of TISSEEL.



 The following adverse reactions have been reported in the post-marketing experience:



   IMMUNE SYSTEM DISORDERS  : Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylactic reactions and anaphylactic shock. Anaphylactic reactions and anaphylactic shock have included fatal outcomes.  VASCULAR DISORDERS  : hypotension, thromboembolism, including cerebral artery embolism and venous thrombotic cerebral infarction as a result of intravascular application  SKIN AND SUBCUTANEOUS TISSUE DISORDERS  : angioedema, erythema, impaired wound healing, pruritus, urticaria



   CARDIAC DISORDERS  : bradycardia, tachycardia



   RESPIRATORY DISORDERS  : bronchospasm, dyspnea



   GASTROINTESTINAL DISORDERS  : nausea



   GENERAL DISORDERS AND ADMINISTRATION SITE CONDITIONS:  flushing



   Air embolism associated with misapplication of fibrin sealant using the spray device, Class Effect: A post marketing fatality was reported in association with the use of another fibrin sealant when applied using a spray device. The case involved an attempt to stop active bleeding by applying the fibrin sealant using a spray device attached to a wall unit at a higher than recommended pressure for the spray device. In addition, the spray head was placed at a distance from the bleeding site that was closer than the recommended distance guidelines for the application of the sealant. The patient suffered a fatal air embolism.  



 There have been reports of serious adverse events such as paralysis and other compressive complications possibly related to the use of fibrin sealants in combination with resorbable hemostatic agents. There have also been reports of fatalities following the misadministration of topical thrombin  (see    WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS, Use in Neurosurgical Procedures (5.4)    )  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  TISSEEL contains aprotinin, a monomeric polypeptide known to be associated with anaphylactic reactions (  4.2,    5.1,    6.1)   
 *  Air or gas embolism has occurred with the use of spray devices employing pressure regulator to administer fibrin sealants. This event appears to be related to the use of the spray device at higher than recommended pressures and in close proximity to the surface of the tissue (  5.2  ) 
 *  Exposure to solutions containing alcohol, iodine or heavy metals may cause TISSEEL to be denatured (  5.2  ) 
 *  Apply only as thin layer. Excess clot thickness may delay the natural wound healing process. (  2,    5.2)   
 *  Caution should be exercised to minimize the risk of inadvertent intravascular application when using TISSEEL in cardiopulmonary bypass surgeries (  4.1,    5.3,    6.3)   
 *  Safety has not been evaluated in neurosurgical procedures (  5.4  ) 
 *  The safety and effectiveness of the combined use of TISSEEL with other biocompatible materials has not been evaluated in controlled clinical trials (  5.4  ,  6.3  ) 
 *  This product is made from pooled human plasma which may contain infectious agents (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity/Allergic/Anaphylactic Reactions



  Hypersensitivity or allergic/anaphylactoid reactions may occur with the use of TISSEEL. Cases (&lt;1/10,000) have been reported in post marketing experience with Baxter's fibrin sealant (see  ADVERSE REACTIONS, Post Marketing (6.3)  ).  In specific cases, these reactions have progressed to severe anaphylaxis. Such reactions may especially be seen if TISSEEL is applied repeatedly over time or in the same setting, or if systemic aprotinin has been administered previously. Even if the first treatment was well tolerated, this may not exclude the occurrence of an allergic reaction after a subsequent administration of TISSEEL or systemic aprotinin. Observed symptoms of allergic anaphylactic reactions to TISSEEL have included: bradycardia, tachycardia, hypotension, flushing, bronchospasm, wheezing, dyspnea, nausea, urticaria, angioedema, pruritus, erythema and paresthesia. Such reactions may also occur in patients receiving TISSEEL for the first time.



 Aprotinin is included in TISSEEL for its antifibrinolytic properties.  Aprotinin, a monomeric polypeptide, is known to be associated with anaphylactic reactions. Even in the case of strict local application of aprotinin, there is a risk of anaphylactic reactions to aprotinin, particularly in the case of previous exposure (see   CONTRAINDICATIONS, Aprotinin Hypersensitivity(4.2))    . TISSEEL does not contain any substances of bovine origin.



 Discontinue administration of TISSEEL in the event of hypersensitivity reactions. Mild reactions can be managed with antihistamines. Severe hypotensive reactions require immediate intervention using current principles of shock therapy. Remove remaining product from the application site.



    5.2 Application Precautions



  Air or gas embolism has occurred with the use of spray devices employing pressure regulator to administer fibrin sealants. This event appears to be related to the use of the spray device at higher than recommended pressures and in close proximity to the tissue surface.



 When applying TISSEEL using a spray device, be sure to use the pressure within the pressure range recommended by the spray device manufacturer. In the absence of a specific recommendation avoid using pressure above 20-25 psi. Do not spray closer than the distance recommended by the spray device manufacturer. In the absence of a specific recommendation avoid spraying closer than 10-15 cm from the surface of the tissue. When spraying TISSEEL, changes in blood pressure, pulse, oxygen saturation and end tidal CO2should be monitored because of the possibility of occurrence of air or gas embolism. When using the EASYSPRAY device, or an equivalent spray device for open surgical procedures cleared by FDA, TISSEEL must not be sprayed in enclosed body areas and must be sprayed onto only visible application sites.



 The sealer protein and thrombin solutions can be denatured by alcohol, iodine or heavy metal ions. If any of these substances have been used to clean the wound area, the area must be thoroughly rinsed before the application of TISSEEL.



 Apply TISSEEL as a thin layer. Excess clot thickness may delay the natural wound healing process.



 The safety and effectiveness of the combined use of TISSEEL with other biocompatible materials has not been evaluated in controlled clinical trials.



    5.3 Use in Cardiopulmonary Surgery



  Caution should be exercised to minimize the risk of inadvertent intravascular application when using TISSEEL in cardiopulmonary bypass surgeries ( see  CONTRAINDICATIONS, Intravascular Application (4.1)  and  ADVERSE REACTIONS, Post Marketing (6.3)  ).  



    5.4 Use in Neurosurgical Procedures



  The safety and effectiveness of TISSEEL used alone or in combination with biocompatible carriers in neurosurgical procedures or other surgeries involving confined spaces have not been evaluated, and its use in this setting is not approved by FDA (see  ADVERSE REACTIONS, Post Marketing (6.3)  and  DRUG INTERACTIONS (7)  ).  



    5.5 Infection Risk from Human Plasma



  TISSEEL is made from human plasma. Products made from human plasma may contain infectious agents, such as viruses, that can cause disease. The risk that such products will transmit an infectious agent has been reduced by screening plasma donors for prior exposure to certain viruses, by testing for the presence of certain virus infections, and by inactivating and removing certain viruses during the manufacturing process ( see   CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Other Clinical Pharmacology Information (12.4)    ).  Despite these measures, such products can still potentially transmit disease. Because this product is made from human blood, it may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents, e.g., viruses, and theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) agent. This also applies to unknown or emerging viruses and other pathogens. The measures taken are considered effective for inactivation/removal of lipid enveloped viruses such as HIV, HBV, and HCV, and for the non-lipid enveloped virus such as HAV. These measures may be of limited value against small non-lipid enveloped viruses such as Parvovirus B19. Parvovirus B19 infection may be serious for pregnant women (fetal infection) and for individuals with immunodeficiency or increased red blood cell turnover (e.g., hemolytic anemia) (see   PATIENT COUNSELING INFORMATION     (  17    )). ALL infections thought by a physician possibly to have been transmitted by this product should be reported by the physician or other healthcare provider to Baxter Healthcare Corporation, telephone number 1-866-888-2472.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
