<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tivorbex" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Cardiovascular thrombotic events [ see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *  Gastrointestinal effects [ see  Boxed Warning  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
 *  Hepatic effects [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ] 
 *  Hypertension [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   ] 
 *  Congestive heart failure and edema [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)   ] 
 *  Renal effects [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)   ] 
 *  Anaphylactic reactions [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
 *  Central nervous system effects [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)   ] 
 *  Skin reactions [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)   ] 
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions in clinical trials (incidence &gt;=2% in TIVORBEX 20 mg and 40 mg groups) include: nausea, post procedural edema, headache, dizziness, vomiting, post procedural hemorrhage, constipation, pruritus, diarrhea, dyspepsia, post procedural swelling, presyncope, rash, abdominal pain (upper), somnolence, pruritus generalized, hyperhidrosis, decreased appetite, hot flush and syncope. (  6.1  )  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Iroko Pharmaceuticals, LLC at 1-877-757-0676 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 Five hundred and fifty-four patients (554) received TIVORBEX 20 mg or 40 mg for up to 48 hours in two double-blind, placebo-controlled, clinical trials of acute pain following bunionectomy. The most frequent adverse reactions in these trials are summarized below.



 Table 1 Summary of Adverse Reactions (&gt;=2% in TIVORBEX 20 mg or 40 mg group) - Phase 3 Studies in Patients With Postsurgical Pain 
  Any Treatment Emergent AE    TIVORBEX 40 mg three times daily  TIVORBEX 40 mg twice daily  TIVORBEX 20 mg three times daily       Placebo         
             (%)                      (%)                 (%)                 (%)           
            N=187                    N=184               N=183               N=188          
  
            Nausea                     33                  33                  34                  36           
    Post procedural edema              24                  22                  26                  32           
           Headache                    16                  14                  11                  11           
          Dizziness                    15                  14                  10                  17           
           Vomiting                    8                   10                  12                  11           
  Post procedural hemorrhage           5                   11                  5                   6            
         Constipation                  4                   5                   6                   5            
           Pruritus                    2                   3                   4                   0            
           Diarrhea                    2                   3                   2                   1            
          Dyspepsia                    3                   2                   1                   1            
   Post procedural swelling            1                   3                   1                   1            
          Presyncope                   2                   3                   1                   2            
             Rash                      2                   1                   2                   0            
    Abdominal pain, upper              2                   1                   2                   1            
          Somnolence                   2                   2                   1                   1            
     Pruritus generalized              1                   2                   1                   0            
        Hyperhidrosis                  0                   2                   1                   1            
      Decreased appetite               0                   2                   1                   1            
          Hot flush                    0                   1                   2                   1            
           Syncope                     0                   2                   1                   1            
             6.2 Adverse Reactions From Spontaneous Reports
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of indomethacin. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



     Gastrointestinal  :  anorexia  ,  bloating (includes distension)  ,  flatulence  ,  peptic ulcer  ,  gastroenteritis  ,  rectal bleeding  ,  proctitis  ,  single or multiple ulcerations, including perforation and hemorrhage of the esophagus, stomach, duodenum or small and large intestines intestinal ulceration associated with stenosis and obstruction, gastrointestinal bleeding without obvious ulcer formation and perforation of pre-existing sigmoid lesions (diverticulum, carcinoma, etc) development of ulcerative colitis and regional ileitis ulcerative stomatitis  ,  toxic hepatitis and jaundice (some fatal cases have been reported)  ,  intestinal strictures (diaphragms).



   Cardiovascular:  hypertension, hypotension, tachycardia, chest pain, congestive heart failure, arrhythmia, palpitations.



   Hematologic:  leukopenia, bone marrow depression, anemia secondary to obvious or occult gastrointestinal bleeding, aplastic anemia, hemolytic anemia, agranulocytosis, thrombocytopenic purpura, disseminated intravascular coagulation.



   Central Nervous System:  anxiety (includes nervousness)  ,  muscle weakness  ,  involuntary muscle movements  ,  insomnia  ,  confusion  ,  psychic disturbances including psychotic episodes, mental confusion, drowsiness, light-headedness, syncope, paresthesia, aggravation of epilepsy and parkinsonism, depersonalization, coma, peripheral neuropathy, convulsion, dysarthria.



   Hypersensitivity:  acute anaphylaxis  ,  acute respiratory distress rapid fall in blood pressure resembling a shock-like state  ,  angioedema  ,  dyspnea  ,  asthma  ,  purpura  ,  angiitis  ,  pulmonary edema  ,  fever.



   Metabolic:  edema  ,  weight gain  ,  fluid retention  ,  flushing or sweating  ,  hyperglycemia  ,  glycosuria  ,  hyperkalemia



   Genitourinary:  hematuria, vaginal bleeding, proteinuria, nephrotic syndrome, interstitial nephritis: BUN elevation, renal insufficiency, including renal failure.



   Special Senses:  ocular - corneal deposits and retinal disturbances, including those of the macula, have been reported in some patients on prolonged therapy with indomethacin; blurred vision, diplopia, hearing disturbances, deafness.



     Skin and Appendages:    pruritus  ,  rash, urticaria  ,  petechiae or ecchymosis  ,  exfoliative dermatitis  ,  erythema nodosum  ,  loss of hair  ,  Stevens-Johnson syndrome  ,  erythema multiforme  ,  toxic epidermal necrolysis.



     Miscellaneous:    epistaxis  ,  breast changes, including enlargement and tenderness  ,  gynecomastia



     Causal relationship unknown  



 Other reactions have been reported but occurred under circumstances where a causal relationship could not be established. However, in these rarely reported events, the possibility cannot be excluded. Therefore, these observations are being listed to serve as alerting information to physicians:



   Cardiovascular:  Thrombophlebitis



     Hematologic:    Although there have been several reports of leukemia, the supporting information is weak



     Genitourinary:    Urinary frequency



     Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue:    A rare occurrence of fulminant necrotizing fasciitis, particularly in association with Group Ab hemolytic streptococcus, has been described in persons treated with nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory agents, including indomethacin, sometimes with fatal outcome [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)    ].
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: RISK OF SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL EVENTS

    WARNING: RISK OF SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL EVENTS  

  EXCERPT:   WARNING: RISK OF SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL EVENTS



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



     Cardiovascular Risk     



 *  Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) may cause an increased risk of serious cardiovascular thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. This risk may increase with duration of use. Patients with cardiovascular disease or risk factors for cardiovascular disease may be at greater risk. (5.1) 
 *  TIVORBEX is contraindicated for the treatment of perioperative pain in the setting of coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery. (4) 
        Gastrointestinal Risk    
 

 *  NSAIDs cause an increased risk of serious gastrointestinal adverse events including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach or intestines, which can be fatal. These events can occur at any time during use and without warning symptoms. Elderly patients are at greater risk for serious gastrointestinal events. (5.2) 
    
 

    Cardiovascular Risk  



 *  NSAIDs may cause an increased risk of serious cardiovascular thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. This risk may increase with duration of use. Patients with cardiovascular disease or risk factors for cardiovascular disease may be at greater risk. [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)] 
 *  TIVORBEX is contraindicated for the treatment of perioperative pain in the setting of coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery. [see Contraindications (4)] 
        Gastrointestinal Risk  
 

 *  NSAIDs cause an increased risk of serious gastrointestinal adverse events including, bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach or intestines, which can be fatal. These events can occur at any time during use and without warning symptoms. Elderly patients are at greater risk for serious gastrointestinal events. [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)] 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Serious and potentially fatal cardiovascular (CV) thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke can occur with NSAID treatment. Patients with known CV disease or risk factors for CV disease may be at greater risk. Use the lowest effective dose for the shortest duration possible. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Serious gastrointestinal (GI) adverse events including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation, which can be fatal. Prescribe TIVORBEX with caution in patients with a prior history of ulcer disease or GI bleeding. Use the lowest effective dose for the shortest duration possible. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Elevation of one or more liver tests and severe hepatic reactions. Measure transaminases (ALT and AST) periodically in patients receiving long-term therapy with TIVORBEX. Discontinue TIVORBEX if abnormal liver tests persist or worsen or if clinical signs and symptoms of liver disease develop. (  5.3  ) 
 *  New onset or worsening of hypertension. Monitor blood pressure closely during treatment with TIVORBEX. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Fluid retention and edema. Prescribe TIVORBEX with caution to patients with fluid retention or heart failure. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Renal papillary necrosis and other renal injury with long-term use. Use TIVORBEX with caution in patients at greatest risk of renal injury, including the elderly, and patients with impaired renal function, heart failure, liver dysfunction, and those taking diuretics and ACE inhibitors. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Anaphylactic reactions may occur in patients with the aspirin triad or without prior exposure to indomethacin. Seek emergency help in cases where an anaphylactic reaction occurs. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Indomethacin may aggravate depression or other psychiatric disturbances, epilepsy, and parkinsonism. Use TIVORBEX, with caution in these patients. Discontinue TIVORBEX if severe CNS adverse reactions develop. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Serious skin adverse events such as exfoliative dermatitis, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome, and toxic epidermal necrolysis, which can be fatal. Discontinue TIVORBEX if rash or other signs of local skin reaction occur. (  5.9  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Cardiovascular Thrombotic Events



  Clinical trials of several COX-2 selective and nonselective NSAIDs of up to three years duration have shown an increased risk of serious cardiovascular (CV) thrombotic events, myocardial infarction (MI), and stroke, which can be fatal. All NSAIDs, both COX-2 selective and nonselective, may have a similar risk. Patients with known CV disease or risk factors for CV disease may be at greater risk. To minimize the potential risk for an adverse CV event in patients treated with an NSAID, use the lowest effective dose for the shortest duration possible. Physicians and patients should remain alert for the development of such events, even in the absence of previous CV symptoms. Inform patients about the signs and/or symptoms of serious CV events and the steps to take if they occur.



 Two large, controlled, clinical trials of a COX-2 selective NSAID for the treatment of pain in the first 10-14 days following CABG surgery found an increased incidence of MI and stroke [ see  Contraindications (4)    ].



 There is no consistent evidence that concurrent use of aspirin mitigates the increased risk of serious CV thrombotic events associated with NSAID use. The concurrent use of aspirin and an NSAID, such as indomethacin, does increase the risk of serious gastrointestinal (GI) events [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ].



    5.2 Gastrointestinal (GI) Effects - Risk of GI Ulceration, Bleeding, and Perforation



  NSAIDs, including TIVORBEX, can cause serious gastrointestinal (GI) adverse events including inflammation, bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the esophagus, stomach, small intestine, or large intestine, which can be fatal. These serious adverse events can occur at any time, with or without warning symptoms, in patients treated with NSAIDs. Only one in five patients, who develop a serious upper GI adverse event on NSAID therapy, is symptomatic. Upper GI ulcers, gross bleeding or perforation caused by NSAIDs occur in approximately 1% of patients treated for 3-6 months, and in about 2%-4% of patients treated for one year. These trends continue with longer duration of use, increasing the likelihood of developing a serious GI event at some time during the course of therapy. However, even short-term NSAID therapy is not without risk.



 In patients taking indomethacin, intestinal ulceration has been associated with stenosis and obstruction. Gastrointestinal bleeding without obvious ulcer formation and perforation of pre-existing sigmoid lesions (diverticulum, carcinoma, etc.) have occurred. Increased abdominal pain in ulcerative colitis patients or the development of ulcerative colitis and regional ileitis have been reported to occur.



 Prescribe NSAIDs, including TIVORBEX, with extreme caution in patients with a prior history of ulcer disease or GI bleeding. Patients with a prior history of peptic ulcer disease and/or GI bleeding who use NSAIDs have a greater than 10-fold increased risk for developing a GI bleed compared to patients with neither of these risk factors. Other factors that increase the risk for GI bleeding in patients treated with NSAIDs include longer duration of NSAID therapy, concomitant use of oral corticosteroids or anticoagulants, smoking, use of alcohol, older age, and poor general health status. Most spontaneous reports of fatal GI events are in elderly or debilitated patients and therefore, special care should be taken in treating this population.



 To minimize the potential risk for an adverse GI event in patients treated with an NSAID, use the lowest effective dose for the shortest possible duration. Patients and physicians should remain alert for signs and symptoms of GI ulceration and bleeding during NSAID therapy and promptly initiate additional evaluation and treatment if a serious GI adverse event is suspected. This should include discontinuation of the NSAID until a serious GI adverse event is ruled out. For high risk patients, alternative therapies that do not include NSAIDs should be considered.



    5.3 Hepatic Effects



  Borderline elevations of one or more liver tests may occur in up to 15% of patients taking NSAIDs, including TIVORBEX. These laboratory abnormalities may progress, may remain unchanged, or may be transient with continuing therapy. Notable elevations of ALT or AST (approximately three or more times the upper limit of normal) have been reported in approximately 1% of patients in clinical trials with NSAIDs. In addition, rare cases of severe hepatic reactions, including jaundice and fatal fulminant hepatitis, liver necrosis and hepatic failure, some of them with fatal outcomes have been reported.



 A patient with symptoms and/or signs suggesting liver dysfunction, or in whom abnormal liver test values have occurred, should be evaluated for evidence of the development of a more severe hepatic reaction while on therapy with indomethacin. If clinical signs and symptoms consistent with liver disease develop, or if systemic manifestations occur (e.g., eosinophilia, rash, etc.), discontinue TIVORBEX immediately.



    5.4 Hypertension



  NSAIDs, including TIVORBEX, can lead to new onset or worsening of pre-existing hypertension, either of which may contribute to the increased incidence of CV events.



 Use NSAIDs, including TIVORBEX, with caution in patients with hypertension. Monitor blood pressure (BP) closely during the initiation of NSAID treatment and throughout the course of therapy.



 Patients taking ACE inhibitors, thiazides or loop diuretics or beta-adrenoceptor blocking agents may have impaired response to these therapies when taking NSAIDs [ see  Drug Interactions (7.1  ,  7.3  ,  7.7)    ].



    5.5 Congestive Heart Failure and Edema



  Fluid retention and edema have been observed in some patients taking NSAIDs. Use TIVORBEX with caution in patients with fluid retention or heart failure.



 In a study of patients with severe heart failure and hyponatremia, indomethacin was associated with significant deterioration of circulatory hemodynamics, presumably due to inhibition of prostaglandin dependent compensatory mechanisms.



    5.6 Renal Effects



  Use caution when initiating treatment with TIVORBEX in patients with considerable dehydration.



 Long-term administration of NSAIDs has resulted in renal papillary necrosis and other renal injury. Renal toxicity has also been seen in patients in whom renal prostaglandins have a compensatory role in the maintenance of renal perfusion. In these patients, administration of a nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug may cause a dose-dependent reduction in prostaglandin formation and, secondarily, in renal blood flow, which may precipitate over renal decompensation. Patients at greatest risk of this reaction are those with impaired renal function, heart failure, liver dysfunction, those taking diuretics and ACE inhibitors, patients with volume depletion, and the elderly. Discontinuation of NSAID therapy is usually followed by recovery to the pretreatment state [ see  Drug Interactions (7.1  ,  7.7)    ] .  



 Increases in serum potassium concentration, including hyperkalemia, have been reported with use of indomethacin, even in some patients without renal impairment. In patients with normal renal function, these effects have been attributed to a hyporeninemic-hypoaldosteronism state.



    Advanced Renal Disease  



 No information is available from controlled clinical studies regarding the use of indomethacin in patients with advanced renal disease. Therefore, treatment with TIVORBEX is not recommended in patients with advanced renal disease. If TIVORBEX therapy must be initiated, monitor patient renal function closely.



    5.7 Anaphylactic Reactions



  As with other NSAIDs, anaphylactic reactions may occur in patients without known prior exposure to TIVORBEX. TIVORBEX is contraindicated in patients with the aspirin triad. This symptom complex typically occurs in asthmatic patients who experience rhinitis with or without nasal polyps, or who exhibit severe, potentially fatal bronchospasm after taking aspirin or other NSAIDs [ see  Contraindications (4)    ].



 Seek emergency help in cases where an anaphylactic reaction occurs.



    5.8 Central Nervous System Effects



  TIVORBEX may aggravate depression or other psychiatric disturbances, epilepsy, and parkinsonism, and should be used with considerable caution in patients with these conditions. Discontinue TIVORBEX if severe CNS adverse reactions develop.



 TIVORBEX may cause drowsiness; therefore, caution patients about engaging in activities requiring mental alertness and motor coordination, such as driving a car. Indomethacin may also cause headache. Headache which persists despite dosage reduction requires cessation of therapy with TIVORBEX.



    5.9 Skin Reactions



  NSAIDs, including TIVORBEX, can cause serious skin adverse reactions such as exfoliative dermatitis, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome (SJS), and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), which can be fatal. These serious events may occur without warning. Patients should be informed about the signs and symptoms of serious skin manifestations, and discontinue the use of TIVORBEX at the first appearance of skin rash or any other sign of hypersensitivity [ see  Contraindications (4)    ].



    5.10 Fetal Toxicity



  Starting at 30 weeks gestation, TIVORBEX and other NSAIDs should be avoided by pregnant women as premature closure of the ductus arteriosus in the fetus may occur. If this drug is used during this time period in pregnancy, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to a fetus [ see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)    ].



    5.11 Corticosteroid Treatment



  TIVORBEX cannot be expected to substitute for corticosteroids or to treat corticosteroid insufficiency. Abrupt discontinuation of corticosteroids may lead to exacerbation of corticosteroid-responsive illness. Patients on prolonged corticosteroid therapy should have their therapy tapered slowly if a decision is made to discontinue corticosteroids.



    5.12 Masking of Inflammation and Fever



  The pharmacological activity of TIVORBEX in reducing inflammation, and possibly fever, may diminish the utility of diagnostic signs in detecting infectious complications of presumed noninfectious, painful conditions.



    5.13 Hematological Effects



  Anemia may occur in patients receiving NSAIDs, including TIVORBEX. This may be due to fluid retention, occult or gross GI blood loss, or an incompletely described effect upon erythropoiesis. In patients receiving long-term therapy with NSAIDs, including TIVORBEX, check hemoglobin or hematocrit if they exhibit any signs or symptoms of anemia or blood loss. TIVORBEX is not indicated for long-term treatment.



 NSAIDs inhibit platelet aggregation and have been shown to prolong bleeding time in some patients. Unlike aspirin, their effect on platelet function is quantitatively less, of shorter duration, and reversible. Carefully monitor patients treated with TIVORBEX who may be adversely affected by alterations in platelet function, such as those with coagulation disorders or patients receiving anticoagulants.



    5.14 Use in Patients with Preexisting Asthma



  Patients with asthma may have aspirin-sensitive asthma. The use of aspirin in patients with aspirin-sensitive asthma has been associated with severe bronchospasm which can be fatal. Since cross reactivity, including bronchospasm, between aspirin and other NSAIDs has been reported in such aspirin-sensitive patients, TIVORBEX is contraindicated in patients with this form of aspirin sensitivity and should be used with caution in all patients with preexisting asthma [ see  Contraindications (4)    ].



    5.15 Monitoring



  Because serious GI tract ulcerations and bleeding can occur without warning symptoms, physicians should monitor for signs or symptoms of GI bleeding. For patients on long-term treatment with NSAIDs, periodically check their CBC and chemistry profile including liver function tests. Discontinue TIVORBEX if clinical signs and symptoms consistent with liver or renal disease develop, systemic manifestations occur (e.g., eosinophilia, rash, etc.) or if abnormal liver tests persist or worsen. TIVORBEX is not indicated for long-term treatment.



    5.16 Ocular Effects



  Corneal deposits and retinal disturbances, including those of the macula, have been observed in some patients who had received prolonged therapy with TIVORBEX. Be alert to the possible association between the changes noted and TIVORBEX. It is advisable to discontinue therapy if such changes are observed. Blurred vision may be a significant symptom and warrants a thorough ophthalmological examination. Since these changes may be asymptomatic, ophthalmologic examination at periodic intervals is desirable in patients receiving prolonged therapy. TIVORBEX is not indicated for long-term treatment.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
