<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tobi0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  TOBI was generally well tolerated during two clinical studies in 258 cystic fibrosis patients ranging in age from 6 to 48 years. Patients received TOBI in alternating periods of 28 days on and 28 days off drug in addition to their standard cystic fibrosis therapy for a total of 24 weeks.



 Voice alteration and tinnitus were the only adverse experiences reported by significantly more TOBI-treated patients. Thirty-three patients (13%) treated with TOBI complained of voice alteration compared to 17 (7%) placebo patients. Voice alteration was more common in the on-drug periods.



 Eight patients from the TOBI group (3%) reported tinnitus compared to no placebo patients. All episodes were transient, resolved without discontinuation of the TOBI treatment regimen, and were not associated with loss of hearing in audiograms. Tinnitus is one of the sentinel symptoms of cochlear toxicity, and patients with this symptom should be carefully monitored for high frequency hearing loss. The numbers of patients reporting vestibular adverse experiences such as dizziness were similar in the TOBI and placebo groups.



 Nine (3%) patients in the TOBI group and nine (3%) patients in the placebo group had increases in serum creatinine of at least 50% over baseline. In all nine patients in the TOBI group, creatinine decreased at the next visit.



 Table 1 lists the percent of patients with treatment-emergent adverse experiences (spontaneously reported and solicited) that occurred in &gt;5% of TOBI patients during the two Phase III studies.



 Table 1: Percent of Patients With Treatment Emergent Adverse Experiences Occurring in &gt;5% of TOBI Patients 
   1  Includes subjective complaints of fever.   
   2  Includes reported decreases in pulmonary function tests or decreased lung volume on chest radiograph associated with intercurrent illness or study drug administration.   
  
   Adverse Event      TOBI    (n=258)    %      Placebo    (n=262)    %     
 Cough Increased  46.1             47.3              
 Pharyngitis      38.0             39.3              
 Sputum Increased  37.6             39.7              
 Asthenia         35.7             39.3              
 Rhinitis         34.5             33.6              
 Dyspnea          33.7             38.5              
 Fever  1         32.9             43.5              
 Lung Disorder    31.4             31.3              
 Headache         26.7             32.1              
 Chest Pain       26.0             29.8              
 Sputum Discoloration  21.3             19.8              
 Hemoptysis       19.4             23.7              
 Anorexia         18.6             27.9              
 Lung Function Decreased  2    16.3             15.3              
 Asthma           15.9             20.2              
 Vomiting         14.0             22.1              
 Abdominal Pain   12.8             23.7              
 Voice Alteration  12.8             6.5               
 Nausea           11.2             16.0              
 Weight Loss      10.1             15.3              
 Pain             8.1              12.6              
 Sinusitis        8.1              9.2               
 Ear Pain         7.4              8.8               
 Back Pain        7.0              8.0               
 Epistaxis        7.0              6.5               
 Taste Perversion  6.6              6.9               
 Diarrhea         6.2              10.3              
 Malaise          6.2              5.3               
 Lower Respiratory Tract Infection  5.8              8.0               
 Dizziness        5.8              7.6               
 Hyperventilation  5.4              9.9               
 Rash             5.4              6.1               
         Adverse drug reactions (&lt;5%) occurring more frequently with TOBI in the placebo-controlled studies and assessed as drug-related in &gt;=1% of patients:
 

   Ear and labyrinth disorders  



 Tinnitus (3.1%, vs 0% for placebo)



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders  



 Myalgia (4.7%, vs 2.7% for placebo)



   Infections and infestations  



 Laryngitis (4.3%, vs 3.1% for placebo)



   Adverse drug reactions derived from spontaneous reports  



 The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of TOBI. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Ear and labyrinth disorders  



 Hearing loss (see WARNINGS - Ototoxicity)



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders  



 Hypersensitivity, pruritus, urticaria, rash



   Nervous system disorders  



 Aphonia, dysgeusia



   Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders  



 Bronchospasm (see WARNINGS-Bronchospasm), oropharyngeal pain, sputum increased, chest pain



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders  



 Decreased appetite
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
