<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tobi1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6     ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=10 % of TOBI Podhaler and TOBI patients in primary safety population) are cough, lung disorder, productive cough, dyspnea, pyrexia, oropharyngeal pain, dysphonia, hemoptysis, and headache (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation at 1-888-669-6682 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1     Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 TOBI Podhaler has been evaluated for safety in 425 cystic fibrosis patients exposed to at least one dose of TOBI Podhaler, including 273 patients who were exposed across three cycles (6 months) of treatment. Each cycle consisted of 28 days on-treatment (with 112 mg administered twice-daily) and 28 days off-treatment. Patients with serum creatinine &gt;=2 mg/dL and blood urea nitrogen (BUN) &gt;=40 mg/dL were excluded from clinical studies. There were 218 males and 207 females in this population, and reflecting the cystic fibrosis population in the U.S., the vast majority of patients were Caucasian. There were 221 patients &gt;=20 years old, 121 patients &gt;=13 to &lt;20 years old, and 83 patients &gt;=6 to &lt;13 years old. There were 239 patients with screening FEV1% predicted &gt;=50%, 156 patients with screening FEV1% predicted &lt;50%, and 30 patients with missing FEV1% predicted.



 The primary safety population reflects patients from Study 1, an open-label study comparing TOBI Podhaler with TOBI (tobramycin inhalation solution, USP) over three cycles of 4 weeks on treatment followed by 4 weeks off treatment. Randomization, in a planned 3:2 ratio, resulted in 308 patients treated with TOBI Podhaler and 209 patients treated with TOBI. For both the TOBI Podhaler and TOBI groups, mean exposure to medication for each cycle was 28 to 29 days. The mean age for both arms was between 25 and 26 years old. The mean baseline FEV1% predicted for both arms was 53%.



 Table 1 displays adverse drug reactions reported by at least 2% of TOBI Podhaler patients in Study 1, inclusive of all cycles (on and off treatment). Adverse drug reactions are listed according to MedDRA system organ class and sorted within system organ class group in descending order of frequency.



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions Reported in Study 1 (Occurring in &gt;=2% of TOBI Podhaler Patients) 
   1  This includes adverse events of pulmonary or cystic fibrosis exacerbations   
  
   Primary System Organ Class  Preferred Term    TOBI Podhaler    N=308    %      TOBI    N=209    %     
   Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders                                       
       Cough      48.4             31.1              
       Lung disorder  1    33.8             30.1              
       Productive cough  18.2             19.6              
       Dyspnea    15.6             12.4              
       Oropharyngeal pain  14.0             10.5              
       Dysphonia  13.6             3.8               
       Hemoptysis  13.0             12.4              
       Nasal congestion  8.1              7.2               
       Rales      7.1              6.2               
       Wheezing   6.8              6.2               
       Chest discomfort  6.5              2.9               
       Throat irritation  4.5              1.9               
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                       
       Nausea     7.5              9.6               
       Vomiting   6.2              5.7               
       Diarrhea   4.2              1.9               
       Dysgeusia  3.9              0.5               
   Infections and infestations                                       
       Upper respiratory tract infection  6.8              8.6               
   Investigations                                       
       Pulmonary function test decreased  6.8              8.1               
       Forced expiratory volume decreased  3.9              1.0               
       Blood glucose increased  2.9              0.5               
   Vascular disorders                                       
       Epistaxis  2.6              1.9               
   Nervous system disorders                                       
       Headache   11.4             12.0              
   General disorders and administration site conditions                                       
       Pyrexia    15.6             12.4              
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders                                       
       Musculoskeletal chest pain  4.5              4.8               
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                                       
       Rash       2.3              2.4               
         Adverse drug reactions that occurred in &lt;2% of patients treated with TOBI Podhaler in Study 1 were: bronchospasm (TOBI Podhaler 1.6%, TOBI 0.5%); deafness including deafness unilateral (reported as mild to moderate hearing loss or increased hearing loss) (TOBI Podhaler 1.0%, TOBI 0.5%); and tinnitus (TOBI Podhaler 1.9%, TOBI 2.4%).
 

 Discontinuations in Study 1 were higher in the TOBI Podhaler arm compared to TOBI (27% TOBI Podhaler versus 18% TOBI). This was driven primarily by discontinuations due to adverse events (14% TOBI Podhaler versus 8% TOBI). Higher rates of discontinuation were seen in subjects &gt;=20 years old and those with baseline FEV1% predicted &lt;50%.



 Respiratory related hospitalizations occurred in 24% of the patients in the TOBI Podhaler arm and 22% of the patients in the TOBI arm. There was an increased new usage of antipseudomonal medication in the TOBI Podhaler arm (65% TOBI Podhaler versus 55% TOBI). This included oral antibiotics in 55% of TOBI Podhaler patients and 40% of TOBI patients and intravenous antibiotics in 35% of TOBI Podhaler patients and 33% of TOBI patients. Median time to first antipseudomonal usage was 89 days in the TOBI Podhaler arm and 112 days in the TOBI arm.



 The supportive safety population reflects patients from two studies: Study 2, a double-blind, placebo-controlled design for the first treatment cycle, followed by all patients receiving TOBI Podhaler (replaced placebo) for two additional cycles, and Study 3, a double-blind, placebo-controlled trial for one treatment cycle only. Placebo in these studies was inhaled powder without the active ingredient, tobramycin. The patient population for these studies was much younger than in Study 1 (mean age 13 years old).



 Adverse drug reactions reported more frequently by TOBI Podhaler patients in the placebo-controlled cycle (Cycle 1) of Study 2, which included 46 TOBI Podhaler and 49 placebo patients, were:



        Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders  



       Pharyngolaryngeal pain (TOBI Podhaler 10.9%, placebo 0%); dysphonia (TOBI Podhaler 4.3%, placebo 0%)



        Gastrointestinal disorders  



       Dysgeusia (TOBI Podhaler 6.5%, placebo 2.0%)



 Adverse drug reactions reported more frequently by TOBI Podhaler patients in Study 3, which included 30 TOBI Podhaler and 32 placebo patients, were:



        Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders  



       Cough (TOBI Podhaler 10%, placebo 0%)



        Ear and labyrinth disorders  



       Hypoacusis (TOBI Podhaler 10%, placebo 6.3%)



   Audiometric Assessment  



 In Study 1, audiology testing was performed in a subset of approximately 25% of TOBI Podhaler (n=78) and TOBI (n=45) patients. Using the criteria for either ear of &gt;=10 dB loss at two consecutive frequencies, &gt;=20 dB loss at any frequency, or loss of response at three consecutive frequencies where responses were previously obtained, five TOBI Podhaler patients and three TOBI patients were judged to have ototoxicity, a ratio similar to the planned 3:2 randomization for this study.



 Audiology testing was also performed in a subset of patients in both Study 2 (n=13 from the TOBI Podhaler group and n=9 from the placebo group) and Study 3 (n=14 from the TOBI Podhaler group and n=11 from the placebo group). In Study 2, no patients reported hearing complaints but two TOBI Podhaler patients met the criteria for ototoxicity. In Study 3, three TOBI Podhaler and two placebo patients had reports of 'hypoacusis.' One TOBI Podhaler and two placebo patients met the criteria for ototoxicity. In some patients, ototoxicity was transient or may have been related to a conductive defect.



   Cough  



 Cough is a common symptom in cystic fibrosis, reported in 42% of the patients in Study 1 at baseline. Cough was the most frequently reported adverse event in Study 1 and was more common in the TOBI Podhaler arm (48% TOBI Podhaler versus 31 % TOBI). There was a higher rate of cough adverse event reporting during the first week of active treatment with TOBI Podhaler (i.e., the first week of Cycle 1). The time to first cough event in the TOBI Podhaler and TOBI groups were similar thereafter. In some patients, cough resulted in discontinuation of TOBI Podhaler treatment. Sixteen patients (5%) receiving treatment with TOBI Podhaler discontinued study treatment due to cough events compared with 2 (1%) in the TOBI treatment group. Children and adolescents coughed more than adults when treated with TOBI Podhaler, yet the adults were more likely to discontinue: of the 16 patients on TOBI Podhaler in Study 1 who discontinued treatment due to cough events, 14 were &gt;=20 years of age, one patient was between the ages of 13 and &lt;20, and one was between the ages of 6 and &lt;13. The rates of bronchospasm (as measured by &gt;=20% decrease in FEV1% predicted post-dose) were approximately 5% in both treatment groups, and none of these patients experienced concomitant cough.



 In Study 2, cough was the most commonly reported adverse event during the first cycle of treatment (the double blind period of treatment) and occurred more frequently in placebo-treated patients (26.5%) than patients treated with TOBI Podhaler (13%). Similar percentages of patients in both treatment groups reported cough as a baseline symptom. In Study 3, cough events were reported by three patients in the TOBI Podhaler group (10%) and none in the placebo group (0%).



   6.2     Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of TOBI Podhaler. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Nervous system disorders  



 Aphonia



   Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders  



 Sputum discolored



   General disorders and administration site conditions  



 Malaise
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">     5     WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *  Caution should be exercised when prescribing TOBI Podhaler to patients with known or suspected auditory, vestibular, renal, or neuromuscular dysfunction (  5.1  ,  5.2  ,  5.3  ) 
 *  Ototoxicity, as measured by complaints of hearing loss or tinnitus, was reported in clinical trials (  5.1  ) 
 *  Aminoglycosides may aggravate muscle weakness because of a potential curare-like effect on neuromuscular function (  5.3  ) 
 *  Bronchospasm can occur with inhalation of TOBI Podhaler (  5.4  ) 
 *  Audiograms, serum concentrations, and renal function should be monitored as appropriate (  5.5  ) 
 *  Fetal harm can occur when aminoglycosides are administered to a pregnant woman. Apprise women of the potential hazard to the fetus (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1     Ototoxicity



  Caution should be exercised when prescribing TOBI Podhaler to patients with known or suspected auditory or vestibular dysfunction.



 Ototoxicity, as measured by complaints of hearing loss or tinnitus, was reported by patients in the TOBI Podhaler clinical studies [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  . Tinnitus may be a sentinel symptom of ototoxicity, and therefore the onset of this symptom warrants caution. Ototoxicity, manifested as both auditory (hearing loss) and vestibular toxicity, has been reported with parenteral aminoglycosides. Vestibular toxicity may be manifested by vertigo, ataxia or dizziness.



    5.2     Nephrotoxicity



  Caution should be exercised when prescribing TOBI Podhaler to patients with known or suspected renal dysfunction.



 Nephrotoxicity was not observed during TOBI Podhaler clinical studies but has been associated with aminoglycosides as a class.



    5.3     Neuromuscular Disorders



  Caution should be exercised when prescribing TOBI Podhaler to patients with known or suspected neuromuscular dysfunction.



 TOBI Podhaler should be used cautiously in patients with neuromuscular disorders, such as myasthenia gravis or Parkinson's disease, since aminoglycosides may aggravate muscle weakness because of a potential curare-like effect on neuromuscular function.



    5.4     Bronchospasm



  Bronchospasm can occur with inhalation of TOBI Podhaler [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  . Bronchospasm should be treated as medically appropriate.



    5.5     Laboratory Tests



   Audiograms  



 Physicians should consider an audiogram at baseline, particularly for patients at increased risk of auditory dysfunction.



 If a patient reports tinnitus or hearing loss during TOBI Podhaler therapy, the physician should refer that patient for audiological assessment.



  Serum Concentrations  



 In patients treated with TOBI Podhaler, serum tobramycin concentrations are approximately 1 to 2 mcg/mL one hour after dose administration and do not require routine monitoring. Serum concentrations of tobramycin in patients with known or suspected auditory or renal dysfunction or patients treated with a concomitant parenteral aminoglycoside (or other nephrotoxic or ototoxic medications) should be monitored at the discretion of the treating physician. If ototoxicity or nephrotoxicity occurs in a patient receiving TOBI Podhaler, tobramycin therapy should be discontinued until serum concentrations fall below 2 mcg/mL.



 The serum concentration of tobramycin should only be monitored through venipuncture and not finger prick blood sampling. Contamination of the skin of the fingers with tobramycin may lead to falsely increased measurements of serum levels of the drug. This contamination cannot be completely avoided by hand washing before testing.



  Renal Function  



 Laboratory tests of urine and renal function should be conducted at the discretion of the treating physician.



    5.6     Use in Pregnancy



  Aminoglycosides can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Aminoglycosides cross the placenta, and streptomycin has been associated with several reports of total, irreversible, bilateral congenital deafness in pediatric patients exposed in utero. Patients who use TOBI Podhaler during pregnancy, or become pregnant while taking TOBI Podhaler should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus [see Use in Specific Populations (8.1)]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
