<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tolak" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Application Site Adverse Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Hypersensitivity Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Ophthalmic Adverse Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Photosensitivity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Embryofetal toxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Toxicity in Patients with Dihydropyrimidine Dehydrogenase Deficiency [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common (incidence &gt; 68%) adverse reactions occur at the application site and include erythema, scaling/dryness, crusting, pruritus, stinging/burning, edema, and erosions. Erythema is observed in 99% of patients with actinic keratosis treated with Tolak Cream (  6.1  ).
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Hill Dermaceuticals at 1-800-344-5707 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The data described below reflect exposure to Tolak Cream in 397 subjects with actinic keratosis in vehicle-controlled trials. The population ranged in age from 33 to 94 years, was 80% male, and almost all were Caucasian. Most subjects were treated with Tolak Cream once daily for 4 weeks. Throughout the 4-week treatment and the 4-week post-treatment periods, the trials specifically monitored for adverse reactions related to tolerability, including erythema, scaling/dryness, edema, crusting, erosions, stinging/burning, and pruritus.



 The number and percentage of subjects with each of these monitored adverse reactions at one or more post-baseline visit(s) during the clinical trials are shown in Table 1.



 Table 1: Incidence of Application Site Adverse Reactions Occurring with 4 Weeks of Tolak Cream Treatment in Clinical Trials 1 and 2 
                           Tolak CreamN=397n (%)  VehicleN=120n (%)     
                           Mild, Moderate or Severe  Severe Only          Mild, Moderate or Severe  Severe Only           
  
 Erythema                  394 (99%)            174 (44%)            102 (85%)            0 (0%)                
 Scaling/ Dryness          377 (95%)            94 (24%)             99 (83%)             0 (0%)                
 Crusting                  346 (87%)            87 (22%)             46 (38%)             0 (0%)                
 Pruritus                  337 (85%)            65 (16%)             46 (38%)             1 (1%)                
 Stinging/ Burning         346 (87%)            101 (25%)            42 (35%)             0 (0%)                
 Edema                     275 (69%)            30 (8%)              11 (9%)              0 (0%)                
 Erosions                  271 (68%)            44 (11%)             14 (12%)             0 (0%)                
           In these clinical trials, the intensity of the adverse reactions in subjects using Tolak Cream generally increased over the 4-week treatment period, usually reaching maximal levels at 4 weeks of treatment and then diminishing to baseline levels within 4 weeks after cessation of treatment.
 

 In Trials 1 and 2, 11% of Tolak Cream-treated and 3% of vehicle-treated subjects discontinued treatment because of adverse reactions. Of these subjects, the majority had adverse reactions at the application site. Eye swelling, leading to discontinuation, occurred in one subject with Tolak Cream use  .  



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of topical fluorouracil. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders  : leukocytosis, pancytopenia, thrombocytopenia, eosinophilia, neutrophil toxic granulation



   Eye disorders  : corneal disorder, conjunctival disorder, eye irritation, conjunctivitis, lacrimation



   Gastrointestinal disorders  : stomatitis



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions  : medicinal taste



   Infections and Infestations  : herpes simplex



   Neoplasms  : chronic lymphocytic leukemia, non-melanoma skin cancer



   Nervous system disorders  : insomnia, irritability



   Psychiatric disorders  : emotional distress



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders  : blistering, allergic contact dermatitis, photosensitivity, pain, scarring, skin irritation, rash, ulceration, hyperpigmentation, alopecia, bullous pemphigoid, ichthyosis, suppuration, swelling, soreness, telangiectasia, tenderness, urticaria
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Application site adverse reactions are likely to occur during and for 4 weeks after treatment of actinic keratosis with Tolak Cream (  5.1  ). 
 *  Hypersensitivity reactions may occur with Tolak Cream (  5.2  ). 
 *  Avoid treatment in the periocular area. Eye disorders, including corneal reactions have occurred with topical fluorouracil use. Avoid accidental transfer of the drug into eyes and to the periocular area. If accidental exposure occurs, seek medical care (  5.3  ). 
 *  Increased sensitivity to ultraviolet light may occur during and immediately after treatment with Tolak Cream (  5.4  ). 
 *  Fluorouracil may cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Advise females of reproductive potential to use effective contraception (  5.5  ). 
 *  Increased fluorouracil exposures may occur in DPD deficiency. Discontinue Tolak Cream if symptoms of fluorouracil's systemic toxicity develop (  5.6  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Application Site Adverse Reactions



  Application site reactions (erythema, scaling/dryness, edema, crusting, erosions, stinging/burning, and pruritus) were observed in almost all patients during treatment of actinic keratosis on the face, ears, and/or scalp with topical fluorouracil [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . In the clinical trials of Tolak Cream, application site irritation returned to baseline (pre-treatment) levels within 4 weeks after discontinuing treatment.



 Do not apply Tolak Cream directly into eyes, nose, mouth, or other mucous membranes because irritation, local inflammation and ulceration can occur.



    5.2 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Allergic contact dermatitis (delayed type hypersensitivity reaction) has been noted for topical fluorouracil drugs. While application site reactions are observed in almost all patients during treatment of actinic keratosis with topical fluorouracil [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ]  , delayed type hypersensitivity should be suspected in the event of severe pruritus or eczema at the application site or at a distant site. Although the potential for a delayed hypersensitivity reaction to fluorouracil exists, patch testing to confirm hypersensitivity may be inconclusive.



 Tolak Cream contains peanut oil. If signs of hypersensitivity occur, patients should discontinue Tolak Cream immediately and contact their healthcare provider.



    5.3 Ophthalmic Adverse Reactions



  Corneal and conjunctival disorders have occurred with topical fluorouracil use [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ]  . Avoid application to the periocular area. To avoid transfer of the drug into the eyes and to the periocular area during and after application, patients should wash hands well after applying Tolak Cream. If accidental exposure occurs, the patient should flush eye(s) with large amounts of water and seek medical care as soon as possible.



    5.4 Photosensitivity



  Topical fluorouracil is associated with photosensitivity reactions including severe sunburn. Minimize exposure to ultraviolet rays including sunlight, sun lamps, and tanning beds during and immediately following treatment with Tolak Cream because the intensity of the photosensitivity reaction may be increased.



    5.5 Embryofetal Toxicity



  Cases of miscarriage and birth defects (including cleft lip and cleft palate) have been reported when pregnant women were exposed to a topical or parenteral fluorouracil product. In addition, ventricular septal defect and cases of miscarriage occurred when pregnant women applied a topical fluorouracil product to mucous membranes (Tolak Cream is not indicated for use on the mucous membrane). Furthermore, fluorouracil interferes with the synthesis of deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA), inhibits the formation of ribonucleic acid (RNA), and provokes unbalanced growth and death of cells. Therefore, Tolak Cream is contraindicated in pregnancy.



 Advise females of reproductive potential to use effective contraception during Tolak use and for one month after the last dose of Tolak Cream .  



    5.6 Toxicity in Patients with Dihydropyrimidine Dehydrogenase Deficiency



  Life-threatening systemic toxicity has been reported with the topical use of fluorouracil in a patient with DPD deficiency. Symptoms included severe abdominal pain, bloody diarrhea, vomiting, fever, and chills. Physical examination revealed stomatitis, erythematous skin rash, neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, inflammation of the esophagus, stomach and small bowel.



 A large percentage of fluorouracil is catabolized by the DPD enzyme. DPD enzyme deficiency may result in increased availability of fluorouracil to the anabolic pathway, which may lead to increased interference with DNA and RNA synthesis and increased cytotoxic activity and potential toxicities [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.1)  ]  . Therefore, Tolak Cream is contraindicated in patients with DPD deficiency.



 Patients should discontinue Tolak Cream if symptoms of fluorouracil's systemic toxicity develop.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
