<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tolterodine" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=4% and &gt;placebo) were dry mouth, headache, constipation, and abdominal pain. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Greenstone LLC at 1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  The efficacy and safety of tolterodine tartrate extended  -  release capsules was evaluated in 1073 patients (537 assigned to tolterodine tartrate extended  -  release capsules; 536 assigned to placebo) who were treated with 2, 4, 6, or 8 mg/day for up to 15 months. These included a total of 1012 patients (505 randomized to tolterodine tartrate extended  -  release capsules 4 mg once daily and 507 randomized to placebo) enrolled in a randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind, 12-week clinical efficacy and safety study.



 Adverse events were reported in 52% (n=263) of patients receiving tolterodine tartrate extended  -  release capsules and in 49% (n=247) of patients receiving placebo. The most common adverse events reported by patients receiving tolterodine tartrate extended  -  release capsules were dry mouth, headache, constipation, and abdominal pain. Dry mouth was the most frequently reported adverse event for patients treated with tolterodine tartrate extended  -  release capsules, occurring in 23.4% of patients treated with tolterodine tartrate extended  -  release capsules and 7.7% of placebo-treated patients. Dry mouth, constipation, abnormal vision (accommodation abnormalities), urinary retention, and dry eyes are expected side effects of antimuscarinic agents. A serious adverse event was reported by 1.4% (n=7) of patients receiving tolterodine tartrate extended  -  release capsules and by 3.6% (n=18) of patients receiving placebo.



 Table 1 lists the adverse events, regardless of causality, that were reported in the randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled 12-week study at an incidence greater than placebo and in greater than or equal to 1% of patients treated with tolterodine tartrate extended  -  release capsules 4 mg once daily.



 Table 1. Incidencein nearest integer. (%) of Adverse Events Exceeding Placebo Rate and Reported in &gt;=1% of Patients Treated with Tolterodine Tartrate Extended-Release Capsules (4 mg daily) in a 12-week, Phase 3 Clinical Trial 
 Body System                  Adverse Event              % Tolterodine Tartrate Extended-Release Capsulesn=505       % Placebon=507         
  
 Autonomic Nervous            dry mouth                            23                         8               
 General                      headache                              6                         5               
 fatigue                      2                                     1              
 Central/Peripheral Nervous   dizziness                             2                         1               
 Gastrointestinal             constipation                          6                         4               
 abdominal pain               4                                     2              
 dyspepsia                    3                                     1              
 Vision                       xerophthalmia                         3                         2               
 vision abnormal              1                                     0              
 Psychiatric                  somnolence                            3                         2               
 anxiety                      1                                     0              
 Respiratory                  sinusitis                             2                         1               
 Urinary                      dysuria                               1                         0               
          The frequency of discontinuation due to adverse events was highest during the first 4 weeks of treatment. Similar percentages of patients treated with tolterodine tartrate extended  -  release capsules or placebo discontinued treatment due to adverse events. Dry mouth was the most common adverse event leading to treatment discontinuation among patients receiving tolterodine tartrate extended  -  release capsules [n=12 (2.4%) vs. placebo n=6 (1.2%)].
 

   6.2 Post-marketing Experience

  The following events have been reported in association with tolterodine use in worldwide post-marketing experience:



   General:  anaphylaxis and angioedema;  Cardiovascular:  tachycardia, palpitations, peripheral edema;  Gastrointestinal:  diarrhea  ;    Central/Peripheral Nervous:  confusion, disorientation, memory impairment, hallucinations.



 Reports of aggravation of symptoms of dementia (e.g., confusion, disorientation, delusion) have been reported after tolterodine therapy was initiated in patients taking cholinesterase inhibitors for the treatment of dementia.



 Because these spontaneously reported events are from the worldwide post-marketing experience, the frequency of events and the role of tolterodine in their causation cannot be reliably determined.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Anaphylaxis and angioedema requiring hospitalization and emergency medical treatment have occurred with the first or subsequent doses of tolterodine tartrate extended - release capsules. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Urinary Retention: use caution in patients with clinically significant bladder outflow obstruction because of the risk of urinary retention. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Gastrointestinal Disorders: use caution in patients with gastrointestinal obstructive disorders or decreased gastrointestinal motility because of the risk of gastric retention. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Controlled Narrow-Angle Glaucoma: use caution in patients being treated for narrow-angle glaucoma. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Central Nervous System Effects: Somnolence has been reported with tolterodine tartrate extended - release capsules. Advise patients not to drive or operate heavy machinery until they know how tolterodine tartrate extended - release capsules affect them (  5.5  ). 
 *  Myasthenia Gravis: use caution in patients with myasthenia gravis. (  5.8  ) 
 *  QT Prolongation : consider observations from the thorough QT study in clinical decisions to prescribe tolterodine tartrate extended - release capsules to patients with a known history of QT prolongation or to patients who are taking Class IA (e.g., quinidine, procainamide) or Class III (e.g., amiodarone, sotalol) antiarrhythmic medications. (  5.9  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Angioedema



  Anaphylaxis and angioedema requiring hospitalization and emergency medical treatment have occurred with the first or subsequent doses of tolterodine tartrate extended -  release capsules. In the event of difficulty in breathing, upper airway obstruction, or fall in blood pressure, tolterodine tartrate extended-release capsules should be discontinued and appropriate therapy promptly provided.



    5.2 Urinary Retention



  Administer tolterodine tartrate extended -  release capsules with caution to patients with clinically significant bladder outflow obstruction because of the risk of urinary retention [ see   CONTRAINDICATIONS (4)      ].



    5.3 Gastrointestinal Disorders



  Administer tolterodine tartrate extended -  release capsules with caution in patients with gastrointestinal obstructive disorders because of the risk of gastric retention.



 Tolterodine tartrate extended -  release capsules, like other antimuscarinic drugs, may decrease gastrointestinal motility and should be used with caution in patients with conditions associated with decreased gastrointestinal motility (e.g., intestinal atony) [ see   CONTRAINDICATIONS (4)      ].



    5.4 Controlled Narrow-Angle Glaucoma



  Administer tolterodine tartrate extended -  release capsules with caution in patients being treated for narrow-angle glaucoma [ see   CONTRAINDICATIONS (4)      ].



    5.5 Central Nervous System Effects



  Tolterodine tartrate extended -  release capsules are associated with anticholinergic central nervous system (CNS) effects [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ] including dizziness and somnolence [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]. Patients should be monitored for signs of anticholinergic CNS effects, particularly after beginning treatment or increasing the dose. Advise patients not to drive or operate heavy machinery until the drug's effects have been determined. If a patient experiences anticholinergic CNS effects, dose reduction or drug discontinuation should be considered.



    5.6 Hepatic Impairment



  The clearance of orally administered tolterodine immediate -  release was substantially lower in cirrhotic patients than in the healthy volunteers. For patients with mild to moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class A or B), the recommended dose for tolterodine tartrate extended -  release capsules is 2 mg once daily. Tolterodine tartrate extended -  release capsules are not recommended for use in patients with severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class C) [ see   DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION (2.2)    and   USE IN SPECIFIC POPULATIONS (8.6)      ] .  



    5.7 Renal Impairment



  Renal impairment can significantly alter the disposition of tolterodine and its metabolites. The dose of tolterodine tartrate extended -  release capsules should be reduced to 2 mg once daily in patients with severe renal impairment (CCr: 10-30 mL/min). Patients with CCr&lt;10 mL/min have not been studied and use of tolterodine tartrate extended -  release capsules in this population is not recommended [ see   DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION (2.2)    and   USE IN SPECIFIC POPULATIONS (8.7)      ].



    5.8 Myasthenia Gravis



  Administer tolterodine tartrate extended -  release capsules with caution in patients with myasthenia gravis, a disease characterized by decreased cholinergic activity at the neuromuscular junction.



    5.9 Use in Patients with Congenital or Acquired QT Prolongation



  In a study of the effect of tolterodine immediate -  release tablets on the QT interval [ see   CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY (12.2)      ], the effect on the QT interval appeared greater for 8 mg/day (two times the therapeutic dose) compared to 4 mg/day and was more pronounced in CYP2D6 poor metabolizers (PM) than extensive metabolizers (EMs). The effect of tolterodine 8 mg/day was not as large as that observed after four days of therapeutic dosing with the active control moxifloxacin. However, the confidence intervals overlapped.



 These observations should be considered in clinical decisions to prescribe tolterodine tartrate extended -  release capsules to patients with a known history of QT prolongation or to patients who are taking Class IA (e.g., quinidine, procainamide) or Class III (e.g., amiodarone, sotalol) antiarrhythmic medications. There has been no association of Torsade de Pointes in the international post-marketing experience with tolterodine tartrate extended -  release capsules.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
