<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="topamax1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Acute Myopia and Secondary Angle Closure [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Visual Field Defects [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Oligohidrosis and Hyperthermia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Metabolic Acidosis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Suicidal Behavior and Ideation [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Cognitive/Neuropsychiatric Adverse Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *  Fetal Toxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)   and   Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ]  
 *  Sudden Unexplained Death in Epilepsy (SUDEP) [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  
 *  Hyperammonemia and Encephalopathy (Without and With Concomitant Valproic Acid [VPA] Use) [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  
 *  Kidney Stones [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.11)  ]  
 *  Hypothermia with Concomitant Valproic Acid (VPA) Use [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.12)  ]  
 *  Paresthesia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.13)  ]  
    The data described in the following sections were obtained using TOPAMAX  (r)  (topiramate) Tablets.
 

   EXCERPT:   The most common (&gt;= 10% more frequent than placebo or low-dose TOPAMAX  (r)  in monotherapy) adverse reactions at recommended dosing in adult and pediatric controlled, epilepsy clinical trials were paresthesia, anorexia, weight decrease, speech disorder related speech problem, fatigue, dizziness, somnolence, nervousness, psychomotor slowing, abnormal vision, and fever. The most common (&gt;= 5% more frequent than placebo) adverse reactions at recommended dosing in adult and adolescent controlled, migraine clinical trials were paresthesia, anorexia, weight decrease, difficulty with memory, taste perversion, upper respiratory tract infection, abdominal pain, diarrhea, hypoesthesia, and nausea (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Janssen Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-800-JANSSEN (1-800-526-7736) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, the incidence of adverse reactions observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to the incidence of adverse reactions in the clinical trials of another drug, and may not reflect the incidence of adverse reactions observed in practice.



     Increased Risk for Bleeding  



 Topiramate treatment is associated with an increased risk for bleeding. In a pooled analysis of placebo-controlled studies of approved and unapproved indications, bleeding was more frequently reported as an adverse event for TOPAMAX  (r)  than for placebo (4.5% versus 3.0% in adult patients, and 4.4% versus 2.3% in pediatric patients). In this analysis, the incidence of serious bleeding events for TOPAMAX  (r)  and placebo was 0.3% versus 0.2% for adult patients, and 0.4% versus 0% for pediatric patients.



 Adverse bleeding reactions reported with TOPAMAX  (r)  ranged from mild epistaxis, ecchymosis, and increased menstrual bleeding to life-threatening hemorrhages. In patients with serious bleeding events, conditions that increased the risk for bleeding were often present, or patients were often taking drugs that cause thrombocytopenia (other antiepileptic drugs) or affect platelet function or coagulation (e.g., aspirin, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors, or warfarin or other anticoagulants).



     Monotherapy Epilepsy  



     Adults &gt;=16 Years  



 The adverse reactions in the controlled trial that occurred most commonly in adults in the 400 mg/day TOPAMAX  (r)  group and at an incidence higher (&gt;= 5 %) than in the 50 mg/day group were: paresthesia, weight decrease, anorexia, somnolence, and difficulty with memory (see  Table 5  ).



 Approximately 21% of the 159 adult patients in the 400 mg/day group who received topiramate as monotherapy in the controlled clinical trial discontinued therapy due to adverse reactions. The most common (&gt;= 2% more frequent than low-dose 50 mg/day TOPAMAX  (r)  ) adverse reactions causing discontinuation in this trial were difficulty with memory, fatigue, asthenia, insomnia, somnolence, and paresthesia.



     Pediatric Patients 6 to &lt;16 Years of Age  



 The adverse reactions in the controlled trial that occurred most commonly in pediatric patients in the 400 mg/day TOPAMAX  (r)  group and at an incidence higher (&gt;= 5%) than in the 50 mg/day group were fever, weight decrease, mood problems, cognitive problems, infection, flushing, and paresthesia (see  Table 5  ). Table 5 also presents the incidence of adverse reactions occurring in at least 2% of adult and pediatric patients treated with 400 mg/day TOPAMAX  (r)  and occurring with greater incidence than 50 mg/day TOPAMAX  (r)  .



 Approximately 14% of the 77 pediatric patients in the 400 mg/day group who received TOPAMAX  (r)  as monotherapy in the controlled clinical trial discontinued therapy due to adverse reactions. The most common (&gt;= 2% more frequent than low-dose 50 mg/day TOPAMAX  (r)  ) adverse reactions resulting in discontinuation in this trial were difficulty with concentration/attention, fever, flushing, and confusion.



 Table 5: Incidence (%) of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions in Monotherapy Epilepsy Where the Incidence Was at Least 2% in Any TOPAMAX(r) Group and the Incidence in the 400 mg/day TOPAMAX(r) Group Was Greater Than the Incidence in the 50 mg/day TOPAMAX(r) Group for Adults (&gt;=16 Years) and Pediatric (6 to &lt;16 Years) Patients in Study TOPMAX-EPMN-106 
                                              Age Group      
                                           Pediatric(6 to &lt;16 Years)  Adult(Age &gt;=16 Years)   
                                           TOPAMAX  (r)  Daily Dosage Group (mg/day)   
                                                 50               400              50               400         
 Body System                                   (N=74)           (N=77)           (N=160)          (N=159)       
   Adverse Reaction                               %                %                %                %          
  
   Body as a Whole - General Disorders      
   Asthenia                                       0                3                4                6          
   Chest pain                                                                       1                2          
   Fever                                          1               12                                            
   Leg pain                                                                         2                3          
   Central &amp; Peripheral Nervous System Disorders     
   Ataxia                                                                           3                4          
   Dizziness                                                                       13               14          
   Hypertonia                                                                       0                3          
   Hypoesthesia                                                                     4                5          
   Muscle contractions involuntary                0                3                                            
   Paresthesia                                    3               12               21               40          
   Vertigo                                        0                3                                            
   Gastro-Intestinal System Disorders       
   Constipation                                                                     1                4          
   Diarrhea                                       8                9                                            
   Gastritis                                                                        0                3          
   Gastroesophageal reflux                                                          1                2          
   Dry mouth                                                                        1                3          
   Liver and Biliary System Disorders       
   Gamma-GT increased                                                               1                3          
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders      
   Weight decrease                                7               17                6               17          
   Platelet, Bleeding &amp; Clotting Disorders     
   Epistaxis                                      0                4                                            
   Psychiatric Disorders                    
   Anorexia                                                                         4               14          
   Anxiety                                                                          4                6          
   Cognitive problems                             1                6                1                4          
   Confusion                                      0                3                                            
   Depression                                     0                3                7                9          
   Difficulty with concentration/attention         7               10                7                8          
   Difficulty with memory                         1                3                6               11          
   Insomnia                                                                         8                9          
   Libido decreased                                                                 0                3          
   Mood problems                                  1                8                2                5          
   Personality disorder(behavior problems)         0                3                                            
   Psychomotor slowing                                                              3                5          
   Somnolence                                                                      10               15          
   Red Blood Cell Disorders                 
   Anemia                                         1                3                                            
   Reproductive Disorders, Female           
   Intermenstrual Bleeding                        0                3                                            
   Vaginal Hemorrhage                                                               0                3          
   Resistance Mechanism Disorders           
   Infection                                      3                8                2                3          
   Infection viral                                3                6                6                8          
   Respiratory System Disorders             
   Bronchitis                                     1                5                3                4          
   Dyspnea                                                                          1                2          
   Rhinitis                                       5                6                2                4          
   Sinusitis                                      1                4                                            
   Upper respiratory tract infection             16               18                                            
   Skin and Appendages Disorders            
   Acne                                                                             2                3          
   Alopecia                                       1                4                3                4          
   Pruritus                                                                         1                4          
   Rash                                           3                4                1                4          
   Special Senses Other, Disorders          
   Taste perversion                                                                 3                5          
   Urinary System Disorders                 
   Cystitis                                                                         1                3          
   Dysuria                                                                          0                2          
   Micturition frequency                          0                3                0                2          
   Renal calculus                                                                   0                3          
   Urinary incontinence                           1                3                                            
   Urinary tract infection                                                          1                2          
   Vascular (Extracardiac) Disorders        
   Flushing                                       0                5                                            
               Adjunctive Therapy Epilepsy  
 

 The most commonly observed adverse reactions associated with the use of TOPAMAX  (r)  at dosages of 200 to 400 mg/day (recommended dose range) in controlled trials in adults with partial onset seizures, primary generalized tonic-clonic seizures, or Lennox-Gastaut syndrome, that were seen at an incidence higher (&gt;= 5%) than in the placebo group were : somnolence, weight decrease, anorexia, dizziness, ataxia, speech disorders and related speech problems, language problems, psychomotor slowing, confusion, abnormal vision, difficulty with memory, paresthesia, diplopia, nervousness, and asthenia (see  Table 6  ). Dose-related adverse reactions at dosages of 200 to 1,000 mg/day are shown in Table 8.



 The most commonly observed adverse reactions associated with the use of TOPAMAX  (r)  at dosages of 5 to 9 mg/kg/day in controlled trials in pediatric patients with partial onset seizures, primary generalized tonic-clonic seizures, or Lennox-Gastaut syndrome, that were seen at an incidence higher (&gt;= 5%) than in the placebo group were : fatigue, somnolence, anorexia, nervousness, difficulty with concentration/attention, difficulty with memory, aggressive reaction, and weight decrease (see  Table 9  ). Table 9 also presents the incidence of adverse reactions occurring in at least 1% of pediatric patients treated with TOPAMAX  (r)  and occurring with greater incidence than placebo.



 In controlled clinical trials in adults, 11% of patients receiving TOPAMAX  (r)  200 to 400 mg/day as adjunctive therapy discontinued due to adverse reactions. This rate appeared to increase at dosages above 400 mg/day. Adverse reactions associated with discontinuing therapy included somnolence, dizziness, anxiety, difficulty with concentration or attention, fatigue, and paresthesia and increased at dosages above 400 mg/day. None of the pediatric patients who received TOPAMAX  (r)  adjunctive therapy at 5 to 9 mg/kg/day in controlled clinical trials discontinued due to adverse reactions.



 Approximately 28% of the 1757 adults with epilepsy who received TOPAMAX  (r)  at dosages of 200 to 1,600 mg/day in clinical studies discontinued treatment because of adverse reactions; an individual patient could have reported more than one adverse reaction. These adverse reactions were psychomotor slowing (4.0%), difficulty with memory (3.2%), fatigue (3.2%), confusion (3.1%), somnolence (3.2%), difficulty with concentration/attention (2.9%), anorexia (2.7%), depression (2.6%), dizziness (2.5%), weight decrease (2.5%), nervousness (2.3%), ataxia (2.1%), and paresthesia (2.0%). Approximately 11% of the 310 pediatric patients who received TOPAMAX  (r)  at dosages up to 30 mg/kg/day discontinued due to adverse reactions. Adverse reactions associated with discontinuing therapy included aggravated convulsions (2.3%), difficulty with concentration/attention (1.6%), language problems (1.3%), personality disorder (1.3%), and somnolence (1.3%).



     Incidence in Epilepsy Controlled Clinical Trials - Adjunctive Therapy - Partial Onset Seizures, Primary Generalized Tonic-Clonic Seizures, and Lennox-Gastaut Syndrome  



 Table 6 lists the incidence of adverse reactions that occurred in at least 1% of adults treated with 200 to 400 mg/day TOPAMAX  (r)  (and also higher daily dosing of 600 mg to 1000 mg) in controlled trials and that was numerically greater with TOPAMAX  (r)  than with placebo. In general, most patients who experienced adverse reactions during the first eight weeks of these trials no longer experienced them by their last visit. Table 9 lists the incidence of treatment-emergent adverse reactions that occurred in at least 1% of pediatric patients treated with 5 to 9 mg/kg TOPAMAX  (r)  in controlled trials and that was numerically greater than the incidence in patients treated with placebo.



 The prescriber should be aware that these data were obtained when TOPAMAX  (r)  was added to concurrent antiepileptic drug therapy and cannot be used to predict the frequency of adverse reactions in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors may differ from those prevailing during clinical studies. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be directly compared with data obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatments, uses, or investigators. Inspection of these frequencies, however, does provide the prescribing physician with a basis to estimate the relative contribution of drug and non-drug factors to the adverse reaction incidences in the population studied.



     Other Adverse Reactions Observed During Double-Blind Epilepsy Adjunctive Therapy Trials  



 Other adverse reactions that occurred in more than 1% of adults treated with 200 to 400 mg of TOPAMAX  (r)  in placebo-controlled epilepsy trials but with equal or greater frequency in the placebo group were headache, injury, anxiety, rash, pain, convulsions aggravated, coughing, fever, diarrhea, vomiting, muscle weakness, insomnia, personality disorder, dysmenorrhea, upper respiratory tract infection, and eye pain.



 Table 6: Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions in Placebo-Controlled, Add-On Epilepsy Trials in AdultsPatients in these add-on/ adjunctive trials were receiving 1 to 2 concomitant antiepileptic drugs in addition to TOPAMAX(r) or placebo., Values represent the percentage of patients reporting a given adverse reaction. Patients may have reported more than one adverse reaction during the study and can be included in more than one adverse reaction category. Where Incidence Was &gt;=1% in Any TOPAMAX(r) Group and Greater Than the Incidence in Placebo-Treated Patients 
                                                                 TOPAMAX  (r)  Dosage (mg/day)   
 Body System/                                    Placebo               200-400              600-1,000         
   Adverse Reaction                              (N=291)               (N=183)               (N=414)          
  
   Body as a Whole-General Disorders        
   Fatigue                                          13                    15                    30            
   Asthenia                                         1                     6                     3             
   Back pain                                        4                     5                     3             
   Chest pain                                       3                     4                     2             
   Influenza-like symptoms                          2                     3                     4             
   Leg pain                                         2                     2                     4             
   Hot flushes                                      1                     2                     1             
   Allergy                                          1                     2                     3             
   Edema                                            1                     2                     1             
   Body odor                                        0                     1                     0             
   Rigors                                           0                     1                     &lt;1            
   Central &amp; Peripheral Nervous System Disorders     
   Dizziness                                        15                    25                    32            
   Ataxia                                           7                     16                    14            
   Speech disorders/Related speech problems           2                     13                    11            
   Paresthesia                                      4                     11                    19            
   Nystagmus                                        7                     10                    11            
   Tremor                                           6                     9                     9             
   Language problems                                1                     6                     10            
   Coordination abnormal                            2                     4                     4             
   Hypoesthesia                                     1                     2                     1             
   Gait abnormal                                    1                     3                     2             
   Muscle contractions involuntary                  1                     2                     2             
   Stupor                                           0                     2                     1             
   Vertigo                                          1                     1                     2             
   Gastro-Intestinal System Disorders       
   Nausea                                           8                     10                    12            
   Dyspepsia                                        6                     7                     6             
   Abdominal pain                                   4                     6                     7             
   Constipation                                     2                     4                     3             
   Gastroenteritis                                  1                     2                     1             
   Dry mouth                                        1                     2                     4             
   Gingivitis                                       &lt;1                    1                     1             
   GI disorder                                      &lt;1                    1                     0             
   Hearing and Vestibular Disorders         
   Hearing decreased                                1                     2                     1             
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders      
   Weight decrease                                  3                     9                     13            
   Muscle-Skeletal System Disorders         
   Myalgia                                          1                     2                     2             
   Skeletal pain                                    0                     1                     0             
   Platelet, Bleeding, &amp; Clotting Disorders     
   Epistaxis                                        1                     2                     1             
   Psychiatric Disorders                    
   Somnolence                                       12                    29                    28            
   Nervousness                                      6                     16                    19            
   Psychomotor slowing                              2                     13                    21            
   Difficulty with memory                           3                     12                    14            
   Anorexia                                         4                     10                    12            
   Confusion                                        5                     11                    14            
   Depression                                       5                     5                     13            
   Difficulty with concentration/attention           2                     6                     14            
   Mood problems                                    2                     4                     9             
   Agitation                                        2                     3                     3             
   Aggressive reaction                              2                     3                     3             
   Emotional lability                               1                     3                     3             
   Cognitive problems                               1                     3                     3             
   Libido decreased                                 1                     2                     &lt;1            
   Apathy                                           1                     1                     3             
   Depersonalization                                1                     1                     2             
   Reproductive Disorders, Female           
   Breast pain                                      2                     4                     0             
   Amenorrhea                                       1                     2                     2             
   Menorrhagia                                      0                     2                     1             
   Menstrual disorder                               1                     2                     1             
   Reproductive Disorders, Male             
   Prostatic disorder                               &lt;1                    2                     0             
   Resistance Mechanism Disorders           
   Infection                                        1                     2                     1             
   Infection viral                                  1                     2                     &lt;1            
   Moniliasis                                       &lt;1                    1                     0             
 R  espiratory System Disorders             
   Pharyngitis                                      2                     6                     3             
   Rhinitis                                         6                     7                     6             
   Sinusitis                                        4                     5                     6             
   Dyspnea                                          1                     1                     2             
   Skin and Appendages Disorders            
   Skin disorder                                    &lt;1                    2                     1             
   Sweating increased                               &lt;1                    1                     &lt;1            
   Rash erythematous                                &lt;1                    1                     &lt;1            
   Special Sense Other, Disorders           
   Taste perversion                                 0                     2                     4             
   Urinary System Disorders                 
   Hematuria                                        1                     2                     &lt;1            
   Urinary tract infection                          1                     2                     3             
   Micturition frequency                            1                     1                     2             
   Urinary incontinence                             &lt;1                    2                     1             
   Urine abnormal                                   0                     1                     &lt;1            
   Vision Disorders                         
   Vision abnormal                                  2                     13                    10            
   Diplopia                                         5                     10                    10            
   White Cell and RES Disorders             
   Leukopenia                                       1                     2                     1             
              Incidence in Study 119 - Add-On Therapy- Adults with Partial Onset Seizures  
 

 Study 119 was a randomized, double-blind, add-on/adjunctive, placebo-controlled, parallel group study with 3 treatment arms: 1) placebo; 2) TOPAMAX  (r)  200 mg/day with a 25 mg/day starting dose, increased by 25 mg/day each week for 8 weeks until the 200 mg/day maintenance dose was reached; and 3) TOPAMAX  (r)  200 mg/day with a 50 mg/day starting dose, increased by 50 mg/day each week for 4 weeks until the 200 mg/day maintenance dose was reached. All patients were maintained on concomitant carbamazepine with or without another concomitant antiepileptic drug.



 The most commonly observed adverse reactions associated with the use of TOPAMAX  (r)  that were seen at an incidence higher (&gt;= 5%) than in the placebo group were : paresthesia, nervousness, somnolence, difficulty with concentration/attention, and fatigue (see  Table 7  ). Because these TOPAMAX  (r)  treatment difference incidence (TOPAMAX  (r)  % - Placebo %) of many adverse reactions reported in this study were markedly lower than those reported in the previous epilepsy studies, they cannot be directly compared with data obtained in other studies.



 Table 7: Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions in Study 119Patients in these add-on/adjunctive trials were receiving 1 to 2 concomitant antiepileptic drugs in addition to TOPAMAX(r) or placebo.,Values represent the percentage of patients reporting a given adverse reaction. Patients may have reported more than one adverse reaction during the study and can be included in more than one adverse reaction category. Where Incidence Was &gt;= 2% in the TOPAMAX(r) Group and Greater Than the Rate in Placebo-Treated Patients 
                                                                                TOPAMAX  (r)  Dosage (mg/day)   
 Body System/                                                 Placebo                      200              
   Adverse Reaction                                           (N=92)                     (N=171)            
  
   Body as a Whole-General Disorders                  
   Fatigue                                                       4                          9               
   Chest pain                                                    1                          2               
   Cardiovascular Disorders, General                  
   Hypertension                                                  0                          2               
   Central &amp; Peripheral Nervous System Disorders      
   Paresthesia                                                   2                          9               
   Dizziness                                                     4                          7               
   Tremor                                                        2                          3               
   Hypoesthesia                                                  0                          2               
   Leg cramps                                                    0                          2               
   Language problems                                             0                          2               
   Gastro-Intestinal System Disorders                 
   Abdominal pain                                                3                          5               
   Constipation                                                  0                          4               
   Diarrhea                                                      1                          2               
   Dyspepsia                                                     0                          2               
   Dry mouth                                                     0                          2               
   Hearing and Vestibular Disorders                   
   Tinnitus                                                      0                          2               
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders                
   Weight decrease                                               4                          8               
   Psychiatric Disorders                              
   Somnolence                                                    9                         15               
   Anorexia                                                      7                          9               
   Nervousness                                                   2                          9               
   Difficulty with concentration/attention                       0                          5               
   Insomnia                                                      3                          4               
   Difficulty with memory                                        1                          2               
   Aggressive reaction                                           0                          2               
   Respiratory System Disorders                       
   Rhinitis                                                      0                          4               
   Urinary System Disorders                           
   Cystitis                                                      0                          2               
   Vision Disorders                                   
   Diplopia                                                      0                          2               
   Vision abnormal                                               0                          2               
        Table 8: Incidence (%) of Dose-Related Adverse Reactions From Placebo-Controlled, Add-On Trials in Adults With Partial Onset SeizuresDose-response studies were not conducted for other adult indications or for pediatric indications. 
                                                            TOPAMAX  (r)  Dosage (mg/day)   
                                               Placebo            200              400          600 - 1,000     
 Adverse Reaction                            (N = 216)%        (N = 45)%        (N = 68)%       (N = 414)%      
  
 Fatigue                                         13               11               12               30          
 Nervousness                                      7               13               18               19          
 Difficulty with concentration/attention          1                7                9               14          
 Confusion                                        4                9               10               14          
 Depression                                       6                9                7               13          
 Anorexia                                         4                4                6               12          
 Language problems                               &lt;1                2                9               10          
 Anxiety                                          6                2                3               10          
 Mood problems                                    2                0                6                9          
 Weight decrease                                  3                4                9               13          
          Table 9: Incidence (%) of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions in Placebo-Controlled, Add-On Epilepsy Trials in Pediatric Patients (Ages 2 -16 Years)Patients in these add-on/adjunctive trials were receiving 1 to 2 concomitant antiepileptic drugs in addition to TOPAMAX(r) or placebo.,Values represent the percentage of patients reporting a given adverse reaction. Patients may have reported more than one adverse reaction during the study and can be included in more than one adverse reaction category. (Reactions That Occurred in at Least 1% of TOPAMAX(r)-Treated Patients and Occurred More Frequently in TOPAMAX(r)-Treated Than Placebo-Treated Patients) 
                                                              Placebo                TOPAMAX  (r)           
 Body System/  Adverse Reaction                              (N=101)%                    (N=98)%            
  
   Body as a Whole - General Disorders                
   Fatigue                                                       5                         16               
   Injury                                                       13                         14               
   Allergic reaction                                             1                          2               
   Back pain                                                     0                          1               
   Pallor                                                        0                          1               
   Cardiovascular Disorders, General                  
   Hypertension                                                  0                          1               
   Central &amp; Peripheral Nervous System Disorders      
   Gait abnormal                                                 5                          8               
   Ataxia                                                        2                          6               
   Hyperkinesia                                                  4                          5               
   Dizziness                                                     2                          4               
   Speech disorders/Related speech problems                      2                          4               
   Hyporeflexia                                                  0                          2               
   Convulsions grand mal                                         0                          1               
   Fecal incontinence                                            0                          1               
   Paresthesia                                                   0                          1               
   Gastro-Intestinal System Disorders                 
   Nausea                                                        5                          6               
   Saliva increased                                              4                          6               
   Constipation                                                  4                          5               
   Gastroenteritis                                               2                          3               
   Dysphagia                                                     0                          1               
   Flatulence                                                    0                          1               
   Gastroesophageal reflux                                       0                          1               
   Glossitis                                                     0                          1               
   Gum hyperplasia                                               0                          1               
   Heart Rate and Rhythm Disorders                    
   Bradycardia                                                   0                          1               
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders                
   Weight decrease                                               1                          9               
   Thirst                                                        1                          2               
   Hypoglycemia                                                  0                          1               
   Weight increase                                               0                          1               
   Platelet, Bleeding, &amp; Clotting Disorders           
   Purpura                                                       4                          8               
   Epistaxis                                                     1                          4               
   Hematoma                                                      0                          1               
   Prothrombin increased                                         0                          1               
   Thrombocytopenia                                              0                          1               
   Psychiatric Disorders                              
   Somnolence                                                   16                         26               
   Anorexia                                                     15                         24               
   Nervousness                                                   7                         14               
   Personality disorder (behavior problems)                      9                         11               
   Difficulty with concentration/attention                       2                         10               
   Aggressive reaction                                           4                          9               
   Insomnia                                                      7                          8               
   Difficulty with memory                                        0                          5               
   Confusion                                                     3                          4               
   Psychomotor slowing                                           2                          3               
   Appetite increased                                            0                          1               
   Neurosis                                                      0                          1               
   Reproductive Disorders, Female                     
   Leukorrhea                                                    0                          2               
   Resistance Mechanism Disorders                     
   Infection viral                                               3                          7               
   Respiratory System Disorders                       
   Pneumonia                                                     1                          5               
   Respiratory disorder                                          0                          1               
   Skin and Appendages Disorders                      
   Skin disorder                                                 2                          3               
   Alopecia                                                      1                          2               
   Dermatitis                                                    0                          2               
   Hypertrichosis                                                1                          2               
   Rash erythematous                                             0                          2               
   Eczema                                                        0                          1               
   Seborrhea                                                     0                          1               
   Skin discoloration                                            0                          1               
   Urinary System Disorders                           
   Urinary incontinence                                          2                          4               
   Nocturia                                                      0                          1               
   Vision Disorders                                   
   Eye abnormality                                               1                          2               
   Vision abnormal                                               1                          2               
   Diplopia                                                      0                          1               
   Lacrimation abnormal                                          0                          1               
   Myopia                                                        0                          1               
   White Cell and RES Disorders                       
   Leukopenia                                                    0                          2               
             Other Adverse Reactions Observed During All Epilepsy Clinical Trials  
 

 TOPAMAX  (r)  has been administered to 2246 adults and 427 pediatric patients with epilepsy during all clinical studies, only some of which were placebo-controlled. During these studies, all adverse reactions were recorded by the clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. To provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals having adverse reactions, similar types of reactions were grouped into a smaller number of standardized categories using modified WHOART dictionary terminology. The frequencies presented represent the proportion of patients who experienced a reaction of the type cited on at least one occasion while receiving TOPAMAX  (r)  . Reported reactions are included except those already listed in the previous tables or text, those too general to be informative, and those not reasonably associated with the use of the drug.



 Reactions are classified within body system categories and enumerated in order of decreasing frequency using the following definitions:  frequent  occurring in at least 1/100 patients;  infrequent  occurring in 1/100 to 1/1000 patients;  rare  occurring in fewer than 1/1000 patients.



 Autonomic Nervous System Disorders:  Infrequent:  vasodilation.



 Body as a Whole:  Frequent:  syncope.  Infrequent  : abdomen enlarged.  Rare:  alcohol intolerance.



 Cardiovascular Disorders, General:  Infrequent:  hypotension, postural hypotension, angina pectoris.



 Central &amp; Peripheral Nervous System Disorders:  Infrequent  : neuropathy, apraxia, hyperesthesia, dyskinesia, dysphonia, scotoma, ptosis, dystonia, visual field defect, encephalopathy, EEG abnormal.  Rare:  upper motor neuron lesion, cerebellar syndrome, tongue paralysis.



 Gastrointestinal System Disorders:  Infrequent:  hemorrhoids, stomatitis, melena, gastritis, esophagitis.  Rare:  tongue edema.



 Heart Rate and Rhythm Disorders:  Infrequent:  AV block.



 Liver and Biliary System Disorders:  Infrequent:  SGPT increased, SGOT increased.



 Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders:  Infrequent:  dehydration, hypocalcemia, hyperlipemia, hyperglycemia, xerophthalmia, diabetes mellitus.  Rare:  hypernatremia, hyponatremia, hypocholesterolemia, creatinine increased.



 Musculoskeletal System Disorders:  Frequent:  arthralgia.  Infrequent:  arthrosis.



 Neoplasms:  Infrequent:  thrombocythemia.  Rare:  polycythemia.



 Platelet, Bleeding, and Clotting Disorders:  Infrequent:  gingival bleeding, pulmonary embolism.



 Psychiatric Disorders:  Frequent:  impotence, hallucination, psychosis, suicide attempt.  Infrequent:  euphoria, paranoid reaction, delusion, paranoia, delirium, abnormal dreaming.  Rare:  libido increased, manic reaction.



 Red Blood Cell Disorders:  Frequent:  anemia.  Rare:  marrow depression, pancytopenia.



 Reproductive Disorders, Male:  Infrequent:  ejaculation disorder, breast discharge.



 Skin and Appendages Disorders:  Infrequent:  urticaria, photosensitivity reaction, abnormal hair texture.  Rare:  chloasma.



 Special Senses Other, Disorders:  Infrequent:  taste loss, parosmia.



 Urinary System Disorders:  Infrequent:  urinary retention, face edema, renal pain, albuminuria, polyuria, oliguria.



 Vascular (Extracardiac) Disorders:  Infrequent:  flushing, deep vein thrombosis, phlebitis.  Rare:  vasospasm.



 Vision Disorders:  Frequent:  conjunctivitis.  Infrequent:  abnormal accommodation, photophobia, strabismus.  Rare:  mydriasis, iritis.



 White Cell and Reticuloendothelial System Disorders:  Infrequent:  lymphadenopathy, eosinophilia, lymphopenia, granulocytopenia.  Rare:  lymphocytosis.



     Migraine  



     Adults  



 In the four multicenter, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, parallel group migraine prophylaxis clinical trials (which included 35 adolescent patients age 12 to 15 years), most of the adverse reactions with TOPAMAX  (r)  were mild or moderate in severity. Most adverse reactions occurred more frequently during the titration period than during the maintenance period.



 The most commonly observed adverse reactions associated with the use of the 100 mg TOPAMAX  (r)  dose in controlled trials in migraine prophylaxis trials of predominantly adults that were seen at an incidence higher (&gt;=5 %) than in the placebo group were : paresthesia, anorexia, weight decrease, taste perversion, diarrhea, difficulty with memory, hypoesthesia, and nausea (see  Table 10  ). Table 10 includes those adverse reactions reported for patients in the placebo-controlled trials where the incidence in any TOPAMAX  (r)  treatment group was at least 2% and was greater than that for placebo patients.



 Table 10: Incidence (%) of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions in Placebo-Controlled, Migraine Trials Where Incidence Was &gt;=2 % in Any TOPAMAX(r) Group and Greater Than the Rate in Placebo-Treated PatientsIncludes 35 adolescent patients age 12 to 15 years.Values represent the percentage of patients reporting a given adverse reaction. Patients may have reported more than one adverse reaction during the study and can be included in more than one adverse reaction category. 
                                                            TOPAMAX  (r)  Dosage (mg/day)   
                                               Placebo            50               100              200         
 Body System/Adverse Reaction                 (N=445)%         (N=235)%         (N=386)%         (N=514)%       
  
   Body as a Whole-General Disorders        
   Fatigue                                       11               14               15               19          
   Injury                                         7                9                6                6          
   Asthenia                                       1               &lt;1                2                2          
   Fever                                          1                1                1                2          
   Influenza-like symptoms                       &lt;1               &lt;1               &lt;1                2          
   Allergy                                       &lt;1                2               &lt;1               &lt;1          
   Central &amp; Peripheral Nervous System Disorders     
   Paresthesia                                    6               35               51               49          
   Dizziness                                     10                8                9               12          
   Hypoesthesia                                   2                6                7                8          
   Language problems                              2                7                6                7          
   Involuntary muscle contractions                1                2                2                4          
   Ataxia                                        &lt;1                1                2                1          
   Speech disorders/Related speech problems        &lt;1                1               &lt;1                2          
   Gastro-Intestinal System Disorders       
   Nausea                                         8                9               13               14          
   Diarrhea                                       4                9               11               11          
   Abdominal pain                                 5                6                6                7          
   Dyspepsia                                      3                4                5                3          
   Dry mouth                                      2                2                3                5          
   Vomiting                                       2                1                2                3          
   Gastroenteritis                                1                3                3                2          
   Hearing and Vestibular Disorders         
   Tinnitus                                       1               &lt;1                1                2          
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders      
   Weight decrease                                1                6                9               11          
   Thirst                                        &lt;1                2                2                1          
   Musculoskeletal System Disorders         
   Arthralgia                                     2                7                3                1          
   Neoplasms                                
   Neoplasm                                      &lt;1                2               &lt;1               &lt;1          
   Psychiatric Disorders                    
   Anorexia                                       6                9               15               14          
   Somnolence                                     5                8                7               10          
   Difficulty with memory                         2                7                7               11          
   Difficulty with concentration/ attention         2                3                6               10          
   Insomnia                                       5                6                7                6          
   Anxiety                                        3                4                5                6          
   Mood problems                                  2                3                6                5          
   Depression                                     4                3                4                6          
   Nervousness                                    2                4                4                4          
   Confusion                                      2                2                3                4          
   Psychomotor slowing                            1                3                2                4          
   Libido decreased                               1                1                1                2          
   Aggravated depression                          1                1                2                2          
   Agitation                                      1                2                2                1          
   Cognitive problems                             1               &lt;1                2                2          
   Reproductive Disorders, Female           
   Menstrual disorder                             2                3                2                2          
   Reproductive Disorders, Male             
   Ejaculation premature                          0                3                0                0          
   Resistance Mechanism Disorders           
   Viral infection                                3                4                4                3          
   Otitis media                                  &lt;1                2                1                1          
   Respiratory System Disorders             
   Upper respiratory tract infection             12               13               14               12          
   Sinusitis                                      6               10                6                8          
   Pharyngitis                                    4                5                6                2          
   Coughing                                       2                2                4                3          
   Bronchitis                                     2                3                3                3          
   Dyspnea                                        2                1                3                2          
   Rhinitis                                       1                1                2                2          
   Skin and Appendages Disorders            
   Pruritis                                       2                4                2                2          
   Special Sense Other, Disorders           
   Taste perversion                               1               15                8               12          
   Taste loss                                    &lt;1                1                1                2          
   Urinary System Disorders                 
   Urinary tract infection                        2                4                2                4          
   Renal calculus                                 0                0                1                2          
   Vision Disorders                         
   Vision abnormal                               &lt;1                1                2                3          
   Blurred vision                                 2                4                2                4          
   Conjunctivitis                                 1                1                2                1          
           Of the 1135 patients exposed to TOPAMAX  (r)  in the adult placebo-controlled studies, 25% discontinued due to adverse reactions, compared to 10% of the 445 placebo patients. The adverse reactions associated with discontinuing therapy in the TOPAMAX  (r)  -treated patients included paresthesia (7%), fatigue (4%), nausea (4%), difficulty with concentration/attention (3%), insomnia (3%), anorexia (2%), and dizziness (2%).
 

 Patients treated with TOPAMAX  (r)  experienced mean percent reductions in body weight that were dose-dependent. This change was not seen in the placebo group. Mean changes of 0%, -2%, -3%, and -4% were seen for the placebo group, TOPAMAX  (r)  50, 100, and 200 mg groups, respectively.



 Table 11 shows adverse reactions that were dose-dependent. Several central nervous system adverse reactions, including some that represented cognitive dysfunction, were dose-related. The most common, dose-related adverse reactions (treatment difference &gt;=5% for the 100 mg dose) were : paresthesia, nausea, anorexia, difficulty with memory, diarrhea, weight decrease, and hypoesthesia.



 Table 11: Incidence (%) of Dose-Related Adverse Reactions From Placebo-Controlled, Migraine TrialsIncludes 35 adolescent patients age 12 to &lt;16 years The incidence of adverse reactions in the 200 mg/day group was &gt;= 2% than the incidence in both the placebo group and the 50 mg/day group. 
                                                            TOPAMAX  (r)  Dosage (mg/day)   
                                               Placebo            50               100              200         
 Adverse Reaction                             (N=445)%         (N=235)%         (N=386)%         (N=514)%       
  
 Paresthesia                                      6               35               51               49          
 Fatigue                                         11               14               15               19          
 Nausea                                           8                9               13               14          
 Anorexia                                         6                9               15               14          
 Dizziness                                       10                8                9               12          
 Weight decrease                                  1                6                9               11          
 Difficulty with memory                           2                7                7               11          
 Diarrhea                                         4                9               11               11          
 Difficulty with concentration/ attention         2                3                6               10          
 Somnolence                                       5                8                7               10          
 Hypoesthesia                                     2                6                7                8          
 Anxiety                                          3                4                5                6          
 Depression                                       4                3                4                6          
 Mood problems                                    2                3                6                5          
 Dry mouth                                        2                2                3                5          
 Confusion                                        2                2                3                4          
 Involuntary muscle contractions                  1                2                2                4          
 Abnormal vision                                 &lt;1                1                2                3          
 Renal calculus                                   0                0                1                2          
               Adolescents 12 to 17 Years of Age  
 

 In five, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, parallel group migraine prophylaxis clinical trials, most of the adverse reactions with TOPAMAX  (r)  were mild or moderate in severity. Most adverse reactions occurred more frequently during the titration period than during the maintenance period. Among adverse reactions with onset during titration, approximately half persisted into the maintenance period.



 In four, fixed-dose, double-blind migraine prophylaxis clinical trials in TOPAMAX  (r)  -treated adolescent patients, the most commonly observed adverse reactions associated with the use of 100 mg of TOPAMAX  (r)  that were seen at an incidence higher (&gt;= 5%) than in the placebo group were : paresthesia, upper respiratory tract infection, anorexia, and abdominal pain (see  Table 12  ). Table 12 shows adverse reactions from the adolescent pivotal trial (Study 3 demonstrating the efficacy of TOPAMAX  (r)  ;  [see  Clinical Studies (14.3)  ]  ) in which there were 103 adolescent patients who were treated with placebo or 50 mg or 100 mg of TOPAMAX  (r)  and three predominantly adult trials in which there were 49 adolescent patients (12 to 17 years) who were treated with placebo or 50 mg, 100 mg or 200 mg of TOPAMAX  (r)  . Table 12 also shows adverse reactions in adolescents in the controlled migraine trials when the incidence in a TOPAMAX  (r)  dose group was at least 5 % or higher than the incidence of placebo. Many adverse reactions shown in Table 12 indicated a dose-dependent relationship.



 Table 12: Incidence (%) of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions in at Least 5% or Greater than the Placebo Incidence of Adolescents (12-17 Years) in Any TOPAMAX(r) Group in Pooled Double-Blind Migraine Prophylaxis Studies35 adolescent patients aged 12 to &lt;16 years were also included in adverse reaction assessment for adults (Tables 10 and 11)Incidence is based on the number of subjects experiencing at least 1 adverse event, not the number of events.Included studies MIG-3006, MIGR-001, MIGR-002 and MIGR-003 
                           TOPAMAX  (r)  Dosage   
   Body System/                  Placebo             50 mg/day           100 mg/day           200 mg/day        
   Adverse Reaction              (N=45)%              (N=46)%              (N=48)%              (N=13)%         
  
   Body as a Whole - General Disorders     
   Allergy                          0                    0                    4                    8            
   Fatigue                          7                    7                    8                   15            
   Fever                            2                    4                    6                    0            
   Leg pain                         0                    2                    2                    8            
   Central &amp; Peripheral Nervous System Disorders     
   Dizziness                        4                    4                    6                    0            
   Headache                         2                    2                    4                    8            
   Language problems                2                    0                    0                   15            
   Muscle contractions involuntary           0                    0                    0                    8            
   Paresthesia                      7                   20                   19                   38            
   Endocrine Disorders      
   Hyperthyroidism                  0                    0                    0                    8            
   Gastrointestinal System Disorders     
   Abdominal pain                   9                    7                   15                   15            
   Diarrhea                         0                    2                    2                    8            
   Nausea                           4                    4                    8                    0            
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders     
   Oedema pharynx                   0                    0                    0                    8            
   Weight decrease                  2                    7                    4                   31            
   Platelet, Bleeding &amp; Clotting Disorders     
   Epistaxis                        0                    2                    2                    8            
   Psychiatric Disorders     
   Anorexia                         4                    9                   10                   15            
   Anxiety                          0                    0                    0                    8            
   Difficulty with concentration/ attention           0                    0                    2                   15            
   Difficulty with memory           2                    0                    0                    8            
   Insomnia                         2                    9                    2                    0            
   Mood problems                    4                    2                    2                    8            
   Psychomotor slowing              0                    2                    0                    8            
   Somnolence                       2                    2                    6                   15            
   Resistance Mechanism Disorders     
   Infection viral                  4                    4                    8                   15            
   Otitis media                     0                    0                    0                    8            
   Respiratory System Disorders     
   Coughing                         0                    7                    2                    0            
   Laryngitis                       0                    0                    0                    8            
   Rhinitis                         2                    7                    6                    8            
   Sinusitis                        2                    9                    4                   15            
   Upper respiratory tract infection          11                   26                   23                   23            
   Skin and Appendages Disorders     
   Rash erythematous                0                    0                    0                    8            
   Special Senses Other, Disorders     
   Taste perversion                 2                    2                    6                    8            
   Vision Disorders         
   Conjunctivitis                   4                    7                    4                    0            
           In the double-blind placebo-controlled studies, adverse reactions led to discontinuation of treatment in 8% of placebo patients compared with 6% of TOPAMAX  (r)  -treated patients. Adverse reactions associated with discontinuing therapy that occurred in more than one TOPAMAX  (r)  -treated patient were fatigue (1%), headache (1%), and somnolence (1%).
 

     Other Adverse Reactions Observed During Migraine Clinical Trials  



     Adults  



 TOPAMAX  (r)  , for the treatment of prophylaxis of migraine headache, has been administered to 1367 patients (including 33 adolescent patients aged 12 to &lt;16 years) in all clinical studies (includes double-blind and open-label extension). During these studies, all adverse reactions were recorded by the clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. To provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals having adverse reactions, similar types of reactions were grouped into a smaller number of standardized categories using modified WHOART dictionary terminology.



 The following additional adverse reactions that were not described in Table 10 were reported by greater than 1% of the 1367 TOPAMAX  (r)  -treated patients in the controlled clinical trials:



   Body as a Whole:  Pain, chest pain, allergic reaction.



   Central &amp; Peripheral Nervous System Disorders:  Headache, vertigo, tremor, sensory disturbance, migraine aggravated.



   Gastrointestinal System Disorders:  Constipation, gastroesophageal reflux.



   Musculoskeletal System Disorders:  Myalgia.



   Platelet, Bleeding, and Clotting Disorders:  Epistaxis.



   Reproductive Disorders, Female:  Intermenstrual bleeding.



   Resistance Mechanism Disorders:  Infection, genital moniliasis.



   Respiratory System Disorders:  Pneumonia, asthma.



   Skin and Appendages Disorders:  Rash, alopecia.



   Vision Disorders:  Abnormal accommodation, eye pain.



     Adolescents 12 to 17 Years of Age  



 In two clinical studies for the treatment of prophylaxis of migraine headache in pediatric patients only, TOPAMAX  (r)  has been administered to 134 adolescent patients (includes double-blind and open-label extension). During these studies, all adverse reactions were recorded by the clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. To provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals having adverse reactions, similar types of reactions were grouped into a smaller number of standardized categories using modified WHOART dictionary terminology.



 The following additional adverse reactions that were not described in Table 12 were reported by at least 2% of the 134 TOPAMAX  (r)  -treated patients in the controlled clinical trials:



   Body as a Whole:  Injury, influenza-like symptoms, back pain, pain.



   Gastrointestinal System Disorders:  Gastroenteritis, vomiting.



   Musculoskeletal system disorders:  Myalgia.



   Psychiatric disorders:  Nervousness.



   Resistance Mechanism Disorders:  Infection.



   Respiratory System Disorders:  Pharyngitis, asthma, bronchitis.



   Skin and Appendages Disorders:  Pruritus, rash.



   Urinary System Disorders:  Urinary incontinence, urinary tract infection.



   Vision Disorders:  Eye pain, vision abnormal.



   6.2 Postmarketing and Other Experience

  In addition to the adverse experiences reported during clinical testing of TOPAMAX  (r)  , the following adverse experiences have been reported worldwide in patients receiving TOPAMAX  (r)  post-approval.



 These adverse experiences have not been listed above and data are insufficient to support an estimate of their incidence or to establish causation. The listing is alphabetized: bullous skin reactions (including erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis), hepatic failure (including fatalities), hepatitis, maculopathy, pancreatitis, and pemphigus.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Acute myopia and secondary angle closure glaucoma: Untreated elevated intraocular pressure can lead to permanent visual loss. The primary treatment to reverse symptoms is discontinuation of TOPAMAX  (r)  as rapidly as possible (  5.1  ) 
 *  Visual field defects: These have been reported independent of elevated intraocular pressure. Consider discontinuation of TOPAMAX  (r)  (  5.2  ) 
 *  Oligohidrosis and hyperthermia: Monitor decreased sweating and increased body temperature, especially in pediatric patients (  5.3  ) 
 *  Metabolic acidosis: Baseline and periodic measurement of serum bicarbonate is recommended. Consider dose reduction or discontinuation of TOPAMAX  (r)  if clinically appropriate (  5.4  ) 
 *  Suicidal behavior and ideation: Antiepileptic drugs increase the risk of suicidal behavior or ideation (  5.5  ) 
 *  Cognitive/neuropsychiatric: TOPAMAX  (r)  may cause cognitive dysfunction. Patients should use caution when operating machinery including automobiles. Depression and mood problems may occur in epilepsy and migraine populations (  5.6  ) 
 *  Fetal Toxicity: TOPAMAX  (r)  use during pregnancy can cause cleft lip and/or palate (  5.7  ) 
 *  Withdrawal of AEDs: Withdrawal of TOPAMAX  (r)  should be done gradually (  5.8  ) 
 *  Hyperammonemia and encephalopathy associated with or without concomitant valproic acid use: Patients with inborn errors of metabolism or reduced mitochondrial activity may have an increased risk of hyper-ammonemia. Measure ammonia if encephalopathic symptoms occur (  5.10  ) 
 *  Kidney stones: Use with other carbonic anhydrase inhibitors, other drugs causing metabolic acidosis, or in patients on a ketogenic diet should be avoided (  5.11  ) 
 *  Hypothermia has been reported with and without hyperammonemia during topiramate treatment with concomitant valproic acid use (  5.12  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Acute Myopia and Secondary Angle Closure Glaucoma



  A syndrome consisting of acute myopia associated with secondary angle closure glaucoma has been reported in patients receiving TOPAMAX  (r)  (topiramate). Symptoms include acute onset of decreased visual acuity and/or ocular pain. Ophthalmologic findings can include myopia, anterior chamber shallowing, ocular hyperemia (redness), and increased intraocular pressure. Mydriasis may or may not be present. This syndrome may be associated with supraciliary effusion resulting in anterior displacement of the lens and iris, with secondary angle closure glaucoma. Symptoms typically occur within 1 month of initiating TOPAMAX  (r)  therapy. In contrast to primary narrow angle glaucoma, which is rare under 40 years of age, secondary angle closure glaucoma associated with topiramate has been reported in pediatric patients as well as adults. The primary treatment to reverse symptoms is discontinuation of TOPAMAX  (r)  as rapidly as possible, according to the judgment of the treating physician. Other measures, in conjunction with discontinuation of TOPAMAX  (r)  , may be helpful.



 Elevated intraocular pressure of any etiology, if left untreated, can lead to serious sequelae including permanent vision loss.



    5.2 Visual Field Defects



   Visual field defects (independent of elevated intraocular pressure) have been reported in clinical trials and in postmarketing experience in patients receiving topiramate. In clinical trials, most of these events were reversible after topiramate discontinuation. If visual problems occur at any time during topiramate treatment, consideration should be given to discontinuing the drug.  



    5.3 Oligohidrosis and Hyperthermia



  Oligohidrosis (decreased sweating), infrequently resulting in hospitalization, has been reported in association with TOPAMAX  (r)  use. Decreased sweating and an elevation in body temperature above normal characterized these cases. Some of the cases were reported after exposure to elevated environmental temperatures.



 The majority of the reports have been in pediatric patients. Patients, especially pediatric patients, treated with TOPAMAX  (r)  should be monitored closely for evidence of decreased sweating and increased body temperature, especially in hot weather. Caution should be used when TOPAMAX  (r)  is prescribed with other drugs that predispose patients to heat-related disorders; these drugs include, but are not limited to, other carbonic anhydrase inhibitors and drugs with anticholinergic activity.



    5.4 Metabolic Acidosis



  Hyperchloremic, non-anion gap, metabolic acidosis (i.e., decreased serum bicarbonate below the normal reference range in the absence of chronic respiratory alkalosis) is associated with TOPAMAX  (r)  treatment. This metabolic acidosis is caused by renal bicarbonate loss due to the inhibitory effect of topiramate on carbonic anhydrase. Such electrolyte imbalance has been observed with the use of topiramate in placebo-controlled clinical trials and in the post-marketing period. Generally, topiramate-induced metabolic acidosis occurs early in treatment although cases can occur at any time during treatment. Bicarbonate decrements are usually mild-moderate (average decrease of 4 mEq/L at daily doses of 400 mg in adults and at approximately 6 mg/kg/day in pediatric patients); rarely, patients can experience severe decrements to values below 10 mEq/L. Conditions or therapies that predispose patients to acidosis (such as renal disease, severe respiratory disorders, status epilepticus, diarrhea, ketogenic diet, or specific drugs) may be additive to the bicarbonate lowering effects of topiramate.



 Some manifestations of acute or chronic metabolic acidosis may include hyperventilation, nonspecific symptoms such as fatigue and anorexia, or more severe sequelae including cardiac arrhythmias or stupor. Chronic, untreated metabolic acidosis may increase the risk for nephrolithiasis or nephrocalcinosis, and may also result in osteomalacia (referred to as rickets in pediatric patients) and/or osteoporosis with an increased risk for fractures. Chronic metabolic acidosis in pediatric patients may also reduce growth rates. A reduction in growth rate may eventually decrease the maximal height achieved. The effect of topiramate on growth and bone-related sequelae has not been systematically investigated in long-term, placebo-controlled trials. Long-term, open-label treatment of infants/toddlers, with intractable partial epilepsy, for up to 1 year, showed reductions from baseline in Z SCORES for length, weight, and head circumference compared to age and sex-matched normative data, although these patients with epilepsy are likely to have different growth rates than normal infants. Reductions in Z SCORES for length and weight were correlated to the degree of acidosis [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ]  . Topiramate treatment that causes metabolic acidosis during pregnancy can possibly produce adverse effects on the fetus and might also cause metabolic acidosis in the neonate from possible transfer of topiramate to the fetus [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  and  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ]  .



    Epilepsy  



    Adult patients  



 In adults, the incidence of persistent treatment-emergent decreases in serum bicarbonate (levels of &lt;20 mEq/L at two consecutive visits or at the final visit) in controlled clinical trials for adjunctive treatment of epilepsy was 32% for 400 mg/day, and 1% for placebo. Metabolic acidosis has been observed at doses as low as 50 mg/day. The incidence of a markedly abnormally low serum bicarbonate (i.e., absolute value &lt;17 mEq/L and &gt;5 mEq/L decrease from pretreatment) in the adjunctive therapy trials was 3% for 400 mg/day, and 0% for placebo. The incidence of persistent treatment-emergent decreases in serum bicarbonate in adult patients (&gt;=16 years of age) in the epilepsy controlled clinical trial for monotherapy was 14% for 50 mg/day and 25% for 400 mg/day. The incidence of a markedly abnormally low serum bicarbonate (i.e., absolute value &lt;17 mEq/L and &gt;5 mEq/L decrease from pretreatment) in this trial for adults was 1% for 50 mg/day and 6% for 400 mg/day. Serum bicarbonate levels have not been systematically evaluated at daily doses greater than 400 mg/day.



    Pediatric patients  



 In pediatric patients (2 to 16 years of age), the incidence of persistent treatment-emergent decreases in serum bicarbonate in placebo-controlled trials for adjunctive treatment of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome or refractory partial onset seizures was 67% for TOPAMAX  (r)  (at approximately 6 mg/kg/day), and 10% for placebo. The incidence of a markedly abnormally low serum bicarbonate (i.e., absolute value &lt;17 mEq/L and &gt;5 mEq/L decrease from pretreatment) in these trials was 11% for TOPAMAX  (r)  and 0% for placebo. Cases of moderately severe metabolic acidosis have been reported in patients as young as 5 months old, especially at daily doses above 5 mg/kg/day.



 Although not approved for use in patients under 2 years of age with partial onset seizures, a controlled trial that examined this population revealed that topiramate produced a metabolic acidosis that is notably greater in magnitude than that observed in controlled trials in older children and adults. The mean treatment difference (25 mg/kg/day topiramate-placebo) was -5.9 mEq/L for bicarbonate. The incidence of metabolic acidosis (defined by a serum bicarbonate &lt;20 mEq/L) was 0% for placebo, 30% for 5 mg/kg/day, 50% for 15 mg/kg/day, and 45% for 25 mg/kg/day. The incidence of markedly abnormal changes (i.e., &lt;17 mEq/L and &gt;5 mEq/L decrease from baseline of &gt;=20 mEq/L) was 0% for placebo, 4% for 5 mg/kg/day, 5% for 15 mg/kg/day, and 5% for 25 mg/kg/day [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ].  



 In pediatric patients (6 to 15 years of age), the incidence of persistent treatment-emergent decreases in serum bicarbonate in the epilepsy controlled clinical trial for monotherapy was 9% for 50 mg/day and 25% for 400 mg/day. The incidence of a markedly abnormally low serum bicarbonate (i.e., absolute value &lt;17 mEq/L and &gt;5 mEq/L decrease from pretreatment) in this trial was 1% for 50 mg/day and 6% for 400 mg/day.



    Migraine  



    Adult patients  



 The incidence of persistent treatment-emergent decreases in serum bicarbonate in placebo-controlled trials for adults for prophylaxis of migraine was 44% for 200 mg/day, 39% for 100 mg/day, 23% for 50 mg/day, and 7% for placebo. The incidence of a markedly abnormally low serum bicarbonate (i.e., absolute value &lt;17 mEq/L and &gt;5 mEq/L decrease from pretreatment) in these trials was 11% for 200 mg/day, 9% for 100 mg/day, 2% for 50 mg/day, and &lt;1% for placebo.



     Adolescent patients    



  In pooled, double-blind migraine prophylaxis studies in adolescent patients (12 to 17 years), the incidence of persistent treatment-emergent decreases in serum bicarbonate was 77% for 200 mg/day, 27% for 100 mg/day, 30% for 50 mg/day, and 9% for placebo. The incidence of markedly low serum bicarbonate (i.e., absolute value &lt;17 mEq/L and &gt;5 mEq/L decrease from pretreatment) was 6% for 100 mg/day, 2% for 50 mg/day, and 2% for placebo. This bicarbonate criterion was not met by any patients in the 200 mg/day group, which had a low number of subjects (n=13).  



    Measurement of Serum Bicarbonate in Epilepsy and Migraine Patients  



 Measurement of baseline and periodic serum bicarbonate during topiramate treatment is recommended. If metabolic acidosis develops and persists, consideration should be given to reducing the dose or discontinuing topiramate (using dose tapering). If the decision is made to continue patients on topiramate in the face of persistent acidosis, alkali treatment should be considered.



    5.5 Suicidal Behavior and Ideation



  Antiepileptic drugs (AEDs), including TOPAMAX  (r)  , increase the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior in patients taking these drugs for any indication. Patients treated with any AED for any indication should be monitored for the emergence or worsening of depression, suicidal thoughts or behavior, and/or any unusual changes in mood or behavior.



 Pooled analyses of 199 placebo-controlled clinical trials (mono- and adjunctive therapy) of 11 different AEDs showed that patients randomized to one of the AEDs had approximately twice the risk (adjusted Relative Risk 1.8, 95% CI:1.2, 2.7) of suicidal thinking or behavior compared to patients randomized to placebo. In these trials, which had a median treatment duration of 12 weeks, the estimated incidence rate of suicidal behavior or ideation among 27,863 AED-treated patients was 0.43%, compared to 0.24% among 16,029 placebo-treated patients, representing an increase of approximately one case of suicidal thinking or behavior for every 530 patients treated. There were four suicides in drug-treated patients in the trials and none in placebo-treated patients, but the number is too small to allow any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.



 The increased risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with AEDs was observed as early as one week after starting drug treatment with AEDs and persisted for the duration of treatment assessed. Because most trials included in the analysis did not extend beyond 24 weeks, the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior beyond 24 weeks could not be assessed.



 The risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior was generally consistent among drugs in the data analyzed. The finding of increased risk with AEDs of varying mechanisms of action and across a range of indications suggests that the risk applies to all AEDs used for any indication. The risk did not vary substantially by age (5 to 100 years) in the clinical trials analyzed.



 Table 4 shows absolute and relative risk by indication for all evaluated AEDs.



 Table 4: Risk by Indication for Antiepileptic Drugs in the Pooled Analysis 
 Indication            Placebo Patients with Events per 1000 Patients  Drug Patients with Events per 1000 Patients  Relative Risk: Incidence of Events in Drug Patients/Incidence in Placebo Patients  Risk Difference: Additional Drug Patients with Events per 1000 Patients   
  
 Epilepsy              1.0                   3.4                   3.5                   2.4                    
 Psychiatric           5.7                   8.5                   1.5                   2.9                    
 Other                 1.0                   1.8                   1.9                   0.9                    
 Total                 2.4                   4.3                   1.8                   1.9                    
           The relative risk for suicidal thoughts or behavior was higher in clinical trials for epilepsy than in clinical trials for psychiatric or other conditions, but the absolute risk differences were similar for the epilepsy and psychiatric indications.
 

 Anyone considering prescribing TOPAMAX  (r)  or any other AED must balance the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with the risk of untreated illness. Epilepsy and many other illnesses for which AEDs are prescribed are themselves associated with morbidity and mortality and an increased risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior. Should suicidal thoughts and behavior emerge during treatment, the prescriber needs to consider whether the emergence of these symptoms in any given patient may be related to the illness being treated.



 Patients, their caregivers, and families should be informed that AEDs increase the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior and should be advised of the need to be alert for the emergence or worsening of the signs and symptoms of depression, any unusual changes in mood or behavior or the emergence of suicidal thoughts, or behavior or thoughts about self-harm. Behaviors of concern should be reported immediately to healthcare providers.



    5.6 Cognitive/Neuropsychiatric Adverse Reactions



  Adverse reactions most often associated with the use of TOPAMAX  (r)  were related to the central nervous system and were observed in both the epilepsy and migraine populations. In adults, the most frequent of these can be classified into three general categories: 1) Cognitive-related dysfunction (e.g., confusion, psychomotor slowing, difficulty with concentration/attention, difficulty with memory, speech or language problems, particularly word-finding difficulties); 2) Psychiatric/behavioral disturbances (e.g., depression or mood problems); and 3) Somnolence or fatigue.



    Adult Patients  



    Cognitive-Related Dysfunction  



 The majority of cognitive-related adverse reactions were mild to moderate in severity, and they frequently occurred in isolation. Rapid titration rate and higher initial dose were associated with higher incidences of these reactions. Many of these reactions contributed to withdrawal from treatment [see  Adverse Reactions (6)  ]  .



 In the add-on epilepsy controlled trials (using rapid titration such as 100-200 mg/day weekly increments), the proportion of patients who experienced one or more cognitive-related adverse reactions was 42% for 200 mg/day, 41% for 400 mg/day, 52% for 600 mg/day, 56% for 800 and 1,000 mg/day, and 14% for placebo. These dose-related adverse reactions began with a similar frequency in the titration or in the maintenance phase, although in some patients the events began during titration and persisted into the maintenance phase. Some patients who experienced one or more cognitive-related adverse reactions in the titration phase had a dose-related recurrence of these reactions in the maintenance phase.



 In the monotherapy epilepsy controlled trial, the proportion of patients who experienced one or more cognitive-related adverse reactions was 19% for TOPAMAX  (r)  50 mg/day and 26% for 400 mg/day.



 In the 6-month migraine prophylaxis controlled trials using a slower titration regimen (25 mg/day weekly increments), the proportion of patients who experienced one or more cognitive-related adverse reactions was 19% for TOPAMAX  (r)  50 mg/day, 22% for 100 mg/day (the recommended dose), 28% for 200 mg/day, and 10% for placebo. These dose-related adverse reactions typically began in the titration phase and often persisted into the maintenance phase, but infrequently began in the maintenance phase. Some patients experienced a recurrence of one or more of these cognitive adverse reactions and this recurrence was typically in the titration phase. A relatively small proportion of topiramate-treated patients experienced more than one concurrent cognitive adverse reaction. The most common cognitive adverse reactions occurring together included difficulty with memory along with difficulty with concentration/attention, difficulty with memory along with language problems, and difficulty with concentration/attention along with language problems. Rarely, topiramate-treated patients experienced three concurrent cognitive reactions.



    Psychiatric/Behavioral Disturbances  



 Psychiatric/behavioral disturbances (depression or mood) were dose-related for both the epilepsy and migraine populations [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ].  



    Somnolence/Fatigue  



 Somnolence and fatigue were the adverse reactions most frequently reported during clinical trials of TOPAMAX  (r)  for adjunctive epilepsy. For the adjunctive epilepsy population, the incidence of somnolence did not differ substantially between 200 mg/day and 1,000 mg/day, but the incidence of fatigue was dose-related and increased at dosages above 400 mg/day. For the monotherapy epilepsy population in the 50 mg/day and 400 mg/day groups, the incidence of somnolence was dose-related (9% for the 50 mg/day group and 15% for the 400 mg/day group) and the incidence of fatigue was comparable in both treatment groups (14% each). For the migraine population, fatigue and somnolence were dose-related and more common in the titration phase.



 Additional nonspecific CNS events commonly observed with topiramate in the add-on epilepsy population included dizziness or ataxia.



    Pediatric Patients  



    Epilepsy  



 In double-blind adjunctive therapy and monotherapy epilepsy clinical studies, the incidences of cognitive/neuropsychiatric adverse reactions in pediatric patients were generally lower than observed in adults. These reactions included psychomotor slowing, difficulty with concentration/attention, speech disorders/related speech problems, and language problems. The most frequently reported neuropsychiatric reactions in pediatric patients during adjunctive therapy double-blind studies were somnolence and fatigue. The most frequently reported neuropsychiatric reactions in pediatric patients in the 50 mg/day and 400 mg/day groups during the monotherapy double-blind study were headache, dizziness, anorexia, and somnolence.



 No patients discontinued treatment due to any adverse reactions in the adjunctive epilepsy double-blind trials. In the monotherapy epilepsy double-blind trial, 1 pediatric patient (2%) in the 50 mg/day group and 7 pediatric patients (12%) in the 400 mg/day group discontinued treatment due to any adverse reactions. The most common adverse reaction associated with discontinuation of therapy was difficulty with concentration/attention; all occurred in the 400 mg/day group.



     Migraine    



  The incidence of cognitive adverse reactions was increased in TOPAMAX  (r)  -treated patients (7%) versus placebo (4%) in pooled, double-blind placebo-controlled studies in which adolescent patients (12 to 17 years) were randomized to placebo or one of several fixed daily doses of TOPAMAX  (r)  (50 mg, 100 mg, 200 mg).  



  The incidence of cognitive adverse reactions was also increased in a placebo-controlled study of pediatric patients (6 to 16 years) treated with 2 to 3 mg/kg/day of TOPAMAX  (r)  (10%) versus placebo treatment (2%). TOPAMAX  (r)  is not approved for prophylaxis of migraine in pediatric patients under 12 years of age.  



  The risk for cognitive adverse reactions was dose-dependent, and was particularly evident at the 200 mg dose. This risk for cognitive adverse reactions was also greater in younger patients (6 to 11 years) than in older patients (12 to 17 years). The most common cognitive adverse reaction in these trials was difficulty with concentration/attention. Cognitive adverse reactions most commonly developed in the titration period and sometimes persisted into the maintenance period. These adverse reactions typically occurred in isolation as single type of cognitive adverse reaction. Cognitive adverse reactions that led to study discontinuation occurred in one patient (difficulty with concentration/attention and language problems). The Cambridge Neuropsychological Test Automated Battery (CANTAB) was administered to adolescents (12 to 17 years) to assess the effects of topiramate on cognitive function at baseline and at the end of the Study 3 [see  Clinical Studies (14.3)  ]  . Mean change from baseline in certain CANTAB tests suggests that topiramate treatment may result in psychomotor slowing and decreased verbal fluency.  



    5.7 Fetal Toxicity



  TOPAMAX  (r)  can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Data from pregnancy registries indicate that infants exposed to topiramate in utero  have an increased risk for cleft lip and/or cleft palate (oral clefts). When multiple species of pregnant animals received topiramate at clinically relevant doses, structural malformations, including craniofacial defects, and reduced fetal weights occurred in offspring [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ]  .



 Consider the benefits and the risks of TOPAMAX  (r)  when administering this drug in women of childbearing potential, particularly when TOPAMAX  (r)  is considered for a condition not usually associated with permanent injury or death [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.9)  and  Patient Counseling Information (17)  ]  . TOPAMAX  (r)  should be used during pregnancy only if the potential benefit outweighs the potential risk. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to a fetus [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  and  (8.9)  ]  .



    5.8 Withdrawal of Antiepileptic Drugs (AEDs)



  In patients with or without a history of seizures or epilepsy, antiepileptic drugs, including TOPAMAX  (r)  , should be gradually withdrawn to minimize the potential for seizures or increased seizure frequency [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  . In situations where rapid withdrawal of TOPAMAX  (r)  is medically required, appropriate monitoring is recommended.



    5.9 Sudden Unexplained Death in Epilepsy (SUDEP)



  During the course of premarketing development of topiramate tablets, 10 sudden and unexplained deaths were recorded among a cohort of treated patients (2796 subject years of exposure). This represents an incidence of 0.0035 deaths per patient year. Although this rate exceeds that expected in a healthy population matched for age and sex, it is within the range of estimates for the incidence of sudden unexplained deaths in patients with epilepsy not receiving TOPAMAX  (r)  (ranging from 0.0005 for the general population of patients with epilepsy, to 0.003 for a clinical trial population similar to that in the TOPAMAX  (r)  program, to 0.005 for patients with refractory epilepsy).



    5.10 Hyperammonemia and Encephalopathy (Without and With Concomitant Valproic Acid [VPA] Use)



   Hyperammonemia/Encephalopathy Without Concomitant Valproic Acid (VPA)  



 Topiramate treatment has produced hyperammonemia (in some instances dose-related) in a clinical investigational program in adolescent patients (12 to 17 years) given topiramate for migraine prophylaxis. The incidence of hyperammonemia (above the upper limit of normal reference) at any time in the trial was 9% for placebo, 14% for 50 mg, and 26% for 100 mg topiramate daily. In some patients, hyperammonemia was observed at the end of the trial at the final visit. The incidence of markedly increased hyperammonemia (at least 50% or higher above upper limit of normal) at any time in the trial in adolescent patients was also increased at 100 mg/day (9%) compared to 50 mg topiramate (0%) or placebo (3%). During this trial, markedly increased ammonia levels returned to normal in all but one patient (in whom the ammonia level fell to high instead of markedly abnormal).



 Topiramate treatment has produced hyperammonemia in a clinical investigational program in very young pediatric patients (1 to 24 months) who were treated with adjunctive topiramate for partial onset epilepsy (8% for placebo, 10% for 5 mg/kg/day, 0% for 15 mg/kg/day, 9% for 25 mg/kg/day). In some patients, ammonia was markedly increased (&gt;= 50% above upper limit of normal). The hyperammonemia associated with topiramate treatment occurred with and without encephalopathy in placebo-controlled trials and in an open-label, extension trial of infants with refractory epilepsy. Dose-related hyperammonemia was observed in the extension trial in pediatric patients up to 2 years old. Clinical symptoms of hyperammonemic encephalopathy often include acute alterations in level of consciousness and/or cognitive function with lethargy or vomiting. TOPAMAX  (r)  is not approved as adjunctive treatment of partial onset seizures in pediatric patients less than 2 years old.



 Hyperammonemia with and without encephalopathy has also been observed in post-marketing reports in patients who were taking topiramate without concomitant valproic acid (VPA).



    Hyperammonemia/Encephalopathy With Concomitant Valproic Acid (VPA)  



 Concomitant administration of topiramate and valproic acid (VPA) has been associated with hyperammonemia with or without encephalopathy in patients who have tolerated either drug alone based upon post-marketing reports. Although hyperammonemia may be asymptomatic, clinical symptoms of hyperammonemic encephalopathy often include acute alterations in level of consciousness and/or cognitive function with lethargy or vomiting. In most cases, symptoms and signs abated with discontinuation of either drug. This adverse reaction is not due to a pharmacokinetic interaction.



 Although TOPAMAX  (r)  is not indicated for use in infants/toddlers (1-24 months), TOPAMAX  (r)  with concomitant VPA clearly produced a dose-related increase in the incidence of treatment-emergent hyperammonemia (above the upper limit of normal, 0% for placebo, 12% for 5 mg/kg/day, 7% for 15 mg/kg/day, 17% for 25 mg/kg/day) in an investigational program. Markedly increased, dose-related hyperammonemia (0% for placebo and 5 mg/kg/day, 7% for 15 mg/kg/day, 8% for 25 mg/kg/day) also occurred in these infants/toddlers. Dose-related hyperammonemia was similarly observed in a long-term extension trial in these very young, pediatric patients [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ]  .



 Hyperammonemia with and without encephalopathy has also been observed in post-marketing reports in patients taking topiramate with VPA.



 The hyperammonemia associated with topiramate treatment appears to be more common when topiramate is used concomitantly with VPA.



    Monitoring for Hyperammonemia  



 Patients with inborn errors of metabolism or reduced hepatic mitochondrial activity may be at an increased risk for hyperammonemia with or without encephalopathy. Although not studied, topiramate treatment or an interaction of concomitant topiramate and valproic acid treatment may exacerbate existing defects or unmask deficiencies in susceptible persons.



 In patients who develop unexplained lethargy, vomiting, or changes in mental status associated with any topiramate treatment, hyperammonemic encephalopathy should be considered and an ammonia level should be measured.



    5.11 Kidney Stones



  A total of 32/2086 (1.5%) of adults exposed to topiramate during its adjunctive epilepsy therapy development reported the occurrence of kidney stones, an incidence about 2 to 4 times greater than expected in a similar, untreated population. In the double-blind monotherapy epilepsy study, a total of 4/319 (1.3%) of adults exposed to topiramate reported the occurrence of kidney stones. As in the general population, the incidence of stone formation among topiramate-treated patients was higher in men. Kidney stones have also been reported in pediatric patients taking topiramate for epilepsy or migraine.



 During long-term (up to 1 year) topiramate treatment in an open-label extension study of 284 pediatric patients 1-24 months old with epilepsy, 7% developed kidney or bladder stones that were diagnosed clinically or by sonogram. TOPAMAX  (r)  is not approved for treatment of epilepsy in pediatric patients less than 2 years old [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ].  



 Kidney stones have also been reported in pediatric patients taking topiramate for migraine prophylaxis. For the double-blind migraine prophylaxis studies, one adverse event (renal calculus) occurred in a topiramate-treated subject in the age 12 to 17 years group. The overall experience with open-label, long-term, topiramate treatment for migraine prophylaxis is limited in pediatric patients.



 An explanation for the association of TOPAMAX  (r)  and kidney stones may lie in the fact that topiramate is a carbonic anhydrase inhibitor. Carbonic anhydrase inhibitors (e.g., zonisamide, acetazolamide, or dichlorphenamide) can promote stone formation by reducing urinary citrate excretion and by increasing urinary pH [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  . The concomitant use of TOPAMAX  (r)  with any other drug producing metabolic acidosis, or potentially in patients on a ketogenic diet, may create a physiological environment that increases the risk of kidney stone formation, and should therefore be avoided.



 Increased fluid intake increases the urinary output, lowering the concentration of substances involved in stone formation. Hydration is recommended to reduce new stone formation.



    5.12 Hypothermia with Concomitant Valproic Acid (VPA) Use



  Hypothermia, defined as an unintentional drop in body core temperature to &lt;35 degrees C (95 degrees F), has been reported in association with topiramate use with concomitant valproic acid (VPA) both in conjunction with hyperammonemia and in the absence of hyperammonemia. This adverse reaction in patients using concomitant topiramate and valproate can occur after starting topiramate treatment or after increasing the daily dose of topiramate [see  Drug Interactions (7.1)  ]  . Consideration should be given to stopping topiramate or valproate in patients who develop hypothermia, which may be manifested by a variety of clinical abnormalities including lethargy, confusion, coma, and significant alterations in other major organ systems such as the cardiovascular and respiratory systems. Clinical management and assessment should include examination of blood ammonia levels.



    5.13 Paresthesia



  Paresthesia (usually tingling of the extremities), an effect associated with the use of other carbonic anhydrase inhibitors, appears to be a common effect of TOPAMAX  (r)  in adult and pediatric patients. Paresthesia was more frequently reported in the monotherapy epilepsy trials and migraine prophylaxis trials than in the adjunctive therapy epilepsy trials. In the majority of instances, paresthesia did not lead to treatment discontinuation.



    5.14 Adjustment of Dose in Renal Failure



  The major route of elimination of unchanged topiramate and its metabolites is via the kidney. Dosage adjustment may be required in patients with reduced renal function [see  Dosage and Administration (2.4)  ]  .



    5.15 Decreased Hepatic Function



  In hepatically impaired patients, TOPAMAX  (r)  should be administered with caution as the clearance of topiramate may be decreased [see  Dosage and Administration (2.7)  ]  .



    5.16 Monitoring: Laboratory Tests



  Topiramate treatment was associated with changes in several clinical laboratory analytes in randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled studies.



 Topiramate treatment causes non-anion gap, hyperchloremic metabolic acidosis manifested by a decrease in serum bicarbonate and an increase in serum chloride. Measurement of baseline and periodic serum bicarbonate during TOPAMAX  (r)  treatment is recommended [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  .



 TOPAMAX  (r)  treatment with or without concomitant valproic acid (VPA) can cause hyperammonemia with or without encephalopathy [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  .



 The clinical significance of decreased serum bicarbonate and associated increased serum chloride reflecting metabolic acidosis and of increased ammonia reflecting hyperammonemia which may be associated with encephalopathy is described [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4  and  5.10)  ]  . However, the clinical significance of these other various abnormalities in other clinical laboratory analytes described here has not been clearly established.



    Epilepsy  



 Controlled trials of adjunctive topiramate treatment of adults for partial onset seizures showed an increased incidence of markedly decreased serum phosphorus (6% topiramate, 2% placebo), markedly increased serum alkaline phosphatase (3% topiramate, 1% placebo), and decreased serum potassium (0.4 % topiramate, 0.1 % placebo).



 Changes in several clinical laboratory analytes (i.e., increased creatinine, BUN, alkaline phosphatase, total protein, total eosinophil count, and decreased potassium) have been observed in a clinical investigational program in very young (&lt;2 years) pediatric patients who were treated with adjunctive topiramate for partial onset seizures [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ]  .



     Migraine    



  In pooled double-blind studies in pediatric patients (6 to 17 years), an increased risk for certain abnormalities (value outside normal reference range) in selected clinical laboratory analytes measured in blood has been observed during topiramate treatment of pediatric patients compared to placebo-treated patients. In some instances, abnormalities were also observed at the end of the trial at the final visit and the changes were considered markedly abnormal.  



  For patients 12 to 17 years, the following were noted to be abnormally increased more frequently with topiramate than with placebo: BUN, creatinine, uric acid, chloride [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  , ammonia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  , total protein, and platelets. The following were abnormally decreased in some subjects: phosphorus, and bicarbonate [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  .  



  For patients 6 to 11 years, the following were noted to be abnormally increased more frequently with topiramate than with placebo: alkaline phosphatase, creatinine and eosinophils. Analytes abnormally decreased were: total white count and neutrophils. There was no testing for serum bicarbonate, chloride, ammonia, or phosphorus in these younger patients.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
