<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="topicort" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 1%) are application site dryness, application site irritation and application site pruritus. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Taro at 1-866-923-4914 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In randomized, multicenter, prospective vehicle-controlled clinical trials, subjects with moderate to severe plaque psoriasis of the body applied Topicort  (r)  Topical Spray or vehicle spray twice daily for 4 weeks. A total of 149 subjects applied Topicort  (r)  Topical Spray.



 Adverse reactions that occurred in &gt;= 1% of subjects treated with Topicort  (r)  Topical Spray were application site dryness (2.7%), application site irritation (2.7%) and application site pruritus (2.0%).



 Another less common adverse reaction (&lt;1% but &gt;0.1%) was folliculitis.



 Table 1. Number (%) of Subjects with Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;= 1% 
                                           Topicort  (r)  Topical Spray, 0.25%  b.i.d.  (N = 149)  Vehicle spray  b.i.d.  (N = 135)   
  
 Number of Subjects with Adverse Reactions            13 (8.7%)                       18 (13.3%)             
 Application site dryness                             4 (2.7%)                        7 (5.2%)              
 Application site irritation                          4 (2.7%)                        5 (3.7%)              
 Application site pruritus                            3 (2.0%)                        5 (3.7%)              
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

    Instructions for UseTOPICORT  (r)   (Top-i-cort)(desoximetasone) Topical Spray  



     Important information: Topicort  (r)   Topical Spray is for use on skin only.   Do not get Topicort  (r)   Topical Spray near or in your mouth, eyes or vagina.



   Read the Instructions for Use that comes with Topicort  (r)   Topical Spray before you start using it and each time you get a refill. There may be new information. This information does not take the place of talking with your doctor about your medical condition or your treatment.



   Parts of Topicort  (r)   Topical Spray bottle (See   Figure A  )  



   Figure A  



 



   How to apply Topicort  (r)   Topical Spray:  



   Step 1:   Remove the cap from the pump top.



   Step 2:   Hold the bottle in an upright position while pointing the opening of the pump top in the direction of the affected area. To spray, push down on the pump top. Apply Topicort  (r)   Topical Spray to the affected area as instructed by your doctor. (  See   Figure B    )



   Figure B  



 



   Step 3:   Spray only enough Topicort  (r)   Topical Spray to cover the affected area, for example, the elbow



   (See   Figure C    ). Rub in Topicort  (r)   Topical Spray gently.



   Figure C  



 



 Repeat Steps 2 and 3 to apply Topicort  (r)   Topical Spray to other affected areas as instructed by your doctor.



   Step 4:   After applying Topicort  (r)   Topical Spray, place the cap back onto the pump top. (  See   Figure D    )



   Figure D  



 



 This Patient Information and Instructions for Use have been approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration.



 Mfd. by: Taro Pharmaceuticals Inc., Brampton, Ontario, Canada L6T 1C1Dist. by: TaroPharma a division of Taro Pharmaceuticals U.S.A., Inc., Hawthorne, NY 10532



 Topicort  (r)   and TaroPharma  (r)   are registered trademarks of Taro Pharmaceuticals U.S.A., Inc. and/or its affiliates.



 Issued: February/ 2013PK-7265-0   110



  Figure A  Figure B  Figure C  Figure D 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Topicort  (r)  Topical Spray can produce reversible HPA axis suppression with the potential for glucocorticosteroid insufficiency during or after treatment. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Cushing's syndrome, hyperglycemia, and unmasking of latent diabetes mellitus can result from systemic absorption of topical corticosteroids. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Because of the potential for systemic absorption, use of topical corticosteroids may require that patients be periodically evaluated for HPA axis suppression. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Modify use if HPA axis suppression develops. (  5.1  ) 
 *  High potency corticosteroids, large treatment surface areas, prolonged use, use of occlusive dressings, altered skin barrier, liver failure and young age may predispose patients to HPA axis suppression. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Pediatric patients may be more susceptible to systemic toxicity when treated with topical corticosteroids. (  5.1  ,  8.4  ) 
 *  Topicort  (r)  Topical Spray is flammable; keep away from heat or flame. (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Effect on Endocrine System



  Topicort  (r)  Topical Spray is a topical corticosteroid that has been shown to suppress the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis.



 Systemic absorption of topical corticosteroids can produce reversible HPA axis suppression with the potential for glucocorticosteroid insufficiency. This may occur during treatment or upon withdrawal of the topical corticosteroid.



 In a study including 21 evaluable subjects 18 years of age or older with moderate to severe plaque psoriasis, adrenal suppression was identified in 1 out of 12 subjects having involvement of 10-15% of body surface area (BSA) and 2 out of 9 subjects having involvement of &gt;15% of BSA after treatment with Topicort  (r)  Topical Spray twice a day for 28 days. [ see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)    ]



 Because of the potential for systemic absorption, use of topical corticosteroids may require that patients be periodically evaluated for HPA axis suppression. Factors that predispose a patient using a topical corticosteroid to HPA axis suppression include the use of high potency steroids, larger treatment surface areas, prolonged use, use of occlusive dressings, altered skin barrier, liver failure and young age.



 An ACTH stimulation test may be helpful in evaluating patients for HPA axis suppression.



 If HPA axis suppression is documented, an attempt should be made to gradually withdraw the drug, to reduce the frequency of application, or to substitute a less potent steroid. Manifestations of adrenal insufficiency may require supplemental systemic corticosteroids. Recovery of HPA axis function is generally prompt and complete upon discontinuation of topical corticosteroids.



 Cushing's syndrome, hyperglycemia, and unmasking of latent diabetes mellitus can also result from systemic absorption of topical corticosteroids.



 Use of more than one corticosteroid-containing product at the same time may increase the total systemic corticosteroid exposure.



 Pediatric patients may be more susceptible to systemic toxicity from use of topical corticosteroids. [ see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)    ]



    5.2 Local Adverse Reactions with Topical Corticosteroids



  Local adverse reactions may be more likely to occur with occlusive use, prolonged use or use of higher potency corticosteroids. Reactions may include atrophy, striae, telangiectasias, burning, itching, irritation, dryness, folliculitis, acneiform eruptions, hypopigmentation, perioral dermatitis, allergic contact dermatitis, secondary infection, and miliaria. Some local adverse reactions may be irreversible.



    5.3 Allergic Contact Dermatitis with Topical Corticosteroids



  Allergic contact dermatitis to any component of topical corticosteroids is usually diagnosed by a failure to heal rather than a clinical exacerbation. Clinical diagnosis of allergic contact dermatitis can be confirmed by patch testing.



    5.4 Concomitant Skin Infections



  Concomitant skin infections should be treated with an appropriate antimicrobial agent.



 If the infection persists, Topicort  (r)  Topical Spray should be discontinued until the infection has been adequately treated.



    5.5 Flammable Contents



  Topicort  (r)  Topical Spray is flammable; keep away from heat or flame.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
