<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="topotecan0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Small cell lung cancer:



 *  The most common hematologic adverse reactions were: neutropenia (97%), leukopenia (97%), anemia (89%), and thrombocytopenia (69%). (6.1) 
 *  The most common (&gt;25%) non-hematologic adverse reactions (all grades) were: nausea, alopecia, vomiting, sepsis or pyrexia/infection with neutropenia, diarrhea, constipation, fatigue, and pyrexia. (6.1) 
    Cervical cancer (Topotecan Injection plus cisplatin):
 

 *  The most common hematologic adverse reactions (all grades) were: anemia (94%), leukopenia (91%), neutropenia (89%), and thrombocytopenia (74%). (6.1) 
 *  The most common (&gt;25%) non-hematologic adverse reactions (all grades) were: pain, nausea, vomiting, and infection/febrile neutropenia. (6.1) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact  Sandoz Inc. at 1-800-525-8747  or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    
 

 

    6.1 Clinical Trials Experience  

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Small Cell Lung Cancer    



 Data in the following section are based on the combined experiences of the 879 patients studied, including 426 patients with small cell lung cancer treated with topotecan.  Table 1  lists the principle hematologic adverse reactions and  Table 2  lists non-hematologic adverse reactions occurring in at least 15% of patients.



   Table 1. Hematologic Adverse Reactions Experienced in &gt;=15% of Patients, Including 426 Patients With Small Cell Lung Cancer, Receiving Topotecan  




 Hematologic Adverse Reaction                         Patients  (n=879) % Incidence                       
  Neutropenia  &lt;1,500 cells/mm3 &lt;500 cells/mm  3      97 78                                               
  Leukopenia  &lt;3,000 cells/mm3 &lt;1,000 cells/mm  3     97 32                                               
  Thrombocytopenia  &lt;75,000/mm3 &lt;25,000/mm  3         69 27                                               
  Anemia  &lt;10 g/dL &lt;8 g/dL                            89 37                                               
          Table 2. Non-hematologic Adverse Reactions Experienced by &gt;=15% of 879 Patients, Including 426 Patients With Small Cell Lung Cancer, Receiving Topotecan  
 


  Non-hematologic   Adverse Reaction              Percentage of Patients with Adverse Reaction (879 Patients)     
   All Grades                                     Grade 3               Grade 4          
                                                                                         
   Infections and infestations                                                                             
 Sepsis or pyrexia/infection with neutropenia  a    43                    NR                23                 
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders                                                                      
   Anorexia                                     19                    2                 &lt;1                 
   Nervous system disorders                                                                                
   Headache                                     18                    1                 &lt;1                 
   Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders                                                               
   Dyspnea                                      22                    5                 3                  
   Coughing                                     15                    1                 0                  
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                              
   Nausea                                       64                    7                 1                  
   Vomiting                                     45                    4                 1                  
   Diarrhea                                     32                    3                 1                  
   Constipation                                 29                    2                 1                  
   Abdominal pain                               22                    2                 2                  
   Stomatitis                                   18                    1                 &lt;1                 
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                                                                  
   Alopecia                                     49                    NA                NA                 
   Rash  b                                      16                    1                 0                  
   General disorders and administrative site conditions                                                               
   Fatigue                                      29                    5                 0                  
   Pyrexia                                      28                    1                 &lt;1                 
   Pain  c                                      23                    2                 1                  
   Asthenia                                     25                    4                 2                  
          NA = Not applicable
 

 NR = Not reported separately



   a  Does not include Grade 1 sepsis or pyrexia



   b  Rash also includes pruritus, rash erythematous, urticaria, dermatitis, bullous eruption, and maculopapular rash.



   c  Pain includes body pain, back pain, and skeletal pain.



     Nervous System Disorders    



 Paresthesia occurred in 7% of patients but was generally grade 1.



     Hepatobiliary Disorders    



 Grade 1 transient elevations in hepatic enzymes occurred in 8% of patients. Greater elevations, grade 3/4, occurred in 4%. Grade 3/4 elevated bilirubin occurred in &lt;2% of patients.



   Table 3  shows the grade 3/4 hematologic and major non-hematologic adverse reactions in the topotecan/CAV comparator trial in small cell lung cancer.



   Table 3. Adverse Reactions Experienced by &gt;=5% of Small Cell Lung Cancer Patients Randomized to Receive Topotecan or CAV  



  




  Adverse Reaction                                    Topotecan (n=107)        CAV (n=104)                 
   Hematologic Grade 3/4                               %                        %                          
  Grade 4 neutropenia (&lt;500 cells/mm  3  )           70                       72                           
  Grade 3/4 anemia (Hgb &lt;8 g dL)                     42                       20                           
  Grade 4 thrombocytopenia (&lt;25,000 plts/mm  3  )    29                       5                            
 Pyrexia/Grade 4 neutropenia                         28                       26                           
   Non-hematologic Grade 3/4                           %                        %                          
  Infections and infestations Documented sepsis  a    5                        5                            
  Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders  Dyspnea    9                        14                          
 Pneumonia                                           8                        6                            
  Gastrointestinal disorders  Abdominal pain          6                        4                           
 Nausea                                              8                        6                            
  General disorders and administrative site conditions  Fatigue    6                        10                          
 Asthenia                                             9                        7                           
 Pain  b                                             5                        7                            
           a  Death related to sepsis occurred in 3% of patients receiving topotecan, and 1% of patients receiving CAV
 

   b  Pain includes body pain, skeletal pain, and back pain.



     Cervical Cancer    



 In the comparative trial with Topotecan Injection plus cisplatin versus cisplatin in patients with cervical cancer, the most common dose-limiting adverse reaction was myelosuppression.  Table 4  shows the hematologic adverse reactions and  Table 5  shows the non-hematologic adverse reactions in patients with cervical cancer.



   Table 4. Hematologic Adverse Reactions in Patients with Cervical Cancer Treated with Topotecan Injection Plus Cisplatin or Cisplatin Monotherapy  a    




   Hematologic Adverse Reaction                  Topotecan Injection Plus Cisplatin   (n = 140)     Cisplatin   (n = 144)     
 Anemia                                                                                                    
   All grades (Hgb &lt;12 g/dL)                    131 (94%)                       130 (90%)                  
   Grade 3 (Hgb &lt;8 to 6.5 g/dL)                 47 (34%)                        28 (19%)                   
   Grade 4 (Hgb &lt;6.5 g/dL)                      9 (6%)                          5 (3%)                     
 Leukopenia                                                                                                
   All grades (&lt;3,800 cells/mm  3  )            128 (91%)                       43 (30%)                   
   Grade 3 (&lt;2,000 to 1,000 cells/mm  3  )      58 (41%)                        1 (1%)                     
   Grade 4 (&lt;1,000 cells/mm  3  )               35 (25%)                        0 (0%)                     
 Neutropenia                                                                                               
   All grades (&lt;2,000 cells/mm  3  )            125 (89%)                       28 (19%)                   
   Grade 3 (&lt;1,000 to 500 cells/mm  3  )        36 (26%)                        1 (1%)                     
   Grade 4 (&lt;500 cells/mm  3  )                 67 (48%)                        1 (1%)                     
 Thrombocytopenia                                                                                          
   All grades (&lt;130,000 cells/mm  3  )          104 (74%)                       21 (15%)                   
   Grade 3 (&lt;50,000 to 10,000 cells/mm  3  )    36 (26%)                        5 (3%)                     
   Grade 4 (&lt;10,000 cells/mm  3  )              10 (7%)                         0 (0%)                     
          
 

   a  Includes patients who were eligible and treated.



   Table 5. Non-hematologic Adverse Reactions Experienced by  &gt;=  5% of Patients with Cervical Cancer Treated with Topotecan Injection Plus Cisplatin or Cisplatin Monotherapy  a    




                                   Topotecan Injection Plus Cisplatin      Cisplatin     
   (n = 140)                       (n = 144)     
 Adverse Reaction                All Grades  b    Grade 3        Grade 4      All Grades  b    Grade 3     Grade 4     
   General disorders and administrative site conditions                                                                                    
   Constitutional  c             96 (69%)       11 (8%)        0            89 (62%)     17 (12%)    0           
   Pain  d                       82 (59%)       28 (20%)       3 (2%)       72 (50%)     18 (13%)    5 (3%)      
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                                    
   Vomiting                      56 (40%)       20 (14%)       2 (1%)       53 (37%)     13 (9%)     0           
   Nausea                        77 (55%)       18 (13%)       2 (1%)       79 (55%)     13 (9%)     0           
   Stomatitis-pharyngitis        8 (6%)         1 (&lt;1%)        0            0            0           0           
   Other                         88 (63%)       16 (11%)       4 (3%)       80 (56%)     12 (8%)     3 (2%)      
   Dermatology                   67 (48%)       1 (&lt;1%)        0            29 (20%)     0           0           
   Metabolic-Laboratory          55 (39%)       13 (9%)        7 (5%)       44 (31%)     14 (10%)    1 (&lt;1%)     
   Genitourinary                 51 (36%)       9 (6%)         9 (6%)       49 (34%)     7 (5%)      7 (5%)      
   Nervous system disorders                                                                                      
   Neuropathy                    4 (3%)         1 (&lt;1%)        0            3 (2%)       1 (&lt;1%)     0           
   Other                         49 (35%)       3 (2%)         1 (&lt;1%)      43 (30%)     7 (5%)      2 (1%)      
   Infection-febrile neutropenia    39 (28%)       21 (15%)       5 (4%)       26 (18%)     11 (8%)     0           
   Cardiovascular                35 (25%)       7 (5%)         6 (4%)       22 (15%)     8 (6%)      3 (2%)      
   Hepatic                       34 (24%)       5 (4%)         2 (1%)       23 (16%)     2 (1%)      0           
   Pulmonary                     24 (17%)       4 (3%)         0            23 (16%)     5 (3%)      3 (2%)      
   Vascular disorders                                                                                            
   Hemorrhage                    21 (15%)       8 (6%)         1 (&lt;1%)      20 (14%)     3 (2%)      1 (&lt;1%)     
   Coagulation                   8 (6%)         4 (3%)         3 (2%)       10 (7%)      7 (5%)      0           
   Musculoskeletal               19 (14%)       3 (2%)         0            7 (5%)       1 (&lt;1%)     1 (&lt;1%)     
   Allergy-Immunology            8 (6%)         2 (1%)         1 (&lt;1%)      4 (3%)       0           1 (&lt;1%)     
   Endocrine                     8 (6%)         0              0            4 (3%)       2 (1%)      0           
   Sexual reproduction function    7 (5%)         0              0            10 (7%)      1 (&lt;1%)     0           
   Ocular-visual                 7 (5%)         0              0            7 (5%)       1 (&lt;1%)     0           
             Data were collected using NCI Common Toxicity Criteria, v. 2.0.
 

   a  Includes patients who were eligible and treated.



   b  Grades 1 through 4 only. There were 3 patients who experienced grade 5 deaths with investigator-designated attribution. One was a grade 5 hemorrhage in which the drug-related thrombocytopenia aggravated the event. A second patient experienced bowel obstruction, cardiac arrest, pleural effusion and respiratory failure which were not treatment related but probably aggravated by treatment. A third patient experienced a pulmonary embolism and adult respiratory distress syndrome, the latter was indirectly treatment-related.



   c  Constitutional includes fatigue (lethargy, malaise, asthenia), fever (in the absence of neutropenia), rigors, chills, sweating, and weight gain or loss.



   d  Pain includes abdominal pain or cramping, arthralgia, bone pain, chest pain (non-cardiac and non-pleuritic), dysmenorrhea, dyspareunia, earache, headache, hepatic pain, myalgia, neuropathic pain, pain due to radiation, pelvic pain, pleuritic pain, rectal or perirectal pain, and tumor pain.



     6.2 Postmarketing Experience  

  In addition to adverse reactions reported from clinical trials or listed in other sections of the prescribing information, the following reactions have been identified during post-marketing use of Topotecan Injection. Because they are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, estimates of frequency cannot be made. These reactions have been chosen for inclusion due to a combination of their seriousness, frequency of reporting, or potential causal connection to Topotecan Injection.



     Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:    Severe bleeding (in association with thrombocytopenia).  [see  Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )  ]  



     Immune System Disorders:    Allergic manifestations; Anaphylactoid reactions.



     Gastrointestinal Disorders:    Abdominal pain potentially associated with neutropenic colitis.  [see  Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )  ]  



     Pulmonary Disorders:    Interstitial lung disease  [see  Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )  ]  



     Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:    Angioedema, severe dermatitis, severe pruritus



     General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:    Inadvertent extravasation  [see  Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )  ]  
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: BONE MARROW SUPPRESSION

    WARNING: BONE MARROW SUPPRESSION  

    Do not give Topotecan Injection to patients with baseline neutrophil counts less than 1,500 cells/mm  3      . In order to monitor the occurrence of bone marrow suppression, primarily neutropenia, which may be severe and result in infection and death, monitor peripheral blood counts frequently on all patients receiving Topotecan Injection  .   [see   Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )  ]  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: BONE MARROW SUPPRESSION  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  



   Do not give Topotecan to patients with baseline neutrophil counts less than 1,500 cells/mm  3  . In order to monitor the occurrence of bone marrow suppression, primarily neutropenia, which may be severe and result in infection and death, monitor peripheral blood cell counts frequently on all patients receiving Topotecan Injection. (5.1)  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Bone marrow suppression: Administer Topotecan Injection only to patients with adequate bone marrow reserves. Monitor peripheral blood counts and adjust the dose if needed. (5.1) 
 *  Topotecan-induced neutropenia can lead to neutropenic colitis. (5.2) 
 *  Interstitial lung disease: topotecan has been associated with reports of interstitial lung disease. Monitor patients for symptoms and discontinue Topotecan Injection if the diagnosis is confirmed. (5.3) 
 *  Pregnancy: Can cause fetal harm. Advise women of potential risk to the fetus. (5.4, 8.1) 
    
 

    5.1 Bone Marrow Suppression  



  Bone marrow suppression (primarily neutropenia) is the dose-limiting toxicity of Topotecan Injection. Neutropenia is not cumulative over time. In the comparative study, in small cell lung cancer, the treatment-related death rates were 5% for topotecan and 4% for CAV (cyclophosphamide-doxorubicin-vincristine).



   Neutropenia    



 *  From a combined experience of patients receiving topotecan which included patients treated for small cell lung cancer: Grade 4 neutropenia (&lt;500 cells/mm  3  ) was most common during course 1 of treatment (60% of patients) and occurred in 39% of all courses, with a median duration of 7 days. The nadir neutrophil count occurred at a median of 12 days. Therapy-related sepsis or febrile neutropenia occurred in 23% of patients, and sepsis was fatal in 1%. Pancytopenia has been reported. 
 *  Cervical cancer experience: Grade 3 and grade 4 neutropenia affected 26% and 48% of patients, respectively. 
      Thrombocytopenia    
 

 *  From a combined experience of patients receiving topotecan which included patients treated for small cell lung cancer: Grade 4 thrombocytopenia (&lt;25,000/mm  3  ) occurred in 27% of patients and in 9% of courses, with a median duration of 5 days and platelet nadir at a median of 15 days. Platelet transfusions were given to 15% of patients in 4% of courses. 
 *  Cervical cancer experience: Grade 3 and grade 4 thrombocytopenia affected 26% and 7% of patients, respectively.    
      Anemia    
 

 *  From a combined experience of patients receiving topotecan which included patients treated for small cell lung cancer: Grade 3/4 anemia (&lt;8 g/dL) occurred in 37% of patients and in 14% of courses. Median nadir was at day 15. Transfusions were needed in 52% of patients in 22% of courses. 
 *  Cervical cancer experience: Grade 3 and grade 4 anemia affected 34% and 6% of patients, respectively. 
      Monitoring of Bone Marrow Function    
 

 Administer Topotecan Injection only in patients with adequate bone marrow reserves, including baseline neutrophil count of at least 1,500 cells/mm  3  and platelet count at least 100,000/mm  3  .



 Monitor peripheral blood counts frequently during treatment with Topotecan Injection. Do not treat patients with subsequent courses of Topotecan Injection until neutrophils recover to &gt;1,000 cells/mm  3  , platelets recover to &gt;100,000 cells/mm  3  , and hemoglobin levels recover to 9 g/dL (with transfusion if necessary). Severe myelotoxicity has been reported when Topotecan Injection is used in combination with cisplatin [see Drug Interactions (  7  )  ]  .



     5.2 Neutropenic Colitis  



  Topotecan-induced neutropenia can lead to neutropenic colitis. Fatalities due to neutropenic colitis have been reported in clinical trials with Topotecan Injection. In patients presenting with fever, neutropenia, and a compatible pattern of abdominal pain, consider the possibility of neutropenic colitis.



     5.3 Interstitial Lung Disease  



  Topotecan Injection has been associated with reports of interstitial lung disease (ILD), some of which have been fatal [see Adverse Reactions (  6.2  )  ].  Underlying risk factors include history of ILD, pulmonary fibrosis, lung cancer, thoracic exposure to radiation, and use of pneumotoxic drugs and/or colony stimulating factors. Monitor patients for pulmonary symptoms indicative of interstitial lung disease (e.g., cough, fever, dyspnea, and/or hypoxia), and discontinue Topotecan Injection if a new diagnosis of ILD is confirmed.



     5.4 Pregnancy  



  Pregnancy Category D



 Topotecan Injection can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman.



 Topotecan caused embryolethality, fetotoxicity, and teratogenicity in rats and rabbits when administered during organogenesis. There are no adequate and well controlled studies of Topotecan Injection in pregnant women. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if a patient becomes pregnant while receiving Topotecan Injection, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus. [see Use in Specific Populations, Pregnancy (  8.1  )  ]  



     5.5 Inadvertent Extravasation  



  Inadvertent extravasation with topotecan has been observed, most reactions have been mild but severe cases have been reported.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
