<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="torisel" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions have been associated with TORISEL in clinical trials and are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the label  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5)  ]  .



 *  Hypersensitivity/Infusion Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Hepatic Impairment [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Hyperglycemia/Glucose Intolerance [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Infections [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Interstitial Lung Disease [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Hyperlipemia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
 *  Bowel Perforation [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
 *  Renal Failure [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]  
 *  Wound Healing Complications [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  
 *  Intracerebral Hemorrhage [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  
    The most common (&gt;=30%) adverse reactions observed with TORISEL are rash, asthenia, mucositis, nausea, edema, and anorexia. The most common (&gt;=30%) laboratory abnormalities observed with TORISEL are anemia, hyperglycemia, hyperlipemia, hypertriglyceridemia, lymphopenia, elevated alkaline phosphatase, elevated serum creatinine, hypophosphatemia, thrombocytopenia, elevated AST, and leukopenia.
 

   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=30%) are rash, asthenia, mucositis, nausea, edema, and anorexia. The most common laboratory abnormalities (incidence &gt;=30%) are anemia, hyperglycemia, hyperlipemia, hypertriglyceridemia, elevated alkaline phosphatase, elevated serum creatinine, lymphopenia, hypophosphatemia, thrombocytopenia, elevated AST, and leukopenia. (  6  )  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Wyeth Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-800-934-5556 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, the adverse reaction rates observed cannot be directly compared to rates in other trials and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 In the phase 3 randomized, open-label study of interferon alfa (IFN-alpha) alone, TORISEL alone, and TORISEL and IFN-alpha, a total of 616 patients were treated. Two hundred patients received IFN-alpha weekly, 208 received TORISEL 25 mg weekly, and 208 patients received a combination of TORISEL and IFN-alpha weekly  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  .



 Treatment with the combination of TORISEL 15 mg and IFN-alpha was associated with an increased incidence of multiple adverse reactions and did not result in a significant increase in overall survival when compared with IFN-alpha alone.



 Table 1 shows the percentage of patients experiencing treatment emergent adverse reactions. Reactions reported in at least 10% of patients who received TORISEL 25 mg alone or IFN-alpha alone are listed. Table 2 shows the percentage of patients experiencing selected laboratory abnormalities. Data for the same adverse reactions and laboratory abnormalities in the IFN-alpha alone arm are shown for comparison  :  



 Table 1 - Adverse Reactions Reported in at Least 10% of Patients Who Received 25 mg IV TORISEL or IFN-alpha in the Randomized Trial 
 Adverse Reaction                          TORISEL25 mgn = 208  IFN-alphan = 200   
 All Gradesn (%)                           Grades 3&amp;4n (%)  All Gradesn (%)  Grades 3&amp;4n (%)   
  
   General disorders                                                                                            
   Asthenia                                   106 (51)          23 (11)         127 (64)          52 (26)       
   Edema                                       73 (35)           7 (3)           21 (11)           1 (1)        
   Pain                                        59 (28)          10 (5)           31 (16)           4 (2)        
   Pyrexia                                     50 (24)           1 (1)           99 (50)           7 (4)        
   Weight Loss                                 39 (19)           3 (1)           50 (25)           4 (2)        
   Headache                                    31 (15)           1 (1)           30 (15)           0 (0)        
   Chest Pain                                  34 (16)           2 (1)           18 (9)            2 (1)        
   Chills                                      17 (8)            1 (1)           59 (30)           3 (2)        
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                                   
   Mucositis                                   86 (41)           6 (3)           19 (10)           0 (0)        
   Anorexia                                    66 (32)           6 (3)           87 (44)           8 (4)        
   Nausea                                      77 (37)           5 (2)           82 (41)           9 (5)        
   Diarrhea                                    56 (27)           3 (1)           40 (20)           4 (2)        
   Abdominal Pain                              44 (21)           9 (4)           34 (17)           3 (2)        
   Constipation                                42 (20)           0 (0)           36 (18)           1 (1)        
   Vomiting                                    40 (19)           4 (2)           57 (29)           5 (3)        
   Infections                                                                                                   
   Infections                                  42 (20)           6 (3)           19 (10)           4 (2)        
   Urinary tract infection                     31 (15)           3 (1)           24 (12)           3 (2)        
   Pharyngitis                                 25 (12)           0 (0)            3 (2)            0 (0)        
   Rhinitis                                    20 (10)           0 (0)            4 (2)            0 (0)        
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders                                                                         
   Back Pain                                   41 (20)           6 (3)           28 (14)           7 (4)        
   Arthralgia                                  37 (18)           2 (1)           29 (15)           2 (1)        
   Myalgia                                     16 (8)            1 (1)           29 (15)           2 (1)        
   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders                                                                         
   Dyspnea                                     58 (28)          18 (9)           48 (24)          11 (6)        
   Cough                                       53 (26)           2 (1)           29 (15)           0 (0)        
   Epistaxis                                   25 (12)           0 (0)            7 (4)            0 (0)        
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                                                                         
   Rash                                        97 (47)          10 (5)           14 (7)            0 (0)        
   Pruritus                                    40 (19)           1 (1)           16 (8)            0 (0)        
   Nail Disorder                               28 (14)           0 (0)            1 (1)            0 (0)        
   Dry Skin                                    22 (11)           1 (1)           14 (7)            0 (0)        
   Acne                                        21 (10)           0 (0)            2 (1)            0 (0)        
   Nervous system disorders                                                                                     
   Dysgeusia                                   41 (20)           0 (0)           17 (9)            0 (0)        
   Insomnia                                    24 (12)           1 (1)           30 (15)           0 (0)        
   Depression                                   9 (4)            0 (0)           27 (14)           4 (2)        
           The following selected adverse reactions were reported less frequently (&lt;10%).
 

 Gastrointestinal Disorders - Gastrointestinal hemorrhage (1%), rectal hemorrhage (1%).



 Eye Disorders - Conjunctivitis (including lacrimation disorder) (8%).



 Immune System - Angioneurotic edema-type reactions (including delayed reactions occurring two months following initiation of therapy) have been observed in some patients who received TORISEL and ACE inhibitors concomitantly.



 Infections - Pneumonia (8%), upper respiratory tract infection (7%), wound infection/post-operative wound infection (1%), sepsis (1%).



 General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions - Diabetes mellitus (5%).



 Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders - Pleural effusion (4%).



 Vascular - Hypertension (7%), venous thromboembolism (including deep vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolus [including fatal outcomes]) (2%), thrombophlebitis (1%), pericardial effusion (1%).



 Nervous System Disorders - Convulsion (1%).



 Table 2 - Incidence of Selected Laboratory Abnormalities in Patients Who Received 25 mg IV TORISEL or IFN-alpha in the Randomized Trial 
 Laboratory Abnormality                    TORISEL25 mgn = 208  IFN-alphan = 200   
 All Gradesn (%)                           Grades 3&amp;4n (%)  All Gradesn (%)  Grades 3&amp;4n (%)   
  
   Any                                        208 (100)        162 (78)         195 (98)         144 (72)       
   Hematology                                                                                                   
   Hemoglobin Decreased                       195 (94)          41 (20)         180 (90)          43 (22)       
   Lymphocytes Decreased                      110 (53)          33 (16)         106 (53)          48 (24)       
   Neutrophils Decreased                       39 (19)          10 (5)           58 (29)          19 (10)       
   Platelets Decreased                         84 (40)           3 (1)           51 (26)           0 (0)        
   Leukocytes Decreased                        67 (32)           1 (1)           93 (47)          11 (6)        
   Chemistry                                                                                                    
   Alkaline Phosphatase Increased             141 (68)           7 (3)          111 (56)          13 (7)        
   AST Increased                               79 (38)           5 (2)          103 (52)          14 (7)        
   Creatinine Increased                       119 (57)           7 (3)           97 (49)           2 (1)        
   Glucose Increased                          186 (89)          33 (16)         128 (64)           6 (3)        
   Phosphorus Decreased                       102 (49)          38 (18)          61 (31)          17 (9)        
   Total Bilirubin Increased                   16 (8)            2 (1)           25 (13)           4 (2)        
   Total Cholesterol Increased                181 (87)           5 (2)           95 (48)           2 (1)        
   Triglycerides Increased                    173 (83)          92 (44)         144 (72)          69 (35)       
   Potassium Decreased                         43 (21)          11 (5)           15 (8)            0 (0)        
             6.2 Post-marketing and Other Clinical Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of TORISEL. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to readily estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 The following adverse reactions have been observed in patients receiving temsirolimus: rhabdomyolysis, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome, complex regional pain syndrome (reflex sympathetic dystrophy), pancreatitis, cholecystitis, and cholelithiasis.



 There are also post-marketing reports of temsirolimus extravasations resulting in swelling, pain, warmth, and erythema.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypersensitivity/Infusion Reactions (including some life-threatening and rare fatal reactions) can occur early in the first infusion of TORISEL. Patients should be monitored throughout the infusion. (  5.1  ) 
 *  To treat hypersensitivity reactions, stop TORISEL and treat with an antihistamine. TORISEL may be restarted at physician discretion at a slower rate. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Hepatic Impairment: Use caution when treating patients with mild hepatic impairment and reduce dose. (  2.4  ,  5.2  ) 
 *  Hyperglycemia and hyperlipemia are likely and may require treatment. Monitor glucose and lipid profiles. (  5.3  ,  5.6  ) 
 *  Infections may result from immunosuppression. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Monitor for symptoms or radiographic changes of interstitial lung disease (ILD). If ILD is suspected, discontinue TORISEL, and consider use of corticosteroids and/or antibiotics. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Bowel perforation may occur. Evaluate fever, abdominal pain, bloody stools, and/or acute abdomen promptly. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Renal failure, sometimes fatal, has occurred. Monitor renal function at baseline and while on TORISEL. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Due to abnormal wound healing, use TORISEL with caution in the perioperative period. (  5.9  ) 
 *  Live vaccinations and close contact with those who received live vaccines should be avoided. (  5.13  ) 
 *  Women of childbearing potential should be advised of the potential hazard to the fetus and to avoid becoming pregnant. (  5.14  ) 
 *  Elderly patients may be more likely to experience certain adverse reactions, including diarrhea, edema and pneumonia. (  5.15  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity/Infusion Reactions



  Hypersensitivity/infusion reactions, including but not limited to flushing, chest pain, dyspnea, hypotension, apnea, loss of consciousness, hypersensitivity and anaphylaxis, have been associated with the administration of temsirolimus. These reactions can occur very early in the first infusion, but may also occur with subsequent infusions. Patients should be monitored throughout the infusion and appropriate supportive care should be available. Temsirolimus infusion should be interrupted in all patients with severe infusion reactions and appropriate medical therapy administered.



 TORISEL should be used with caution in persons with known hypersensitivity to temsirolimus or its metabolites (including sirolimus), polysorbate 80, or to any other component (including the excipients) of TORISEL.



 An H1antihistamine should be administered to patients before the start of the intravenous temsirolimus infusion. TORISEL should be used with caution in patients with known hypersensitivity to an antihistamine, or patients who cannot receive an antihistamine for other medical reasons.



 If a patient develops a hypersensitivity reaction during the TORISEL infusion, the infusion should be stopped and the patient should be observed for at least 30 to 60 minutes (depending on the severity of the reaction). At the discretion of the physician, treatment may be resumed with the administration of an H1-receptor antagonist (such as diphenhydramine), if not previously administered [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ]  , and/or an H2-receptor antagonist (such as intravenous famotidine 20 mg or intravenous ranitidine 50 mg) approximately 30 minutes before restarting the TORISEL infusion. The infusion may then be resumed at a slower rate (up to 60 minutes).



 A benefit-risk assessment should be done prior to the continuation of temsirolimus therapy in patients with severe or life-threatening reactions.



    5.2 Hepatic Impairment



  The safety and pharmacokinetics of TORISEL were evaluated in a dose escalation phase 1 study in 110 patients with normal or varying degrees of hepatic impairment. Patients with baseline bilirubin &gt;1.5*ULN experienced greater toxicity than patients with baseline bilirubin &lt;=1.5*ULN when treated with TORISEL. The overall frequency of &gt;= grade 3 adverse reactions and deaths, including deaths due to progressive disease, were greater in patients with baseline bilirubin &gt;1.5*ULN due to increased risk of death [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  .



 Use caution when treating patients with mild hepatic impairment. Concentrations of temsirolimus and its metabolite sirolimus were increased in patients with elevated AST or bilirubin levels. If TORISEL must be given in patients with mild hepatic impairment (bilirubin &gt;1 - 1.5*ULN or AST &gt;ULN but bilirubin &lt;=ULN), reduce the dose of TORISEL to 15 mg/week [see  Dosage and Administration (2.4)  ]  .



    5.3 Hyperglycemia/Glucose Intolerance



  The use of TORISEL is likely to result in increases in serum glucose. In the phase 3 trial, 89% of patients receiving TORISEL had at least one elevated serum glucose while on treatment, and 26% of patients reported hyperglycemia as an adverse event. This may result in the need for an increase in the dose of, or initiation of, insulin and/or oral hypoglycemic agent therapy. Serum glucose should be tested before and during treatment with TORISEL. Patients should be advised to report excessive thirst or any increase in the volume or frequency of urination.



    5.4 Infections



   The use of TORISEL may result in immunosuppression. Patients should be carefully observed for the occurrence of infections, including opportunistic infections [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .  



  Pneumocystis jiroveci pneumonia (PJP), including fatalities, has been reported in patients who received temsirolimus. This may be associated with concomitant use of corticosteroids or other immunosuppressive agents. Prophylaxis of PJP should be considered when concomitant use of corticosteroids or other immunosuppressive agents are required.  



    5.5 Interstitial Lung Disease



   Cases of interstitial lung disease, some resulting in death, occurred in patients who received TORISEL. Some patients were asymptomatic, or had minimal symptoms, with infiltrates detected on computed tomography scan or chest radiograph. Others presented with symptoms such as dyspnea, cough, hypoxia, and fever. Some patients required discontinuation of TORISEL and/or treatment with corticosteroids and/or antibiotics, while some patients continued treatment without additional intervention. Patients should be advised to report promptly any new or worsening respiratory symptoms.  



  It is recommended that patients undergo baseline radiographic assessment by lung computed tomography scan or chest radiograph prior to the initiation of TORISEL therapy. Follow such assessments periodically, even in the absence of clinical respiratory symptoms.  



  It is recommended that patients be followed closely for occurrence of clinical respiratory symptoms. If clinically significant respiratory symptoms develop, consider withholding TORISEL administration until after recovery of symptoms and improvement of radiographic findings related to pneumonitis. Empiric treatment with corticosteroids and/or antibiotics may be considered. Opportunistic infections such as PJP should be considered in the differential diagnosis. For patients who require use of corticosteroids, prophylaxis of PJP may be considered.  



    5.6 Hyperlipemia



  The use of TORISEL is likely to result in increases in serum triglycerides and cholesterol. In the phase 3 trial, 87% of patients receiving TORISEL had at least one elevated serum cholesterol value and 83% had at least one elevated serum triglyceride value. This may require initiation, or increase in the dose, of lipid-lowering agents. Serum cholesterol and triglycerides should be tested before and during treatment with TORISEL.



    5.7 Bowel Perforation



  Cases of fatal bowel perforation occurred in patients who received TORISEL. These patients presented with fever, abdominal pain, metabolic acidosis, bloody stools, diarrhea, and/or acute abdomen. Patients should be advised to report promptly any new or worsening abdominal pain or blood in their stools.



    5.8 Renal Failure



  Cases of rapidly progressive and sometimes fatal acute renal failure not clearly related to disease progression occurred in patients who received TORISEL. Some of these cases were not responsive to dialysis.



    5.9 Wound Healing Complications



  Use of TORISEL has been associated with abnormal wound healing. Therefore, caution should be exercised with the use of TORISEL in the perioperative period.



    5.10 Intracerebral Hemorrhage



  Patients with central nervous system tumors (primary CNS tumor or metastases) and/or receiving anticoagulation therapy may be at an increased risk of developing intracerebral bleeding (including fatal outcomes) while receiving TORISEL.



    5.11 Co-administration with Inducers or Inhibitors of CYP3A Metabolism



  Agents Inducing CYP3A Metabolism:



 Strong inducers of CYP3A4/5 such as dexamethasone, carbamazepine, phenytoin, phenobarbital, rifampin, rifabutin, and rifampacin may decrease exposure of the active metabolite, sirolimus. If alternative treatment cannot be administered, a dose adjustment should be considered. St. John's Wort may decrease TORISEL plasma concentrations unpredictably. Patients receiving TORISEL should not take St. John's Wort concomitantly [see  Dosage and Administration (2.4)  and  Drug Interactions (7.1)  ]  .



   Agents Inhibiting CYP3A Metabolism:



 Strong CYP3A4 inhibitors such as atazanavir, clarithromycin, indinavir, itraconazole, ketoconazole, nefazodone, nelfinavir, ritonavir, saquinavir, and telithromycin may increase blood concentrations of the active metabolite sirolimus. If alternative treatments cannot be administered, a dose adjustment should be considered [see  Dosage and Administration (2.4)  and  Drug Interactions (7.2)  ]  .



    5.12 Concomitant use of TORISEL with sunitinib



  The combination of TORISEL and sunitinib resulted in dose-limiting toxicity. Dose-limiting toxicities (Grade 3/4 erythematous maculopapular rash, and gout/cellulitis requiring hospitalization) were observed in two out of three patients treated in the first cohort of a phase 1 study at doses of TORISEL 15 mg IV per week and sunitinib 25 mg oral per day (Days 1-28 followed by a 2-week rest).



    5.13 Vaccinations



  The use of live vaccines and close contact with those who have received live vaccines should be avoided during treatment with TORISEL. Examples of live vaccines are: intranasal influenza, measles, mumps, rubella, oral polio, BCG, yellow fever, varicella, and TY21a typhoid vaccines.



    5.14 Use in Pregnancy



  There are no adequate and well-controlled studies of TORISEL in pregnant women. However, based on its mechanism of action, TORISEL may cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Temsirolimus administered daily as an oral formulation caused embryo-fetal and intrauterine toxicities in rats and rabbits at human sub-therapeutic exposures. If this drug is used during pregnancy or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking the drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus. Women of childbearing potential should be advised to avoid becoming pregnant throughout treatment and for 3 months after TORISEL therapy has stopped [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ].  



 Men should be counseled regarding the effects of TORISEL on the fetus and sperm prior to starting treatment [see  Nonclinical Toxicology (13.1)  ]  . Men with partners of childbearing potential should use reliable contraception throughout treatment and are recommended to continue this for 3 months after the last dose of TORISEL.



    5.15 Elderly Patients



  Based on the results of a phase 3 study, elderly patients may be more likely to experience certain adverse reactions including diarrhea, edema, and pneumonia [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.5)  ].  



    5.16 Monitoring Laboratory Tests



  In the randomized, phase 3 trial, complete blood counts (CBCs) were checked weekly, and chemistry panels were checked every two weeks. Laboratory monitoring for patients receiving TORISEL may need to be performed more or less frequently at the physician's discretion.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
