<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="toujeo" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6. ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere:



 *  Hypoglycemia [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Hypersensitivity and allergic reactions [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Hypokalemia [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions commonly associated with TOUJEO (&gt;=5%) are:
 

 *  Hypoglycemia, allergic reactions, injection site reaction, lipodystrophy, pruritus, rash, edema and weight gain. (  6.1  ,  6.2  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact sanofi- aventis at 1-800-633-1610 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    
 

 

  6.1 Clinical trial experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug, and may not reflect the rates actually observed in clinical practice.



 The data in Table 1 reflect the exposure of 304 patients with type 1 diabetes to TOUJEO with mean exposure duration of 23 weeks. The type 1 diabetes population had the following characteristics: Mean age was 46 years and mean duration of diabetes was 21 years. Fifty five percent were male, 86% were Caucasian, 5 % were Black or African American and 5 % were Hispanic. At baseline, the mean eGFR was 82 mL/min/1.73m  2  and 35% of patients had eGFR&gt;=90 mL/min/1.73m  2  . The mean BMI was 28 kg/m  2  . HbA1c at baseline was greater or equal to 8% in 58% of patients.



 The data in Table 2 reflect the exposure of 1242 patients with type 2 diabetes to TOUJEO with mean exposure duration of 25 weeks. The type 2 diabetes population had the following characteristics: Mean age was 59 years and mean duration of diabetes was 13 years. Fifty three percent were male, 88% were Caucasian, 7% were Black or African American and 17% were Hispanic. At baseline, mean eGFR was 79 mL/min/1.73m  2  and 27% of patients had an eGFR&gt;=90 mL/min/1.73m  2  . The mean BMI was 35 kg/m  2  . HbA1c at baseline was greater or equal to 8% in 66% of patients.



 Common adverse reactions were defined as reactions occurring in &gt;=5% of the population studied.



 Common adverse reactions occurring for TOUJEO-treated subjects during clinical trials in patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus and type 2 diabetes mellitus are listed in Table 1 and Table 2, respectively. Hypoglycemia is discussed in a dedicated subsection below  .  



 Table 1: Adverse reactions in two pooled clinical trials of 26 weeks and 16 weeks duration in adults with type 1 diabetes (with incidence &gt;=5%) 
                                                                 TOUJEO + mealtime insulin, %(n=304)      
  
 Nasopharyngitis                                                                 12.8                     
 Upper respiratory tract infection                                               9.5                      
       Table 2: Adverse reactions in three pooled clinical trials of 26 weeks duration in adults with type 2 diabetes (with incidence &gt;=5%) 
                                                                          TOUJEO, %(n=1,242)              
  
 Nasopharyngitis                                                                 7.1                      
 Upper respiratory tract infection                                               5.7                      
            Hypoglycemia  
 

 Hypoglycemia is the most commonly observed adverse reaction in patients using insulin, including TOUJEO  [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  . In the TOUJEO program, severe hypoglycemia was defined as an event requiring assistance of another person to administer a resuscitative action and documented symptomatic hypoglycemia was defined as an event with typical symptoms of hypoglycemia accompanied by a self-monitored or plasma glucose value equal to or less than 54 mg/dL.



 The incidence of severe hypoglycemia in patients with type 1 diabetes receiving TOUJEO as part of a multiple daily injection regimen was 6.6% at 26 weeks. The incidence of documented symptomatic hypoglycemia was 69% at 26 weeks. There were no clinically important differences in hypoglycemia between TOUJEO and LANTUS among type 1 diabetes patients.



 The incidence of severe hypoglycemia in patients with type 2 diabetes was 5% at 26 weeks in patients receiving TOUJEO as part of a multiple daily injection regimen, and 1.0% and 0.9% respectively at 26 weeks in the two studies where patients received TOUJEO as part of a basal-insulin only regimen. The incidence of documented symptomatic hypoglycemia in patients with type 2 diabetes receiving TOUJEO ranged from 8% to 37% at 26 weeks and the highest risk was again seen in patients receiving TOUJEO as part of a multiple daily injection regimen.



     Insulin initiation and intensification of glucose control  



 Intensification or rapid improvement in glucose control has been associated with a transitory, reversible ophthalmologic refraction disorder, worsening of diabetic retinopathy, and acute painful peripheral neuropathy. However, long-term glycemic control decreases the risk of diabetic retinopathy and neuropathy.



     Peripheral Edema  



 Insulin, including TOUJEO, may cause sodium retention and edema, particularly if previously poor metabolic control is improved by intensified insulin therapy.



     Lipodystrophy  



 Long-term use of insulin, including TOUJEO, can cause lipoatrophy (depression in the skin) or lipohypertrophy (enlargement or thickening of tissue) in some patients and may affect insulin absorption  [see  Dosage and Administration (2.1)  ].  



     Weight gain  



 Weight gain has occurred with some insulin therapies including TOUJEO and has been attributed to the anabolic effects of insulin and the decrease in glucosuria.



     Allergic Reactions  



 Some patients taking insulin therapy, including TOUJEO have experienced erythema, local edema, and pruritus at the site of injection. These conditions were usually self-limiting. Severe cases of generalized allergy (anaphylaxis) have been reported  [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ].  



     Cardiovascular Safety  



 No clinical studies to establish the cardiovascular safety of TOUJEO have been conducted. A cardiovascular outcomes trial, ORIGIN, has been conducted with LANTUS. It is unknown whether the results of ORIGIN can be applied to TOUJEO.



 The Outcome Reduction with Initial Glargine Intervention trial (i.e., ORIGIN) was an open-label, randomized, 12,537 patient study that compared LANTUS to standard care on the time to first occurrence of a major adverse cardiovascular event (MACE). MACE was defined as the composite of CV death, nonfatal myocardial infarction and nonfatal stroke. The incidence of MACE was similar between LANTUS and standard care in ORIGIN [Hazard Ratio (95% CI) for MACE; 1.02 (0.94, 1.11)].



 In the ORIGIN trial, the overall incidence of cancer (all types combined) [Hazard Ratio (95% CI); 0.99 (0.88, 1.11)] or death from cancer [Hazard Ratio (95% CI); 0.94 (0.77, 1.15)] was also similar between treatment groups.



   6.2 Immunogenicity

  As with all therapeutic proteins, there is potential for immunogenicity.



 In a 6-month study of type 1 diabetes patients, 79% of patients who received TOUJEO once daily were positive for anti-insulin antibodies (AIA) at least once during the study, including 62% that were positive at baseline and 44% of patients who developed anti-drug antibody [i.e., anti-insulin glargine antibody (ADA)] during the study. Eighty percent of the AIA positive patients on TOUJEO with antibody test at baseline, remained AIA positive at month 6.



 In two 6-month studies in type 2 diabetes patients, 25% of patients who received TOUJEO once daily were positive for AIA at least once during the study, including 42% who were positive at baseline and 20% of patients who developed ADA during the study. Ninety percent of the AIA positive patients on TOUJEO with antibody test at baseline, remained AIA positive at month 6.



 The detection of antibody formation is highly dependent on the sensitivity and specificity of the assay and may be influenced by several factors such as: assay methodology, sample handling, timing of sample collection, concomitant medication, and underlying disease. For these reasons, comparison of the incidence of antibodies to TOUJEO with the incidence of antibodies in other studies or to other products, may be misleading.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5. WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Never share a TOUJEO SoloStar  (r)  disposable prefilled pen between patients, even if the needle is changed (  5.1  ) 
 *   Hyper- or hypoglycemia with changes in insulin regimen: Carry out under close medical supervision. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Hypoglycemia : May be life-threatening. Increase frequency of glucose monitoring with changes to: insulin dosage, co-administered glucose lowering medications, meal pattern, physical activity; and in patients with renal impairment or hepatic impairment or hypoglycemia unawareness. (  5.3  ,  6.1  ) 
 *   Medication Errors: Accidental mix-ups between insulin products can occur. Instruct patients to check insulin labels before injection. (  5.4  ) 
 *   Hypersensitivity reactions: Severe, life-threatening, generalized allergy, including anaphylaxis, can occur. Discontinue TOUJEO, monitor and treat if indicated (  5.5  ,  6.1  ) 
 *   Hypokalemia: May be life-threatening. Monitor potassium levels in patients at risk of hypokalemia and treat if indicated (  5.6  ). 
 *   Fluid retention and heart failure with concomitant use of Thiazolidinediones (TZDs) : Observe for signs and symptoms of heart failure; consider dosage reduction or discontinuation if heart failure occurs (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Never Share a TOUJEO SoloStar pen Between Patients



  TOUJEO SoloStar disposable prefilled pens must never be shared between patients, even if the needle is changed. Pen sharing poses a risk for transmission of blood-borne pathogens.



    5.2 Hyperglycemia or Hypoglycemia with Changes in Insulin Regimen



  Changes in insulin strength, manufacturer, type, or method of administration may affect glycemic control and predispose to hypoglycemia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  or hyperglycemia. These changes should be made cautiously and only under close medical supervision, and the frequency of blood glucose monitoring should be increased. For patients with type 2 diabetes, dosage adjustments of concomitant oral anti-diabetic products may be needed.



 On a unit to unit basis, TOUJEO has a lower glucose lowering effect than LANTUS [See  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)  ]  . In clinical trials, patients who changed to TOUJEO from other basal insulins experienced higher average fasting plasma glucose levels in the first weeks of therapy compared to patients who were changed to LANTUS. To minimize the risk of hyperglycemia when initiating TOUJEO monitor glucose daily, titrate TOUJEO according to labeling instructions, and adjust co-administered glucose lowering therapies per standard of care [See  Dosage and Administration (2.2  ,  2.3)  ].  Higher doses of TOUJEO were required to achieve similar levels of glucose control compared to LANTUS in clinical trials [  see   Clinical Studies (14.1)  ].  



 The onset of action of TOUJEO develops over 6 hours following an injection. In type 1 diabetes patients treated with IV insulin, consider the longer onset of action of TOUJEO before stopping IV insulin .  The full glucose lowering effect may not be apparent for at least 5 days [See  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)  ]  .



    5.3 Hypoglycemia



  Hypoglycemia is the most common adverse reaction associated with insulin, including TOUJEO. Severe hypoglycemia can cause seizures, may be life-threatening or cause death. Hypoglycemia can impair concentration ability and reaction time; this may place an individual and others at risk in situations where these abilities are important (e.g., driving, or operating other machinery). Hypoglycemia can happen suddenly and symptoms may differ in each individual and change over time in the same individual. Symptomatic awareness of hypoglycemia may be less pronounced in patients with longstanding diabetes, in patients with diabetic nerve disease, in patients using medications that block the sympathetic nervous system (e.g., beta-blockers) [See  Drug Interactions (7)  ]  , or in patients who experience recurrent hypoglycemia.



    Risk Factors for Hypoglycemia  



 The timing of hypoglycemia usually reflects the time-action profile of the administered insulin formulation.



 As with all insulin preparations, the glucose lowering effect time course of TOUJEO may vary in different individuals or at different times in the same individual and depends on many conditions, including the area of injection as well as the injection site blood supply and temperature [  s ee  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)  ]  . Other factors which may increase the risk of hypoglycemia include changes in meal pattern (e.g., macronutrient content or timing of meals), changes in level of physical activity, or changes to co-administered medication [  s ee  Drug Interactions (7)  ]  . Patients with renal or hepatic impairment may be at higher risk of hypoglycemia [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.5  ,  8.6)  ]  .



    Risk Mitigation Strategies for Hypoglycemia  



 Patients and caregivers must be educated to recognize and manage hypoglycemia. Self-monitoring of blood glucose plays an essential role in the prevention and management of hypoglycemia. In patients at higher risk for hypoglycemia and patients who have reduced symptomatic awareness of hypoglycemia, increased frequency of blood glucose monitoring is recommended. To minimize the risk of hypoglycemia do not administer TOUJEO intravenously, intramuscularly or in an insulin pump or dilute or mix TOUJEO with any other insulin products or solutions.



    5.4 Medication Errors



  Accidental mix-ups between basal insulin products and other insulins, particularly rapid-acting insulins, have been reported. To avoid medication errors between TOUJEO and other insulins, instruct patients to always check the insulin label before each injection.



    5.5 Hypersensitivity and Allergic Reactions



  Severe, life-threatening, generalized allergy, including anaphylaxis, can occur with insulin products, including TOUJEO. If hypersensitivity reactions occur, discontinue TOUJEO; treat per standard of care and monitor until symptoms and signs resolve [See  Adverse Reactions (6)  ].  TOUJEO is contraindicated in patients who have had hypersensitivity reactions to insulin glargine or other of the excipients [See  Contraindications (4)  ].  



    5.6 Hypokalemia



  All insulin products, including TOUJEO, cause a shift in potassium from the extracellular to intracellular space, possibly leading to hypokalemia. Untreated hypokalemia may cause respiratory paralysis, ventricular arrhythmia, and death. Monitor potassium levels in patients at risk for hypokalemia if indicated (e.g., patients using potassium-lowering medications, patients taking medications sensitive to serum potassium concentrations).



    5.7 Fluid Retention and Heart Failure with Concomitant Use of PPAR-gamma Agonists



  Thiazolidinediones (TZDs), which are peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor (PPAR)-gamma agonists, can cause dose-related fluid retention, particularly when used in combination with insulin. Fluid retention may lead to or exacerbate heart failure. Patients treated with insulin, including TOUJEO, and a PPAR-gamma agonist should be observed for signs and symptoms of heart failure. If heart failure develops, it should be managed according to current standards of care, and discontinuation or dose reduction of the PPAR-gamma agonist must be considered.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
