<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tracleer" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6. ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following important adverse reactions are described elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Hepatotoxicity [see  Boxed Warning  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Fluid retention [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Common adverse reactions (&gt;=3% more than placebo) are respiratory tract infection and anemia (  6.1  ).  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Actelion at 1-866-228-3546 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Safety data on Tracleer were obtained from 13 clinical studies (9 placebo-controlled and 4 open-label) in 870 patients with pulmonary arterial hypertension and other diseases. Doses up to 8 times the currently recommended clinical dose (125 mg twice daily) were administered for a variety of durations. The exposure to Tracleer in these trials ranged from 1 day to 4.1 years (n=94 for 1 year; n=61 for 1.5 years and n=39 for more than 2 years). Exposure of pulmonary arterial hypertension patients (n=328) to Tracleer ranged from 1 day to 1.7 years (n=174 more than 6 months and n=28 more than 12 months).



 Treatment discontinuations due to adverse events other than those related to pulmonary hypertension during the clinical trials in patients with pulmonary arterial hypertension were more frequent on Tracleer (6%; 15/258 patients) than on placebo (3%; 5/172 patients). In this database the only cause of discontinuations &gt; 1% and occurring more often on Tracleer was abnormal liver function.



 The adverse drug events that occurred in &gt;=3% of the Tracleer-treated patients and were more common on Tracleer in placebo-controlled trials in pulmonary arterial hypertension at doses of 125 or 250 mg twice daily are shown in Table 2:



 Table 2. Adverse eventsNote: only AEs with onset from start of treatment to 1 calendar day after end of treatment are included. All reported events (at least 3%) are included except those too general to be informative, and those not reasonably associated with the use of the drug because they were associated with the condition being treated or are very common in the treated population.Combined data from Study 351, BREATHE-1 and EARLY occurring in &gt;=3% of patients treated with Tracleer 125-250 mg twice daily and more common on Tracleer in placebo-controlled studies in pulmonary arterial hypertension 
   Adverse Event               Tracleern = 258     Placebon = 172       
  
                                 No.                 %                   No.                 %                  
 Respiratory Tract Infection   56                  22%                 30                  17%                  
 Headache                      39                  15%                 25                  14%                  
 Edema                         28                  11%                 16                  9%                   
 Chest Pain                    13                  5%                  8                   5%                   
 Syncope                       12                  5%                  7                   4%                   
 Flushing                      10                  4%                  5                   3%                   
 Hypotension                   10                  4%                  3                   2%                   
 Sinusitis                     9                   4%                  4                   2%                   
 Arthralgia                    9                   4%                  3                   2%                   
 Serum Aminotransferases, abnormal  9                   4%                  3                   2%                   
 Palpitations                  9                   4%                  3                   2%                   
 Anemia                        8                   3%                  -                                        
               Decreased Sperm Counts  
 

 An open-label, single arm, multicenter, safety study evaluated the effect on testicular function of Tracleer 62.5 mg twice daily for 4 weeks, followed by 125 mg twice daily for 5 months. Twenty-five male patients with WHO functional class III and IV PAH and normal baseline sperm count were enrolled. Twenty-three completed the study and 2 discontinued due to adverse events not related to testicular function. There was a decline in sperm count of at least 50% in 25% of the patients after 3 or 6 months of treatment with Tracleer. Sperm count remained within the normal range in all 22 patients with data after 6 months and no changes in sperm morphology, sperm motility, or hormone levels were observed. One patient developed marked oligospermia at 3 months and the sperm count remained low with 2 follow-up measurements over the subsequent 6 weeks. Tracleer was discontinued and after 2 months the sperm count had returned to baseline levels. Based on these findings and preclinical data from endothelin receptor antagonists, it cannot be excluded that endothelin receptor antagonists such as Tracleer have an adverse effect on spermatogenesis.



     Decreases in Hemoglobin and Hematocrit  



 Treatment with Tracleer can cause a dose-related decrease in hemoglobin and hematocrit. It is recommended that hemoglobin concentrations be checked after 1 and 3 months, and every 3 months thereafter. If a marked decrease in hemoglobin concentration occurs, further evaluation should be undertaken to determine the cause and need for specific treatment.



 The overall mean decrease in hemoglobin concentration for Tracleer-treated patients was 0.9 g/dL (change to end of treatment). Most of this decrease of hemoglobin concentration was detected during the first few weeks of Tracleer treatment and hemoglobin levels stabilized by 4-12 weeks of Tracleer treatment. In placebo-controlled studies of all uses of Tracleer, marked decreases in hemoglobin (&gt; 15% decrease from baseline resulting in values &lt; 11 g/dL) were observed in 6% of Tracleer-treated patients and 3% of placebo-treated patients. In patients with PAH treated with doses of 125 and 250 mg twice daily, marked decreases in hemoglobin occurred in 3% compared to 1% in placebo-treated patients.



 A decrease in hemoglobin concentration by at least 1 g/dL was observed in 57% of Tracleer-treated patients as compared to 29% of placebo-treated patients. In 80% of those patients whose hemoglobin decreased by at least 1 g/dL, the decrease occurred during the first 6 weeks of Tracleer treatment.



 During the course of treatment the hemoglobin concentration remained within normal limits in 68% of Tracleer-treated patients compared to 76% of placebo patients. The explanation for the change in hemoglobin is not known, but it does not appear to be hemorrhage or hemolysis.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  There have been several postmarketing reports of angioedema associated with the use of Tracleer. The onset of the reported cases occurred within a range of 8 hours to 21 days after starting therapy. Some patients were treated with an antihistamine and their signs of angioedema resolved without discontinuing Tracleer.



 The following additional adverse reactions have been reported during the postapproval use of Tracleer. Because these adverse reactions are reported from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to Tracleer exposure:



 *     Unexplained hepatic cirrhosis [see  Boxed Warning  ]  
 *     Liver failure [see  Boxed Warning  ]  
 *     Hypersensitivity [see  Contraindications (4.4)  ]  
 *     Thrombocytopenia 
 *     Rash 
 *     Jaundice 
 *     Anemia requiring transfusion 
 *     Neutropenia and leukopenia 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING:  RISKS OF HEPATOTOXICITY and TERATOGENICITY

    WARNING:  RISKS OF HEPATOTOXICITY and TERATOGENICITY  

    Because of the risks of hepatotoxicity and birth defects, Tracleer is available only through a restricted program called the Tracleer Access Program (T.A.P.). T.A.P. is a component of the Tracleer Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS). Under the Tracleer REMS, prescribers, patients, and pharmacies must enroll in the program  . [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ].    



   Hepatotoxicity  



   In clinical studies, Tracleer caused at least 3-fold upper limit of normal (ULN) elevation of liver aminotransferases (ALT and AST) in about 11% of patients, accompanied by elevated bilirubin in a small number of cases. Because these changes are a marker for potential serious hepatotoxicity, serum aminotransferase levels must be measured prior to initiation of treatment and then monthly   [see   Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ,   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  . In the postmarketing period, in the setting of close monitoring, rare cases of unexplained hepatic cirrhosis were reported after prolonged (&gt; 12 months) therapy with Tracleer in patients with multiple comorbidities and drug therapies. There have also been reports of liver failure. The contribution of Tracleer in these cases could not be excluded.   



   In at least one case, the initial presentation (after &gt; 20 months of treatment) included pronounced elevations in aminotransferases and bilirubin levels accompanied by non-specific symptoms, all of which resolved slowly over time after discontinuation of Tracleer. This case reinforces the importance of strict adherence to the monthly monitoring schedule for the duration of treatment and the treatment algorithm, which includes stopping Tracleer with a rise of aminotransferases accompanied by signs or symptoms of liver dysfunction   [see   Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ]  .   



   Elevations in aminotransferases require close attention   [see   Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ]  . Tracleer should generally be avoided in patients with elevated aminotransferases (&gt; 3 * ULN) at baseline because monitoring for hepatotoxicity may be more difficult. If liver aminotransferase elevations are accompanied by clinical symptoms of hepatotoxicity (such as nausea, vomiting, fever, abdominal pain, jaundice, or unusual lethargy or fatigue) or increases in bilirubin &gt;= 2 * ULN, treatment with Tracleer should be stopped. There is no experience with the reintroduction of Tracleer in these circumstances.   



   Teratogenicity  



   Tracleer is likely to cause major birth defects if used by pregnant females based on animal data   [see   Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ]  . Therefore, pregnancy must be excluded before the start of treatment with Tracleer. Throughout treatment and for one month after stopping Tracleer, females of childbearing potential must use two reliable methods of contraception unless the patient has a tubal sterilization or Copper T 380A IUD or LNg 20 IUS inserted, in which case no other contraception is needed. Hormonal contraceptives, including oral, injectable, transdermal, and implantable contraceptives should not be used as the sole means of contraception because these may not be effective in patients receiving Tracleer   [see   Drug Interactions (7.2)  ]  . Obtain monthly pregnancy tests.  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING:  RISKS OF HEPATOTOXICITY and TERATOGENICITY



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



   Tracleer is available only through a restricted distribution program called the Tracleer Access Program (T.A.P.) because of these risks (  5.2  ):  



   Elevations of liver aminotransferases (ALT, AST) and liver failure have been reported with Tracleer (  5.1  ).  



 *  Measure liver aminotransferases prior to initiation of treatment and then monthly (5.1). 
 *  Discontinue Tracleer if aminotransferase elevations are accompanied by signs or symptoms of liver dysfunction or injury or increases in bilirubin &gt;=2 * ULN (2.2, 5.1). 
      Based on animal data, Tracleer is likely to cause major birth defects if used during pregnancy (  4.1  ,   8.1  ).  
 

 *  Must exclude pregnancy before and during treatment (4.1, 8.1). 
 *  To prevent pregnancy, females of childbearing potential must use two reliable forms of contraception during treatment and for one month after stopping Tracleer (4.1, 8.1). 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Pre-existing hepatic impairment: Avoid use in moderate and severe impairment (  5.3  ). 
 *  Fluid retention: May require intervention (  5.4  ). 
 *  Pulmonary veno-occlusive disease ( PVOD ) : If signs of pulmonary edema occur, consider the diagnosis of associated PVOD and consider discontinuing Tracleer (  5.5  ) 
 *  Decreased sperm counts (  5.6  ) 
 *  Decreases in hemoglobin and hematocrit: Monitor hemoglobin levels after 1 and 3 months of treatment, then every 3 months thereafter (  5.7  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Hepatotoxicity



  Elevations in ALT or AST by more than 3 * ULN were observed in 11% of Tracleer-treated patients (n = 658) compared to 2% of placebo-treated patients (n = 280). Three-fold increases were seen in 12% of 95 pulmonary arterial hypertension (PAH) patients on 125 mg twice daily and 14% of 70 PAH patients on 250 mg twice daily. Eight-fold increases were seen in 2% of PAH patients on 125 mg twice daily and 7% of PAH patients on 250 mg twice daily. Bilirubin increases to &gt;=3 * ULN were associated with aminotransferase increases in 2 of 658 (0.3%) of patients treated with Tracleer. The combination of hepatocellular injury (increases in aminotransferases of &gt; 3 * ULN) and increases in total bilirubin (&gt;= 2* ULN) is a marker for potential serious hepatotoxicity.



 Elevations of AST or ALT associated with Tracleer are dose-dependent, occur both early and late in treatment, usually progress slowly, are typically asymptomatic, and usually have been reversible after treatment interruption or cessation. Aminotransferase elevations also may reverse spontaneously while continuing treatment with Tracleer.



 Liver aminotransferase levels must be measured prior to initiation of treatment and then monthly and therapy adjusted accordingly [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ]  . Discontinue Tracleer if liver aminotransferase elevations are accompanied by clinical symptoms of hepatotoxicity (such as nausea, vomiting, fever, abdominal pain, jaundice, or unusual lethargy or fatigue) or increases in bilirubin &gt;= 2 * ULN.



    5.2 Prescribing and Distribution Program for Tracleer



   Because of the risks of hepatotoxicity and birth defects, Tracleer is available only through a restricted program called the Tracleer Access Program (T.A.P.) As a component of the Tracleer REMS, prescribers, patients, and pharmacies must enroll in the program . [see  Boxed Warning  and  Contraindications (4.1)  ]  .  



 Required components of the Tracleer REMS are:



 *  Healthcare professionals who prescribe Tracleer must review the prescriber educational materials, enroll in T.A.P. and comply with its requirements. 
 *  Healthcare professionals must (1) review serum aminotransferases (ALT/AST) and bilirubin, and agree to order and monitor these tests monthly; and (2) for females of childbearing potential, confirm that the patient is not pregnant, and agree to order and monitor pregnancy tests monthly. 
 *  To receive Tracleer, all patients must understand the risks and benefits, complete a patient enrollment form, and be re-enrolled annually by their prescriber. 
 *  Pharmacies that dispense Tracleer must enroll in the program and agree to comply with the T.A.P. requirements. 
    Further information about Tracleer and T.A.P. is available at www.tracleerrems.com or 1-866-228-3546.
 

    5.3 Patients with Pre-existing Hepatic Impairment



  Tracleer is not recommended in patients with moderate or severe liver impairment. In addition, initiation of Tracleer should generally be avoided in patients with elevated aminotransferases (&gt; 3 * ULN) prior to drug initiation because monitoring hepatotoxicity in these patients may be more difficult [see  Boxed Warning  ,  Dosage and Administration (2.5)    Use in Specific Populations (8.6)  ]  .



    5.4 Fluid Retention



  Peripheral edema is a known clinical consequence of PAH and worsening PAH and is also a known effect of Tracleer and other endothelin receptor antagonists. In PAH clinical trials with Tracleer, combined adverse events of fluid retention or edema were reported in 1.7 percent (placebo-corrected) of patients



 In addition, there have been numerous postmarketing reports of fluid retention in patients with pulmonary hypertension occurring within weeks after starting Tracleer. Patients required intervention with a diuretic, fluid management, or hospitalization for decompensating heart failure.



 If clinically significant fluid retention develops, with or without associated weight gain, further evaluation should be undertaken to determine the cause, such as Tracleer or underlying heart failure, and the possible need for treatment or discontinuation of Tracleer. [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  and  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]  .



    5.5 Pulmonary Veno-Occlusive Disease



  Should signs of pulmonary edema occur, consider the possibility of associated pulmonary veno-occlusive disease and consider whether Tracleer should be discontinued.



    5.6 Decreased Sperm Counts



   Decreased sperm counts have been observed in patients receiving Tracleer. Preclinical data also suggest that Tracleer, like other endothelin receptor antagonists, may have an adverse effect on spermatogenesis [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ,  Nonclinical Toxicology (13.1)  ].    



    5.7 Decreases in Hemoglobin and Hematocrit



   Treatment with Tracleer can cause a dose-related decrease in hemoglobin and hematocrit. There have been postmarketing reports of decreases in hemoglobin concentration and hematocrit that have resulted in anemia requiring transfusion. It is recommended that hemoglobin concentrations be checked after 1 and 3 months, and every 3 months thereafter. If a marked decrease in hemoglobin concentration occurs, further evaluation should be undertaken to determine the cause and need for specific treatment [see  Adverse Reactions 6.1  ]  .  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
