<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tramadol1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Table 2 reports the incidence rate of treatment-emergent adverse events over five days of Tramadol HCl 37.5 mg/Acetaminophen 325 mg use in clinical trials (subjects took an average of at least 6 tablets per day).



 Table 2: Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events (&gt;=2.0%) 
 Body System                                                                                              
   Preferred Term                                    Tramadol Hydrochloride 37.5 mg/Acetaminophen 325 mg (N=142)(%)   
  
   Gastrointestinal System Disorders                                                                      
   Constipation                                                              6                            
   Diarrhea                                                                  3                            
   Nausea                                                                    3                            
   Dry Mouth                                                                 2                            
   Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                  
   Somnolence                                                                6                            
   Anorexia                                                                  3                            
   Insomnia                                                                  2                            
   Central &amp; Peripheral Nervous System                                                                    
   Dizziness                                                                 3                            
   Skin and Appendages                                                                                    
   Sweating Increased                                                        4                            
   Pruritus                                                                  2                            
   Reproductive Disorders, Male                                                                           
   Prostatic Disorder                                                        2                            
          Incidence at least 1%, causal relationship at least possible or greater
   the following lists adverse reactions that occurred with an incidence of at least 1% in single-dose or repeated-dose clinical trials of Tramadol HCl 37.5 mg/Acetaminophen 325 mg.



   Body as a Whole -  Asthenia, fatigue, hot flushes



   Central and Peripheral Nervous System -  Dizziness, headache, tremor



   Gastrointestinal System -  Abdominal pain, constipation, diarrhea, dyspepsia, flatulence, dry mouth, nausea, vomiting



   Psychiatric Disorders -  Anorexia, anxiety, confusion, euphoria, insomnia, nervousness, somnolence



   Skin and Appendages -  Pruritus, rash, increased sweating



   Selected Adverse events occurring at less than 1%

  the following lists clinically relevant adverse reactions that occurred with an incidence of less than 1% in Tramadol HCl 37.5 mg/Acetaminophen 325 mg clinical trials.



   Body as a Whole -  Chest pain, rigors, syncope, withdrawal syndrome



   Cardiovascular Disorders -  Hypertension, aggravated hypertension, hypotension



   Central and Peripheral Nervous System -  Ataxia, convulsions, hypertonia, migraine, aggravated migraine, involuntary muscle contractions, paresthesias, stupor, vertigo



   Gastrointestinal System -  Dysphagia, melena, tongue edema



   Hearing and Vestibular Disorders -  Tinnitus



   Heart Rate and Rhythm Disorders -  Arrhythmia, palpitation, tachycardia



   Liver and Biliary System -  Hepatic function abnormal



   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders -  Weight decrease



   Psychiatric Disorders -  Amnesia, depersonalization, depression, drug abuse, emotional lability, hallucination, impotence, paroniria, abnormal thinking



   Red Blood Cell Disorders -  Anemia



   Respiratory System -  Dyspnea



   Urinary System -  Albuminuria, micturition disorder, oliguria, urinary retention



   Vision Disorders -  Abnormal vision



   Other clinically significant adverse experiences previously reported with tramadol hydrochloride:

  Other events which have been reported with the use of tramadol products and for which a causal association has not been determined include: vasodilation, orthostatic hypotension, myocardial ischemia, pulmonary edema, allergic reactions (including anaphylaxis and urticaria, Stevens-Johnson syndrome/TENS), cognitive dysfunction, difficulty concentrating, depression, suicidal tendency, hepatitis, liver failure, and gastrointestinal bleeding. Reported laboratory abnormalities included elevated creatinine and liver function tests. Serotonin syndrome (whose symptoms may include mental status change, hyperreflexia, fever, shivering, tremor, agitation, diaphoresis, seizures, and coma) has been reported with tramadol when used concomitantly with other serotonergic agents such as SSRIs and MAOIs.



   Other clinically significant adverse experiences previously reported with acetaminophen:

  Allergic reactions (primarily skin rash) or reports of hypersensitivity secondary to acetaminophen are rare and generally controlled by discontinuation of the drug and, when necessary, symptomatic treatment.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: HEPATOTOXICITY

  HEPATOTOXICITY

    Tramadol Hydrochloride 37.5 mg/Acetaminophen 325 mg tablets contains tramadol HCl and acetaminophen. Acetaminophen has been associated with cases of acute liver failure, at times resulting in liver transplant and death. Most of the cases of liver injury are associated with the use of acetaminophen at doses that exceed 4,000 milligrams per day, and often involve more than one acetaminophen-containing product (see   WARNINGS  ).  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
