<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="travatan" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reaction (30% to 50%) is conjunctival hyperemia.    (6.1)    



          



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Alcon Laboratories Inc. at 1-800-757-9195 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The most common adverse reaction observed in controlled clinical studies with TRAVATAN(r) (travoprost ophthalmic solution) 0.004% and TRAVATAN Z(r) (travoprost ophthalmic solution) 0.004% was ocular hyperemia which was reported in 30 to 50% of patients. Up to 3% of patients discontinued therapy due to conjunctival hyperemia. Ocular adverse reactions reported at an incidence of 5 to 10% in these clinical studies included decreased visual acuity, eye discomfort, foreign body sensation, pain and pruritus.



 Ocular adverse reactions reported at an incidence of 1 to 4% in clinical studies with TRAVATAN(r) or TRAVATAN Z(r) included abnormal vision, blepharitis, blurred vision, cataract, conjunctivitis, corneal staining, dry eye, iris discoloration, keratitis, lid margin crusting, ocular inflammation, photophobia, subconjunctival hemorrhage and tearing.



 Nonocular adverse reactions reported at an incidence of 1 to 5% in these clinical studies were allergy, angina pectoris, anxiety, arthritis, back pain, bradycardia, bronchitis, chest pain, cold/flu syndrome, depression, dyspepsia, gastrointestinal disorder, headache, hypercholesterolemia, hypertension, hypotension, infection, pain, prostate disorder, sinusitis, urinary incontinence and urinary tract infections.



 In postmarketing use with prostaglandin analogs, periorbital and lid changes including deepening of the eyelid sulcus have been observed.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  EXCERPT:   Pigmentation.



 Pigmentation of the iris, periorbital tissue (eyelid) and eyelashes can occur. Iris pigmentation likely to be permanent.   (5.1)    



      



 Eyelash Changes.



 Gradual change to eyelashes including increased length, thickness and number of lashes. Usually reversible.   (5.2)    



 



   5.1 Pigmentation



  Travoprost ophthalmic solution has been reported to cause changes to pigmented tissues. The most frequently reported changes have been increased pigmentation of the iris, periorbital tissue (eyelid) and eyelashes. Pigmentation is expected to increase as long as travoprost is administered. The pigmentation change is due to increased melanin content in the melanocytes rather than to an increase in the number of melanocytes. After discontinuation of travoprost, pigmentation of the iris is likely to be permanent, while pigmentation of the periorbital tissue and eyelash changes have been reported to be reversible in some patients. Patients who receive treatment should be informed of the possibility of increased pigmentation. The long term effects of increased pigmentation are not known.



 Iris color change may not be noticeable for several months to years. Typically, the brown pigmentation around the pupil spreads concentrically towards the periphery of the iris and the entire iris or parts of the iris become more brownish. Neither nevi nor freckles of the iris appear to be affected by treatment. While treatment with TRAVATAN Z   (r)    (travoprost ophthalmic solution) 0.004% can be continued in patients who develop noticeably increased iris pigmentation, these patients should be examined regularly. (see   PATIENT COUNSELING INFORMATION, 17.1    ).



    5.2 Eyelash Changes



  TRAVATAN Z   (r)    may gradually change eyelashes and vellus hair in the treated eye. These changes include increased length, thickness, and number of lashes. Eyelash changes are usually reversible upon discontinuation of treatment.



    5.3 Intraocular Inflammation



  TRAVATAN Z   (r)    should be used with caution in patients with active intraocular inflammation (e.g., uveitis) because the inflammation may be exacerbated.



    5.4 Macular Edema



  Macular edema, including cystoid macular edema, has been reported during treatment with travoprost ophthalmic solution. TRAVATAN Z   (r)    should be used with caution in aphakic patients, in pseudophakic patients with a torn posterior lens capsule, or in patients with known risk factors for macular edema.



    5.5 Angle-closure, Inflammatory or Neovascular Glaucoma



  TRAVATAN Z   (r)    has not been evaluated for the treatment of angle-closure, inflammatory or neovascular glaucoma.



    5.6 Bacterial Keratitis



  There have been reports of bacterial keratitis associated with the use of multiple-dose containers of topical ophthalmic products. These containers had been inadvertently contaminated by patients who, in most cases, had a concurrent corneal disease or a disruption of the ocular epithelial surface (see   PATIENT COUNSELING INFORMATION, 17.3    ).



    5.7 Use with Contact Lenses



  Contact lenses should be removed prior to instillation of TRAVATAN Z   (r)    and may be reinserted 15 minutes following its administration.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
