<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tresiba" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are also discussed elsewhere:



 *    Hypoglycemia [see Warnings and Precautions  (    5.3    )]  
 *    Hypersensitivity and allergic reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *    Hypokalemia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
      EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions commonly associated with TRESIBA are:
 

 *    hypoglycemia, allergic reactions, injection site reactions, lipodystrophy, pruritus, rash, edema and weight gain (  6.1  ). 
    To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novo Nordisk at 1-800-727-6500 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of TRESIBA was evaluated in nine treat to target trials of 6-12 months duration, conducted in subjects with type 1 diabetes or type 2 diabetes  [see Clinical Studies (  14  )].  



 The data in Table 1 reflect the exposure of 1102 patients with type 1 diabetes to TRESIBA with a mean exposure duration to TRESIBA of 34 weeks. The mean age was 43 years and 1% were older than 75 years. Fifty-seven percent were male, 81% were White, 2% were Black or African American and 4% were Hispanic. The mean body mass index (BMI) was 26 kg/m  2  . The mean duration of diabetes was 18 years and the mean HbA1cat baseline was 7.8%. A history of neuropathy, ophthalmopathy, nephropathy and cardiovascular disease at baseline was reported in 11%, 16%, 7% and 0.5% respectively. The mean eGFR at baseline was 87 mL/min/1.73 m  2  and 7% of the patients had an eGFR less than 60 mL/min/1.73 m  2  .



 The data in Table 2 reflect the exposure of 2713 patients with type 2 diabetes to TRESIBA with a mean exposure duration to TRESIBA of 36 weeks. The mean age was 58 years and 3% were older than 75 years. Fifty-eight percent were male, 71% were White, 7% were Black or African American and 13% were Hispanic. The mean BMI was 30 kg/m  2  . The mean duration of diabetes was 11 years and the mean HbA1cat baseline was 8.3%. A history of neuropathy, ophthalmopathy, nephropathy and cardiovascular disease at baseline was reported for 14%, 10%, 6% and 0.6% of participants respectively. At baseline, the mean eGFR was 83 mL/min/1.73 m  2  and 9% had an eGFR less than 60 mL/min/1.73 m  2  .



 Common adverse reactions (excluding hypoglycemia)    occurring in TRESIBA treated subjects during clinical trials in patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus and type 2 diabetes mellitus are listed in Table 1 and Table 2, respectively. Common adverse reactions were defined as reactions occurring in &gt;=5% of the population studied. Hypoglycemia is not shown in these tables but discussed in a dedicated subsection below.



   Table 1: Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=5% of TRESIBA-Treated Patients with Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus  




  Adverse Reaction                    TRESIBA  (n=1102)                  
  Nasopharyngitis                     23.9 %                             
  Upper respiratory tract infection    11.9 %                             
  Headache                            11.8 %                             
  Sinusitis                           5.1 %                              
  Gastroenteritis                     5.1 %                              
         
 

   Table 2: Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=5% of TRESIBA-Treated Patients with Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus  




  Adverse Reaction                    TRESIBA  (n=2713)                  
  Nasopharyngitis                     12.9 %                             
  Headache                            8.8 %                              
  Upper respiratory tract infection    8.4 %                              
  Diarrhea                            6.3 %                              
            Hypoglycemia    
 

 Hypoglycemia is the most commonly observed adverse reaction in patients using insulin, including TRESIBA  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  . The rates of reported hypoglycemia depend on the definition of hypoglycemia used, diabetes type, insulin dose, intensity of glucose control, background therapies, and other intrinsic and extrinsic patient factors. For these reasons, comparing rates of hypoglycemia in clinical trials for TRESIBA with the incidence of hypoglycemia for other products may be misleading and also, may not be representative of hypoglycemia rates that will occur in clinical practice.



 The percent of participants randomized to TRESIBA who experienced at least one episode of hypoglycemia in adult clinical trials  [see Clinical Studies (  14  )]  of patients with type 1 and type 2 diabetes respectively, are shown in Table 3 and 4  .  No clinically important differences in risk of hypoglycemia between TRESIBA and comparators was observed in clinical trials.



 Severe hypoglycemia was defined as an episode requiring assistance of another person to actively administer carbohydrate, glucagon, or other resuscitative actions. A Novo Nordisk hypoglycemia episode was defined as a severe hypoglycemia episode or an episode where a laboratory or a self-measured glucose calibrated to plasma was less than 56 mg/dL or where a whole blood glucose was less than 50 mg/dL (i.e., with or without the presence of hypoglycemic symptoms).



   Table 3: Percent (%) of Type 1 Diabetes Patients Experiencing at Least One Episode of Severe Hypoglycemia or Novo Nordisk Hypoglycemia  S  on TRESIBA in Adult Clinical Trials  




                    Study A    + insulin aspart    52 weeks      Study B    + insulin aspart    26 weeks      Study C    + insulin aspart    26 weeks     
                    TRESIBA    (N=472)      TRESIBA    (N=301)      TRESIBA at the same time each day    (N=165)      TRESIBA at alternating times    (N=164)     
  
  Severe hypoglycemia    
  Percent of patients    12.3%                 10.6%                12.7%    10.4%                
  Novo Nordisk hypoglycemiaS    
  Percent of patients    95.6%                 93.0%                99.4%    93.9%                
                S    Novo Nordisk hypoglycemia  :  a severe hypoglycemia episode or an episode where a laboratory or a self-measured glucose calibrated to plasma was less than 56 mg/dL or where a whole blood glucose was less than 50 mg/dL (i.e., with or without the presence of hypoglycemic symptoms).
 

   Table 4: Percent (%) of Patients with Type 2 Diabetes Experiencing at Least One Episode of Severe Hypoglycemia or Novo Nordisk Hypoglycemia  S  on TRESIBA in Adult Clinical Trials  




                Study D    + 1-2 OADs*    insulin naive    52 weeks      Study E    + 1-2 OAD*s    insulin naive    26 weeks      Study F    +/- 1-3 OADs*    insulin naive    26 weeks      Study G    T2DM +/- 0-3 OADs*    26 weeks      Study H    T2DM +/- 0-2    OADs* +    insulin aspart    26 weeks      Study I    T2DM +/- 1-2    OADs*    insulin naive    26 weeks     
                TRESIBA    (N=766)      TRESIBA    (N=228)      TRESIBA    (N=284)      TRESIBA    (N=226)      TRESIBA (alternating    time)    (N=230)      TRESIBA    (N=753)      TRESIBA    (N=226)     
  
  Severe Hypoglycemia    
  Percent of patients    0.3%           0              0                0.9%        0.4%        4.5%          0.4%            
  Novo Nordisk HypoglycemiaS    
  Percent of patients    46.5%          28.5%          50%              43.8%       50.9%       80.9%         42.5%           
              *OAD: oral antidiabetic agent,    S    Novo Nordisk hypoglycemia  :  a severe hypoglycemia episode or an episode where a laboratory or a self-measured glucose calibrated to plasma was less than 56 mg/dL or where a whole blood glucose was less than 50 mg/dL (i.e., with or without the presence of hypoglycemic symptoms).
 

     Allergic Reactions    



 Severe, life-threatening, generalized allergy, including anaphylaxis, generalized skin reactions, angioedema, bronchospasm, hypotension, and shock may occur with any insulin, including TRESIBA and may be life threatening  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.  5)]  . Hypersensitivity (manifested with swelling of tongue and lips, diarrhea, nausea, tiredness, and itching) and urticaria were reported in 0.9% of patients treated with TRESIBA.



     Lipodystrophy    



 Long-term use of insulin, including TRESIBA, can cause lipodystrophy at the site of repeated insulin injections. Lipodystrophy includes lipohypertrophy (thickening of adipose tissue) and lipoatrophy (thinning of adipose tissue) and may affect insulin absorption. Rotate insulin injection sites within the same region to reduce the risk of lipodystrophy  [see Dosage and Administration (  2.1  )]  . In the clinical program, lipodystrophy, lipohypertrophy, or lipoatrophy was reported in 0.3% of patients treated with TRESIBA.



     Injection Site Reactions    



 Patients taking TRESIBA may experience injection site reactions, including injection site hematoma, pain, hemorrhage, erythema, nodules, swelling, discoloration, pruritus, warmth, and injection site mass. In the clinical program, injection site reactions occurred in 3.8% of patients treated with TRESIBA.



     Weight Gain    



 Weight gain can occur with insulin therapy, including TRESIBA, and has been attributed to the anabolic effects of insulin. In the clinical program after 52 weeks of treatment, patients with type 1 diabetes treated with TRESIBA gained an average of 1.8 kg and patients with type 2 diabetes treated with TRESIBA gained an average of 3.0 kg.



     Peripheral Edema    



 Insulin, including TRESIBA, may cause sodium retention and edema. In the clinical program, peripheral edema occurred in 0.9% of patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus and 3.0% of patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus treated with TRESIBA.



   6.2 Immunogenicity

  As with all therapeutic proteins, insulin administration may cause anti-insulin antibodies to form. The detection of antibody formation is highly dependent on the sensitivity and specificity of the assay and may be influenced by several factors such as: assay methodology, sample handling, timing of sample collection, concomitant medication, and underlying disease. For these reasons, comparison of the incidence of antibodies to TRESIBA with the incidence of antibodies in other studies or to other products, may be misleading.



 In studies of type 1 diabetes patients, 95.9% of patients who received TRESIBA once daily were positive for anti-insulin antibodies (AIA) at least once during the studies, including 89.7% that were positive at baseline. In studies of type 2 diabetes patients, 31.5% of patients who received TRESIBA once daily were positive for AIA at least once during the studies, including 14.5% that were positive at baseline. The antibody incidence rates for type 2 diabetes may be underreported due to potential assay interference by endogenous insulin in samples in these patients. The presence of antibodies that affect clinical efficacy may necessitate dose adjustments to correct for tendencies toward hyper or hypoglycemia.



 The incidence of anti-insulin degludec antibodies has not been established.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *     Never share a TRESIBA FlexTouch pen between patients, even if the needle is changed (  5.1  ). 
 *     Hyper- or hypoglycemia with changes in insulin regimen: Carry out under close medical supervision and increase frequency of blood glucose monitoring (  5.2  ). 
 *     Hypoglycemia : May be life-threatening. Increase monitoring with changes to: insulin dosage, co-administered glucose lowering medications, meal pattern, physical activity; and in patients with renal impairment or hepatic impairment or hypoglycemia unawareness (  5.3  ,  5.4  ,  6.1  ). 
 *     Hypoglycemia due to medication errors: Accidental mix-ups between insulin products can occur. Instruct patients to check insulin labels before injection. DO NOT transfer TRESIBA into a syringe for administration as overdosage and severe hypoglycemia can result (  5.4  ). 
 *     Hypersensitivity reactions : Severe, life-threatening, generalized allergy, including anaphylaxis, can occur. Discontinue TRESIBA, monitor and treat if indicated (  5.5  ). 
 *     Hypokalemia: May be life-threatening. Monitor potassium levels in patients at risk for hypokalemia and treat if indicated (  5.6  ). 
 *     Fluid retention and heart failure with concomitant use of Thiazolidinediones (TZDs): Observe for signs and symptoms of heart failure; consider dosage reduction or discontinuation if heart failure occurs (  5.7  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Never Share a TRESIBA FlexTouch Pen Between Patients



  TRESIBA FlexTouch disposable prefilled pens should never be shared between patients, even if the needle is changed. Sharing poses a risk for transmission of blood-borne pathogens.



    5.2 Hyperglycemia or Hypoglycemia with Changes in Insulin Regimen



  Changes in insulin, manufacturer, type, or method of administration may affect glycemic control and predispose to hypoglycemia or hyperglycemia. These changes should be made cautiously and only under medical supervision and the frequency of blood glucose monitoring should be increased. For patients with type 2 diabetes, adjustments in concomitant oral anti-diabetic treatment may be needed. When converting from other insulin therapies to TRESIBA follow dosing recommendations [see Dosage and Administration (  2.4  )]  .



    5.3 Hypoglycemia



  Hypoglycemia is the most common adverse reaction of insulin, including TRESIBA [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )].  Severe hypoglycemia can cause seizures, may be life-threatening or cause death. Hypoglycemia can impair concentration ability and reaction time; this may place an individual and others at risk in situations where these abilities are important (e.g., driving or operating other machinery). TRESIBA, or any insulin, should not be used during episodes of hypoglycemia [see Contraindications (  4  )].  



 Hypoglycemia can happen suddenly and symptoms may differ in each individual and change over time in the same individual. Symptomatic awareness of hypoglycemia may be less pronounced in patients with longstanding diabetes, in patients with diabetic nerve disease, in patients using medications that block the sympathetic nervous system (e.g., beta-blockers) [see Drug Interactions (  7  )],  or in patients who experience recurrent hypoglycemia.



  Risk Factors for Hypoglycemia  



 The risk of hypoglycemia generally increases with intensity of glycemic control. The risk of hypoglycemia after an injection is related to the duration of action of the insulin [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  )]  and, in general, is highest when the glucose lowering effect of the insulin is maximal. As with all insulin preparations, the glucose lowering effect time course of TRESIBA may vary among different individuals or at different times in the same individual and depends on many conditions, including the area of injection as well as the injection site blood supply and temperature.



 Other factors which may increase the risk of hypoglycemia include changes in meal pattern (e.g., macronutrient content or timing of meals), changes in level of physical activity, or changes to co-administered medication [see Drug Interactions (  7  )]  . Patients with renal or hepatic impairment may be at higher risk of hypoglycemia [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.6  ,  8.7  )]  .



  Risk Mitigation Strategies for Hypoglycemia  



 Patients and caregivers must be educated to recognize and manage hypoglycemia. Self-monitoring of blood glucose plays an essential role in the prevention and management of hypoglycemia. In patients at higher risk for hypoglycemia and patients who have reduced symptomatic awareness of hypoglycemia, increased frequency of blood glucose monitoring is recommended.



    5.4 Hypoglycemia Due to Medication Errors



  Accidental mix-ups between basal insulin products and other insulins, particularly rapid-acting insulins, have been reported. To avoid medication errors between TRESIBA and other insulins, instruct patients to always check the insulin label before each injection.



 Do not transfer TRESIBA from the TRESIBA pen to a syringe. The markings on the insulin syringe will not measure the dose correctly and can result in overdosage and severe hypoglycemia [see Dosage and Administration   (  2.1  ) and Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  .



    5.5 Hypersensitivity and Allergic Reactions



  Severe, life-threatening, generalized allergy, including anaphylaxis, can occur with insulin products, including TRESIBA. If hypersensitivity reactions occur, discontinue TRESIBA; treat per standard of care and monitor until symptoms and signs resolve. TRESIBA is contraindicated in patients who have had hypersensitivity reactions to insulin degludec or one of the excipients [see Contraindications (  4  )].  



    5.6 Hypokalemia



  All insulin products, including TRESIBA, cause a shift in potassium from the extracellular to intracellular space, possibly leading to hypokalemia. Untreated hypokalemia may cause respiratory paralysis, ventricular arrhythmia, and death. Monitor potassium levels in patients at risk for hypokalemia if indicated (e.g., patients using potassium-lowering medications, patients taking medications sensitive to serum potassium concentrations).



    5.7 Fluid Retention and Congestive Heart Failure with Concomitant Use of a PPAR Gamma Agonist



  Thiazolidinediones (TZDs), which are peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor (PPAR)-gamma agonists can cause dose related fluid retention, particularly when used in combination with insulin. Fluid retention may lead to or exacerbate congestive heart failure. Patients treated with insulin, including TRESIBA and a PPAR-gamma agonist should be observed for signs and symptoms of congestive heart failure. If congestive heart failure develops, it should be managed according to current standards of care and discontinuation or dose reduction of the PPAR-gamma agonist must be considered.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
