<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="treximet" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are described below and elsewhere in labeling:



 *  Myocardial Ischemia/Infarction, Stroke, Prinzmetal's Angina [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Gastrointestinal effects [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Arrhythmias [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Chest, throat, neck, and/or jaw pain/tightness/pressure [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Cerebrovascular events [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Other vasospasm reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)    
 *  Increase in blood pressure [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
 *  Congestive heart failure and edema [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]  
 *  Medication overuse headache [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)    
 *  Serotonin syndrome [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  
 *  Renal Toxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.11)  ]  
 *  Anaphylactic reactions [see  Contraindications (4)  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.12)  ]  
 *  Serious skin reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.13)  ]  
 *  Hepatotoxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.15)  ]  
 *  Hematological toxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.16)  ]  
 *  Exacerbation Asthma Related to Aspirin Sensitivity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.17)  ]  
 *  Seizures [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.18)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=2%) were:
 

 *  Adults: Dizziness, somnolence, nausea, chest discomfort/chest pain, neck/throat/jaw pain/tightness/pressure, paresthesia, dyspepsia, dry mouth. (  6.1  ) 
 *  Pediatrics: Hot flush (i.e., hot flash[es]) and muscle tightness. (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pernix Therapeutics at 1-800-793-2145 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Adults  



 The adverse reactions reported below are specific to the clinical trials with TREXIMET 85/500 mg. See also the full prescribing information for naproxen and sumatriptan products.



 Table 1 lists adverse reactions that occurred in 2 placebo-controlled clinical trials (Study 1 and 2) in adult patients who received 1 dose of study drug. Only adverse reactions that occurred at a frequency of 2% or more in any group treated with TREXIMET 85/500 mg and that occurred at a frequency greater than the placebo group are included in Table 1.



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions in Pooled Placebo-Controlled Trials in Adult Patients with Migraine 
 Adverse Reactions                                         
 TREXIMET85/500 mg%(n = 737)         Placebo%(n = 752)    Sumatriptan85 mg%(n = 735)  Naproxen Sodium500 mg%(n = 732)   
  
 Nervous system disorders                                                                                       
   Dizziness                                 4                  2                2                  2           
   Somnolence                                3                  2                2                  2           
   Paresthesia                               2                 &lt;1                2                 &lt;1           
 Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                                     
   Nausea                                    3                  1                3                 &lt;1           
   Dyspepsia                                 2                  1                2                  1           
   Dry mouth                                 2                  1                2                 &lt;1           
 Pain and other pressure sensations                                                                              
   Chest discomfort/chest pain               3                 &lt;1                2                  1           
   Neck/throat/jaw pain/tightness/pressure           3                  1                3                  1           
           The incidence of adverse reactions in controlled clinical trials was not affected by gender or age of the patients. There were insufficient data to assess the impact of race on the incidence of adverse reactions.
 

     Pediatric Patients 12 to 17 Years of Age  



 In a placebo-controlled clinical trial that evaluated pediatric patients 12 to 17 years of age who received 1 dose of TREXIMET 10/60 mg, 30/180 mg, or 85/500 mg, adverse reactions occurred in 13% of patients who received 10/60 mg, 9% of patients who received 30/180 mg, 13% who received 85/500 mg, and 8% who received placebo. No patients who received TREXIMET experienced adverse reactions leading to withdrawal from the trial. The incidence of adverse reactions in pediatric patients 12 to 17 years of age was comparable across all 3 doses compared with placebo. Table 2 lists adverse reactions that occurred in a placebo-controlled trial in pediatric patients 12 to 17 years of age at a frequency of 2% or more with TREXIMET and were more frequent than the placebo group.



 Table 2. Adverse Reactions in a Placebo-Controlled Trial in Pediatric Patients 12 to 17 Years of Age with Migraine 
 Adverse Reactions                                        
 TREXIMET 10/60 mg%                    TREXIMET 30/180 mg%  TREXIMET 85/500 mg%      Placebo%       
 (n = 96)                                  (n = 97)         (n = 152)         (n = 145)       
  
 Vascular                                                                                                       
   Hot flush (i.e., hot flash[es])            0                 2                 &lt;1                0           
 Musculoskeletal                                                                                                
   Muscle tightness                           0                 0                 2                 0           
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL RISKS

  WARNING: CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL RISKS

    *  Cardiovascular Risk: Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) cause an increased risk of serious cardiovascular thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. This risk may increase with duration of use. Patients with cardiovascular disease or risk factors for cardiovascular disease may be at greater risk [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  Gastrointestinal Risk: NSAIDs cause an increased risk of serious gastrointestinal adverse events including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach or intestines, which can be fatal. These events can occur at any time during use and without warning symptoms. Elderly patients are at greater risk for serious gastrointestinal events [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]. 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING: CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL RISKS  
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) cause an increased risk of serious cardiovascular thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. This risk may increase with duration of use. Patients with cardiovascular disease or risk factors for cardiovascular disease may be at greater risk. (5.1) 
 *  NSAIDs cause an increased risk of serious gastrointestinal adverse events including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach or intestines, which can be fatal. These events can occur at any time during use and without warning symptoms. Elderly patients are at greater risk for serious gastrointestinal events. (5.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Myocardial ischemia/infarction, stroke, Prinzmetal's angina: Perform cardiac evaluation in patients with cardiovascular risk factors. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Arrhythmias: Discontinue TREXIMET if occurs. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Chest/throat/neck/jaw pain, tightness, pressure, or heaviness: Generally not associated with myocardial ischemia; evaluate for coronary artery disease in patients at high risk. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Cerebral hemorrhage, subarachnoid hemorrhage, and stroke: Discontinue TREXIMET if occurs. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Gastrointestinal ischemic reactions and peripheral vasospastic reactions: Discontinue TREXIMET if occurs. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Hypertension: Monitor blood pressure. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Heart failure and edema: Use with caution in patients with fluid retention or heart failure. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Medication overuse headache: Detoxification may be necessary (  5.9  ) 
 *  Serotonin syndrome: Discontinue TREXIMET if occurs. (  5.10  ) 
 *  Renal papillary necrosis and other renal injury with long-term use: Discontinue TREXIMET if occurs. (  5.11  ) 
 *  Anaphylactic reactions: TREXIMET should not be given to patients with the aspirin triad. (  5.12  ) 
 *  Serious skin reactions: Discontinue TREXIMET at first sign of rash. (  5.13  ) 
 *  Elevated liver enzymes and severe hepatic reactions: Discontinue use immediately if abnormal liver enzymes persist or worsen. (  5.15  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Myocardial Ischemia, Myocardial Infarction, Stroke, Prinzmetal's Angina



  The use of TREXIMET is contraindicated in patients with ischemic or vasospastic coronary artery disease (CAD) or with a history of CABG surgery due to increased risk of serious cardiovascular events with sumatriptan and NSAIDS [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  .



    Cardiovascular Events With Sumatriptan  



 There have been rare reports of serious cardiac adverse reactions, including acute myocardial infarction, occurring within a few hours following administration of sumatriptan. Some of these reactions occurred in patients without known CAD. TREXIMET may cause coronary artery vasospasm (Prinzmetal's angina), even in patients without a history of CAD.



    Cardiovascular Events With Nonsteroidal Anti-inflammatory Drugs  



 Clinical trials of several COX-2 selective and nonselective NSAIDs of up to three years' duration have shown an increased risk of serious cardiovascular thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. All NSAIDs, both COX-2 selective and nonselective, may have a similar risk. Patients with known cardiovascular disease or risk factors for cardiovascular disease may be at greater risk. To minimize the potential risk for an adverse cardiovascular event in patients treated with an NSAID, the lowest effective dose should be used for the shortest duration possible.



 There is no consistent evidence that concurrent use of aspirin mitigates the increased risk of serious cardiovascular thrombotic events associated with NSAID use. The concurrent use of aspirin and an NSAID does increase the risk of serious gastrointestinal events [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  .



 Perform a cardiovascular evaluation in patients who have multiple cardiovascular risk factors (e.g., increased age, diabetes, hypertension, smoking, obesity, strong family history of CAD) prior to receiving TREXIMET. If there is evidence of CAD or coronary artery vasospasm, TREXIMET is contraindicated. For patients with multiple cardiovascular risk factors who have a negative cardiovascular evaluation, consider administering the first dose of TREXIMET in a medically supervised setting and performing an electrocardiogram (ECG) immediately following administration of TREXIMET. For such patients, consider periodic cardiovascular evaluation in intermittent long-term users of TREXIMET.



 Physicians and patients should remain alert for the development of cardiovascular events, even in the absence of previous cardiovascular symptoms. Patients should be informed about the signs and/or symptoms of serious cardiovascular events and the steps to take if they occur.



    Premarketing Experience with TREXIMET  



 Among 3,302 adult patients with migraine who received TREXIMET in premarketing controlled and uncontrolled clinical trials, a 47-year-old female with cardiac risk factors in an open-label 12-month safety trial experienced signs and symptoms of acute coronary syndrome approximately 2 hours after receiving TREXIMET.



    5.2 Gastrointestinal Bleeding, Ulceration, and Perforation



  NSAIDs, including naproxen, a component of TREXIMET cause serious gastrointestinal adverse events including inflammation, bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach, small intestine, or large intestine, which can be fatal. These serious adverse events can occur at any time, with or without warning symptoms, in patients treated with NSAIDs. Only 1 in 5 patients who develop a serious upper gastrointestinal adverse event on NSAID therapy is symptomatic. Upper gastrointestinal ulcers, gross bleeding, or perforation caused by NSAIDs appear to occur in approximately 1% of patients treated daily for 3 to 6 months and in about 2% to 4% of patients treated for 1 year. However, even short-term therapy is not without risk.



 Among 3,302 adult patients with migraine who received TREXIMET in controlled and uncontrolled clinical trials, 1 patient experienced a recurrence of gastric ulcer after taking 8 doses over 3 weeks, and 1 patient developed a gastric ulcer after treating an average of 8 attacks per month over 7 months.



 TREXIMET should be prescribed with extreme caution in those with a prior history of ulcer disease or gastrointestinal bleeding. Patients with a prior history of peptic ulcer disease and/or gastrointestinal bleeding who use NSAIDs have a greater than 10-fold increased risk for developing gastrointestinal bleeding compared with patients with neither of these risk factors. Other factors that increase the risk for gastrointestinal bleeding in patients treated with NSAIDs include concomitant use of oral corticosteroids or anticoagulants or antiplatelets (including low-dose aspirin), longer duration of NSAID therapy, smoking, use of alcohol, older age, and poor general health status. Most postmarketing reports of fatal gastrointestinal events occurred in elderly or debilitated patients, and therefore special care should be taken in treating this population.



 To minimize the potential risk for an adverse gastrointestinal event in NSAID-treated patients, the lowest effective dose should be used for the shortest possible duration. Patients and physicians should remain alert for signs and symptoms of gastrointestinal ulceration and bleeding during NSAID therapy and promptly initiate additional evaluation and treatment if a serious gastrointestinal adverse event is suspected. This should include discontinuation of the NSAID until a serious gastrointestinal adverse event is ruled out. For high-risk patients, alternate therapies that do not involve NSAIDs should be considered.



    5.3 Arrhythmias



  Life-threatening disturbances of cardiac rhythm, including ventricular tachycardia and ventricular fibrillation leading to death, have been reported within a few hours following the administration of 5-HT1agonists. Discontinue TREXIMET if these disturbances occur. TREXIMET is contraindicated in patients with Wolff-Parkinson-White syndrome or arrhythmias associated with other cardiac accessory conduction pathway disorders.



    5.4 Chest, Throat, Neck, and/or Jaw Pain/Tightness/Pressure



  Sensations of tightness, pain, pressure, and heaviness in the precordium, throat, neck, and jaw commonly occur after treatment with sumatriptan and are usually non-cardiac in origin. However, perform a cardiac evaluation if these patients are at high cardiac risk. The use of TREXIMET is contraindicated in patients with CAD and those with Prinzmetal's variant angina.



    5.5 Cerebrovascular Events



  Cerebral hemorrhage, subarachnoid hemorrhage, and stroke have occurred in patients treated with 5-HT1agonists, and some have resulted in fatalities. In a number of cases, it appears possible that the cerebrovascular events were primary, the 5-HT1agonist having been administered in the incorrect belief that the symptoms experienced were a consequence of migraine when they were not. Also, patients with migraine may be at increased risk of certain cerebrovascular events (e.g., stroke, hemorrhage, TIA). Discontinue TREXIMET if a cerebrovascular event occurs.



 Before treating headaches in patients not previously diagnosed as migraineurs, and in migraineurs who present with atypical symptoms, exclude other potentially serious neurological conditions. TREXIMET is contraindicated in patients with a history of stroke or TIA [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  .



    5.6 Other Vasospasm Reactions



  Sumatriptan may cause non-coronary vasospastic reactions, such as peripheral vascular ischemia, gastrointestinal vascular ischemia and infarction (presenting with abdominal pain and bloody diarrhea), splenic infarction, and Raynaud's syndrome. In patients who experience symptoms or signs suggestive of non-coronary vasospasm reaction following the use of any 5-HT1agonist, rule out a vasospastic reaction before receiving additional TREXIMET.



 Reports of transient and permanent blindness and significant partial vision loss have been reported with the use of 5-HT1agonists. Since visual disorders may be part of a migraine attack, a causal relationship between these events and the use of 5-HT1agonists have not been clearly established.



    5.7 Hypertension



  Significant elevation in blood pressure, including hypertensive crisis with acute impairment of organ systems, has been reported on rare occasions in patients treated with 5-HT1agonists, including patients without a history of hypertension.



 NSAIDs, including naproxen, a component of TREXIMET, can lead to onset of new hypertension or worsening of preexisting hypertension, either of which may contribute to the increased incidence of cardiovascular events. Patients taking thiazides or loop diuretics may have impaired response to these therapies when taking NSAIDs.



 Monitor blood pressure in patients treated with TREXIMET. TREXIMET is contraindicated in patients with uncontrolled hypertension [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  .



    5.8 Heart Failure and Edema



  Fluid retention, edema, and peripheral edema have been observed in some patients taking NSAIDs. Since each TREXIMET 85/500 mg tablet contains approximately 60 mg of sodium and each TREXIMET 10/60 mg tablet contains approximately 20 mg of sodium, this should be considered in patients whose overall intake of sodium must be severely restricted. TREXIMET should be used with caution in patients with fluid retention or heart failure.



    5.9 Medication Overuse Headache



  Overuse of acute migraine drugs (e.g., ergotamine, triptans, opioids, or a combination of these drugs for 10 or more days per month) may lead to exacerbation of headache (medication overuse headache). Medication overuse headache may present as migraine-like daily headaches, or as a marked increase in frequency of migraine attacks. Detoxification of patients, including withdrawal of the overused drugs, and treatment of withdrawal symptoms (which often includes a transient worsening of headache) may be necessary.



    5.10 Serotonin Syndrome



  Serotonin syndrome may occur with TREXIMET, particularly during coadministration with selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs), serotonin norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs), tricyclic antidepressants (TCAs), and MAO inhibitors [see  Drug Interactions (7.6)  ]  . Serotonin syndrome symptoms may include mental status changes (e.g., agitation, hallucinations, coma), autonomic instability (e.g., tachycardia, labile blood pressure, hyperthermia), neuromuscular aberrations (e.g., hyperreflexia, incoordination), and/or gastrointestinal symptoms (e.g., nausea, vomiting, diarrhea). The onset of symptoms usually occurs within minutes to hours of receiving a new or a greater dose of a serotonergic medication. Discontinue TREXIMET if serotonin syndrome is suspected.



    5.11 Renal Toxicity



  Long-term administration of NSAIDs has resulted in renal papillary necrosis and other renal injury. Renal toxicity has also been seen in patients in whom renal prostaglandins have a compensatory role in the maintenance of renal perfusion. In these patients administration of an NSAID may cause a dose-dependent reduction in prostaglandin formation and, secondarily, in renal blood flow, which may precipitate overt renal decompensation. Patients at greatest risk of this reaction are those with impaired renal function, hypovolemia, heart failure, liver dysfunction, salt depletion, those taking diuretics and angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors, and the elderly. Discontinuation of NSAID therapy is usually followed by recovery to the pretreatment state.



 TREXIMET should be discontinued if clinical signs and symptoms consistent with renal disease develop or if systemic manifestations occur.



 TREXIMET is not recommended for use in patients with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance [CrCl] &lt;30 mL/min) [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.6)  ,  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  . Monitor renal function in patients with mild (CrCl = 60 to 89 mL/min) or moderate (CrCl = 30 to 59 mL/min) renal impairment, preexisting kidney disease, or dehydration.



    5.12 Anaphylactic Reactions



  Anaphylactic reactions may occur in patients without known prior exposure to either component of TREXIMET. Such reactions can be life-threatening or fatal. In general, anaphylactic reactions to drugs are more likely to occur in individuals with a history of sensitivity to multiple allergens. TREXIMET is contraindicated in patients with a history of hypersensitivity reaction to sumatriptan, naproxen, or any other component of TREXIMET [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  .



 TREXIMET should not be given to patients with the aspirin triad. This symptom complex typically occurs in patients with asthma who experience rhinitis with or without nasal polyps, or who exhibit severe, potentially fatal bronchospasm after taking aspirin or other NSAIDs [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  .



    5.13 Serious Skin Reactions



  NSAID-containing products can cause serious adverse events such as exfoliative dermatitis, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and toxic epidermal necrolysis, which can be fatal. These serious events may occur without warning. Patients should be informed about the signs and symptoms of serious skin manifestations and use of the drug should be discontinued at the first appearance of skin rash or any other sign of hypersensitivity.



    5.14 Pregnancy



  TREXIMET should not be used during the third trimester of pregnancy because NSAID-containing products have been shown to cause premature closure of the ductus arteriosus [see  Contraindications (4)  ,  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ]  .



    5.15 Hepatotoxicity



  Borderline elevations of 1 or more liver tests may occur in up to 15% of patients who take NSAIDs including naproxen, a component of TREXIMET. Hepatic abnormalities may be the result of hypersensitivity rather than direct toxicity. These abnormalities may progress, may remain essentially unchanged, or may be transient with continued therapy. Notable (3 times the upper limit of normal) elevations of SGPT (ALT) or SGOT (AST) have been reported in approximately 1% of patients in clinical trials with NSAIDs. In addition, cases of severe hepatic reactions, including jaundice and fatal fulminant hepatitis, liver necrosis, and hepatic failure, some of them with fatal outcomes, have been reported with NSAIDs.



 TREXIMET is contraindicated in patients with severe hepatic impairment [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.7)  ,  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  . A patient with symptoms and/or signs suggesting liver dysfunction, or in whom an abnormal liver test has occurred, should be evaluated for evidence of the development of a more severe hepatic reaction while on therapy with TREXIMET. TREXIMET should be discontinued if clinical signs and symptoms consistent with liver disease develop, if systemic manifestations occur (e.g., eosinophilia, rash), or if abnormal liver tests persist or worsen.



    5.16 Hematologic Toxicity



  Anemia is sometimes seen in patients receiving NSAIDs. This may be due to fluid retention, occult or gross gastrointestinal blood loss, or an incompletely described effect upon erythropoiesis. Patients on long-term treatment with NSAIDs, including TREXIMET, should have their hemoglobin or hematocrit checked if they exhibit any signs or symptoms of anemia.



 NSAID-containing products inhibit platelet aggregation and have been shown to prolong bleeding time in some patients. Unlike aspirin, their effect on platelet function is quantitatively less, of shorter duration, and reversible. Patients receiving TREXIMET who may be adversely affected by alterations in platelet function, such as those with coagulation disorders or patients receiving anticoagulants, should be carefully monitored.



    5.17 Exacerbation of Asthma Related to Aspirin Sensitivity



  Patients with asthma may have aspirin-sensitive asthma. The use of aspirin in patients with aspirin-sensitive asthma has been associated with severe bronchospasm that can be fatal. Since cross reactivity, including bronchospasm, between aspirin and other NSAIDs has been reported in such aspirin-sensitive patients, TREXIMET should not be administered to patients with this form of aspirin sensitivity and should be used with caution in patients with preexisting asthma [see  Contraindications (4)  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.12)  ].  



    5.18 Seizures



  Seizures have been reported following administration of sumatriptan. Some have occurred in patients with either a history of seizures or concurrent conditions predisposing to seizures. There are also reports in patients where no such predisposing factors are apparent. TREXIMET should be used with caution in patients with a history of epilepsy or conditions associated with a lowered seizure threshold.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
