<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="triamterene" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Side effects observed in association with the use of triamterene and hydrochlorothiazide tablets, other combination products containing triamterene/hydrochlorothiazide, and products containing triamterene or hydrochlorothiazide include the following:



   Gastrointestinal:  jaundice (intrahepatic cholestatic jaundice), pancreatitis, nausea, appetite disturbance, taste alteration, vomiting, diarrhea, constipation, anorexia, gastric irritation, cramping.



   Central Nervous System:  drowsiness and fatigue, insomnia, headache, dizziness, dry mouth, depression, anxiety, vertigo, restlessness, paresthesias.



   Cardiovascular:  tachycardia, shortness of breath and chest pain, orthostatic hypotension (may be aggravated by alcohol, barbiturates or narcotics).



   Renal:  acute renal failure, acute interstitial nephritis, renal stones composed of triamterene in association with other calculus materials, urine discoloration.



   Hematologic:  leukopenia, agranulocytosis, thrombocytopenia, aplastic anemia, hemolytic anemia and megaloblastosis.



   Ophthalmic:  xanthopsia, transient blurred vision.



   Hypersensitivity:  anaphylaxis, photosensitivity, rash, urticaria, purpura, necrotizing angiitis (vasculitis, cutaneous vasculitis), fever, respiratory distress including pneumonitis.



   Other:  muscle cramps and weakness, decreased sexual performance and sialadenitis.



 Whenever adverse reactions are moderate to severe, therapy should be reduced or withdrawn.



  



   Altered Laboratory Findings

      Serum Electrolytes:    hyperkalemia, hypokalemia, hyponatremia, hypomagnesemia, hypochloremia (see  WARNINGS  and  PRECAUTIONS  ).



     Creatinine, Blood Urea Nitrogen:    Reversible elevations in BUN and serum creatinine have been observed in hypertensive patients treated with triamterene and hydrochlorothiazide.



     Glucose:    hyperglycemia, glycosuria and diabetes mellitus (see  PRECAUTIONS  ).



     Serum Uric Acid, PBI and Calcium:    (see  PRECAUTIONS  ).



     Other:    Elevated liver enzymes have been reported in patients receiving triamterene and hydrochlorothiazide.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
