<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="triazolam" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  During placebo-controlled clinical studies in which 1,003 patients received triazolam tablets, the most troublesome side effects were extensions of the pharmacologic activity of triazolam, eg, drowsiness, dizziness, or light-headedness.



 The figures cited below are estimates of untoward clinical event incidence among subjects who participated in the relatively short duration (i.e., 1 to 42 days) placebo-controlled clinical trials of triazolam. The figures cannot be used to predict precisely the incidence of untoward events in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors often differ from those in clinical trials. These figures cannot be compared with those obtained from other clinical studies involving related drug products and placebo, as each group of drug trials is conducted under a different set of conditions.



 Comparison of the cited figures, however, can provide the prescriber with some basis for estimating the relative contributions of drug and nondrug factors to the untoward event incidence rate in the population studied. Even this use must be approached cautiously, as a drug may relieve a symptom in one patient while inducing it in others. (For example, an anticholinergic, anxiolytic drug may relieve dry mouth [a sign of anxiety] in some subjects but induce it [an untoward event] in others.)




                                                             Triazolam                   PLACEBO            
 Number of Patients                                            1003                        997              
 % Patients Reporting:                                                                                      
  
   Central Nervous System                                                                                   
 Drowsiness                                                    14.0                        6.4              
 Headache                                                       9.7                        8.4              
 Dizziness                                                      7.8                        3.1              
 Nervousness                                                    5.2                        4.5              
 Light-headedness                                               4.9                        0.9              
 Coordination disorders/ataxia                                  4.6                        0.8              
   Gastrointestinal                                                                                         
 Nausea/vomiting                                                4.6                        3.7              
         In addition to the relatively common (i.e., 1% or greater) untoward events enumerated above, the following adverse events have been reported less frequently (i.e., 0.9% to0.5%): euphoria, tachycardia, tiredness, confusional states/memory impairment, cramps/pain, depression, visual disturbances.
 

 Rare (i.e., less than 0.5%) adverse reactions included constipation, taste alterations, diarrhea, dry mouth, dermatitis/allergy, dreaming/nightmares, insomnia, paresthesia, tinnitus, dysesthesia, weakness, congestion, death from hepatic failure in a patient also receiving diuretic drugs.



 In addition to these untoward events for which estimates of incidence are available, the following adverse events have been reported in association with the use of triazolam and other benzodiazepines: amnestic symptoms (anterograde amnesia with appropriate or inappropriate behavior), confusional states (disorientation, derealization, depersonalization, and/or clouding of consciousness), dystonia, anorexia, fatigue, sedation, slurred speech, jaundice, pruritus, dysarthria, changes in libido, menstrual irregularities, incontinence, and urinary retention. Other factors may contribute to some of these reactions, eg, concomitant intake of alcohol or other drugs, sleep deprivation, an abnormal premorbid state, etc.



 Other events reported include: paradoxical reactions such as stimulation, mania, an agitational state (restlessness, irritability, and excitation), increased muscle spasticity, sleep disturbances, hallucinations, delusions, aggressiveness, falling, somnambulism, syncope, inappropriate behavior and other adverse behavioral effects. Should these occur, use of the drug should be discontinued.



 The following events have also been reported: chest pain, burning tongue/glossitis/stomatitis.



 Laboratory analyses were performed on all patients participating in the clinical program for triazolam. The following incidences of abnormalities were observed in patients receiving triazolam and the corresponding placebo group. None of these changes were considered to be of physiological significance.




                                       Triazolam           PLACEBO        
 Number of Patients                       380                361          
 % of Patients Reporting:                 Low               High                Low               High          
  
   Hematology                                                                                                   
 Hematocrit                                                                                                     
 Hemoglobin                                                                                                     
 Total WBC count                          1.7                2.1                                   1.3          
 Neutrophil count                         1.5                1.5                3.3                1.0          
 Lymphocyte count                         2.3                4.0                3.1                3.8          
 Monocyte count                           3.6                                   4.4                1.5          
 Eosinophil count                        10.2                3.2                9.8                3.4          
 Basophil count                           1.7                2.1                                   1.8          
   Urinalysis                                                                                                   
 Albumin                                   -                 1.1                 -                              
 Sugar                                     -                                     -                              
 RBC/HPF                                   -                 2.9                 -                 2.9          
 WBC/HPF                                   -                11.7                 -                 7.9          
   Blood chemistry                                                                                              
 Creatinine                               2.4                1.9                3.6                1.5          
 Bilirubin                                                   1.5                1.0                             
 SGOT                                                        5.3                                   4.5          
 Alkaline phosphatase                                        2.2                                   2.6          
           When treatment with triazolam is protracted, periodic blood counts, urinalysis, and blood chemistry analyses are advisable.
 

 Minor changes in EEG patterns, usually low-voltage fast activity, have been observed in patients during therapy with triazolam and are of no known significance.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: MEDICATION GUIDE

  MEDICATION GUIDE

    TRIAZOLAM Tablets/ C-IV  



 Read this Medication Guide before you start taking triazolam and each time you get a refill. There may be new information. This Medication Guide does not take the place of talking to your doctor about your medical condition or treatment. You and your doctor should talk about the SEDATIVE-HYPNOTIC when you start taking it and at regular checkups. 




                                                                                                        
         What is the most important information I should know about triazolam?  
 

   After taking a SEDATIVE-HYPNOTIC, you may get up out of bed while not being fully awake and do an activity that you do not know you are doing. The next morning, you may not remember that you did anything during the night.   You have a higher chance for doing these activities if you drink alcohol or take other medicines that make you sleepy with a SEDATIVE-HYPNOTIC. Reported activities include:



 *  driving a car ("sleep-driving") 
 *  making and eating food 
 *  talking on the phone 
 *  having sex 
 *  sleep-walking 
      Important:  
 

 *  1.Take triazolam exactly as prescribedDo not take more triazolam than prescribed.Take triazolam right before you get in bed, not sooner. 
 *  2.Do not take triazolam if you:drink alcohol take other medicines that can make you sleepy. Talk to your doctor about all of your medicines. Your doctor will tell you if you can take triazolam with your other medicines cannot get a full night's sleep are pregnant or considering becoming pregnant 
 *  3.Call your doctor right away if you find out that you have done any of the above activities after taking triazolam. 
  
                                                                                                        
         What are SEDATIVE-HYPNOTICS?  
 

 SEDATIVE-HYPNOTICs are sleep medicines. SEDATIVE-HYPNOTICS are used in adults for the treatment of the symptom of trouble falling asleep due to insomnia. 



 Triazolam is not indicated for use in children.



 Elderly patients are especially susceptible to dose related adverse effects when taking triazolam.



   

    Triazolam is a federally controlled substance (C-IV) because it can be abused or lead to dependence. Keep triazolam in a safe place to prevent misuse and abuse. Selling or giving away triazolam may harm others, and is against the law. Tell your doctor if you have ever abused or been dependent on alcohol, prescription medicines or street drugs.  



   

    Who should not take triazolam?  



 Do not take triazolam if you are allergic to anything in it. See the end of this Medication Guide for a complete list of ingredients in triazolam.



   SEDATIVE-HYPNOTICS may not be right for you. Before starting SEDATIVE-HYPNOTICS, tell your doctor about all of your health conditions, including if you:  



 *  have a history of depression, mental illness, or suicidal thoughts 
 *  have a history of drug or alcohol abuse or addiction 
 *  have kidney or liver disease 
 *  have a lung disease or breathing problems 
 *  are pregnant, planning to become pregnant, or breastfeeding 
    Tell your doctor about all of the medicines you take including prescription and nonprescription medicines, vitamins and herbal supplements. Medicines can interact, sometimes causing side effects.    Do not take SEDATIVE-HYPNOTICS with other medicines that can make you sleepy.   
 

 Know the medicines you take. Keep a list of your medicines with you to show your doctor and pharmacist each time you get a new medicine.



 Triazolam should not be taken with some drugs including ketoconazole, itraconazole, nefazodone, ritonavir, indinavir, nelfinavir, saquinavir or lopinavir.



   How should I take triazolam?  



 *  Take triazolam exactly as prescribed. Do not take more triazolam than prescribed for you. 
 *  Take triazolam right before you get into bed. Or you can take the triazolam after you have been in bed and have trouble falling asleep. 
 *  Do not take triazolam with or right after a meal. 
 *  Do not take triazolam unless you are able to get a full night's sleep before you must be active again. 
 *  Call your healthcare provider if your insomnia worsens or is not better within 7 to 10 days. This may mean that there is another condition causing your sleep problem. 
 *  If you take too much triazolam or overdose, call your doctor or poison control center right away, or get emergency treatment. 
      What are the possible side effects of SEDATIVE-HYPNOTICS?  
 

   Serious side effects of SEDATIVE-HYPNOTICS include:  



 *  getting out of bed while not being fully awake and doing an activity that you do not know you are doing. (See "What is the most important information I should know about SEDATIVE-HYPNOTICS?) 
 *  abnormal thoughts and behavior. Symptoms include more outgoing or aggressive behavior than normal, confusion, agitation, hallucinations, worsening of depression, and suicidal thoughts or actions. 
 *  memory loss, including "traveler's amnesia" 
 *  anxiety 
 *  severe allergic reactions. Symptoms include swelling of the tongue or throat, trouble breathing, and nausea and vomiting. Get emergency medical help if you get these symptoms after taking SEDATIVE-HYPNOTICS. 
      Call your doctor right away if you have any of the above side effects or any other side effects that worry you while using the SEDATIVE-HYPNOTIC.  
 

   Common side effects of triazolam include:  



 *  drowsiness 
 *  headache 
 *  dizziness 
 *  lightheadedness 
 *  "pins and needles" feelings on your skin 
 *  difficulty with coordination 
 *  You may still feel drowsy the next day after taking triazolam. Do not drive or do other dangerous activities (including operating machinery) after taking triazolam until you feel fully awake. 
 *  You may have withdrawal symptoms for 1 to 2 days when you stop taking the SEDATIVE-HYPNOTIC suddenly. Withdrawal symptoms include trouble sleeping, unpleasant feelings, stomach and muscle cramps, vomiting, sweating, shakiness, and seizures. 
    These are not all the side effects of SEDATIVE-HYPNOTICS. Ask your doctor or pharmacist for more information.
 

 Call your doctor for medical advice about side effects. You may report side effects to FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088.



   How should I store triazolam?  



 *  Store triazolam at room temperature between 68 degrees  and 77 degrees  F (20o to 25oC). 
 *  Protect from light. 
 *  Keep triazolam and all medicines out of the reach of children. 
 *  Do not use triazolam after the expiration date on the bottle. 
      General Information about SEDATIVE-HYPNOTICS  
 

 *  Medicines are sometimes prescribed for purposes not mentioned in a Medication Guide. 
 *  Do not use the SEDATIVE-HYPNOTIC for a condition for which it was not prescribed. 
 *  Do not give the SEDATIVE-HYPNOTIC to other people, even if they have the same condition. It may harm them and it is against the law. 
    This Medication Guide summarizes the most important information about triazolam. If you would like more information, talk with your doctor. You can ask your doctor or pharmacist for information about triazolam that was written for healthcare professionals.
 

 If you would like more information, contact 1-800-438-1985



   What are the ingredients in triazolam?  



   Active Ingredient:   Triazolam



   Inactive Ingredients:  0.125 mg tablet: cellulose, corn starch, docusate sodium, lactose, magnesium stearate, silicon dioxide, sodium benzoate, 0.25 mg tablet: cellulose, corn starch, docusate sodium, FD&amp;C Blue No. 2, lactose, magnesium stearate, silicon dioxide, sodium benzoate.  



 Distributed by: Greenstone LLC



 This Medication Guide has been approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration. August  2014



 This product's label may have been updated. For current full prescribing information, please visit www.greenstonellc.com



 



 LAB-0260-9.0



 August 2014
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
