<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tribenzor" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=2%) are dizziness, peripheral edema, headache, fatigue, nasopharyngitis, muscle spasms, nausea, upper respiratory tract infection, diarrhea, urinary tract infection, and joint swelling (  6.1  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Daiichi Sankyo, Inc. at 1-877-437-7763 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Tribenzor  In the controlled trial of Tribenzor, patients were randomized to Tribenzor (olmesartan medoxomil/amlodipine/hydrochlorothiazide 40/10/25 mg), olmesartan medoxomil/amlodipine 40/10 mg, olmesartan medoxomil/hydrochlorothiazide 40/25 mg, or amlodipine/hydrochlorothiazide 10/25 mg. Subjects who received triple combination therapy were treated between two and four weeks with one of the three dual combination therapies. Safety data from this study were obtained in 574 patients with hypertension who received Tribenzor for 8 weeks.



 The frequency of adverse reactions was similar between men and women, patients &lt;65 years of age and patients &gt;=65 years of age, patients with and without diabetes, and Black and non-Black patients. Discontinuations because of adverse events occurred in 4% of patients treated with Tribenzor 40/10/25 mg compared to 1% of patients treated with olmesartan medoxomil/amlodipine 40/10 mg, 2% of patients treated with olmesartan medoxomil/hydrochlorothiazide 40/25 mg, and 2% of patients treated with amlodipine/hydrochlorothiazide 10/25 mg. The most common reason for discontinuation with Tribenzor was dizziness (1%).



 Dizziness was one of the most frequently reported adverse reactions with incidence of 1.4% to 3.6% in subjects continuing on dual combination therapy compared to 5.8% to 8.9% in subjects who switched to Tribenzor.



 The other most frequent adverse reactions that occurred in at least 2% of subjects are presented in the table below:



   Table 1  




 Adverse Reaction           OM40/AML10/HCTZ25 mg(N = 574)n (%)  OM40/AML10 mg(N = 596)n (%)  OM40/HCTZ25mg(N = 580)n (%)  AML10/HCTZ25 mg(N = 552)n (%)   
 Edema peripheral           44 (7.7)                   42 (7.0)                   6 (1.0)                    46 (8.3)                    
 Headache                   37 (6.4)                   42 (7.0)                   38 (6.6)                   33 (6.0)                    
 Fatigue                    24 (4.2)                   34 (5.7)                   31 (5.3)                   36 (6.5)                    
 Nasopharyngitis            20 (3.5)                   11 (1.8)                   20 (3.4)                   16 (2.9)                    
 Muscle spasms              18 (3.1)                   12 (2.0)                   14 (2.4)                   13 (2.4)                    
 Nausea                     17 (3.0)                   12 (2.0)                   22 (3.8)                   12 (2.2)                    
 Upper respiratory tract infection  16 (2.8)                   26 (4.4)                   18 (3.1)                   14 (2.5)                    
 Diarrhea                   15 (2.6)                   14 (2.3)                   12 (2.1)                   9 (1.6)                     
 Urinary tract infection    14 (2.4)                   8 (1.3)                    6 (1.0)                    7 (1.3)                     
 Joint swelling             12 (2.1)                   17 (2.9)                   2 (0.3)                    16 (2.9)                    
      Syncope was reported by 1% of Tribenzor subjects compared to 0.5% or less for the other treatment groups.
 

   Olmesartan medoxomil  Olmesartan medoxomil has been evaluated for safety in more than 3825 patients/subjects, including more than 3275 patients treated for hypertension in controlled trials. This experience included about 900 patients treated for at least 6 months and more than 525 treated for at least 1 year. Treatment with olmesartan medoxomil was well tolerated, with an incidence of adverse reactions similar to that seen with placebo. Adverse reactions were generally mild, transient, and without relationship to the dose of olmesartan medoxomil.



   Amlodipine  Amlodipine has been evaluated for safety in more than 11,000 patients in U.S. and foreign clinical trials.



 The following adverse reactions occurred in &lt;1% but &gt;0.1% of patients in controlled clinical trials under conditions of open trials or marketing experience where a causal relationship is uncertain; they are listed to alert physicians to a possible relationship:  Cardiovascular:  arrhythmia (including ventricular tachycardia and atrial fibrillation), bradycardia, chest pain, hypotension, peripheral ischemia, syncope, tachycardia, postural dizziness, postural hypotension, vasculitis  Central and Peripheral Nervous System:  hypoesthesia, neuropathy peripheral, paresthesia, tremor, vertigo  Gastrointestinal:  anorexia, constipation, dyspepsia*, dysphagia, diarrhea, flatulence, pancreatitis, vomiting, gingival hyperplasia  General:  allergic reaction, asthenia*, back pain, hot flushes, malaise, pain, rigors, weight gain, weight decrease  Musculoskeletal System:  arthralgia, arthrosis, muscle cramps*, myalgia  Psychiatric:  sexual dysfunction (male* and female), insomnia, nervousness, depression, abnormal dreams, anxiety, depersonalization  Respiratory:  dyspnea*, epistaxis  Skin and Appendages:  angioedema, erythema multiforme, pruritus*, rash*, rash erythematous, rash maculopapular  Special Senses:  abnormal vision, conjunctivitis, diplopia, eye pain, tinnitus  Urinary System:  micturition frequency, micturition disorder, nocturia  Autonomic Nervous System:  dry mouth, sweating increased  Metabolic and Nutritional:  hyperglycemia, thirst  Hemopoietic:  leukopenia, purpura, thrombocytopenia* = events that occurred in less than 1% in placebo-controlled trials, but the incidence of these side effects was between 1% and 2% in all multiple dose studies.



 The following adverse reactions occurred in &lt;0.1% of patients: cardiac failure, pulse irregularity, extrasystoles, skin discoloration, urticaria, skin dryness, alopecia, dermatitis, muscle weakness, twitching, ataxia, hypertonia, migraine, cold and clammy skin, apathy, agitation, amnesia, gastritis, increased appetite, loose stools, coughing, rhinitis, dysuria, polyuria, parosmia, taste perversion, abnormal visual accommodation, and xerophthalmia.



   Hydrochlorothiazide  Other adverse reactions that have been reported with hydrochlorothiazide, without regard to causality, are listed below:  Body as a Whole:  weakness  Digestive:  pancreatitis, jaundice (intrahepatic cholestatic jaundice), sialadenitis, cramping, gastric irritation  Hematologic:  aplastic anemia, agranulocytosis, leukopenia, hemolytic anemia, thrombocytopenia  Hypersensitivity:  purpura, photosensitivity, urticaria, necrotizing angiitis (vasculitis and cutaneous vasculitis), fever, respiratory distress including pneumonitis and pulmonary edema, anaphylactic reactions  Metabolic:  hyperglycemia, glycosuria, hyperuricemia  Musculoskeletal:  muscle spasm  Nervous System/Psychiatric:  restlessness  Renal:  renal failure, renal dysfunction, interstitial nephritis  Skin:  erythema multiforme including Stevens-Johnson syndrome, exfoliative dermatitis including toxic epidermal necrolysis  Special Senses:  transient blurred vision, xanthopsia



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of the individual components of Tribenzor. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Olmesartan medoxomil.  The following adverse reactions have been reported in post marketing experience:  Body as a Whole:  asthenia, angioedema, anaphylactic reactions, peripheral edema  Gastrointestinal:  vomiting, diarrhea, sprue-like enteropathy [  see Warnings and Precautions (  5.10  )  ]  Musculoskeletal:  rhabdomyolysis  Urogenital System:  acute renal failure  Skin and Appendages:  alopecia, pruritus, urticaria



 Data from one controlled trial and an epidemiologic study have suggested that high-dose olmesartan may increase cardiovascular (CV) risk in diabetic patients, but the overall data are not conclusive. The randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind ROADMAP trial (Randomized Olmesartan And Diabetes MicroAlbuminuria Prevention trial, n=4447) examined the use of olmesartan, 40 mg daily, vs. placebo in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus, normoalbuminuria, and at least one additional risk factor for CV disease. The trial met its primary endpoint, delayed onset of microalbuminuria, but olmesartan had no beneficial effect on decline in glomerular filtration rate (GFR). There was a finding of increased CV mortality (adjudicated sudden cardiac death, fatal myocardial infarction, fatal stroke, revascularization death) in the olmesartan group compared to the placebo group (15 olmesartan vs. 3 placebo, HR 4.9, 95% confidence interval [CI], 1.4, 17), but the risk of non-fatal myocardial infarction was lower with olmesartan (HR 0.64, 95% CI 0.35, 1.18).



 The epidemiologic study included patients 65 years and older with overall exposure of &gt; 300,000 patient-years. In the sub-group of diabetic patients receiving high-dose olmesartan (40 mg/d) for &gt; 6 months, there appeared to be an increased risk of death (HR 2.0, 95% CI 1.1, 3.8) compared to similar patients taking other angiotensin receptor blockers. In contrast, high-dose olmesartan use in non-diabetic patients appeared to be associated with a decreased risk of death (HR 0.46, 95% CI 0.24, 0.86) compared to similar patients taking other angiotensin receptor blockers. No differences were observed between the groups receiving lower doses of olmesartan compared to other angiotensin blockers or those receiving therapy for &lt; 6 months.



 Overall, these data raise a concern of a possible increased CV risk associated with the use of high-dose olmesartan in diabetic patients. There are, however, concerns with the credibility of the finding of increased CV risk, notably the observation in the large epidemiologic study for a survival benefit in non-diabetics of a magnitude similar to the adverse finding in diabetics.



   Amlodipine.  The following post-marketing event has been reported infrequently where a causal relationship is uncertain: gynecomastia. In post-marketing experience, jaundice and hepatic enzyme elevations (mostly consistent with cholestasis or hepatitis), in some cases severe enough to require hospitalization, have been reported in association with use of amlodipine.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY

  WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY

    *  When pregnancy is detected, discontinue Tribenzor as soon as possible. (5.1) 
 *  Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus. (5.1) 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY    See full prescribing information for   complete boxed warning  .  
 

 *  When pregnancy is detected, discontinue Tribenzor as soon as possible (5.1). 
 *  Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus (5.1). 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Avoid fetal or neonatal exposure (  5.1  ) 
 *  Hypotension in volume- or salt-depleted patients with treatment initiation may occur. Correct volume-depletion prior to administration. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Increased angina or myocardial infarction with calcium channel blockers may occur upon dosage initiation or increase (  5.3  ). 
 *  Avoid in patients with severely impaired renal function (creatinine clearance &lt;=30 mL/min) (  2  ,  5.4  ). 
 *  Withhold or discontinue Tribenzor if progressive renal impairment becomes evident (  5.4  ). 
 *  Thiazides should be used with caution in patients with mildly to moderately impaired hepatic function or progressive liver disease. Avoid in patients with severely impaired hepatic function (  5.5  ). 
 *  Observe for signs of fluid or electrolyte imbalance (  5.6  ). 
 *  Thiazide diuretics may cause an exacerbation or activation of systemic lupus erythematosus (  5.8  ). 
 *  Thiazides have been associated with acute angle-closure glaucoma (  5.9  ) 
 *  Sprue-like enteropathy has been reported.  Consider discontinuation of Tribenzor in cases where no other etiology is found (  5.10  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Fetal toxicity



   Pregnancy Category D  



 Use of drugs that act on the renin-angiotensin system during the second and third trimesters of pregnancy reduces fetal renal function and increases fetal and neonatal morbidity and death. Resulting oligohydramnios can be associated with fetal lung hypoplasia and skeletal deformations. Potential neonatal adverse effects include skull hypoplasia, anuria, hypotension, renal failure, and death. When pregnancy is detected, discontinue Tribenzor as soon as possible [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  )]  .



    5.2 Hypotension in Volume- or Salt-Depleted Patients



   Olmesartan medoxomil.  Symptomatic hypotension may be anticipated after initiation of treatment with olmesartan medoxomil. Patients with an activated renin-angiotensin system, such as volume- and/or salt-depleted patients (e.g., those being treated with high doses of diuretics) may be particularly vulnerable. Initiate treatment with Tribenzor under close medical supervision. If hypotension does occur, place the patient in the supine position and, if necessary, give an intravenous infusion of normal saline. A transient hypotensive response is not a contraindication to further treatment, which usually can be continued without difficulty once the blood pressure has stabilized.



    5.3 Increased Angina and/or Myocardial Infarction



   Amlodipine.  Patients, particularly those with severe obstructive coronary artery disease, may develop increased frequency, duration, or severity of angina or acute myocardial infarction upon starting calcium channel blocker therapy or at the time of dosage increase. The mechanism of this effect has not been elucidated.



    5.4 Impaired Renal Function



   Tribenzor.  Tribenzor has not been studied in patients with impaired renal function. Avoid use in patients with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance &lt;=30 ml/min) [see Dosage and Administration (  2  )]  .



 An adverse event of impaired renal function was reported in 2.1% of subjects receiving Tribenzor compared to 0.2% to 1.3% of subjects receiving dual combination therapy.



 If progressive renal impairment becomes evident consider withholding or discontinuing either diuretic or angiotensin receptor blocker therapies.



  Olmesartan medoxomil.  Changes in renal function occur in some individuals treated with olmesartan medoxomil as a consequence of inhibiting the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system. In patients whose renal function may depend upon the activity of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (e.g., patients with severe congestive heart failure), treatment with ACE inhibitors and angiotensin receptor antagonists has been associated with oliguria or progressive azotemia and (rarely) with acute renal failure and/or death. Similar effects may occur in patients treated with Tribenzor due to the olmesartan medoxomil component [see Drug Interactions (  7.2  ) and Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  .



 In studies of ACE inhibitors in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, increases in serum creatinine or blood urea nitrogen (BUN) have been reported. There has been no long-term use of olmesartan medoxomil in patients with unilateral or bilateral renal artery stenosis, but similar effects would be expected with Tribenzor because of the olmesartan medoxomil component.



  Hydrochlorothiazide.  Thiazides may precipitate azotemia in patients with renal disease. Cumulative effects of the drug may develop in patients with impaired renal function.



    5.5 Hepatic Impairment



   Amlodipine.  Amlodipine is extensively metabolized by the liver and the plasma elimination half-life (t1/2) is 56 hours in patients with severely impaired hepatic function [see Dosage and Administration (  2  )]  .



  Hydrochlorothiazide.  Minor alterations of fluid and electrolyte balance may precipitate hepatic coma.



    5.6 Electrolyte and Metabolic Imbalances



   Hydrochlorothiazide.  Perform periodic determinations of serum electrolytes to detect possible electrolyte imbalance. Observe patients receiving thiazide therapy for clinical signs of fluid or electrolyte imbalance: hyponatremia, hypochloremic alkalosis, and hypokalemia. Serum and urine electrolyte determinations are important when the patient is vomiting excessively or receiving parental fluids. Warning signs or symptoms of fluid and electrolyte imbalance, irrespective of cause, include dryness of mouth, thirst, weakness, lethargy, drowsiness, restlessness, confusion, seizures, muscle pains or cramps, muscular fatigue, hypotension, oliguria, tachycardia, and gastrointestinal disturbances such as nausea and vomiting.



 Hypokalemia may develop, especially during brisk diuresis, when severe cirrhosis is present, or after prolonged therapy.



 Interference with adequate oral electrolyte intake will also contribute to hypokalemia. Hypokalemia may cause cardiac arrhythmia and may also sensitize or exaggerate the response of the heart to the toxic effects of digitalis (e.g., increased ventricular irritability).



 Metabolic acidosis may occur. Although a chloride deficit in a particular patient is generally mild and usually does not require specific treatment, except under extraordinary circumstances (as in liver disease or renal disease), chloride replacement may be required in the treatment of metabolic alkalosis.



 Dilutional hyponatremia may occur in edematous patients in hot weather; appropriate therapy is water restriction, rather than administration of salt, except in rare instances when the hyponatremia is life-threatening. In actual salt depletion, appropriate replacement is the therapy of choice.



 Hyperuricemia may occur or frank gout may be precipitated in certain patients receiving thiazide therapy.



 In diabetic patients dosage adjustments of insulin or oral hypoglycemic agents may be required. Hyperglycemia may occur with thiazide diuretics. Thus, latent diabetes mellitus may become manifest during thiazide therapy.



 The antihypertensive effects of the drug may be enhanced in the post-sympathectomy patient.



 Thiazides have been shown to increase the urinary excretion of magnesium; this may result in hypomagnesemia.



 Thiazides may decrease urinary calcium excretion. Thiazides may cause intermittent and slight elevation of serum calcium in the absence of known disorders of calcium metabolism. Marked hypercalcemia may be evidence of hyperparathyroidism. Tribenzor should be discontinued before carrying out tests for parathyroid function.



    5.7 Hypersensitivity Reaction



   Hydrochlorothiazide.  Hypersensitivity reactions to hydrochlorothiazide may occur in patients with or without a history of allergy or bronchial asthma, but are more likely in patients with such a history.



    5.8 Systemic Lupus Erythematosus



   Hydrochlorothiazide.  Thiazide diuretics have been reported to cause exacerbation or activation of systemic lupus erythematosus.



    5.9 Acute Myopia and Secondary Angle-Closure Glaucoma



  Hydrochlorothiazide, a sulfonamide, can cause an idiosyncratic reaction, resulting in acute transient myopia and acute angle-closure glaucoma. Symptoms include acute onset of decreased visual acuity or ocular pain and typically occur within hours to weeks of drug initiation. Untreated acute angle-closure glaucoma can lead to permanent vision loss. The primary treatment is to discontinue hydrochlorothiazide as rapidly as possible. Prompt medical or surgical treatments may need to be considered if the intraocular pressure remains uncontrolled. Risk factors for developing acute angle-closure glaucoma may include a history of sulfonamide or penicillin allergy.



    5.10 Sprue-like Enteropathy



  Severe, chronic diarrhea with substantial weight loss has been reported in patients taking olmesartan months to years after drug initiation. Intestinal biopsies of patients often demonstrated villous atrophy. If a patient develops these symptoms during treatment with olmesartan, exclude other etiologies. Consider discontinuation of Tribenzor in cases where no other etiology is identified.



    5.11 Vasodilation



   Amlodipine.  Although vasodilation attributable to amlodipine is generally gradual in onset, acute hypotension has rarely been reported after oral administration. Patients with severe aortic stenosis may be at particular risk.



    5.12 Heart Failure



   Tribenzor.  Tribenzor has not been studied in patients with heart failure.



  Amlodipine.  Amlodipine (5-10 mg per day) has been studied in a placebo-controlled trial of 1153 patients with New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class III or IV heart failure on stable doses of ACE inhibitor, digoxin, and diuretics. Follow-up was at least 6 months, with a mean of about 14 months. There was no overall adverse effect on survival or cardiac morbidity (as defined by life threatening arrhythmia, acute myocardial infarction, or hospitalization for worsened heart failure). Amlodipine has been compared to placebo in four 8-12 week studies of patients with NYHA Class II/III heart failure, involving a total of 697 patients. In these studies, there was no evidence of worsening of heart failure based on measures of exercise tolerance, NYHA classification, symptoms, or left ventricular ejection fraction.



    5.13 Laboratory Tests



   Olmesartan medoxomil.  In post-marketing experience, increased blood creatinine levels and hyperkalemia have been reported.



  Amlodipine.  In post-marketing experience, hepatic enzyme elevations have been reported [see Adverse Reactions (  6.2  )]  .



  Hydrochlorothiazide.  Increases in cholesterol and triglyceride levels may be associated with thiazide diuretic therapy.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
