<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tricor" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

    

  Adverse events reported by 2% or more of patients treated with fenofibrate during the double-blind, placebo-controlled trials, regardless of causality, are listed in the table below. Adverse events led to discontinuation of treatment in 5.0% of patients treated with fenofibrate and in 3.0% treated with placebo. Increases in liver function tests were the most frequent events, causing discontinuation of fenofibrate treatment in 1.6% of patients in double-blind trials.




   BODY SYSTEM                           Fenofibrate*                     Placebo                         
  
  *   Dosage equivalent to 145 mg TRICOR.  **   Significantly different from Placebo.    
  
   Adverse Event                         (N=439)                          (N=365)                         
   BODY AS A WHOLE                                                                                        
 Abdominal Pain                        4.6%                             4.4%                              
 Back Pain                             3.4%                             2.5%                              
 Headache                              3.2%                             2.7%                              
 Asthenia                              2.1%                             3.0%                              
 Flu Syndrome                          2.1%                             2.7%                              
   DIGESTIVE                                                                                              
 Liver Function Tests Abnormal         7.5%**                           1.4%                              
 Diarrhea                              2.3%                             4.1%                              
 Nausea                                2.3%                             1.9%                              
 Constipation                          2.1%                             1.4%                              
   METABOLIC AND NUTRITIONAL DISORDERS                                      
 SGPT Increased                        3.0%                             1.6%                              
 Creatine Phosphokinase Increased      3.0%                             1.4%                              
 SGOT Increased                        3.4% **                          0.5%                              
   RESPIRATORY                                                                                            
 Respiratory Disorder                  6.2%                             5.5%                              
 Rhinitis                              2.3%                             1.1%                              
      Additional adverse events reported during post-marketing surveillance or by three or more patients in placebo-controlled trials or reported in other controlled or open trials, regardless of causality are listed below.
 

   Body as a Whole

  Accidental injury, allergic reaction, chest pain, cyst, fever, hernia, infection, malaise and pain (unspecified).



   Cardiovascular System

  Angina pectoris, arrhythmia, atrial fibrillation, cardiovascular disorder, coronary artery disorder, electrocardiogram abnormal, extrasystoles, hypertension, hypotension, migraine, myocardial infarct, palpitation, peripheral vascular disorder, phlebitis, tachycardia, varicose vein, vascular disorder, vasodilatation, venous thromboembolic events (deep vein thrombosis, pulmonary embolus) and ventricular extrasystoles.



   Digestive System

  Anorexia, cholecystitis, cholelithiasis, colitis, diarrhea, duodenal ulcer, dyspepsia, eructation, esophagitis, flatulence, gastritis, gastroenteritis, gastrointestinal disorder, increased appetite, jaundice, liver fatty deposit, nausea, pancreatitis, peptic ulcer, rectal disorder, rectal hemorrhage, tooth disorder and vomiting.



   Endocrine System

  Diabetes mellitus.



   Hemic and Lymphatic System

  Anemia, ecchymosis, eosinophilia, leukopenia, lymphadenopathy, and thrombocytopenia.



   Laboratory Investigations

  Alkaline phosphatase increased, bilirubin increased, blood urea nitrogen increased, serum creatinine increased, gamma glutamyl transpeptidase increased, lactate dehydrogenase increased, SGOT and SGPT increased.



   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders

  Edema, gout, hyperuricemia, hypoglycemia, peripheral edema, weight gain, and weight loss.



   Musculoskeletal System

  Arthralgia, arthritis, arthrosis, bursitis, joint disorder, leg cramps, myalgia, myasthenia, myositis, rhabdomyolysis and tenosynovitis.



   Nervous System

  Anxiety or nervousness, depression, dizziness, dry mouth, hypertonia, insomnia, libido decreased, neuralgia, paresthesia, somnolence and vertigo.



   Respiratory System

  Allergic pulmonary alveolitis, asthma, bronchitis, cough increased, dyspnea, laryngitis, pharyngitis, pneumonia and sinusitis.



   Skin and Appendages

  Acne, alopecia, contact dermatitis, eczema, fungal dermatitis, herpes simplex, herpes zoster, maculopapular rash, nail disorder, photosensitivity reaction, pruritus, rash, sweating, skin disorder, skin ulcer and urticaria.



   Special Senses

  Abnormal vision, amblyopia, cataract specified, conjunctivitis, ear pain, eye disorder, otitis media and refraction disorder.



   Urogenital System

  Abnormal kidney function, cystitis, dysuria, gynecomastia, prostatic disorder, unintended pregnancy, urinary frequency, urolithiasis and vaginal moniliasis.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
