<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="triferic0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are described below and elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Hypersensitivity reactions [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ]. 
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions in controlled clinical studies include: headache, peripheral edema, asthenia, AV fistula thrombosis, urinary tract infection, AV fistula site hemorrhage, pyrexia, fatigue, procedural hypotension, muscle spasms, pain in extremity, back pain, and dyspnea.
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Rockwell Medical at 1-855-333-4315 or 1-248-960-9009 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In two randomized, placebo-controlled clinical trials, a total of 292 patients were administered Triferic for periods of up to 1 year [  see  Clinical Studies (14)    ]. The mean total exposure in the randomized treatment period was 5 months. A total of 296 patients received placebo treatment for a similar time period. In the two studies, 64% were male and 54% were Caucasian. The median age of patients was 60 years (range, 20 to 89 years).



 Adverse events occurring in 3% or greater of patients treated with Triferic in the randomized clinical trials are listed in Table 1.



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions Reported in Two Clinical Trials in at Least 3% of Patients Receiving Triferic and at an Incidence at Least 1% Greater than Placebo 
 System Organ Class  Preferred Term                     TrifericN=292n (%)          PlaceboN=296n (%)       
  
 Number of patients with at least one adverse reaction         229 (78.4)                 223 (75.3)           
 General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions                                                         
   Peripheral edema                                          20 (6.8)                   11 (3.7)            
   Pyrexia                                                   13 (4.5)                    9 (3.0)            
   Asthenia                                                  12 (4.1)                    9 (3.0)            
   Fatigue                                                   11 (3.8)                    6 (2.0)            
 Infections and Infestations                                                                                
   Urinary tract infection                                   13 (4.5)                    4 (1.4)            
 Injury, Poisoning, and Procedural Complications                                                            
   Procedural hypotension                                    63 (21.6)                  57 (19.3)           
   Arteriovenous fistula thrombosis                          10 (3.4)                    6 (2.0)            
   Arteriovenous fistula site hemorrhage                     10 (3.4)                    5 (1.7)            
 Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders                                                            
   Muscle spasms                                             28 (9.6)                   24 (8.1)            
   Pain in extremity                                         20 (6.8)                   17 (5.7)            
   Back pain                                                 13 (4.5)                   10 (3.4)            
 Nervous System Disorders                                                                                   
   Headache                                                  27 (9.2)                   16 (5.4)            
 Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders                                                            
   Dyspnea                                                   17 (5.8)                   13 (4.4)            
               Adverse Reactions Leading to Treatment Discontinuation    
 

 In clinical trials, adverse reactions leading to treatment discontinuation included headache, asthenia, dizziness, constipation, nausea, hypersensitivity reactions, intradialytic hypotension, pruritus, and pyrexia.



 Adverse reactions reported in the treatment extension period were similar to those observed in the randomized clinical studies.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  EXCERPT:   Hypersensitivity Reactions: Observe for signs and symptoms of hypersensitivity during and after hemodialysis and until clinically stable. (  5.1  )



 



   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Serious hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylactic-type reactions, some of which have been life-threatening and fatal, have been reported in patients receiving parenteral iron products. Patients may present with shock, clinically significant hypotension, loss of consciousness, and/or collapse. Monitor patients for signs and symptoms of hypersensitivity during and after hemodialysis until clinically stable. Personnel and therapies should be immediately available for the treatment of serious hypersensitivity reactions [ see  Adverse Reactions (6)    ].



 Hypersensitivity reactions have been reported in 1 (0.3%) of 292 patients receiving Triferic in two randomized clinical trials.



    5.2 Iron Laboratory Testing



  Iron status should be determined on pre-dialysis blood samples. Post dialysis serum iron parameters may overestimate serum iron and transferrin saturation.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
