<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="trintellix" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the label.



 *    Hypersensitivity [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  
 *    Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *    Serotonin Syndrome [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *    Abnormal Bleeding [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *    Activation of Mania/Hypomania [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *    Hyponatremia [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=5% and at least twice the rate of placebo) were: nausea, constipation and vomiting (  6  ).
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Takeda Pharmaceuticals at 1-877-TAKEDA-7 (1-877-825-3327) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



   Patient Exposure  



 TRINTELLIX was evaluated for safety in 4746 patients (18 years to 88 years of age) diagnosed with MDD who participated in pre-marketing clinical studies; 2616 of those patients were exposed to TRINTELLIX in 6 to 8 week, placebo-controlled studies at doses ranging from 5 mg to 20 mg once daily and 204 patients were exposed to TRINTELLIX in a 24 week to 64 week placebo-controlled maintenance study at doses of 5 mg to 10 mg once daily. Patients from the 6 to 8 week studies continued into 12-month open-label studies. A total of 2586 patients were exposed to at least one dose of TRINTELLIX in open-label studies, 1727 were exposed to TRINTELLIX for six months and 885 were exposed for at least one year.



   Adverse Reactions Reported as Reasons for Discontinuation of Treatment  



 In pooled 6 to 8 week placebo-controlled studies the incidence of patients who received TRINTELLIX 5 mg/day, 10 mg/day, 15 mg/day and 20 mg/day and discontinued treatment because of an adverse reaction was 5%, 6%, 8% and 8%, respectively, compared to 4% of placebo-treated patients. Nausea was the most common adverse reaction reported as a reason for discontinuation.



   Common Adverse Reactions in Placebo-Controlled MDD Studies  



 The most commonly observed adverse reactions in MDD patients treated with TRINTELLIX in 6 to 8 week placebo-controlled studies (incidence &gt;=5% and at least twice the rate of placebo) were nausea, constipation and vomiting.



   Table 2  shows the incidence of common adverse reactions that occurred in &gt;=2% of MDD patients treated with any TRINTELLIX dose and at least 2% more frequently than in placebo-treated patients in the 6 to 8 week placebo-controlled studies.




  Table 2. Common Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=2% of Patients Treated with any TRINTELLIX Dose and at Least 2% Greater than the Incidence in Placebo-treated Patients    
  System Organ Class Preferred Term    TRINTELLIX5 mg/day    TRINTELLIX10 mg/day    TRINTELLIX15 mg/day    TRINTELLIX20 mg/day    Placebo     
  N=1013%                   N=699%             N=449%             N=455%             N=1621%            
  Gastrointestinal disorders                       
    Nausea                  21                 26                 32                 32                 9           
    Diarrhea                7                  7                  10                 7                  6           
    Dry mouth               7                  7                  6                  8                  6           
    Constipation            3                  5                  6                  6                  3           
    Vomiting                3                  5                  6                  6                  1           
    Flatulence              1                  3                  2                  1                  1           
  Nervous system disorders                       
    Dizziness               6                  6                  8                  9                  6           
  Psychiatric disorders                        
    Abnormal dreams         &lt;1                 &lt;1                 2                  3                  1           
  Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                       
    PruritusIncludes pruritus generalized    1                  2                  3                  3                  1           
              Nausea  
 

 Nausea was the most common adverse reaction and its frequency was dose-related  (Table 2)  . It was usually considered mild or moderate in intensity and the median duration was 2 weeks. Nausea was more common in females than males. Nausea most commonly occurred in the first week of TRINTELLIX treatment with 15 to 20% of patients experiencing nausea after 1 to 2 days of treatment. Approximately 10% of patients taking TRINTELLIX 10 mg/day to 20 mg/day had nausea at the end of the 6 to 8 week placebo-controlled studies.



   Sexual Dysfunction  



 Difficulties in sexual desire, sexual performance and sexual satisfaction often occur as manifestations of psychiatric disorders, but they may also be consequences of pharmacologic treatment.



 In the MDD 6 to 8 week controlled trials of TRINTELLIX, voluntarily reported adverse reactions related to sexual dysfunction were captured as individual event terms. These event terms have been aggregated and the overall incidence was as follows. In male patients the overall incidence was 3%, 4%, 4%, 5% in TRINTELLIX 5 mg/day, 10 mg/day, 15 mg/day, 20 mg/day, respectively, compared to 2% in placebo. In female patients, the overall incidence was &lt;1%, 1%, &lt;1%, 2% in TRINTELLIX 5 mg/day, 10 mg/day, 15 mg/day, 20 mg/day, respectively, compared to &lt;1% in placebo.



 Because voluntarily reported adverse sexual reactions are known to be underreported, in part because patients and physicians may be reluctant to discuss them, the Arizona Sexual Experiences Scale (ASEX), a validated measure designed to identify sexual side effects, was used prospectively in seven placebo-controlled trials. The ASEX scale includes five questions that pertain to the following aspects of sexual function: 1) sex drive, 2) ease of arousal, 3) ability to achieve erection (men) or lubrication (women), 4) ease of reaching orgasm, and 5) orgasm satisfaction.



 The presence or absence of sexual dysfunction among patients entering clinical studies was based on their ASEX scores. For patients without sexual dysfunction at baseline (approximately 1/3 of the population across all treatment groups in each study),  Table 3  shows the incidence of patients that developed treatment-emergent sexual dysfunction when treated with TRINTELLIX or placebo in any fixed dose group. Physicians should routinely inquire about possible sexual side effects.




  Table 3. ASEX Incidence of Treatment Emergent Sexual DysfunctionIncidence based on number of subjects with sexual dysfunction during the study / number of subjects without sexual dysfunction at baseline. Sexual dysfunction was defined as a subject scoring any of the following on the ASEX scale at two consecutive visits during the study: 1) total score &gt;=19; 2) any single item &gt;=5; 3) three or more items each with a score &gt;=4    
               TRINTELLIX  5 mg/day  N=65:67Sample size for each dose group is the number of patients (females:males) without sexual dysfunction at baseline    TRINTELLIX  10 mg/day  N=94:86    TRINTELLIX  15 mg/day  N=57:67    TRINTELLIX  20 mg/day  N=67:59    Placebo  N=135:162    
  Females      22%                 23%                 33%                 34%                 20%              
  Males        16%                 20%                 19%                 29%                 14%              
              Adverse Reactions Following Abrupt Discontinuation of TRINTELLIX Treatment  
 

 Discontinuation symptoms have been prospectively evaluated in patients taking TRINTELLIX 10 mg/day, 15 mg/day, and 20 mg/day using the Discontinuation-Emergent Signs and Symptoms (DESS) scale in clinical trials. Some patients experienced discontinuation symptoms such as headache, muscle tension, mood swings, sudden outbursts of anger, dizziness, and runny nose in the first week of abrupt discontinuation of TRINTELLIX 15 mg/day and 20 mg/day.



   Laboratory Tests  



 TRINTELLIX has not been associated with any clinically important changes in laboratory test parameters in serum chemistry (except sodium), hematology and urinalysis as measured in the 6 to 8 week placebo-controlled studies. Hyponatremia has been reported with the treatment of TRINTELLIX  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  . In the 6-month, double-blind, placebo-controlled phase of a long-term study in patients who had responded to TRINTELLIX during the initial 12-week, open-label phase, there were no clinically important changes in lab test parameters between TRINTELLIX and placebo-treated patients.



   Weight  



 TRINTELLIX had no significant effect on body weight as measured by the mean change from baseline in the 6 to 8 week placebo-controlled studies. In the 6-month, double-blind, placebo-controlled phase of a long-term study in patients who had responded to TRINTELLIX during the initial 12-week, open-label phase, there was no significant effect on body weight between TRINTELLIX and placebo-treated patients.



   Vital Signs  



 TRINTELLIX has not been associated with any clinically significant effects on vital signs, including systolic and diastolic blood pressure and heart rate, as measured in placebo-controlled studies.



   Other Adverse Reactions Observed in Clinical Studies  



 The following listing does not include reactions: 1) already listed in previous tables or elsewhere in labeling, 2) for which a drug cause was remote, 3) which were so general as to be uninformative, 4) which were not considered to have significant clinical implications, or 5) which occurred at a rate equal to or less than placebo.



   Ear and labyrinth disorders -  vertigo  Gastrointestinal disorders -  dyspepsia  Nervous system disorders -  dysgeusia  Vascular disorders -  flushing
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: SUICIDAL THOUGHTS AND BEHAVIORS

  WARNING: SUICIDAL THOUGHTS AND BEHAVIORS

    Antidepressants increased the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term studies. These studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior with antidepressant use in patients over age 24; there was a trend toward reduced risk with antidepressant use in patients aged 65 and older   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ].    



   In patients of all ages who are started on antidepressant therapy, monitor closely for worsening, and for emergence of suicidal thoughts and behaviors. Advise families and caregivers of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ].    



   TRINTELLIX has not been evaluated for use in pediatric patients   [see   Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  ].    



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: SUICIDAL THOUGHTS AND BEHAVIORS



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  .



 *  Increased risk of suicidal thinking and behavior in children, adolescents, and young adults taking antidepressants (5.1). 
 *  Monitor for worsening and emergence of suicidal thoughts and behaviors (5.1). 
 *  TRINTELLIX has not been evaluated for use in pediatric patients (8.4). 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Serotonin Syndrome has been reported with serotonergic antidepressants (SSRIs, SNRIs, and others), including with TRINTELLIX, both when taken alone, but especially when co-administered with other serotonergic agents (including triptans, tricyclic antidepressants, fentanyl, lithium, tramadol, tryptophan, buspirone, and St. John's Wort). If such symptoms occur, discontinue TRINTELLIX and initiate supportive treatment. If concomitant use of TRINTELLIX with other serotonergic drugs is clinically warranted, patients should be made aware of a potential increased risk for serotonin syndrome, particularly during treatment initiation and dose increases (  5.2  ). 
 *    Treatment with serotonergic antidepressants (SSRIs, SNRIs, and others) may increase the risk of abnormal bleeding. Patients should be cautioned about the increased risk of bleeding when TRINTELLIX is coadministered with nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), aspirin, or other drugs that affect coagulation (  5.3  ). 
 *    Activation of Mania/Hypomania can occur with antidepressant treatment. Screen patients for bipolar disorder (  5.4  ). 
 *    Angle Closure Glaucoma: Angle closure glaucoma has occurred in patients with untreated anatomically narrow angles treated with antidepressants. (  5.5  ) 
 *    Hyponatremia can occur in association with the syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion (SIADH) (  5.6  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk



  Patients with major depressive disorder (MDD), both adult and pediatric, may experience worsening of their depression and/or the emergence of suicidal ideation and behavior (suicidality) or unusual changes in behavior, whether or not they are taking antidepressant medications, and this risk may persist until significant remission occurs. Suicide is a known risk of depression and certain other psychiatric disorders, and these disorders themselves are the strongest predictors of suicide. There has been a long-standing concern, however, that antidepressants may have a role in inducing worsening of depression and the emergence of suicidality in certain patients during the early phases of treatment. Pooled analyses of short-term placebo-controlled studies of antidepressant drugs (selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors [SSRIs] and others) showed that these drugs increase the risk of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults (ages 18 to 24) with MDD and other psychiatric disorders. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a trend toward reduction with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older.



 The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled studies in children and adolescents with MDD, obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD), or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 24 short-term studies of nine antidepressant drugs in over 4,400 patients. The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled studies in adults with MDD or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 295 short-term studies (median duration of two months) of 11 antidepressant drugs in over 77,000 patients. There was considerable variation in risk of suicidality among drugs, but a tendency toward an increase in the younger patients for almost all drugs studied. There were differences in absolute risk of suicidality across the different indications, with the highest incidence in MDD. The risk differences (drug vs. placebo), however, were relatively stable within age strata and across indications. These risk differences (drug-placebo difference in the number of cases of suicidality per 1000 patients treated) are provided in Table 1  .




  Table 1. Drug-Placebo Difference in Number of Cases of Suicidality per 1000 Patients Treated    
  Age Range                                                                                               
  Increases Compared to Placebo             
  &lt;18                                       14 additional cases                                           
  18-24                                     5 additional cases                                            
  Decreases Compared to Placebo             
  25-64                                     1 fewer case                                                  
  &gt;=65                                      6 fewer cases                                                 
        No suicides occurred in any of the pediatric studies. There were suicides in the adult studies, but the number was not sufficient to reach any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.
 

 It is unknown whether the suicidality risk extends to longer-term use, i.e., beyond several months. However, there is substantial evidence from placebo-controlled maintenance studies in adults with depression that the use of antidepressants can delay the recurrence of depression.



  All patients being treated with antidepressants for any indication should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, and unusual changes in behavior, especially during the initial few months of a course of drug therapy, or at times of dose changes, either increases or decreases.  



 The following symptoms anxiety, agitation, panic attacks, insomnia, irritability, hostility, aggressiveness, impulsivity, akathisia (psychomotor restlessness), hypomania, and mania have been reported in adult and pediatric patients being treated with antidepressants for MDD as well as for other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric. Although a causal link between the emergence of such symptoms and either the worsening of depression and/or the emergence of suicidal impulses has not been established, there is concern that such symptoms may represent precursors to emerging suicidality.



 Consideration should be given to changing the therapeutic regimen, including possibly discontinuing the medication, in patients whose depression is persistently worse, or who are experiencing emergent suicidality or symptoms that might be precursors to worsening depression or suicidality, especially if these symptoms are severe, abrupt in onset, or were not part of the patient's presenting symptoms.



  Families and caregivers of patients being treated with antidepressants for MDD or other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric, should be alerted about the need to monitor patients for the emergence of agitation, irritability, unusual changes in behavior, and the other symptoms described above, as well as the emergence of suicidality, and to report such symptoms immediately to healthcare providers. Such monitoring should include daily observation by families and caregivers.  



  Screening Patients for Bipolar Disorder  



 A major depressive episode may be the initial presentation of bipolar disorder. It is generally believed (though not established in controlled studies) that treating such an episode with an antidepressant alone may increase the likelihood of precipitation of a mixed/manic episode in patients at risk for bipolar disorder. Whether any of the symptoms described above represent such a conversion is unknown. However, prior to initiating treatment with an antidepressant, patients with depressive symptoms should be adequately screened to determine if they are at risk for bipolar disorder; such screening should include a detailed psychiatric history, including a family history of suicide, bipolar disorder, and depression. It should be noted that TRINTELLIX is not approved for use in treating bipolar depression.



    5.2 Serotonin Syndrome



  The development of a potentially life-threatening serotonin syndrome has been reported with serotonergic antidepressants including TRINTELLIX, when used alone but more often when used concomitantly with other serotonergic drugs (including triptans, tricyclic antidepressants, fentanyl, lithium, tramadol, tryptophan, buspirone, and St. John's Wort), and with drugs that impair metabolism of serotonin (in particular, MAOIs, both those intended to treat psychiatric disorders and also others, such as linezolid and intravenous methylene blue).



 Serotonin syndrome symptoms may include mental status changes (e.g., agitation, hallucinations, delirium, and coma), autonomic instability (e.g., tachycardia, labile blood pressure, dizziness, diaphoresis, flushing, hyperthermia), neuromuscular symptoms (e.g., tremor, rigidity, myoclonus, hyperreflexia, incoordination), seizures, and/or gastrointestinal symptoms (e.g., nausea, vomiting, diarrhea). Patients should be monitored for the emergence of serotonin syndrome.



 The concomitant use of TRINTELLIX with MAOIs intended to treat psychiatric disorders is contraindicated. TRINTELLIX should also not be started in a patient who is being treated with MAOIs such as linezolid or intravenous methylene blue. All reports with methylene blue that provided information on the route of administration involved intravenous administration in the dose range of 1 mg/kg to 8 mg/kg. No reports involved the administration of methylene blue by other routes (such as oral tablets or local tissue injection) or at lower doses. There may be circumstances when it is necessary to initiate treatment with a MAOI such as linezolid or intravenous methylene blue in a patient taking TRINTELLIX. TRINTELLIX should be discontinued before initiating treatment with the MAOI [see  Contraindications (4)      and  Dosage and Administration (2.4)  ]  .



 If concomitant use of TRINTELLIX with other serotonergic drugs, including triptans, tricyclic antidepressants, fentanyl, lithium, tramadol, buspirone, tryptophan, and St. John's Wort is clinically warranted, patients should be made aware of a potential increased risk for serotonin syndrome, particularly during treatment initiation and dose increases.



 Treatment with TRINTELLIX and any concomitant serotonergic agents should be discontinued immediately if the above events occur and supportive symptomatic treatment should be initiated.



    5.3 Abnormal Bleeding



  The use of drugs that interfere with serotonin reuptake inhibition, including TRINTELLIX, may increase the risk of bleeding events. Concomitant use of aspirin, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), warfarin, and other anticoagulants may add to this risk. Case reports and epidemiological studies (case-control and cohort design) have demonstrated an association between use of drugs that interfere with serotonin reuptake and the occurrence of gastrointestinal bleeding. Bleeding events related to drugs that inhibit serotonin reuptake have ranged from ecchymosis, hematoma, epistaxis, and petechiae to life-threatening hemorrhages.



 Patients should be cautioned about the increased risk of bleeding when TRINTELLIX is coadministered with NSAIDs, aspirin, or other drugs that affect coagulation or bleeding [see  Drug Interactions (7.2)  ].  



    5.4 Activation of Mania/Hypomania



  Symptoms of mania/hypomania were reported in &lt;0.1% of patients treated with TRINTELLIX in pre-marketing clinical studies. Activation of mania/hypomania has been reported in a small proportion of patients with major affective disorder who were treated with other antidepressants. As with all antidepressants, use TRINTELLIX cautiously in patients with a history or family history of bipolar disorder, mania, or hypomania.



    5.5 Angle Closure Glaucoma



   Angle Closure Glaucoma: The pupillary dilation that occurs following use of many antidepressant drugs, including TRINTELLIX, may trigger an angle closure attack in a patient with anatomically narrow angles who does not have a patent iridectomy.  



    5.6 Hyponatremia



  Hyponatremia has occurred as a result of treatment with serotonergic drugs. In many cases, hyponatremia appears to be the result of the syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion (SIADH). One case with serum sodium lower than 110 mmol/L was reported in a subject treated with TRINTELLIX in a pre-marketing clinical study. Elderly patients may be at greater risk of developing hyponatremia with a serotonergic antidepressant. Also, patients taking diuretics or who are otherwise volume-depleted can be at greater risk. Discontinuation of TRINTELLIX in patients with symptomatic hyponatremia and appropriate medical intervention should be instituted. Signs and symptoms of hyponatremia include headache, difficulty concentrating, memory impairment, confusion, weakness, and unsteadiness, which can lead to falls. More severe and/or acute cases have included hallucination, syncope, seizure, coma, respiratory arrest, and death.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
