<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="trisenox" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions have been associated with TRISENOX in clinical trials and are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the label.



 *    APL Differentiation Syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.1  )]  
 *    Cardiac Conduction Abnormalities: Torsade de Pointes, Complete Heart Block, and QT Prolongation [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *    Carcinogenesis [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *    Embryo-Fetal Toxicity [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *    Laboratory Tests [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions in patients with relapsed or refractory APL were leukocytosis, gastrointestinal (nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, and abdominal pain), fatigue, edema, hyperglycemia, dyspnea, cough, rash or itching, headaches, and dizziness. (  6.1  )
 

 To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Teva Pharmaceuticals USA, Inc. at 1-800-896-5855 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Safety information was available for 52 patients with relapsed or refractory APL who participated in clinical trials of TRISENOX. Forty patients in the Phase 2 study received the recommended dose of 0.15 mg/kg of which 28 completed both induction and consolidation treatment cycles. An additional 12 patients with relapsed or refractory APL received doses generally similar to the recommended dose. Most patients experienced some drug-related toxicity, most commonly leukocytosis, gastrointestinal (nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, and abdominal pain), fatigue, edema, hyperglycemia, dyspnea, cough, rash or itching, headaches, and dizziness. These adverse effects have not been observed to be permanent or irreversible nor do they usually require interruption of therapy.



 Serious adverse events (SAEs), Grade 3/4 according to version 2 of the NCI Common Toxicity Criteria, were common. Those SAEs attributed to TRISENOX in the Phase 2 study of 40 patients with refractory or relapsed APL included APL differentiation syndrome (n=3), hyperleukocytosis (n=3), QTc interval &gt;= 500 msec (n=16, 1 with torsade de pointes), atrial dysrhythmias (n=2), and hyperglycemia (n=2).



 Table 1 describes the adverse events that were observed in patients, between the ages of 5-73 years, treated for APL with TRISENOX at the recommended dose at a rate of 5% or more. Similar adverse event profiles were seen in the other patient populations who received TRISENOX.



   Table 1  



   Adverse Events (Any Grade) Occurring in &gt;= 5% of 40 Patients with APL Who Received  



   TRISENOX (arsenic trioxide) Injection at a Dose of 0.15 mg/kg/day  




  System organ class  Adverse event               All Adverse Events,  Any Grade    Grade 3/4 Events    
  n                                               %          n          %          
  General disorders and administration site conditions                                                  
  Fatigue                                         25         63         2          5            
  Pyrexia (fever)                                 25         63         2          5            
  Edema - non-specific                            16         40                                 
  Rigors                                          15         38                                 
  Chest pain                                      10         25         2          5            
  Injection site pain                             8          20                                 
  Pain - non-specific                             6          15         1          3            
  Injection site erythema                         5          13                                 
  Injection site edema                            4          10                                 
  Weakness                                        4          10         2          5            
  Hemorrhage                                      3          8                                  
  Weight gain                                     5          13                                 
  Weight loss                                     3          8                                  
  Drug hypersensitivity                           2          5          1          3            
  Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                    
  Nausea                                          30         75                                 
  Anorexia                                        9          23                                 
  Appetite decreased                              6          15                                 
  Diarrhea                                        21         53                                 
  Vomiting                                        23         58                                 
  Abdominal pain (lower &amp; upper)                  23         58         4          10           
  Sore throat                                     14         35                                 
  Constipation                                    11         28         1          3            
  Loose stools                                    4          10                                 
  Dyspepsia                                       4          10                                 
  Oral blistering                                 3          8                                  
  Fecal incontinence                              3          8                                  
  Gastrointestinal hemorrhage                     3          8                                  
  Dry mouth                                       3          8                                  
  Abdominal tenderness                            3          8                                  
  Diarrhea hemorrhagic                            3          8                                  
  Abdominal distension                            3          8                                  
  Metabolism and nutrition disorders                                                            
  Hypokalemia                                     20         50         5          13           
  Hypomagnesemia                                  18         45         5          13           
  Hyperglycemia                                   18         45         5          13           
  ALT increased                                   8          20         2          5            
  Hyperkalemia                                    7          18         2          5            
  AST increased                                   5          13         1          3            
  Hypocalcemia                                    4          10                                 
  Hypoglycemia                                    3          8                                  
  Acidosis                                        2          5                                  
  Nervous system disorders                                                                      
  Headache                                        24         60         1          3            
  Insomnia                                        17         43         1          3            
  Paresthesia                                     13         33         2          5            
  Dizziness (excluding vertigo)                   9          23                                 
  Tremor                                          5          13                                 
  Convulsion                                      3          8          2          5            
  Somnolence                                      3          8                                  
  Coma                                            2          5          2          5            
  Respiratory                                                                                   
  Cough                                           26         65                                 
  Dyspnea                                         21         53         4          10           
  Epistaxis                                       10         25                                 
  Hypoxia                                         9          23         4          10           
  Pleural effusion                                8          20         1          3            
  Post nasal drip                                 5          13                                 
  Wheezing                                        5          13                                 
  Decreased breath sounds                         4          10                                 
  Crepitations                                    4          10                                 
  Rales                                           4          10                                 
  Hemoptysis                                      3          8                                  
  Tachypnea                                       3          8                                  
  Rhonchi                                         3          8                                  
  Skin &amp; subcutaneous tissue disorders                                                          
  Dermatitis                                      17         43                                 
  Pruritus                                        13         33         1          3            
  Ecchymosis                                      8          20                                 
  Dry skin                                        6          15                                 
  Erythema - non-specific                         5          13                                 
  Increased sweating                              5          13                                 
  Facial edema                                    3          8                                  
  Night sweats                                    3          8                                  
  Petechiae                                       3          8                                  
  Hyperpigmentation                               3          8                                  
  Non-specific skin lesions                       3          8                                  
  Urticaria                                       3          8                                  
  Local exfoliation                               2          5                                  
  Eyelid edema                                    2          5                                  
  Cardiac disorders                                                                             
  Tachycardia                                     22         55                                 
  ECG QT corrected interval prolonged  &gt; 500 msec    16         40                                 
  Palpitations                                    4          10                                 
  ECG abnormal other than QT interval prolongation    3          8                                  
  Infections and infestations                                                                   
  Sinusitis                                       8          20                                 
  Herpes simplex                                  5          13                                 
  Upper respiratory tract infection               5          13         1          3            
  Bacterial infection - non-specific              3          8          1          3            
  Herpes zoster                                   3          8                                  
  Nasopharyngitis                                 2          5                                  
  Oral candidiasis                                2          5                                  
  Sepsis                                          2          5          2          5            
  Musculoskeletal, connective tissue and bone disorders                                                  
  Arthralgia                                      13         33         3          8            
  Myalgia                                         10         25         2          5            
  Bone pain                                       9          23         4          10           
  Back pain                                       7          18         1          3            
  Neck pain                                       5          13                                 
  Pain in limb                                    5          13         2          5            
  Hematologic disorders                                                                         
  Leukocytosis                                    20         50         1          3            
  Anemia                                          8          20         2          5            
  Thrombocytopenia                                7          18         5          13           
  Febrile neutropenia                             5          13         3          8            
  Neutropenia                                     4          10         4          10           
  Disseminated intravascular coagulation          3          8          3          8            
  Lymphadenopathy                                 3          8                                  
  Vascular disorders                                                                            
  Hypotension                                     10         25         2          5            
  Flushing                                        4          10                                 
  Hypertension                                    4          10                                 
  Pallor                                          4          10                                 
  Psychiatric disorders                                                                         
  Anxiety                                         12         30                                 
  Depression                                      8          20                                 
  Agitation                                       2          5                                  
  Confusion                                       2          5                                  
  Ocular disorders                                                                              
  Eye irritation                                  4          10                                 
  Blurred vision                                  4          10                                 
  Dry eye                                         3          8                                  
  Painful red eye                                 2          5                                  
  Renal and urinary disorders                                                                   
  Renal failure                                   3          8          1          3            
  Renal impairment                                3          8                                  
  Oliguria                                        2          5                                  
  Incontinence                                    2          5                                  
  Reproductive system disorders                                                                 
  Vaginal hemorrhage                              5          13                                 
  Intermenstrual bleeding                         3          8                                  
  Ear disorders                                                                                 
  Earache                                         3          8                                  
  Tinnitus                                        2          5                                  
           The following additional adverse events were reported as related to TRISENOX treatment in 13 pediatric patients (defined as ages 4 through 20): gastrointestinal (dysphagia, mucosal inflammation/stomatitis, oropharyngeal pain, caecitis), metabolic and nutrition disorders (hyponatremia, hypoalbuminemia, hypophosphatemia, and lipase increased), cardiac failure congestive, respiratory (acute respiratory distress syndrome, lung infiltration, pneumonitis, pulmonary edema, respiratory distress, capillary leak syndrome), neuralgia, and enuresis. Pulmonary edema (n=1) and caecitis (n=1) were considered serious reactions.
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following reactions have been reported from clinical trials and/or worldwide postmarketing surveillance. Because they are reported from a population of unknown size, precise estimates of frequency cannot be made.



   Cardiac disorders:  ventricular extrasystoles in association with QT prolongation, and ventricular tachycardia in association with QT prolongation.



   Nervous system disorders:  peripheral neuropathy



   Hematologic disorders:  pancytopenia



   Investigations:  gamma-glutamyltransferase increased



   Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders:  A differentiation syndrome, like retinoic acid syndrome, has been reported with the use of TRISENOX for the treatment of malignancies other than APL  [see  Boxed Warning  ]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: APL DIFFERENTIATION SYNDROME, CARDIAC CONDUCTION ABNORMALITIES, AND ELECTROLYTE MONITORING

  WARNING: APL DIFFERENTIATION SYNDROME, CARDIAC CONDUCTION ABNORMALITIES, AND ELECTROLYTE MONITORING

    APL Differentiation Syndrome:   Patients with APL treated with TRISENOX have experienced symptoms similar to a syndrome called the retinoic-acid-Acute Promyelocytic Leukemia (RA-APL) or APL differentiation syndrome, characterized by fever, dyspnea, weight gain, pulmonary infiltrates and pleural or pericardial effusions, with or without leukocytosis. This syndrome can be fatal. High-dose steroids have been administered at the first suspicion of the APL differentiation syndrome and appear to mitigate signs and symptoms. At the first signs that could suggest the syndrome (unexplained fever, dyspnea and/or weight gain, abnormal chest auscultatory findings or radiographic abnormalities), immediately initiate high-dose steroids (dexamethasone 10 mg intravenously BID) , irrespective of the leukocyte count, and continue for at least 3 days or longer until signs and symptoms have abated. The majority of patients do not require termination of TRISENOX therapy during treatment of the APL differentiation syndrome   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )].  



   Cardiac Conduction Abnormalities:   Before initiating therapy, perform a 12-lead ECG, assess serum electrolytes and creatinine, correct preexisting electrolyte abnormalities, and consider discontinuing drugs known to prolong QT interval. Arsenic trioxide can cause QT interval prolongation and complete atrioventricular block. QT prolongation can lead to a torsade de pointes-type ventricular arrhythmia, which can be fatal. The risk of torsade de pointes is related to the extent of QT prolongation, concomitant administration of QT prolonging drugs, a history of torsade de pointes, preexisting QT interval prolongation, congestive heart failure, administration of potassium-wasting diuretics, or other conditions that result in hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia. One patient (also receiving amphotericin B) had torsade de pointes during induction therapy for relapsed APL with arsenic trioxide   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )].  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING:  APL DIFFERENTIATION SYNDROME, CARDIAC CONDUCTION ABNORMALITIES, and AND ELECTROLYTE MONITORING



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 *  Patients have experienced symptoms similar to retinoic-acid-Acute Promyelocytic Leukemia or APL differentiation syndrome, which can be fatal. If symptoms occur, initiate high-dose steroids immediately and continue for at least 3 days until symptoms have abated. 
 *  Arsenic trioxide can cause QT interval prolongation and complete atrioventricular block. QT prolongation can lead to a torsade de pointes-type ventricular arrhythmia, which can be fatal. 
 *  Before intiating therapy, perform a 12-lead ECG, assess serum electrolytes and creatinine, correct preexisting electrolyte abnormalities, and consider discontinuing drugs known to prolong QT interval. 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Cardiac Conduction Abnormalities: During TRISENOX therapy, maintain potassium, concentrations above 4 mEq/L and magnesium concentrations above 1.8 mg/dL. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Carcinogenesis: Arsenic trioxide is a human carcinogen. Monitor patients for the development of second primary malignancies. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Embryo-Fetal Toxicity: Can cause fetal harm. Advise of potential risk to a fetus and use of effective contraception. (  5.4  ,  8.1  ,  8.3  ) 
 *    Laboratory Tests: Monitor patient's electrolyte, hematologic and coagulation profiles and obtain ECGs. (  5.5  ) 
    
 

   5.1 APL Differentiation Syndrome



  Nine of 40 patients with APL treated with TRISENOX, at a dose of 0.15 mg/kg, experienced the APL differentiation syndrome. High-dose steroids have been administered at the first suspicion of the APL differentiation syndrome and appear to mitigate signs and symptoms. At the first signs that could suggest the syndrome (unexplained fever, dyspnea and/or weight gain, abnormal chest auscultatory findings or radiographic abnormalities), high-dose steroids (dexamethasone 10 mg intravenously BID) should be immediately initiated, irrespective of the leukocyte count, and continued for at least 3 days or longer until signs and symptoms have abated. The majority of patients do not require termination of TRISENOX therapy during treatment of the APL differentiation syndrome. [see Adverse Reactions (  6  )]  .



     5.2 Cardiac Conduction Abnormalities: Torsade de Pointes, Complete Heart Block, and QT Prolongation  



  Torsade de pointes and complete heart block have been reported. QT/QTc prolongation can occur. Sixteen of 40 patients (40%) had at least one ECG tracing with a QTc interval greater than 500 msec. Prolongation of the QTc was observed between 1 and 5 weeks after TRISENOX infusion, and then returned towards baseline by the end of 8 weeks after TRISENOX infusion.



 Prior to initiating therapy with TRISENOX, a 12-lead ECG should be performed and serum electrolytes (potassium, calcium, and magnesium) and creatinine should be assessed. Preexisting electrolyte abnormalities should be corrected and, if possible, drugs that are known to prolong the QT interval should be discontinued. If it's not possible to discontinue the interacting drug, perform cardiac monitoring frequently [see Drug Interactions (  7  )].  



 Monitor ECG weekly, and more frequently for clinically unstable patients.



 For QTc greater than 500 msec, complete corrective measures and reassess the QTc with serial ECGs prior to initiating TRISENOX. During TRISENOX therapy, maintain potassium concentrations above 4 mEq/L and magnesium concentrations above 1.8 mg/dL. Reassess patients who reach an absolute QT interval value &gt; 500 msec and immediately correct concomitant risk factors, if any, while the risk/benefit of continuing versus suspending TRISENOX therapy should be considered. There are no data on the effect of TRISENOX on the QTc interval during the infusion.



 The risk may be increased when TRISENOX is coadministered with medications that can lead to electrolyte abnormalities (such as diuretics or amphotericin B) [see Drug Interactions (  7  )]  .



    5.3 Carcinogenesis



  The active ingredient of TRISENOX, arsenic trioxide, is a human carcinogen. Monitor patients for the development of second primary malignancies.



    5.4 Embryo-Fetal Toxicity



  TRISENOX can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Arsenic trioxide was embryolethal and teratogenic in rats when administered on gestation day 9 at a dose approximately 10 times the recommended human daily dose on a mg/m2 basis. A related trivalent arsenic, sodium arsenite, produced teratogenicity when administered during gestation in mice at a dose approximately 5 times the projected human dose on a mg/m2 basis and in hamsters at an intravenous dose approximately equivalent to the projected human daily dose on a mg/m2 basis. Advise pregnant women of the potential risk to a fetus. Advise females and males of reproductive potential to use effective contraception during and after treatment with TRISENOX [  see    Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  ,  8.3  )]  .



    5.5 Laboratory Tests



  The patient's electrolyte and glucose levels, as well as hepatic, renal, hematologic and coagulation profiles should be monitored at least twice weekly, and more frequently for clinically unstable patients during the induction phase and at least weekly during the consolidation phase.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
