<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="triumeq" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in other sections of the labeling:



 *    Serious and sometimes fatal hypersensitivity reaction [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.1)] . 
 *    Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.2)] . 
 *    Effects on serum liver biochemistries in patients with hepatitis B or C co-infection [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)] . 
 *    Exacerbations of hepatitis B [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.3)] . 
 *    Hepatic decompensation in patients co-infected with HIV-1 and Hepatitis C [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)] . 
 *    Immune reconstitution syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)] . 
 *    Fat redistribution [see Warnings and Precautions (5.6)] . 
 *    Myocardial infarction [see Warnings and Precautions (5.7)] . 
      EXCERPT:   The most commonly reported adverse reactions of at least moderate intensity and incidence at least 2% (in those receiving TRIUMEQ) were insomnia, headache and fatigue. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact ViiV Healthcare at 1-877-844-8872 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



   Serious and Fatal Abacavir-Associated Hypersensitivity Reactions  



 In clinical trials, serious and sometimes fatal hypersensitivity reactions have occurred with abacavir, a component of TRIUMEQ  [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.1)].  These reactions have been characterized by 2 or more of the following signs or symptoms: (1) fever; (2) rash; (3) gastrointestinal symptoms (including nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, or abdominal pain); (4) constitutional symptoms (including generalized malaise, fatigue, or achiness); (5) respiratory symptoms (including dyspnea, cough, or pharyngitis). Almost all abacavir hypersensitivity reactions include fever and/or rash as part of the syndrome.



 Other signs and symptoms have included lethargy, headache, myalgia, edema, arthralgia, and paresthesia. Anaphylaxis, liver failure, renal failure, hypotension, adult respiratory distress syndrome, respiratory failure, myolysis, and death have occurred in association with these hypersensitivity reactions. Physical findings have included lymphadenopathy, mucous membrane lesions (conjunctivitis and mouth ulcerations), and maculopapular or urticarial rash (although some patients had other types of rashes and others did not have a rash). There were reports of erythema multiforme. Laboratory abnormalities included elevated liver chemistries, elevated creatine phosphokinase, elevated creatinine, and lymphopenia and abnormal chest x-ray findings (predominantly infiltrates, which were localized).



   Serious Dolutegravir Hypersensitivity Reactions  



 In clinical trials, hypersensitivity reactions have occurred with dolutegravir, a component of TRIUMEQ  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)].  These hypersensitivity reactions have been characterized by rash, constitutional findings, and sometimes organ dysfunction, including liver injury.



   Additional Treatment-Emergent Adverse Drug Reactions (ADRs) with Use of TRIUMEQ  



 The safety assessment of TRIUMEQ is primarily based on the analyses of data from a randomized, international, multicenter, double-blind, active-controlled trial, SINGLE (ING114467) and supported by data in treatment-experienced, INSTI-naive subjects from SAILING (ING111762) and by data from other treatment-naive trials. See full prescribing information for TIVICAY.



   Treatment-Naive Subjects:  In SINGLE, 833 adult subjects were randomized and received at least one dose of either dolutegravir (TIVICAY) 50 mg with fixed-dose abacavir and lamivudine (EPZICOM  (r)  ) once daily (n = 414) or fixed-dose efavirenz/emtricitabine/tenofovir (ATRIPLA  (r)  ) once daily (n = 419) (study treatment was blinded through Week 96 and open-label from Week 96 through Week 144). Through 144 weeks, the rate of adverse events leading to discontinuation was 4% in subjects receiving TIVICAY + EPZICOM and 14% in subjects receiving ATRIPLA once daily.



 Treatment-emergent ADRs of moderate to severe intensity observed in at least 2% of subjects in either treatment arm of SINGLE are provided in Table 2.



   Table 2. Treatment  -E  mergent Adverse Drug Reactions of at Least Moderate Intensity (Grades 2 to 4) and at Least 2% Frequency in Treatment  -N  aive Subjects in SINGLE (Week 144 Analysis)  




  Adverse Reaction                               TIVICAY + EPZICOM  Once Daily  (n = 414)    ATRIPLA  Once Daily  (n = 419)    
  Psychiatric                                                                                               
  Insomnia                                       3%                                    3%                   
  Depression                                     1%                                    2%                   
  Abnormal dreams                                &lt;1%                                   2%                   
  Nervous System                                                                                            
  Dizziness                                      &lt;1%                                   5%                   
  Headache                                       2%                                    2%                   
  Gastrointestinal                                                                                          
  Nausea                                         &lt;1%                                   3%                   
  Diarrhea                                       &lt;1%                                   2%                   
  General Disorders                                                                                         
  Fatigue                                        2%                                    2%                   
  Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue                                                                              
  Rasha                                          &lt;1%                                   6%                   
  Ear and Labyrinth                                                                                         
  Vertigo                                        0                                     2%                   
           a  Includes pooled terms: rash, rash generalized, rash macular, rash maculo-papular, rash pruritic, and drug eruption.
 

   Treatment-Experienced Subjects:  SAILING is an international, double-blind trial in INSTI-naive, antiretroviral treatment-experienced adult subjects. Subjects were randomized and received either TIVICAY 50 mg once daily or raltegravir 400 mg twice daily with investigator-selected background regimen consisting of up to 2 agents, including at least one fully active agent. At 48 weeks, the rate of adverse events leading to discontinuation was consistent with that seen in the overall treatment-naive patient population. See full prescribing information for TIVICAY.



 The ADRs observed in the subset of subjects who received TIVICAY + EPZICOM were generally consistent with those seen in the overall treatment-naive patient population.



   Less Common Adverse Reactions Observed in Clinical Trials  



 The following adverse reactions occurred in less than 2% of treatment-naive or treatment-experienced subjects in any one trial. These events have been included because of their seriousness and/or assessment of potential causal relationship.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  Abdominal pain, abdominal distention, abdominal discomfort, dyspepsia, flatulence, gastroesophageal reflux disease, upper abdominal pain, vomiting.



   General Disorders:  Fever, lethargy.



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:  Hepatitis.



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  Anorexia, hypertriglyceridemia.



   Musculoskeletal Disorders:  Arthralgia, myositis.



   Nervous:  Somnolence.



   Psychiatric:  Suicidal ideation, attempt, behavior, or completion. These events were observed primarily in subjects with a pre-existing history of depression or other psychiatric illness. Nightmare and sleep disorder.



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  Renal impairment.



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  Pruritus.



   Laboratory Abnormalities  



   Treatment-Naive Subjects:  Selected laboratory abnormalities (Grades 2 to 4) with a worsening grade from baseline and representing the worst-grade toxicity in at least 2% of subjects in SINGLE are presented in Table 3. The mean change from baseline observed for selected lipid values is presented in Table 4.



   Table 3. Selected Laboratory Abnormalities (Grades 2 to 4) in Treatment-Naive Subjects in SINGLE (Week 144 Analysis)  




  Laboratory Abnormality                       TIVICAY + EPZICOM  Once Daily  (n = 414)    ATRIPLA  Once Daily  (n = 419)    
  ALT                                                                                                       
  Grade 2 (&gt;2.5-5.0 x ULN)                     3%                                      5%                   
  Grade 3 to 4 (&gt;5.0 x ULN)                    1%                                      &lt;1%                  
  AST                                                                                                       
  Grade 2 (&gt;2.5-5.0 x ULN)                     3%                                      4%                   
  Grade 3 to 4 (&gt;5.0 x ULN)                    1%                                      3%                   
  Creatine kinase                                                                                           
  Grade 2 (6.0-9.9 x ULN)                      5%                                      3%                   
  Grade 3 to 4 (&gt;=10.0 x ULN)                  7%                                      8%                   
  Hyperglycemia                                                                                             
  Grade 2 (126-250 mg/dL)                      9%                                      6%                   
  Grade 3 (&gt;250 mg/dL)                         2%                                      &lt;1%                  
  Lipase                                                                                                    
  Grade 2 (&gt;1.5-3.0 x ULN)                     11%                                     11%                  
  Grade 3 to 4 (&gt;3.0 ULN)                      5%                                      4%                   
  Total neutrophils                                                                                         
  Grade 2 (0.75-0.99 x 109)                    4%                                      5%                   
  Grade 3 to 4 (&lt;0.75 x 109)                   3%                                      3%                   
         ULN = Upper limit of normal.
 

   Table 4. Mean Change from Baseline in Fasted Lipid Values in Treatment-Naive Subjects in SINGLE (Week 144 Analysis  a  )  




  Lipid                                     TIVICAY + EPZICOM  Once Daily  (n = 414)    ATRIPLA  Once Daily  (n = 419)    
  Cholesterol (mg/dL)                       24.0                                      26.7                  
  HDL cholesterol (mg/dL)                   5.4                                       7.2                   
  LDL cholesterol (mg/dL)                   16.0                                      14.6                  
  Triglycerides (mg/dL)                     13.6                                      31.9                  
           a  Subjects on lipid-lowering agents at baseline were excluded from these analyses (TIVICAY + EPZICOM n = 30 and ATRIPLA n = 27). Seventy-two subjects initiated a lipid-lowering agent post-baseline; their last fasted on-treatment values (prior to starting the agent) were used regardless if they discontinued the agent (TIVICAY + EPZICOM n = 36 and ATRIPLA: n = 36).
 

   Treatment-Experienced Subjects:  Laboratory abnormalities observed in SAILING were generally similar compared with observations seen in the treatment-naive trials.



   Hepatitis C Virus Co-infection  



 In SINGLE, the pivotal Phase 3 trial, subjects with hepatitis C virus co-infection were permitted to enroll provided that baseline liver chemistry tests did not exceed 5 times the upper limit of normal; subjects with hepatitis B co-infection were excluded. Overall, the safety profile in subjects with hepatitis C virus co-infection was similar to that observed in subjects without hepatitis C co-infection, although the rates of AST and ALT abnormalities were higher in the subgroup with hepatitis C virus co-infection for both treatment groups. Grades 2 to 4 ALT abnormalities in hepatitis C co-infected compared with HIV mono-infected subjects receiving TRIUMEQ were observed in 15% and 2% (vs. 24% and 4% of subjects treated with ATRIPLA) (Week 96 analysis), respectively  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]  . See also full prescribing information for TIVICAY.



   Changes in Serum Creatinine:  Dolutegravir has been shown to increase serum creatinine due to inhibition of tubular secretion of creatinine without affecting renal glomerular function  [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)]  . Increases in serum creatinine occurred within the first 4 weeks of treatment and remained stable through 144 weeks. In SINGLE, a mean change from baseline of 0.14 mg per dL (range: -0.25 mg per dL to 0.81 mg per dL) was observed after 144 weeks of treatment. Creatinine increases were similar in treatment-experienced subjects.



   Abacavir and Lamivudine  



 Laboratory abnormalities observed in clinical trials of ZIAGEN (in combination with other antiretroviral treatment) were anemia, neutropenia, liver function test abnormalities, and elevations of CPK, blood glucose, and triglycerides. Additional laboratory abnormalities observed in clinical trials of EPIVIR (in combination with other antiretroviral treatment) were thrombocytopenia and elevated levels of bilirubin, amylase, and lipase.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  In addition to adverse reactions reported from clinical trials, the following adverse reactions have been identified during postmarketing use. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Abacavir and/or Lamivudine:  



   Digestive:  Stomatitis.



   Gastrointestinal:  Pancreatitis.



   General:  Weakness.



   Blood and Lymphatic Systems:  Aplastic anemia, anemia (including pure red cell aplasia and severe anemias progressing on therapy), lymphadenopathy, splenomegaly.



   Hypersensitivity:  Sensitization reactions (including anaphylaxis), urticaria  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1), Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  .



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  Hyperlactemia.



   Musculoskeletal:  Muscle weakness, CPK elevation, rhabdomyolysis.



   Nervous:  Paresthesia, peripheral neuropathy, seizures.



   Respiratory:  Abnormal breath sounds/wheezing.



   Skin:  Alopecia, erythema multiforme. Suspected Stevens-Johnson syndrome (SJS) and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN) have been reported in patients receiving abacavir primarily in combination with medications known to be associated with SJS and TEN, respectively. Because of the overlap of clinical signs and symptoms between hypersensitivity to abacavir and SJS and TEN, and the possibility of multiple drug sensitivities in some patients, abacavir should be discontinued and not restarted in such cases  [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: HYPERSENSITIVITY REACTIONS, LACTIC ACIDOSIS AND SEVERE HEPATOMEGALY, and EXACERBATIONS OF HEPATITIS B

  WARNING: HYPERSENSITIVITY REACTIONS, LACTIC ACIDOSIS AND SEVERE HEPATOMEGALY, and EXACERBATIONS OF HEPATITIS B

        Hypersensitivity Reactions      



     Serious and sometimes fatal hypersensitivity reactions, with multiple organ involvement, have occurred with abacavir, a component of TRIUMEQ  (r)   (abacavir, dolutegravir, and lamivudine). Patients who carry the HLA    -    B*5701 allele are at a higher risk of a hypersensitivity reaction to abacavir; although, hypersensitivity reactions have occurred in patients who do not carry the HLA    -    B*5701 allele   [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  .    



     TRIUMEQ is contraindicated in patients with a prior hypersensitivity reaction to abacavir and in HLA    -    B*5701-positive patients   [see Contraindications (4), Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  . All patients should be screened for the HLA    -    B*5701 allele prior to initiating therapy with TRIUMEQ or reinitiation of therapy with TRIUMEQ, unless patients have a previously documented HLA    -    B*5701 allele assessment. Discontinue TRIUMEQ immediately if a hypersensitivity reaction is suspected, regardless of HLA-B*5701 status and even when other diagnoses are possible   [see Contraindications (4), Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  .     



     Following a hypersensitivity reaction to TRIUMEQ, NEVER restart TRIUMEQ or any other abacavir    -    containing product because more severe symptoms, including death can occur within hours. Similar severe reactions have also occurred rarely following the reintroduction of abacavir-containing products in patients who have no history of abacavir hypersensitivity   [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  .    



     Lactic Acidosis and Severe Hepatomegaly with Steatosis    



   Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogues alone or in combination, including abacavir, lamivudine, and other antiretrovirals. Discontinue TRIUMEQ if clinical or laboratory findings suggestive of lactic acidosis or pronounced hepatotoxicity occur   [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  .  



     Exacerbations of Hepatitis B    



   Severe acute exacerbations of hepatitis B have been reported in patients who are co  -  infected with hepatitis B virus (HBV) and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV-1) and have discontinued lamivudine, a component of TRIUMEQ. Hepatic function should be monitored closely with both clinical and laboratory follow-up for at least several months in patients who discontinue TRIUMEQ and are co-infected with HIV-1 and HBV. If appropriate, initiation of anti  -  hepatitis B therapy may be warranted   [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]  .  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: HYPERSENSITIVITY REACTIONS, LACTIC ACIDOSIS AND SEVERE HEPATOMEGALY, and EXACERBATIONS OF HEPATITIS B



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



     Hypersensitivity Reactions    



 *  Serious and sometimes fatal hypersensitivity reactions have occurred with abacavir-containing products. (5.1) 
 *  Hypersensitivity to abacavir is a multi-organ clinical syndrome. (5.1) 
 *  Patients who carry the HLA-B*5701 allele are at a higher risk of experiencing a hypersensitivity reaction to abacavir. (5.1) 
 *  TRIUMEQ is contraindicated in patients with a prior hypersensitivity reaction to abacavir and in HLA-B*5701-positive patients. (4) 
 *  Discontinue TRIUMEQ as soon as a hypersensitivity reaction is suspected. Regardless of HLA-B*5701 status, permanently discontinue TRIUMEQ if hypersensitivity cannot be ruled out, even when other diagnoses are possible. (5.1) 
 *  Following a hypersensitivity reaction to TRIUMEQ, NEVER restart TRIUMEQ or any other abacavir-containing product. (5.1) 
        Lactic Acidosis and Severe Hepatomegaly with Steatosis    
 

 *  Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogues. (5.4) 
        Exacerbations of Hepatitis B    
 

 *  Severe acute exacerbations of hepatitis B have been reported in patients who are co-infected with hepatitis B virus (HBV) and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV-1) and have discontinued lamivudine, a component of TRIUMEQ. Monitor hepatic function closely in these patients and, if appropriate, initiate anti-hepatitis B treatment. (5.5) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Patients with underlying hepatitis B or C may be at increased risk for worsening or development of transaminase elevations with use of TRIUMEQ. Appropriate laboratory testing prior to initiating therapy and monitoring for hepatotoxicity during therapy with TRIUMEQ is recommended in patients with underlying hepatic disease such as hepatitis B or C. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Hepatic decompensation, some fatal, has occurred in HIV-1/HCV co-infected patients receiving combination antiretroviral therapy and interferon alfa with or without ribavirin. Discontinue TRIUMEQ as medically appropriate and consider dose reduction or discontinuation of interferon alfa, ribavirin, or both. (  5.4  ) 
 *    Immune reconstitution syndrome and redistribution/accumulation of body fat have been reported in patients treated with combination antiretroviral therapy. (  5.5  ,  5.6  ) 
 *    Administration of TRIUMEQ is not recommended in patients receiving other products containing abacavir or lamivudine. (  5.8  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Hypersensitivity reactions have been reported with the use of abacavir or dolutegravir, components of TRIUMEQ.



  Abacavir  



 Serious and sometimes fatal hypersensitivity reactions have occurred with abacavir containing regimens. See full prescribing information for ZIAGEN  (r)  (abacavir).



  Abacavir hypersensitivity reactions have included multi-organ failure and anaphylaxis and typically occurred within the first 6 weeks of treatment with abacavir (median time to onset was 9 days); although abacavir hypersensitivity reactions have occurred any time during treatment [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  . Patients who carry the HLA  - B*5701 allele are at a higher risk of abacavir hypersensitivity reactions; although, patients who do not carry the HLA  - B*5701 allele have developed hypersensitivity reactions. Hypersensitivity to abacavir was reported in approximately 206 (8%) of 2,670 patients in 9 clinical trials with abacavir-containing products where HLA  - B*5701 screening was not performed. The incidence of suspected abacavir hypersensitivity reactions in clinical trials was 1% when subjects carrying the HLA-B*5701 allele were excluded. In any patient treated with abacavir, the clinical diagnosis of hypersensitivity reaction must remain the basis of clinical decision making.  



  Due to the potential for severe, serious, and possibly fatal hypersensitivity reactions with abacavir:  



 *     All patients should be screened for the HLA - B*5701 allele prior to initiating therapy with TRIUMEQ or reinitiation of therapy with TRIUMEQ, unless patients have a previously documented HLA - B*5701 allele assessment.  
 *     TRIUMEQ is contraindicated in patients with a prior hypersensitivity reaction to abacavir and in HLA - B*5701 - positive patients.  
 *     Before starting TRIUMEQ, review medical history for prior exposure to any abacavir-containing product. NEVER restart TRIUMEQ or any other abacavir-containing product following a hypersensitivity reaction to abacavir, regardless of HLA - B*5701 status.  
 *     To reduce the risk of a life - threatening hypersensitivity reaction, regardless of HLA - B*5701 status, discontinue TRIUMEQ immediately if a hypersensitivity reaction is suspected, even when other diagnoses are possible (e.g., acute onset respiratory diseases such as pneumonia, bronchitis, pharyngitis, or influenza; gastroenteritis; or reactions to other medications). Clinical status, including liver chemistries, should be monitored and appropriate therapy initiated.  
 *     If a hypersensitivity reaction cannot be ruled out, do not restart TRIUMEQ or any other abacavir-containing products because more severe symptoms, which may include life-threatening hypotension and death, can occur within hours.  
 *     Clinically, it is not possible to determine whether a hypersensitivity reaction with TRIUMEQ would be caused by abacavir or dolutegravir. Therefore, never restart TRIUMEQ or any other abacavir- or dolutegravir-containing product in patients who have stopped therapy with TRIUMEQ due to a hypersensitivity reaction.  
 *     If a hypersensitivity reaction is ruled out, patients may restart TRIUMEQ. Rarely, patients who have stopped abacavir for reasons other than symptoms of hypersensitivity have also experienced life-threatening reactions within hours of reinitiating abacavir therapy. Therefore, reintroduction of TRIUMEQ, or any other abacavir-containing product, is recommended only if medical care can be readily accessed.  
 *     A Medication Guide and Warning Card that provide information about recognition of abacavir hypersensitivity reactions should be dispensed with each new prescription and refill.  
     Dolutegravir  
 

 Hypersensitivity reactions have been reported and were characterized by rash, constitutional findings, and sometimes organ dysfunction, including liver injury. The events were reported in less than 1% of subjects receiving TIVICAY  (r)  in Phase 3 clinical trials. Discontinue TRIUMEQ and other suspect agents immediately if signs or symptoms of hypersensitivity reactions develop (including, but not limited to, severe rash or rash accompanied by fever, general malaise, fatigue, muscle or joint aches, blisters or peeling of the skin, oral blisters or lesions, conjunctivitis, facial edema, hepatitis, eosinophilia, angioedema, difficulty breathing). Clinical status, including liver aminotransferases, should be monitored and appropriate therapy initiated. Delay in stopping treatment with TRIUMEQ or other suspect agents after the onset of hypersensitivity may result in a life-threatening reaction.



 Clinically, it is not possible to determine whether a hypersensitivity reaction with TRIUMEQ would be caused by abacavir or dolutegravir. Therefore, never restart TRIUMEQ or any other abacavir- or dolutegravir-containing product in patients who have stopped therapy with TRIUMEQ due to a hypersensitivity reaction.



    5.2 Lactic Acidosis and Severe Hepatomegaly with Steatosis



  Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogues and other antiretrovirals. See full prescribing information for ZIAGEN (abacavir) and EPIVIR  (r)  (lamivudine). Treatment with TRIUMEQ should be suspended in any patient who develops clinical or laboratory findings suggestive of lactic acidosis or pronounced hepatotoxicity (which may include hepatomegaly and steatosis even in the absence of marked transaminase elevations).



    5.3 Patients with Hepatitis B or C Virus Co-infection



   Effects on Serum Liver Biochemistries  



 Patients with underlying hepatitis B or C may be at increased risk for worsening or development of transaminase elevations with use of TRIUMEQ [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  . See full prescribing information for TIVICAY  (r)  (dolutegravir). In some cases the elevations in transaminases were consistent with immune reconstitution syndrome or hepatitis B reactivation particularly in the setting where anti-hepatitis therapy was withdrawn. Appropriate laboratory testing prior to initiating therapy and monitoring for hepatotoxicity during therapy with TRIUMEQ are recommended in patients with underlying hepatic disease such as hepatitis B or C.



  Posttreatment Exacerbations of Hepatitis  



 Clinical and laboratory evidence of exacerbations of hepatitis have occurred after discontinuation of lamivudine. See full prescribing information for EPIVIR (lamivudine). Patients should be closely monitored with both clinical and laboratory follow-up for at least several months after stopping treatment.



  Emergence of Lamivudine-Resistant HBV  



 Safety and efficacy of lamivudine have not been established for treatment of chronic hepatitis B in subjects dually infected with HIV-1 and HBV. Emergence of hepatitis B virus variants associated with resistance to lamivudine has been reported in HIV-1-infected subjects who have received lamivudine-containing antiretroviral regimens in the presence of concurrent infection with hepatitis B virus. See full prescribing information for EPIVIR-HBV  (r)  (lamivudine).



    5.4 Use with Interferon- and Ribavirin-Based Regimens



  Patients receiving interferon alfa with or without ribavirin and TRIUMEQ should be closely monitored for treatment-associated toxicities, especially hepatic decompensation. See full prescribing information for EPIVIR (lamivudine). Discontinuation of TRIUMEQ should be considered as medically appropriate. Dose reduction or discontinuation of interferon alfa, ribavirin, or both should also be considered if worsening clinical toxicities are observed, including hepatic decompensation (e.g., Child-Pugh greater than 6) (see full prescribing information for interferon and ribavirin).



    5.5 Immune Reconstitution Syndrome



  Immune reconstitution syndrome has been reported in patients treated with combination antiretroviral therapy, including TRIUMEQ. During the initial phase of combination antiretroviral treatment, patients whose immune systems respond may develop an inflammatory response to indolent or residual opportunistic infections (such as Mycobacterium avium  infection, cytomegalovirus, Pneumocystis jirovecii  pneumonia [PCP], or tuberculosis), which may necessitate further evaluation and treatment.



 Autoimmune disorders (such as Graves' disease, polymyositis, and Guillain-Barre syndrome) have also been reported to occur in the setting of immune reconstitution; however, the time to onset is more variable, and can occur many months after initiation of treatment.



    5.6 Fat Redistribution



  Redistribution/accumulation of body fat including central obesity, dorsocervical fat enlargement (buffalo hump), peripheral wasting, facial wasting, breast enlargement, and "cushingoid appearance" have been observed in patients receiving antiretroviral therapy. The mechanism and long-term consequences of these events are currently unknown. A causal relationship has not been established.



    5.7 Myocardial Infarction



  In a published prospective, observational, epidemiological trial designed to investigate the rate of myocardial infarction (MI) in patients on combination antiretroviral therapy, the use of abacavir within the previous 6 months was correlated with an increased risk of MI. In a sponsor-conducted pooled analysis of clinical trials, no excess risk of MI was observed in abacavir-treated subjects as compared with control subjects. In totality, the available data from the observational cohort and from clinical trials are inconclusive.



 As a precaution, the underlying risk of coronary heart disease should be considered when prescribing antiretroviral therapies, including abacavir, and action taken to minimize all modifiable risk factors (e.g., hypertension, hyperlipidemia, diabetes mellitus, smoking).



    5.8 Related Products that are Not Recommended



  TRIUMEQ contains fixed doses of an INSTI (dolutegravir) and 2 nucleoside analogue reverse transcriptase inhibitors (abacavir and lamivudine); concomitant administration of TRIUMEQ with other products containing abacavir or lamivudine is not recommended.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
