<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="trizivir" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *    Serious and sometimes fatal hypersensitivity reactions [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.1)] . 
 *    Hematologic toxicity, including neutropenia and anemia [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.2)] . 
 *    Symptomatic myopathy [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.3)] . 
 *    Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.4)] . 
 *    Acute exacerbations of hepatitis B [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.5)] . 
 *    Hepatic decompensation in patients co-infected with HIV-1 and hepatitis C [see Warnings and Precautions (5.6)] . 
 *    Exacerbation of anemia in HIV-1/HCV co-infected patients receiving ribavirin and zidovudine [see Warnings and Precautions (5.6)] . 
 *    Immune reconstitution syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions (5.7)] . 
 *    Fat redistribution [see Warnings and Precautions (5.8)] . 
 *    Myocardial infarction [see Warnings and Precautions (5.9)] . 
      EXCERPT:   The most commonly reported adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=10%) in clinical trials were nausea, headache, malaise and fatigue, and nausea and vomiting. (6.1) 
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact ViiV Healthcare at 1-877-844-8872 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 Treatment-emergent clinical adverse reactions (rated by the investigator as moderate or severe) with a frequency greater than or equal to 5% during therapy with abacavir 300 mg twice daily, lamivudine 150 mg twice daily, and zidovudine 300 mg twice daily compared with indinavir 800 mg 3 times daily, lamivudine 150 mg twice daily, and zidovudine 300 mg twice daily from CNA3005 are listed in Table 1.



 Table 1. Treatment-Emergent (All Causality) Adverse Reactions of at Least Moderate Intensity (Grades 2-4, &gt;=5% Frequency) in Therapy-Naive Adults (CNA3005) Through 48 Weeks of Treatment 
  Adverse Reaction             ZIAGEN plus  Lamivudine/Zidovudine  (n = 262)    Indinavir plus  Lamivudine/Zidovudine  (n = 264)    
  Nausea                       19%                        17%                        
  Headache                     13%                        9%                         
  Malaise and fatigue          12%                        12%                        
  Nausea and vomiting          10%                        10%                        
  Hypersensitivity reaction    8%                         2%                         
  Diarrhea                     7%                         5%                         
  Fever and/or chills          6%                         3%                         
  Depressive disorders         6%                         4%                         
  Musculoskeletal pain         5%                         7%                         
  Skin rashes                  5%                         4%                         
  Ear/nose/throat infections    5%                         4%                         
  Viral respiratory infections    5%                         5%                         
  Anxiety                      5%                         3%                         
  Renal signs/symptoms         &lt;1%                        5%                         
  Pain (non-site-specific)     &lt;1%                        5%                         
         Five subjects receiving abacavir in CNA3005 experienced worsening of pre-existing depression compared to none in the indinavir arm. The background rates of pre-existing depression were similar in the 2 treatment arms.
 

   Laboratory Abnormalities:  Laboratory abnormalities in CNA3005 are listed in Table 2.



 Table 2. Treatment-Emergent Laboratory Abnormalities (Grades 3/4) in CNA3005 
  Grade 3/4 Laboratory Abnormalities    Number of Subjects by Treatment Group    
  ZIAGEN plus  Lamivudine/Zidovudine  (n = 262)    Indinavir plus  Lamivudine/Zidovudine  (n = 264)    
  Elevated CPK (&gt;4 x ULN)               18 (7%)                    18 (7%)                    
  ALT (&gt;5.0 x ULN)                      16 (6%)                    16 (6%)                    
  Neutropenia (&lt;750/mm3)                13 (5%)                    13 (5%)                    
  Hypertriglyceridemia (&gt;750 mg/dL)     5 (2%)                     3 (1%)                     
  Hyperamylasemia (&gt;2.0 x ULN)          5 (2%)                     1 (&lt;1%)                    
  Hyperglycemia (&gt;13.9 mmol/L)          2 (&lt;1%)                    2 (&lt;1%)                    
  Anemia (Hgb &lt;=6.9 g/dL)               0 (0%)                     3 (1%)                     
  ULN = Upper limit of normal.          
  n = Number of patients assessed.      
           Other Adverse Events:  In addition to adverse reactions in Tables 1 and 2, other adverse events observed in the expanded access program for abacavir were pancreatitis and increased GGT.
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  In addition to adverse reactions reported from clinical trials, the following reactions have been identified during postmarketing use of abacavir, lamivudine, and/or zidovudine. Because they are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, estimates of frequency cannot be made. These reactions have been chosen for inclusion due to a combination of their seriousness, frequency of reporting, or potential causal connection to abacavir, lamivudine and/or zidovudine.



   Abacavir:  



   Cardiovascular:  Myocardial infarction.



   Skin:  Suspected Stevens-Johnson syndrome (SJS) and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN) have been reported in patients receiving abacavir primarily in combination with medications known to be associated with SJS and TEN, respectively. Because of the overlap of clinical signs and symptoms between hypersensitivity to abacavir and SJS and TEN, and the possibility of multiple drug sensitivities in some patients, abacavir should be discontinued and not restarted in such cases.



 There have also been reports of erythema multiforme with abacavir use.



   Abacavir, Lamivudine, and/or Zidovudine:  



   Body as a Whole:  Redistribution/accumulation of body fat  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.8)]  .



   Cardiovascular:  Cardiomyopathy.



   Digestive:  Stomatitis.



   Endocrine and Metabolic:  Gynecomastia, hyperglycemia.



   Gastrointestinal:  Anorexia and/or decreased appetite, abdominal pain, dyspepsia, oral mucosal pigmentation.



   General:  Vasculitis, weakness.



   Hemic and Lymphatic:  Aplastic anemia, anemia (including pure red cell aplasia and severe anemias progressing on therapy), lymphadenopathy, splenomegaly, thrombocytopenia.



   Hepatic:  Lactic acidosis and hepatic steatosis  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)]  , elevated bilirubin, elevated transaminases, posttreatment exacerbation of hepatitis B  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)]  .



   Hypersensitivity:  Sensitization reactions (including anaphylaxis), urticaria.



   Musculoskeletal:  Arthralgia, myalgia, muscle weakness, CPK elevation, rhabdomyolysis.



   Nervous:  Dizziness, paresthesia, peripheral neuropathy, seizures.



   Psychiatric:  Insomnia and other sleep disorders.



   Respiratory:  Abnormal breath sounds/wheezing.



   Skin:  Alopecia, erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: RISK OF HYPERSENSITIVITY REACTIONS, HEMATOLOGIC TOXICITY, MYOPATHY, LACTIC ACIDOSIS AND SEVERE HEPATOMEGALY, EXACERBATIONS OF HEPATITIS B

  WARNING: RISK OF HYPERSENSITIVITY REACTIONS, HEMATOLOGIC TOXICITY, MYOPATHY, LACTIC ACIDOSIS AND SEVERE HEPATOMEGALY, EXACERBATIONS OF HEPATITIS B

    Hypersensitivity Reactions: Serious and sometimes fatal hypersensitivity reactions have been associated with abacavir sulfate, a component of TRIZIVIR. Hypersensitivity to abacavir is a multi-organ clinical syndrome usually characterized by a sign or symptom in 2 or more of the following groups: (1) fever, (2) rash, (3) gastrointestinal (including nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, or abdominal pain), (4) constitutional (including generalized malaise, fatigue, or achiness), and (5) respiratory (including dyspnea, cough, or pharyngitis). Discontinue TRIZIVIR as soon as a hypersensitivity reaction is suspected.  



   Patients who carry the HLA-B*5701 allele are at high risk for experiencing a hypersensitivity reaction to abacavir. Prior to initiating therapy with abacavir, screening for the HLA-B*5701 allele is recommended; this approach has been found to decrease the risk of hypersensitivity reaction. Screening is also recommended prior to reinitiation of abacavir in patients of unknown HLA-B*5701 status who have previously tolerated abacavir. HLA-B*5701-negative patients may develop a suspected hypersensitivity reaction to abacavir; however, this occurs significantly less frequently than in HLA-B*5701-positive patients.  



   Regardless of HLA-B*5701 status, permanently discontinue TRIZIVIR if hypersensitivity cannot be ruled out, even when other diagnoses are possible.  



   Following a hypersensitivity reaction to abacavir, NEVER restart TRIZIVIR or any other abacavir-containing product because more severe symptoms can occur within hours and may include life-threatening hypotension and death.  



   Reintroduction of TRIZIVIR or any other abacavir-containing product, even in patients who have no identified history or unrecognized symptoms of hypersensitivity to abacavir therapy, can result in serious or fatal hypersensitivity reactions. Such reactions can occur within hours   [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  .  



   Hematologic Toxicity: Zidovudine, a component of TRIZIVIR, has been associated with hematologic toxicity, including neutropenia and severe anemia, particularly in patients with advanced Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV-1) disease   [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  .  



   Myopathy: Prolonged use of zidovudine has been associated with symptomatic myopathy   [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]  .  



   Lactic Acidosis and Severe Hepatomegaly: Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogues alone or in combination, including abacavir, lamivudine, zidovudine, and other antiretrovirals   [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)]  .  



   Exacerbations of Hepatitis B: Severe acute exacerbations of hepatitis B have been reported in patients who are co-infected with hepatitis B virus (HBV) and HIV-1 and have discontinued lamivudine, which is one component of TRIZIVIR. Hepatic function should be monitored closely with both clinical and laboratory follow-up for at least several months in patients who discontinue TRIZIVIR and are co-infected with HIV-1 and HBV. If appropriate, initiation of anti-hepatitis B therapy may be warranted   [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)]  .  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: RISK OF HYPERSENSITIVITY REACTIONS, HEMATOLOGIC TOXICITY, MYOPATHY, LACTIC ACIDOSIS AND SEVERE HEPATOMEGALY, EXACERBATIONS OF HEPATITIS B



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 *  Serious and sometimes fatal hypersensitivity reactions have been associated with abacavir-containing products. (5.1) 
 *  Hypersensitivity to abacavir is a multi-organ clinical syndrome. (5.1) 
 *  Patients who carry the HLA-B*5701 allele are at high risk for experiencing a hypersensitivity reaction to abacavir. (5.1) 
 *  Discontinue TRIZIVIR as soon as a hypersensitivity reaction is suspected. Regardless of HLA-B*5701 status, permanently discontinue TRIZIVIR if hypersensitivity cannot be ruled out. (5.1) 
 *  Following a hypersensitivity reaction to abacavir, NEVER restart TRIZIVIR or any other abacavir-containing product. (5.1) 
 *  Hematologic toxicity, including neutropenia and anemia, has been associated with the use of zidovudine, a component of TRIZIVIR. (5.2) 
 *  Symptomatic myopathy associated with prolonged use of zidovudine. (5.3) 
 *  Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogues. (5.4) 
 *  Severe acute exacerbations of hepatitis B have been reported in patients who are co-infected with hepatitis B virus (HBV) and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV-1) and have discontinued lamivudine, a component of TRIZIVIR. Monitor hepatic function closely in these patients and, if appropriate, initiate anti-hepatitis B treatment. (5.5) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    



   EXCERPT:    *    See boxed warning for information about the following: hypersensitivity reactions, hematologic toxicity, myopathy, lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly, and severe acute exacerbations of hepatitis B. (5.1, 5.2, 5.3, 5.4, 5.5) 
 *    Hepatic decompensation, some fatal, has occurred in HIV-1/HCV co-infected patients receiving combination antiretroviral therapy and interferon alfa with or without ribavirin. Discontinue TRIZIVIR as medically appropriate and consider dose reduction or discontinuation of interferon alfa, ribavirin, or both. (5.6) 
 *    Exacerbation of anemia has been reported in HIV-1/HCV co-infected patients receiving ribavirin and zidovudine. Coadministration of ribavirin and zidovudine is not advised. (5.6) 
 *    Immune reconstitution syndrome (5.7) and redistribution/accumulation of body fat (5.8) have been reported in patients treated with combination antiretroviral therapy. 
 *    TRIZIVIR should not be administered with other products containing abacavir, lamivudine, or zidovudine; or with emtricitabine. (5.11) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reaction



  Serious and sometimes fatal hypersensitivity reactions have been associated with TRIZIVIR and other abacavir-containing products. Patients who carry the HLA-B*5701 allele are at high risk for experiencing a hypersensitivity reaction to abacavir. Prior to initiating therapy with abacavir, screening for the HLA-B*5701 allele is recommended; this approach has been found to decrease the risk of a hypersensitivity reaction. Screening is also recommended prior to reinitiation of abacavir in patients of unknown HLA-B*5701 status who have previously tolerated abacavir. For HLA-B*5701-positive patients, treatment with an abacavir-containing regimen is not recommended and should be considered only with close medical supervision and under exceptional circumstances when the potential benefit outweighs the risk.



 HLA-B*5701-negative patients may develop a hypersensitivity reaction to abacavir; however, this occurs significantly less frequently than in HLA-B*5701-positive patients. Regardless of HLA-B*5701 status, permanently discontinue TRIZIVIR if hypersensitivity cannot be ruled out, even when other diagnoses are possible.



 Important information on signs and symptoms of hypersensitivity, as well as clinical management, is presented below.



  Signs and Symptoms of Hypersensitivity:  Hypersensitivity to abacavir is a multi-organ clinical syndrome usually characterized by a sign or symptom in 2 or more of the following groups.



 Group 1: Fever



 Group 2: Rash



 Group 3: Gastrointestinal (including nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, or abdominal pain)



 Group 4: Constitutional (including generalized malaise, fatigue, or achiness)



 Group 5: Respiratory (including dyspnea, cough, or pharyngitis)



 Hypersensitivity to abacavir following the presentation of a single sign or symptom has been reported infrequently.



 Hypersensitivity to abacavir was reported in approximately 8% of 2,670 subjects (n = 206) in 9 clinical trials (range: 2% to 9%) with enrollment from November 1999 to February 2002. Data on time to onset and symptoms of suspected hypersensitivity were collected on a detailed data collection module. The frequencies of symptoms are shown in Figure 1. Symptoms usually appeared within the first 6 weeks of treatment with abacavir, although the reaction may occur at any time during therapy. Median time to onset was 9 days; 89% appeared within the first 6 weeks; 95% of subjects reported symptoms from 2 or more of the 5 groups listed above.



 A trial with ZIAGEN  (r)  (abacavir sulfate) used double-blind ascertainment of suspected hypersensitivity reactions. During the blinded portion of the trial, suspected hypersensitivity to abacavir was reported by investigators in 9% of 324 subjects in the abacavir group and 3% of 325 subjects in the zidovudine group.



  Figure 1. Hypersensitivity-Related Symptoms Reported With &gt;=10% Frequency in Clinical Trials (n = 206 Subjects)  



 



 Other less common signs and symptoms of hypersensitivity include lethargy, myolysis, edema, abnormal chest x-ray findings (predominantly infiltrates, which can be localized), and paresthesia. Anaphylaxis, liver failure, renal failure, hypotension, adult respiratory distress syndrome, respiratory failure, and death have occurred in association with hypersensitivity reactions.



 Physical findings associated with hypersensitivity to abacavir in some subjects include lymphadenopathy, mucous membrane lesions (conjunctivitis and mouth ulcerations), and rash. The rash usually appears maculopapular or urticarial, but may be variable in appearance. There have been reports of erythema multiforme. Hypersensitivity reactions have occurred without rash.



 Laboratory abnormalities associated with hypersensitivity to abacavir in some subjects include elevated liver function tests, elevated creatinine phosphokinase, elevated creatinine, and lymphopenia.



  Clinical Management of Hypersensitivity:  Discontinue TRIZIVIR as soon as a hypersensitivity reaction is suspected. To minimize the risk of a life-threatening hypersensitivity reaction, permanently discontinue TRIZIVIR if hypersensitivity cannot be ruled out, even when other diagnoses are possible (e.g., acute onset respiratory diseases such as pneumonia, bronchitis, pharyngitis, or influenza; gastroenteritis; or reactions to other medications).



 Following a hypersensitivity reaction to abacavir, NEVER restart TRIZIVIR or any other abacavir-containing product because more severe symptoms can occur within hours and may include life-threatening hypotension and death.



 When therapy with TRIZIVIR has been discontinued for reasons other than symptoms of a hypersensitivity reaction, and if reinitiation of abacavir is under consideration, carefully evaluate the reason for discontinuation to ensure that the patient did not have symptoms of a hypersensitivity reaction. If the patient is of unknown HLA-B*5701 status, screening for the allele is recommended prior to reinitiation of TRIZIVIR.



 If hypersensitivity cannot be ruled out, DO NOT reintroduce TRIZIVIR or any other abacavir-containing product. Even in the absence of the HLA-B*5701 allele, it is important to permanently discontinue abacavir and not rechallenge with abacavir if a hypersensitivity reaction cannot be ruled out on clinical grounds, due to the potential for a severe or even fatal reaction.



 If symptoms consistent with hypersensitivity are not identified, reintroduction can be undertaken with continued monitoring for symptoms of a hypersensitivity reaction. Make patients aware that a hypersensitivity reaction can occur with reintroduction of abacavir and that abacavir reintroduction needs to be undertaken only if medical care can be readily accessed by the patient or others.



  Risk Factor:   HLA-B*5701 Allele:  Trials have shown that carriage of the HLA-B*5701 allele is associated with a significantly increased risk of a hypersensitivity reaction to abacavir.



 CNA106030 (PREDICT-1), a randomized, double-blind trial, evaluated the clinical utility of prospective HLA-B*5701 screening on the incidence of abacavir hypersensitivity reaction in abacavir-naive HIV-1-infected adults (n = 1,650). In this trial, use of pre-therapy screening for the HLA-B*5701 allele and exclusion of subjects with this allele reduced the incidence of clinically suspected abacavir hypersensitivity reactions from 7.8% (66/847) to 3.4% (27/803). Based on this trial, it is estimated that 61% of patients with the HLA-B*5701 allele will develop a clinically suspected hypersensitivity reaction during the course of abacavir treatment compared with 4% of patients who do not have the HLA-B*5701 allele.



 Screening for carriage of the HLA-B*5701 allele is recommended prior to initiating treatment with abacavir. Screening is also recommended prior to reinitiation of abacavir in patients of unknown HLA-B*5701 status who have previously tolerated abacavir. For HLA-B*5701-positive patients, initiating or reinitiating treatment with an abacavir-containing regimen is not recommended and should be considered only with close medical supervision and under exceptional circumstances where potential benefit outweighs the risk.



 Skin patch testing is used as a research tool and should not be used to aid in the clinical diagnosis of abacavir hypersensitivity.



 In any patient treated with abacavir, the clinical diagnosis of hypersensitivity reaction must remain the basis of clinical decision-making. Even in the absence of the HLA-B*5701 allele, it is important to permanently discontinue abacavir and not rechallenge with abacavir if a hypersensitivity reaction cannot be ruled out on clinical grounds, due to the potential for a severe or even fatal reaction.



  Figure 1.    5.2 Hematologic Toxicity/Bone Marrow Suppression



  Zidovudine, a component of TRIZIVIR, has been associated with hematologic toxicity including neutropenia and anemia, particularly in patients with advanced HIV-1 disease. TRIZIVIR should be used with caution in patients who have bone marrow compromise evidenced by granulocyte count less than 1,000 cells/mm  3  or hemoglobin less than 9.5 g/dL.



 Frequent blood counts are strongly recommended in patients with advanced HIV-1 disease who are treated with TRIZIVIR. Periodic blood counts are recommended for other HIV-1-infected patients. If anemia or neutropenia develops, dosage interruption may be needed.



    5.3 Myopathy



  Myopathy and myositis, with pathological changes similar to that produced by HIV-1 disease, have been associated with prolonged use of zidovudine, and therefore may occur with therapy with TRIZIVIR.



    5.4 Lactic Acidosis/Hepatomegaly With Steatosis



  Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogues alone or in combination, including abacavir, lamivudine, zidovudine, and other antiretrovirals. A majority of these cases have been in women. Obesity and prolonged nucleoside exposure may be risk factors. Particular caution should be exercised when administering TRIZIVIR to any patient with known risk factors for liver disease; however, cases have also been reported in patients with no known risk factors. Treatment with TRIZIVIR should be suspended in any patient who develops clinical or laboratory findings suggestive of lactic acidosis or pronounced hepatotoxicity (which may include hepatomegaly and steatosis even in the absence of marked transaminase elevations).



    5.5 Patients With HIV-1 and Hepatitis B Virus Co-infection



   Posttreatment Exacerbations of Hepatitis:  In clinical trials in non-HIV-1-infected subjects treated with lamivudine for chronic HBV, clinical and laboratory evidence of exacerbations of hepatitis have occurred after discontinuation of lamivudine. These exacerbations have been detected primarily by serum ALT elevations in addition to re-emergence of hepatitis B viral DNA (HBV DNA). Although most events appear to have been self-limited, fatalities have been reported in some cases. Similar events have been reported from post-marketing experience after changes from lamivudine-containing HIV-1 treatment regimens to non-lamivudine-containing regimens in patients infected with both HIV-1 and HBV. The causal relationship to discontinuation of lamivudine treatment is unknown. Patients should be closely monitored with both clinical and laboratory follow-up for at least several months after stopping treatment. There is insufficient evidence to determine whether reinitiation of lamivudine alters the course of posttreatment exacerbations of hepatitis.



  Emergence of Lamivudine-Resistant HBV:  Safety and efficacy of lamivudine have not been established for treatment of chronic hepatitis B in subjects dually infected with HIV-1 and HBV. In non-HIV-infected subjects treated with lamivudine for chronic hepatitis B, emergence of lamivudine-resistant HBV has been detected and has been associated with diminished treatment response (see full prescribing information for EPIVIR-HBV  (r)  [lamivudine] for additional information). Emergence of hepatitis B virus variants associated with resistance to lamivudine has also been reported in HIV-1-infected subjects who have received lamivudine-containing antiretroviral regimens in the presence of concurrent infection with hepatitis B virus.



    5.6 Use With Interferon- and Ribavirin-Based Regimens



  In vitro studies have shown ribavirin can reduce the phosphorylation of pyrimidine nucleoside analogues such as lamivudine and zidovudine. Although no evidence of a pharmacokinetic or pharmacodynamic interaction (e.g., loss of HIV-1/HCV virologic suppression) was seen when ribavirin was coadministered with lamivudine or zidovudine in HIV-1/HCV co-infected subjects [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)]  , hepatic decompensation (some fatal) has occurred in HIV-1/HCV co-infected subjects receiving combination antiretroviral therapy for HIV-1 and interferon alfa with or without ribavirin. Patients receiving interferon alfa with or without ribavirin and TRIZIVIR should be closely monitored for treatment-associated toxicities, especially hepatic decompensation, neutropenia, and anemia. Discontinuation of TRIZIVIR should be considered as medically appropriate. Dose reduction or discontinuation of interferon alfa, ribavirin, or both should also be considered if worsening clinical toxicities are observed, including hepatic decompensation (e.g., Child-Pugh greater than 6) (see the complete prescribing information for interferon and ribavirin).



 Exacerbation of anemia has been reported in HIV-1/HCV co-infected patients receiving ribavirin and zidovudine. Coadministration of ribavirin and TRIZIVIR is not advised.



    5.7 Immune Reconstitution Syndrome



  Immune reconstitution syndrome has been reported in patients treated with combination antiretroviral therapy, including TRIZIVIR. During the initial phase of combination antiretroviral treatment, patients whose immune systems respond may develop an inflammatory response to indolent or residual opportunistic infections (such as Mycobacterium avium  infection, cytomegalovirus, Pneumocystis jirovecii  pneumonia [PCP], or tuberculosis), which may necessitate further evaluation and treatment.



 Autoimmune disorders (such as Graves' disease, polymyositis, and Guillain-Barre syndrome) have also been reported to occur in the setting of immune reconstitution; however, the time to onset is more variable, and can occur many months after initiation of treatment.



    5.8 Fat Redistribution



  Redistribution/accumulation of body fat including central obesity, dorsocervical fat enlargement (buffalo hump), peripheral wasting, facial wasting, breast enlargement, and "cushingoid appearance" have been observed in patients receiving antiretroviral therapy. The mechanism and long-term consequences of these events are currently unknown. A causal relationship has not been established.



    5.9 Myocardial Infarction



  In a published prospective, observational, epidemiological trial designed to investigate the rate of myocardial infarction in patients on combination antiretroviral therapy, the use of abacavir within the previous 6 months was correlated with an increased risk of myocardial infarction (MI).  1  In a sponsor-conducted pooled analysis of clinical trials, no excess risk of myocardial infarction was observed in abacavir-treated subjects as compared with control subjects. In totality, the available data from the observational cohort and from clinical trials are inconclusive.



 As a precaution, the underlying risk of coronary heart disease should be considered when prescribing antiretroviral therapies, including abacavir, and action taken to minimize all modifiable risk factors (e.g., hypertension, hyperlipidemia, diabetes mellitus, smoking).



    5.10 Therapy Experienced Patients



  In clinical trials, subjects with prolonged prior nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor (NRTI) exposure or who had HIV-1 isolates that contained multiple mutations conferring resistance to NRTIs had limited response to abacavir. The potential for cross-resistance between abacavir and other NRTIs should be considered when choosing new therapeutic regimens in therapy-experienced patients [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.4)].  



    5.11 Use With Other Abacavir-, Lamivudine-, Zidovudine-, and/or Emtricitabine-Containing Products



  TRIZIVIR is a fixed-dose combination of abacavir, lamivudine, and zidovudine and is intended only for patients whose regimen would otherwise include these 3 components. TRIZIVIR should not be administered concomitantly with other abacavir-, lamivudine-, or zidovudine-containing products including ZIAGEN (abacavir sulfate) Tablets and Oral Solution, EPIVIR  (r)  (lamivudine) Tablets and Oral Solution, EPIVIR-HBV (lamivudine) Tablets and Oral Solution, RETROVIR  (r)  (zidovudine) Tablets, Capsules, Syrup, and IV Infusion, COMBIVIR  (r)  (lamivudine and zidovudine) Tablets, EPZICOM  (r)  (abacavir sulfate and lamivudine) Tablets; or emtricitabine-containing products, including ATRIPLA  (r)  (efavirenz/emtricitabine/tenofovir disoproxil fumarate) Tablets, EMTRIVA  (r)  (emtricitabine) Capsules and Oral Solution, TRUVADA  (r)  (emtricitabine/tenofovir disoproxil fumarate) Tablets, or COMPLERA  (r)  (emtricitabine/rilpirivine/tenofovir disoproxil fumarate) Tablets.



 The complete prescribing information for all agents being considered for use with TRIZIVIR should be consulted before combination therapy with TRIZIVIR is initiated.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
