<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="true" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (occurring in more than 1% of the study population) were burning, tape irritation, persistent reactions, erythema, and hyper/hypo pigmentation. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact SmartPractice at 1-800-878-3837 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice. Table 1 presents a summary of ten clinical trials conducted in North America and Europe using T.R.U.E. TEST.



 Table 1- Overview of Clinical Studies using T.R.U.E. TEST Among Adults 18 Years of Age and Older 
 Clinical Study Overview    Study 1     Study 2  Study 3  Study 4  Study 5  Study 6  Study 7  Study 8  Study 9  Study 10   Total    
      N                       127      121      119      50       130      128      200      235      49        9      1168     
  
 Age Range (years)     19-79       18-77    19-76    19-82    19-86    20-83    19-78    18-85    18-68    36-76    18-86    
 Sex (% female)      68%         68%      73%      72%      68%      63%      59%      71%      98%      78%      69%     
  Ethnicity    Caucasian      86%      88%      83%      92%      85%      88%      97%      91%      98%     100%      83%     
                 Black        9%       12%      11%      4%       13%      12%      0%       5%       0%       0%       9%      
                 Other        5%       1%       6%       4%       2%      0.8%      3%       4%       2%       0%       7%      
  Allergens   Nickel sulfate     X                 X        X                                            X                        
              Wool alcohols              X        X        X                                                                     
              Neomycin sulfate     X                 X        X                                            X                        
              Potassium dichromate     X                 X        X                                            X                        
               Caine Mix       X                 X        X                                            X                        
              Fragrance Mix     X                 X        X                                            X                        
               Colophony       X                 X        X                                            X                        
              Paraben Mix               X        X        X                                                                     
              Balsam of Peru     X                 X        X                                            X                        
              Ethylenediamine dihydrochloride     X                 X        X                                            X                        
              Cobalt dichloride     X                 X        X                                            X                        
              p-tert-Butylphenol formaldehyde resin              X        X        X                                                                     
              Epoxy resin      X                 X        X                                            X                        
               Carba mix                X        X        X                                                                     
              Black rubber mix              X        X        X                                                                     
              Cl+ Me- Isothiazolinone              X        X        X                                                                     
              Quaternium-15              X        X        X                                                     X               
              Methyldibromo glutaronitrile                                                                    X                                 
              p-Phenylenediamine     X                 X        X                                            X                        
              Formaldehyde                       X        X                                                                     
              Mercapto Mix              X        X        X                                                                     
               Thimerosal               X        X        X                                                                     
              Thiuram Mix      X                 X        X                                            X                        
              Diazolidinyl urea                                         X                                                            
              Quinoline Mix              X        X        X                                                                     
              Tixocortol-21-pivalate                                                  X        X                                          
              Gold Sodium Thiosulfate                                                                    X                                 
              Imidazolidinyl urea                                         X                                                            
               Budesonide                                                   X        X                                          
              Hydrocortisone-17-butyrate                                                           X        X                                 
              Mercaptobenzothiazole              X        X        X                                                                     
               Bacitracin                                                                     X                                 
              Parthenolide                                                                    X                                 
              Disperse blue 106                                                                    X                                 
                Bronopol                                                                      X                                 
                       Adverse Reactions - Studies in Subjects 18 Years of Age and Older  
 

 The most common adverse reactions (occurring in more than 1% of the study population) were burning, tape irritation, persistent reactions, erythema, and hyper/hypo pigmentation. Table 2 summarizes the adverse reactions recorded in ten clinical studies. Subjects' adverse reactions were recorded on case report forms by study personnel. Adverse reactions were recorded during subject follow-up visits, which varied between 24 and/or 96 hours and/or Day 21 [see    Clinical Studies (14)    ].



 Table 2- Summary of Adverse Reactions Reported Among Adult Subjects 18 Years of Age and Older 
               Study 1   Study 2   Study 3   Study 4   Study 5   Study 6   Study 7   Study 8   Study 9   Study 10  Total (%)   
      N          127       121       119        50       130       128       200       235        49        9        1168     
  
 ND=Not Done    
  
   Burning        12        6         9         16        50        51        25       123        5         0      297 (25.4)   
 Tape Irritation     4         0         2         1         22        51        25        79        0         0      184 (15.8)   
 Persistent Reactions     11        0         0         8         2         16        1         41        0         0      79 (6.8)   
   Erythema       0         3         27        2         0         3         0         32        0         0      67 (5.7)   
 Hyper/Hypopigmentation     11        2         8         6         1         7         0         14        8         0      57 (4.9)   
 Sensitization (possible)     0         2         5         1         0         0         0         ND        ND        ND     8 (0.9)    
 Late Reaction     0         0         0         1         0         0         0         7         0         0      8 (0.7)    
   Scarring       0         0         2         ND        ND        ND        ND        ND        ND        ND     2 (0.5)    
 Ectopic Flare     ND        ND        ND        ND        1         0         1         ND        ND        ND      2(0.4)    
                      Panel Adhesion:  Problems with panel adhesion were observed during some of the clinical studies. Poor panel adhesion was defined as any panel that fell off prior to the 48 hour removal time, any test panel that was not in good contact with the skin, or if one or more of the patch test allergens were not in good contact with the skin as evidenced at the time of panel removal, 48 hours. If the panel fell off the back prior to the 48-hour removal time frame, the subject was excluded from the efficacy calculations (sensitivity and specificity) but not from the safety analysis. Over all studies, poor panel adhesion occurred 49 times (4.2%) (Table 3). In study 2, the poor adhesion was attributed to the particular lot of adhesive used to manufacture the clinical test tape.
 

 Table 3- Incidence and Proportion of Poor Panel Adhesion Among Subjects 18 Years of Age and Older 
            Study 1   Study 2   Study 3   Study 4   Study 5   Study 6   Study 7   Study 8    Study 9   Study 10     Total     
     N        127       121       119        50       130       128       200       235        49          9        1168      
  
 Poor Adhesion (%)  0 (0.0)   14 (11.6)  2 (1.7)   5 (10.0)  1 (0.8)   1 (0.8)   0 (0.0)   10 (4.3)  12 (23.5)   0 (0.0)   49 (4.2)    
                    6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following additional adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of T.R.U.E. TEST in adults. Because these reactions are continuously reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to T.R.U.E. TEST exposure.



 *  Acute allergic reactions [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *  Extreme positive reactions [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ] 
 *  Excited skin syndrome (Angry back) [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   ] 
 *  Irritant contact dermatitis [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.6)   ] 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Acute allergic reactions, including anaphylaxis, may occur. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Sensitization to one or more of the allergens may occur with initial or repeat testing. (  5.2  ,  5.9  ) 
 *  Extreme positive reactions, excited skin syndrome, tape reactions, irritant contact dermatitis, persistent reactions, and late reactions at the test site may occur. (  5.3  ,  5.4  ,  5.5  ,  5.6  ,  5.7  ,  5.8  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Acute Allergic Reactions



  Acute allergic reactions, including anaphylaxis, may occur. Appropriate medical treatment must be available in case of an acute allergic reaction, including anaphylaxis, following the application of T.R.U.E. TEST. If a severe allergic reaction occurs, remove the T.R.U.E. TEST panel(s) and initiate treatment. Immediate contact urticaria may present within minutes to an hour after application in patients who are pre-sensitized to some allergens and may be local or generalized. Patients may be advised to remove the panels themselves if they experience systemic symptoms [see   Patient Counseling Information (17)    ].



    5.2 Sensitization



  A negative patch test reaction, followed by a positive reaction 10 to 20 days after panel application, may indicate active sensitization. Active sensitization is confirmed upon retesting with a positive reaction occurring at the 72 and/or the 96 hour reading. If patients undergo a second series of patch tests immediately, select a new test site for T.R.U.E. TEST application. Alternatively, the same site may be retested after a 3-week clearing period, provided the site remains free of conditions that might affect test results [see   Dosage and Administration (2.1)    ]. The safety and effectiveness of repetitive testing with T.R.U.E. TEST is unknown [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.9)    ].



    5.3 Extreme Positive Reactions



  Extreme positive (+++) reactions that are bullous or ulcerative with pronounced erythema, infiltration, and coalescing vesicles may present in extremely sensitive patients [see   Dosage and Administration (2.3)    ].



    5.4 Excited Skin Syndrome (Angry Back)



  Excited skin syndrome is a regional state of skin hyper-reactivity caused by the presence of a strong positive reaction which may result in other patch test sites to become reactive.



    5.5 Tape Reactions



  Reactions to the T.R.U.E. TEST tape or adhesive may occur. T.R.U.E. TEST panel tape and the individual patches are composed of polyester. The adhesive used in the panels is acrylate-based and processed to remove free monomers that may be allergenic [see   Description (11)    ].



    5.6 Irritant Contact Dermatitis



  Patients may experience irritant contact dermatitis upon exposure to any of the allergens contained within T.R.U.E. TEST that cause direct damage to the skin at the test site. Recurrence of an irritant response is not limited to exposure to the specific substance, but may follow exposure to any chemical irritants.



    5.7 Persistent Reactions



  Positive reactions may persist from 7 days to months after panel application.



    5.8 Late Reactions



  Late positive reactions may occur 7 to 10 days after application of the panels.



    5.9 Repeat Testing



  The safety and efficacy of repetitive testing with T.R.U.E. TEST is unknown. Sensitization or increased reactivity to one or more of the allergens may occur [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ]. If patients undergo a second series of patch tests immediately, select a new test site for T.R.U.E. TEST application. Alternatively, the same site may be retested after a 3-week clearing period, provided the site remains free of conditions that might affect test results [see   Dosage and Administration (2.1)    ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
