<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="trumenba" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  In clinical studies, the most common solicited adverse reactions were pain at the injection site (&gt;=85%), fatigue (&gt;=40%), headache (&gt;=35%), muscle pain (&gt;=30%), and chills (&gt;=15%).



   EXCERPT:   The most common solicited adverse reactions were pain at the injection site (&gt;=85%), fatigue (&gt;=40%), headache (&gt;=35%), muscle pain (&gt;=30%), and chills (&gt;=15%). (  6.1  )  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer, Inc. at 1-800-438-1985 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or http://vaers.hhs.gov.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The safety of Trumenba was evaluated in 4,282 subjects 11 through 25 years of age in 7 clinical studies (4 randomized controlled and 3 supportive non-controlled studies) conducted in the US, Europe, and Australia. A total of 4,250 adolescents (11 through 18 years of age) and 32 adults (19 through 25 years of age) received at least one dose of Trumenba. A total of 1,004 subjects 11 through 25 years of age in the control groups received saline placebo and/or one of the following vaccines: Human Papillomavirus Quadrivalent (Types 6, 11, 16, and 18) Vaccine, Recombinant [HPV4]; a non-US licensed tetanus toxoid, reduced diphtheria toxoid, acellular pertussis and inactivated polio virus vaccine; or Tetanus Toxoid, Reduced Diphtheria Toxoid and Acellular Pertussis Vaccine Adsorbed (Sanofi Pasteur Ltd.).



 The safety evaluation in the 7 studies included an assessment of: (1) solicited local and systemic reactions, and use of antipyretic medication after each vaccination in an electronic diary maintained by the subject or the subject's parent/legal guardian; and (2) spontaneous reports of adverse events (AEs), including serious adverse events (SAEs), throughout the study (day of vaccination through one month or 6 months after the last vaccination, depending on the study and safety parameter).



 In controlled studies, demographic characteristics were generally similar with regard to gender, race, and ethnicity among subjects who received Trumenba and those who received control. Overall, across the 7 studies, among the subjects who received Trumenba, 56.1% were male and 44.0% were female, and the majority were White (90.8%) and non-Hispanic/non-Latino (91.4%).



     Solicited Local and Systemic Adverse Reactions  



 In a randomized, active-controlled, observer-blinded, multicenter trial in the US, 1,982 adolescents 11 to &lt;18 years of age received Trumenba at 0-, 2-, and 6-months. Subjects were randomized to 1 of 3 groups: Trumenba + HPV4 (Group 1), Trumenba + Saline (Group 2), Saline + HPV4 (Group 3). 81.6% of subjects were White, 13% were Black or African-American, 1.2% were Asian and 17.4% were Hispanic or Latino. Overall, 66.5% of subjects were male, 65.9% of participants were 11 to &lt;=14 years age and 34.1% were 15 to &lt;18 years of age.



 Local adverse reactions at the Trumenba injection site (Groups 1 and 2), and saline injection site (Group 3) were assessed in this study. Table 1 presents the percentage and severity of reported local adverse reactions within 7 days following each dose of Trumenba (Groups 1 and 2 combined) or saline control (Group 3).



 Local adverse reactions were reported more frequently following Trumenba compared to saline (see  Table 1  ).



 Table 1: Percentage of Subjects 11 to &lt;18 Years of Age Reporting Local Adverse Reactions Within 7 Days After Each VaccinationNational Clinical Trial (NCT) number NCT01461993 
                        Trumenba          Saline        
 Local Reaction       Dose 1N=1970     Dose 2N=1826     Dose 3N=1688      Dose 1N=496    Dose 2N=468  Dose 3N=438   
  
 Pain                                  
   Any                    92.8             86.1             84.5             36.9           29.1         23.3       
   Mild                   42.5             49.9             44.1             33.1           24.6         20.8       
   Moderate               42.1             31.6             34.7              3.6            4.5          2.3       
   Severe                  8.2              4.6              5.7              0.2            0.0          0.2       
 Redness                               
   Any                    20.4             14.9             15.8              1.2            1.7          1.1       
   Mild                    9.0              6.6              7.3              1.0            1.7          0.9       
   Moderate                9.1              7.0              7.0              0.2            0.0          0.2       
   Severe                  2.2              1.3              1.4              0.0            0.0          0.0       
 Swelling                              
   Any                    21.6             18.2             20.1              2.8            2.8          1.8       
   Mild                   12.5             10.8             11.7              1.8            2.1          1.4       
   Moderate                8.5              7.1              8.2              1.0            0.6          0.5       
   Severe                  0.5              0.3              0.2              0.0            0.0          0.0       
             Table 2 presents the percentage of subjects who had at least one injection and who also reported a solicited systemic adverse reaction within 7 days of vaccination, by study group. These reactions resolved within 8 days in 90% of subjects. Fever (temperature &gt;=38.0 degrees C) resolved within 3 days in 84% of subjects.
 

 Table 2: Percentage of Subjects 11 to &lt;18 Years of Age Reporting Systemic Adverse Reactions and Use of Antipyretic Medications Within 7 Days After Each VaccinationNCT01461993 
                       Group 1    Group 2    Group 3    
                      Trumenba + HPV4  Trumenba + Saline  Saline + HPV4   
                      Dose 1N=985  Dose 2N=919  Dose 3N=842  Dose 1N=985  Dose 2N=907  Dose 3N=846  Dose 1N=496  Dose 2N=468  Dose 3N=438   
 Systemic Reactions               
  
 Fever (&gt;=38.0 degrees C)              
   &gt;=38.0 degrees C      8.3        2.1        2.1        6.4        1.3        1.1        0.8        0.9        0.7      
   38.0 degrees  to &lt;38.5 degrees C     4.9        1.2        1.1        3.7        1.1        0.8        0.4        0.4        0.2      
   38.5 degrees  to &lt;39.0 degrees C     2.5        0.4        0.6        1.5        0.1        0.1        0.0        0.2        0.0      
   39.0 degrees  to &lt;=40.0 degrees C     0.6        0.3        0.4        1.0        0.1        0.1        0.2        0.2        0.2      
 Vomiting                         
   Any  ,                7.8        2.8        2.4        7.4        2.4        2.5        3.4        3.0        1.6      
   Mild                  5.8        2.1        2.1        5.3        1.4        1.8        3.2        2.4        0.9      
   Moderate              1.9        0.7        0.2        1.7        0.9        0.5        0.2        0.6        0.7      
   Severe                0.0        0.0        0.0        0.0        0.0        0.0        0.0        0.0        0.0      
 Diarrhea                         
   Any                  14.5       10.9        9.3       15.2        9.3        8.9       15.5       11.1        9.4      
   Mild                 12.6        9.1        7.7       13.3        7.5        7.3       12.5        9.8        7.8      
   Moderate              1.7        1.6        1.1        1.7        1.8        1.2        2.6        1.3        1.6      
   Severe                0.2        0.1        0.5        0.2        0.0        0.4        0.4        0.0        0.0      
 Headache                         
   Any                  56.9       44.8       41.0       54.8       40.8       34.8       43.1       36.5       27.4      
   Mild                 37.7       32.9       30.0       36.1       28.3       24.0       33.3       25.4       21.0      
   Moderate             17.8       11.1       10.5       16.5       10.7       10.2        9.3       10.5        6.2      
   Severe                1.4        0.9        0.5        2.1        1.8        0.6        0.6        0.6        0.2      
 Fatigue                          
   Any                  64.4       48.9       44.1       62.4       44.8       42.9       50.6       34.4       31.5      
   Mild                 39.5       33.4       28.4       39.1       30.8       30.9       37.1       25.6       24.2      
   Moderate             20.6       12.8       14.3       19.7       12.3       10.9       13.1        7.9        7.1      
   Severe                4.3        2.6        1.4        3.7        1.7        1.2        0.4        0.9        0.2      
 Chills                           
   Any                  30.3       19.2       17.5       29.0       17.4       15.6       16.7       12.0        8.2      
   Mild                 21.5       13.8       13.1       22.0       13.6       12.5       13.9        9.6        7.1      
   Moderate              7.4        4.1        3.7        5.6        2.9        3.0        2.6        2.1        1.1      
   Severe                1.3        1.2        0.7        1.4        1.0        0.1        0.2        0.2        0.0      
 Muscle pain (other than muscle pain at the injection site)              
   Any                  41.1       36.6       35.3       42.4       30.5       30.9       28.6       24.6       20.8      
   Mild                 24.7       25.0       22.2       25.7       19.8       21.3       23.4       19.4       16.2      
   Moderate             13.3       10.2       11.2       13.9        9.3        8.5        4.6        4.9        3.9      
   Severe                3.1        1.3        1.9        2.8        1.4        1.1        0.6        0.2        0.7      
 Joint pain                       
   Any                  21.6       15.5       19.2       21.6       15.4       17.0       13.7       12.2       11.0      
   Mild                 15.7       11.1       13.4       14.7       11.8       13.7       10.9        9.8        8.7      
   Moderate              5.0        3.8        4.9        5.9        3.0        3.1        2.8        2.4        1.6      
   Severe                0.9        0.5        1.0        1.0        0.7        0.2        0.0        0.0        0.7      
 Use of Antipyretic medication    26.3       16.1       16.5       27.0       17.5       17.0       13.3       13.9        6.6      
                    Serious Adverse Events  
 

 Overall in clinical studies in which 4282 subjects 11 through 25 years of age received at least one dose of Trumenba, serious adverse events were reported in 88 (2.0%) subjects. Among the 4 controlled studies (Trumenba N=2557, control N=1004), serious adverse events were reported in 44 (1.7%) subjects who received Trumenba and 16 (1.6%) control subjects, for individuals who received at least one dose.



     Non-serious Adverse Events  



 Overall in clinical studies in which 4282 subjects 11 through 25 years of age received Trumenba, non-serious AEs within 30 days after any dose were reported in 1049 (24.5%) subjects. Among the 4 controlled studies (Trumenba N=2557, control N=1004), AEs that occurred within 30 days of vaccination were reported in 739 (28.9%) subjects who received Trumenba and 313 (31.2%) subjects in the control group, for individuals who received at least one dose. AEs that occurred at a frequency of at least 2% and were more frequently observed in subjects who received Trumenba than subjects in the control group were injection site pain and headache.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   5.1 Management of Allergic Reactions



  Epinephrine and other appropriate agents used to manage immediate allergic reactions must be immediately available should an acute anaphylactic reaction occur following administration of Trumenba.



    5.2 Altered Immunocompetence



  Individuals with altered immunocompetence may have reduced immune responses to Trumenba.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
