<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="truvada" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Lactic Acidosis/Severe Hepatomegaly with Steatosis [see  Boxed Warning  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ] . 
 *  Severe Acute Exacerbations of hepatitis B [see  Boxed Warning  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ] . 
 *  New Onset or Worsening Renal Impairment [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ] . 
 *  Bone Effects of Tenofovir DF [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ] . 
 *  Immune Reconstitution Syndrome [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ] . 
      EXCERPT:   In HIV-1 infected patients, the most common adverse reactions (incidence greater than or equal to 10%) are diarrhea, nausea, fatigue, headache, dizziness, depression, insomnia, abnormal dreams, and rash. (  6.1  )
 

 In HIV-1 uninfected individuals in PrEP trials, adverse reactions that were reported by more than 2% of TRUVADA subjects and more frequently than by placebo subjects were headache, abdominal pain and weight decreased. (  6.2  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Gilead Sciences, Inc. at 1-800-445-3235 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Adverse Reactions from Clinical Trials Experience in HIV-1 Infected Subjects

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Clinical Trials in Adult Subjects  



 The most common adverse reactions (incidence greater than or equal to 10%, any severity) occurring in Study 934, an active-controlled clinical trial of efavirenz, emtricitabine, and tenofovir disoproxil fumarate, include diarrhea, nausea, fatigue, headache, dizziness, depression, insomnia, abnormal dreams, and rash. See also  Table 3  for the frequency of treatment-emergent adverse reactions (Grades 2-4) occurring in greater than or equal to 5% of subjects treated in any treatment group in this trial.



 Skin discoloration, manifested by hyperpigmentation on the palms and/or soles, was generally mild and asymptomatic. The mechanism and clinical significance are unknown.



     Study 934 - Treatment Emergent Adverse Reactions:  In Study 934, 511 antiretroviral-naive subjects received either VIREAD + EMTRIVA administered in combination with efavirenz (N=257) or zidovudine/lamivudine administered in combination with efavirenz (N=254) for 144 weeks. Subjects had a mean age of 40 years (range 20 to 73 years) and were predominantly male (88%). Overall, 65% were White, 17% were Black, and 13% were Hispanic. Adverse reactions observed in this trial were generally consistent with those seen in other trials in treatment-experienced or treatment-naive subjects receiving VIREAD and/or EMTRIVA (Table 3).



 Table 3 Selected Treatment-Emergent Adverse ReactionsFrequencies of adverse reactions are based on all treatment-emergent adverse events, regardless of relationship to study drug. (Grades 2-4) Reported in &gt;=5% in Any Treatment Group in Study 934 (0-144 Weeks) 
                                                    FTC+TDF+EFV                     AZT/3TC+EFV             
                                                       N=257                           N=254                
  
 Gastrointestinal Disorder                                                                                  
   Diarrhea                                              9%                              5%                 
   Nausea                                                9%                              7%                 
   Vomiting                                              2%                              5%                 
 General Disorders and Administration Site Condition                                                                   
   Fatigue                                               9%                              8%                 
 Infections and Infestations                                                                                
   Sinusitis                                             8%                              4%                 
   Upper respiratory tract infections                    8%                              5%                 
   Nasopharyngitis                                       5%                              3%                 
 Nervous System Disorders                                                                                   
   Headache                                              6%                              5%                 
   Dizziness                                             8%                              7%                 
 Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                      
   Depression                                            9%                              7%                 
   Insomnia                                              5%                              7%                 
 Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                                                                     
   Rash event                                            7%                              9%                 
             Laboratory Abnormalities:  Laboratory abnormalities observed in this trial were generally consistent with those seen in other trials of VIREAD and/or EMTRIVA (Table 4).
 

 Table 4 Significant Laboratory Abnormalities Reported in &gt;=1% of Subjects in Any Treatment Group in Study 934 (0-144 Weeks) 
                                                    FTC+TDF+EFV                     AZT/3TC+EFV             
                                                       N=257                           N=254                
  
 Any &gt;= Grade 3 Laboratory Abnormality                  30%                             26%                 
 Fasting Cholesterol (&gt;240 mg/dL)                       22%                             24%                 
 Creatine Kinase(M: &gt;990 U/L)(F: &gt;845 U/L)                9%                              7%                 
 Serum Amylase (&gt;175 U/L)                                8%                              4%                 
 Alkaline Phosphatase (&gt;550 U/L)                         1%                              0%                 
 AST(M: &gt;180 U/L)(F: &gt;170 U/L)                           3%                              3%                 
 ALT(M: &gt;215 U/L)(F: &gt;170 U/L)                           2%                              3%                 
 Hemoglobin (&lt;8.0 mg/dL)                                 0%                              4%                 
 Hyperglycemia (&gt;250 mg/dL)                              2%                              1%                 
 Hematuria (&gt;75 RBC/HPF)                                 3%                              2%                 
 Glycosuria (&gt;=3+)                                      &lt;1%                              1%                 
 Neutrophils (&lt;750/mm  3  )                              3%                              5%                 
 Fasting Triglycerides (&gt;750 mg/dL)                      4%                              2%                 
         In addition to the events described above for Study 934, other adverse reactions that occurred in at least 5% of subjects receiving EMTRIVA or VIREAD with other antiretroviral agents in clinical trials include anxiety, arthralgia, increased cough, dyspepsia, fever, myalgia, pain, abdominal pain, back pain, paresthesia, peripheral neuropathy (including peripheral neuritis and neuropathy), pneumonia, and rhinitis.
 

 In addition to the laboratory abnormalities described above for Study 934, Grades 3-4 laboratory abnormalities of increased bilirubin (&gt;2.5 * ULN), increased pancreatic amylase (&gt;2.0 * ULN), increased or decreased serum glucose (&lt;40 or &gt;250 mg/dL), and increased serum lipase (&gt;2.0 * ULN) occurred in up to 3% of subjects treated with EMTRIVA or VIREAD with other antiretroviral agents in clinical trials.



     Clinical Trials in Pediatric Subjects  



     Emtricitabine:  In addition to the adverse reactions reported in adults, anemia and hyperpigmentation were observed in 7% and 32%, respectively, of pediatric subjects (3 months to less than 18 years of age) who received treatment with EMTRIVA in the larger of two open-label, uncontrolled pediatric trials (N=116). For additional information, consult the EMTRIVA prescribing information.



     Tenofovir Disoproxil Fumarate:  In pediatric clinical trials (Studies 352 and 321) conducted in 184 HIV-1 infected subjects 2 to less than 18 years of age, the adverse reactions observed in pediatric subjects who received treatment with VIREAD were consistent with those observed in clinical trials of VIREAD in adults.



 Eighty-nine pediatric subjects (2 to less than 12 years of age) received VIREAD in Study 352 for a median exposure of 104 weeks. Of these, 4 subjects discontinued from the trial due to adverse reactions consistent with proximal renal tubulopathy. Three of these 4 subjects presented with hypophosphatemia and also had decreases in total body or spine BMD Z score  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ].  For additional information, consult the VIREAD prescribing information.



   6.2 Adverse Reactions from Clinical Trial Experience in HIV-1 Uninfected Adult Subjects

  No new adverse reactions to TRUVADA were identified from two randomized placebo-controlled clinical trials (iPrEx, Partners PrEP), in which 2,830 HIV-1 uninfected adults received TRUVADA once daily for pre-exposure prophylaxis. Subjects were followed for a median of 71 weeks and 87 weeks, respectively. These trials enrolled HIV-negative individuals ranging in age from 18 to 67 years. The iPrEx trial enrolled only men or transgender women of Hispanic/Latino (72%), White (18%), Black (9%) and Asian (5%) race. The Partners PrEP trial enrolled both men (61-64% across treatment groups) and women in Kenya and Uganda. Table 5 provides a list of all adverse events that occurred in 2% or more of subjects in any treatment group in the iPrEx and Partners PrEP trials.



     Laboratory Abnormalities:  Table 6 provides a list of laboratory abnormalities observed in both trials. Six subjects in the TDF-containing arms of the Partners PrEP trial discontinued participation in the study due to an increase in blood creatinine compared with no discontinuations in the placebo group. One subject in the TRUVADA arm of the iPrEx trial discontinued from the study due to an increase in blood creatinine and another due to low phosphorous.



 In addition to the laboratory abnormalities described above, Grade 1 proteinuria (1+) occurred in 6% of subjects receiving TRUVADA in the iPrEx trial. Grades 2-3 proteinuria (2-4+) and glycosuria (3+) occurred in less than 1% of subjects treated with TRUVADA in the iPrEx trial and Partners PrEP trial.



 Table 5 Selected Adverse Events (All Grades) Reported in &gt;=2% in Any Treatment Group in the iPrEx Trial and Partners PrEP Trial 
                                         iPrEx Trial     Partners PrEP Trial   
                                       FTC/TDF(N=1251)   Placebo(N=1248)   FTC/TDF(N=1579)   Placebo(N=1584)    
  
 Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                                     
   Diarrhea                                   7%                8%                2%                3%          
   Abdominal pain                             4%                2%                -                 -           
 Infections and Infestations                                                                                    
   Pharyngitis                               13%               16%                -                 -           
   Urethritis                                 5%                7%                -                 -           
   Urinary tract infection                    2%                2%                5%                7%          
   Syphilis                                   6%                5%                -                 -           
   Secondary syphilis                         6%                4%                -                 -           
   Anogenital warts                           2%                3%                -                 -           
 Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders                                                                           
   Back pain                                  5%                5%                -                 -           
 Nervous System Disorders                                                                                       
   Headache                                   7%                6%                -                 -           
 Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                          
   Depression                                 6%                7%                -                 -           
   Anxiety                                    3%                3%                -                 -           
 Reproductive System and Breast Disorders                                                                           
   Genital ulceration                         2%                2%                2%                2%          
 Investigations                                                                                                 
   Weight decreased                           3%                2%                -                 -           
          Table 6 Laboratory Abnormalities (Highest Toxicity Grade) Reported for Each Subject in the iPrEx Trial and Partners PrEP Trial 
                                                 iPrEx Trial    Partners PrEP Trial   
                  Grade  FTC/TDF(N= 1251)      Placebo(N= 1248)  FTC/TDF(N=1579)  Placebo(N=1584)   
  
 Creatinine       1      (1.1-1.3 * ULN)           27 (2%)          21 (2%)          18 (1%)         12 (&lt;1%)       
                  2-4    (&gt; 1.4 * ULN)             5 (&lt;1%)          3 (&lt;1%)          2 (&lt;1%)          1 (&lt;1%)       
 Phosphorus       1      (2.5 - &lt;LLN mg/dL)        81 (7%)         110 (9%)            NR               NR          
 2-4              (&lt;2.0 mg/dL)  123 (10%)                101 (8%)         140 (9%)         136 (9%)       
 AST              1      (1.25-&lt;2.5 * ULN)        175 (14%)        175 (14%)         20 (1%)          25 (2%)       
 2-4              (&gt; 2.6 * ULN)  57 (5%)                   61 (5%)         10 (&lt;1%)          4 (&lt;1%)       
 ALT              1      (1.25-&lt;2.5 * ULN)        178 (14%)        194 (16%)         21 (1%)         13 (&lt;1%)       
 2-4              (&gt; 2.6 * ULN)  84 (7%)                   82 (7%)          4 (&lt;1%)          6 (&lt;1%)       
 Hemoglobin       1      (8.5 - 10 mg/dL)          49 (4%)          62 (5%)          56 (4%)          39 (2%)       
 2-4              (&lt;9.4 mg/dL)  13 (1%)                   19 (2%)          28 (2%)          39 (2%)       
 Neutrophils      1      (1000-1300/mm  3  )       23 (2%)          25 (2%)         208 (13%)        163 (10%)      
 2-4              (&lt;750/mm  3  )  7 (&lt;1%)                   7 (&lt;1%)          73 (5%)          56 (3%)       
                 Changes in Bone Mineral Density:  
 

 In clinical trials of HIV-1 uninfected individuals, decreases in BMD were observed. In the iPrEx trial, a substudy of 503 subjects found mean changes from baseline in BMD ranging from -0.4% to -1.0% across total hip, spine, femoral neck, and trochanter in the TRUVADA group compared with the placebo group, which returned toward baseline after discontinuation of treatment. Thirteen percent of subjects receiving TRUVADA versus 6% of subjects receiving placebo lost at least 5% of BMD at the spine during treatment. Bone fractures were reported in 1.7% of the TRUVADA group compared with 1.4% in the placebo group. No correlation between BMD and fractures was noted  [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]  . The Partners PrEP trial found similar fracture rates between treatment and placebo groups (0.8% and 0.6%, respectively). No BMD evaluations were performed during this trial  [see  Clinical Studies (14.3)  ]  .



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of VIREAD. No additional adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of EMTRIVA. Because postmarketing reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Immune System Disorders  allergic reaction, including angioedema



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders  lactic acidosis, hypokalemia, hypophosphatemia



   Respiratory, Thoracic  ,  and Mediastinal Disorders  dyspnea



   Gastrointestinal Disorders  pancreatitis, increased amylase, abdominal pain



   Hepatobiliary Disorders  hepatic steatosis, hepatitis, increased liver enzymes (most commonly AST, ALT gamma GT)



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  rash



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders  rhabdomyolysis, osteomalacia (manifested as bone pain and which may contribute to fractures), muscular weakness, myopathy



   Renal and Urinary Disorders  acute renal failure, renal failure, acute tubular necrosis, Fanconi syndrome, proximal renal tubulopathy, interstitial nephritis (including acute cases), nephrogenic diabetes insipidus, renal insufficiency, increased creatinine, proteinuria, polyuria



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions  asthenia



 The following adverse reactions, listed under the body system headings above, may occur as a consequence of proximal renal tubulopathy: rhabdomyolysis, osteomalacia, hypokalemia, muscular weakness, myopathy, hypophosphatemia.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS/SEVERE HEPATOMEGALY WITH STEATOSIS, POST TREATMENT ACUTE EXACERBATION OF HEPATITIS B, and RISK OF DRUG RESISTANCE WITH USE OF TRUVADA FOR PRE-EXPOSURE PROPHYLAXIS (PrEP) IN UNDIAGNOSED EARLY HIV-1 INFECTION

    WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS/SEVERE HEPATOMEGALY WITH STEATOSIS, POST TREATMENT ACUTE EXACERBATION OF HEPATITIS B, and RISK OF DRUG RESISTANCE WITH USE OF TRUVADA FOR PRE-EXPOSURE PROPHYLAXIS (PrEP) IN UNDIAGNOSED EARLY HIV-1 INFECTION  

    Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogs, including VIREAD, a component of TRUVADA, in combination with other antiretrovirals   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .  



   TRUVADA is not approved for the treatment of chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection and the safety and efficacy of TRUVADA have not been established in patients coinfected with HBV and HIV-1. Severe acute exacerbations of hepatitis B have been reported in patients who are coinfected with HBV and HIV-1 and have discontinued TRUVADA. Therefore, hepatic function should be monitored closely with both clinical and laboratory follow-up for at least several months in patients who are infected with HBV and discontinue TRUVADA. If appropriate, initiation of anti-hepatitis B therapy may be warranted   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  .  



   TRUVADA used for a PrEP indication must only be prescribed to individuals confirmed to be HIV-negative immediately prior to initiating and periodically (at least every 3 months) during use. Drug-resistant HIV-1 variants have been identified with use of TRUVADA for a PrEP indication following undetected acute HIV-1 infection. Do not initiate TRUVADA for a PrEP indication if signs or symptoms of acute HIV-1 infection are present unless negative infection status is confirmed   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  .   



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS/SEVERE HEPATOMEGALY WITH STEATOSIS,  POST-TREATMENT ACUTE EXACERBATION OF HEPATITIS B, and RISK OF DRUG RESISTANCE WITH USE OF TRUVADA FOR PRE-EXPOSURE PROPHYLAXIS (PrEP) IN UNDIAGNOSED EARLY HIV-1 INFECTION



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogs, including VIREAD, a component of TRUVADA. (5.1) 
 *  TRUVADA is not approved for the treatment of chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection. Severe acute exacerbations of hepatitis B have been reported in patients coinfected with HIV-1 and HBV who have discontinued TRUVADA. Therefore, hepatic function should be monitored closely in HBV-infected patients who discontinue TRUVADA. If appropriate, initiation of anti-hepatitis B therapy may be warranted. (5.2) 
 *  TRUVADA used for a PrEP indication must only be prescribed to individuals confirmed to be HIV-negative immediately prior to initial use and periodically during use. Drug-resistant HIV-1 variants have been identified with the use of TRUVADA for a PrEP indication following undetected acute HIV-1 infection. Do not initiate TRUVADA for a PrEP indication if signs or symptoms of acute HIV infection are present unless negative infection status is confirmed. (5.9) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS





   5.1 Lactic Acidosis/Severe Hepatomegaly with Steatosis



  Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogs, including VIREAD, a component of TRUVADA, in combination with other antiretrovirals. A majority of these cases have been in women. Obesity and prolonged nucleoside exposure may be risk factors. Particular caution should be exercised when administering nucleoside analogs to any patient or uninfected individual with known risk factors for liver disease; however, cases have also been reported in HIV-1 infected patients with no known risk factors. Treatment with TRUVADA should be suspended in any patient or uninfected individual who develops clinical or laboratory findings suggestive of lactic acidosis or pronounced hepatotoxicity (which may include hepatomegaly and steatosis even in the absence of marked transaminase elevations).



    5.2 HBV Infection



  It is recommended that all individuals be tested for the presence of chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) before initiating TRUVADA. TRUVADA is not approved for the treatment of chronic HBV infection and the safety and efficacy of TRUVADA have not been established in patients infected with HBV. Severe acute exacerbations of hepatitis B have been reported in patients who are coinfected with HBV and HIV-1 and have discontinued TRUVADA. In some patients infected with HBV and treated with EMTRIVA, the exacerbations of hepatitis B were associated with liver decompensation and liver failure. Patients who are infected with HBV should be closely monitored with both clinical and laboratory follow-up for at least several months after stopping treatment with TRUVADA. If appropriate, initiation of anti-hepatitis B therapy may be warranted. HBV-uninfected individuals should be offered vaccination.



    5.3 New Onset or Worsening Renal Impairment



  Emtricitabine and tenofovir are principally eliminated by the kidney. Renal impairment, including cases of acute renal failure and Fanconi syndrome (renal tubular injury with severe hypophosphatemia), has been reported with the use of VIREAD [see  Adverse Reactions (6.3)  ]  .



 It is recommended that estimated creatinine clearance be assessed in all individuals prior to initiating therapy and as clinically appropriate during therapy with TRUVADA. In patients at risk of renal dysfunction, including patients who have previously experienced renal events while receiving HEPSERA  (r)  , it is recommended that estimated creatinine clearance, serum phosphorus, urine glucose, and urine protein be assessed prior to initiation of TRUVADA, and periodically during TRUVADA therapy.



 TRUVADA should be avoided with concurrent or recent use of a nephrotoxic agent (e.g., high-dose or multiple non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs)) [see  Drug Interactions (7.4)  ]  . Cases of acute renal failure after initiation of high dose or multiple NSAIDs have been reported in HIV-infected patients with risk factors for renal dysfunction who appeared stable on tenofovir disoproxil fumarate (tenofovir DF). Some patients required hospitalization and renal replacement therapy. Alternatives to NSAIDs should be considered, if needed, in patients at risk for renal dysfunction.



 Persistent or worsening bone pain, pain in extremities, fractures and/or muscular pain or weakness may be manifestations of proximal renal tubulopathy and should prompt an evaluation of renal function in at-risk patients.



    Treatment of HIV-1 Infection  



 Dosing interval adjustment of TRUVADA and close monitoring of renal function are recommended in all patients with estimated creatinine clearance 30-49 mL/min [see  Dosage and Administration (2.4)  ]  . No safety or efficacy data are available in patients with renal impairment who received TRUVADA using these dosing guidelines, so the potential benefit of TRUVADA therapy should be assessed against the potential risk of renal toxicity. TRUVADA should not be administered to patients with estimated creatinine clearance below 30 mL/min or patients requiring hemodialysis.



    Pre-exposure Prophylaxis  



 TRUVADA for a PrEP indication should not be used if estimated creatinine clearance is less than 60 mL/min. If a decrease in estimated creatinine clearance is observed in uninfected individuals while using TRUVADA for PrEP, evaluate potential causes and re-assess potential risks and benefits of continued use [see  Dosage and Administration (2.4)  ]  .



    5.4 Coadministration with Other Products



   TRUVADA is a fixed-dose combination of emtricitabine and tenofovir disoproxil fumarate. Do not coadminister TRUVADA with other drugs containing emtricitabine or tenofovir disoproxil fumarate, or containing tenofovir alafenamide, including ATRIPLA, COMPLERA, EMTRIVA, GENVOYA, ODEFSEY, STRIBILD, or VIREAD. Due to similarities between emtricitabine and lamivudine, do not coadminister TRUVADA with other drugs containing lamivudine, including Combivir (lamivudine/zidovudine), Dutrebis (lamivudine/raltegravir) ,  Epivir or Epivir-HBV (lamivudine), Epzicom (abacavir sulfate/lamivudine), Triumeq (abacavir sulfate/dolutegravir/lamivudine), or Trizivir (abacavir sulfate/lamivudine/zidovudine).  



 Do not coadminister TRUVADA with HEPSERA (adefovir dipivoxil) .  



    5.5 Bone Effects of Tenofovir DF



   Bone Mineral Density:  



 In clinical trials in HIV-1 infected adults and in a clinical trial of HIV-1 uninfected individuals, tenofovir DF was associated with slightly greater decreases in bone mineral density (BMD) and increases in biochemical markers of bone metabolism, suggesting increased bone turnover relative to comparators [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)    and VIREAD prescribing information ]  . Serum parathyroid hormone levels and 1,25 Vitamin D levels were also higher in subjects receiving tenofovir DF.



 Clinical trials evaluating tenofovir DF in pediatric and adolescent subjects were conducted. Under normal circumstances, BMD increases rapidly in pediatric patients. In HIV-1 infected subjects aged 2 years to less than 18 years, bone effects were similar to those observed in adult subjects and suggest increased bone turnover. Total body BMD gain was less in the tenofovir DF treated HIV-1 infected pediatric subjects as compared to the control groups. Similar trends were observed in chronic hepatitis B infected adolescent subjects aged 12 years to less than 18 years. In all pediatric trials, skeletal growth (height) appeared to be unaffected. For more information, consult the VIREAD prescribing information.



 The effects of tenofovir DF-associated changes in BMD and biochemical markers on long-term bone health and future fracture risk are unknown. Assessment of BMD should be considered for adult and pediatric patients who have a history of pathologic bone fracture or other risk factors for osteoporosis or bone loss. Although the effect of supplementation with calcium and vitamin D was not studied, such supplementation may be beneficial. If bone abnormalities are suspected then appropriate consultation should be obtained.



    Mineralization Defects:  



 Cases of osteomalacia associated with proximal renal tubulopathy, manifested as bone pain or pain in extremities and which may contribute to fractures, have been reported in association with the use of tenofovir DF [see  Adverse Reactions (6.3)  ]  . Arthralgias and muscle pain or weakness have also been reported in cases of proximal renal tubulopathy. Hypophosphatemia and osteomalacia secondary to proximal renal tubulopathy should be considered in patients at risk of renal dysfunction who present with persistent or worsening bone or muscle symptoms while receiving products containing tenofovir DF [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ].  



    5.6 Fat Redistribution



  Redistribution/accumulation of body fat including central obesity, dorsocervical fat enlargement (buffalo hump), peripheral wasting, facial wasting, breast enlargement, and "cushingoid appearance" have been observed in HIV-1 infected patients receiving antiretroviral therapy. The mechanism and long-term consequences of these events are currently unknown. A causal relationship has not been established.



    5.7 Immune Reconstitution Syndrome



  Immune reconstitution syndrome has been reported in HIV-1 infected patients treated with combination antiretroviral therapy, including TRUVADA. During the initial phase of combination antiretroviral treatment, HIV-1 infected patients whose immune system responds may develop an inflammatory response to indolent or residual opportunistic infections [such as Mycobacterium avium  infection, cytomegalovirus, Pneumocystis jirovecii  pneumonia (PCP), or tuberculosis], which may necessitate further evaluation and treatment.



 Autoimmune disorders (such as Graves' disease, polymyositis, and Guillain-Barre syndrome) have also been reported to occur in the setting of immune reconstitution, however, the time to onset is more variable, and can occur many months after initiation of treatment.



    5.8 Early Virologic Failure



  Clinical trials in HIV-1 infected subjects have demonstrated that certain regimens that only contain three nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NRTI) are generally less effective than triple drug regimens containing two NRTIs in combination with either a non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor or a HIV-1 protease inhibitor. In particular, early virologic failure and high rates of resistance substitutions have been reported. Triple nucleoside regimens should therefore be used with caution. Patients on a therapy utilizing a triple nucleoside-only regimen should be carefully monitored and considered for treatment modification.



    5.9 Comprehensive Management to Reduce the Risk of Acquiring HIV-1



  Use TRUVADA for pre-exposure prophylaxis only as part of a comprehensive prevention strategy that includes other prevention measures, such as safer sex practices, because TRUVADA is not always effective in preventing the acquisition of HIV-1 [see  Clinical Studies (14.2  and  14.3)  ]  .





   EXCERPT:    *  New onset or worsening renal impairment: Can include acute renal failure and Fanconi syndrome. Assess estimated creatinine clearance before initiating treatment with TRUVADA. In patients at risk for renal dysfunction, assess estimated creatinine clearance, serum phosphorus, urine glucose and urine protein before initiating treatment with TRUVADA and periodically during treatment. Avoid administering Truvada with concurrent or recent use of nephrotoxic drugs. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Coadministration with Other Products: Do not use with drugs containing emtricitabine, tenofovir alafenamide or tenofovir disoproxil fumarate including ATRIPLA, COMPLERA, EMTRIVA, GENVOYA, ODEFSEY, STRIBILD, VIREAD; or with drugs containing lamivudine. Do not administer in combination with HEPSERA. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Decreases in bone mineral density (BMD): Consider assessment of BMD in patients with a history of pathologic fracture or other risk factors for osteoporosis or bone loss. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Redistribution/accumulation of body fat: Observed in patients receiving antiretroviral therapy. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Immune reconstitution syndrome: May necessitate further evaluation and treatment. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Triple nucleoside-only regimens: Early virologic failure has been reported in HIV-infected patients. Monitor carefully and consider treatment modification. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Comprehensive management to reduce the risk of acquiring HIV-1: Use as part of a comprehensive prevention strategy including other prevention measures; strictly adhere to dosing schedule. (  5.9  ) 
 *  Management to reduce the risk of acquiring HIV-1 drug resistance: Prior to initiating TRUVADA for PrEP - if clinical symptoms consistent with acute viral infection are present and recent (&lt;1 month) exposures are suspected, delay starting PrEP for at least one month and reconfirm negative HIV-1 status or use a test approved by the FDA as an aid in the diagnosis of HIV-1 infection, including acute or primary HIV-1 infection.



 While using TRUVADA for PrEP - HIV-1 screening tests should be repeated at least every 3 months. (  5.9  )



 
   *  Counsel uninfected individuals about safer sex practices that include consistent and correct use of condoms, knowledge of their HIV-1 status and that of their partner(s), and regular testing for other sexually transmitted infections that can facilitate HIV-1 transmission (such as syphilis and gonorrhea). 
 *  Inform uninfected individuals about and support their efforts in reducing sexual risk behavior. 
   *  *  If clinical symptoms consistent with acute viral infection are present and recent (&lt;1 month) exposures are suspected, delay starting PrEP for at least one month and reconfirm HIV-1 status or use a test approved by the FDA as an aid in the diagnosis of HIV-1 infection, including acute or primary HIV-1 infection. 
   Many HIV-1 tests, such as rapid tests, detect anti-HIV antibodies and may not identify HIV-1 during the acute stage of infection. Prior to initiating TRUVADA for a PrEP indication, evaluate seronegative individuals for current or recent signs or symptoms consistent with acute viral infections (e.g., fever, fatigue, myalgia, skin rash, etc.) and ask about potential exposure events (e.g., unprotected, or condom broke during sex with an HIV-1 infected partner) that may have occurred within the last month. 
 *  While using TRUVADA for a PrEP indication, HIV-1 screening tests should be repeated at least every 3 months. If symptoms consistent with acute HIV-1 infection develop following a potential exposure event, PrEP should be discontinued until negative infection status is confirmed using a test approved by the FDA as an aid in the diagnosis of HIV-1, including acute or primary HIV-1 infection. 
    

  Use TRUVADA to reduce the risk of acquiring HIV-1 only in individuals confirmed to be HIV-negative.  HIV-1 resistance substitutions may emerge in individuals with undetected HIV-1 infection who are taking only TRUVADA, because TRUVADA alone does not constitute a complete treatment regimen for HIV-1 treatment [see  Microbiology (12.4)  ]  ; therefore, care should be taken to minimize drug exposure in HIV-infected individuals.

 Counsel uninfected individuals to strictly adhere to the recommended TRUVADA dosing schedule. The effectiveness of TRUVADA in reducing the risk of acquiring HIV-1 is strongly correlated with adherence as demonstrated by measurable drug levels in clinical trials [see  Clinical Studies (14.2  and  14.3)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
