<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tuzistra" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Use of codeine, a semisynthetic opioid, may result in the following:



 *  Respiratory depression [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    and    Overdosage (10)    ]  
 *  Drug dependence [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.3)    ]  
 *  Increased intracranial pressure [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.4)    and    Overdosage (10)    ]  
 *  Decreased mental alertness with impaired mental and/or physical abilities [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.5)    ]  
 *  Paralytic ileus [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.7)    ]  
    Use of chlorpheniramine, an antihistamine, may result in:
 

 *  Decreased mental alertness with impaired mental and/or physical abilities [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.5)    ]  
    Adverse reactions listed below have been reported in the literature for codeine and chlorpheniramine and may be expected to occur with TUZISTRA XR. Also included are events that occurred during clinical pharmacokinetic studies (in a total of 66 healthy adult volunteers with either single or multiple dose exposure) with TUZISTRA XR and judged by the investigator to be related to study treatment.  Because these reactions may be reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.
 

   Allergic  : Allergic laryngospasm, nasal stuffiness, bronchospastic allergic reaction, hives, itching, swelling of face.



   Body as a whole  : Asthenia, feeling of relaxation, redness or flushing of the face, unusual tiredness, weakness.



   Cardiovascular  : Fast, or slow heartbeat, hypertension, hypotension, orthostatic hypotension, palpitations, shock-like state, syncope.



   Dermatological System  : Skin rash, pruritus, erythema, urticaria, excessive perspiration, dermatitis.



   Endocrine System  : Changes in glucose utilization, decreased lactation, early menses, glycosuria, gynecomastia, hypoglycemia, increased appetite, increased libido, pheochromocytoma stimulation.



   Gastrointestinal System  : Nausea and vomiting, constipation, abdominal distension, abdominal pain, acute pancreatitis, dry mouth, dyspepsia, epigastric distress, loss of appetite, diarrhea, gastro-esophageal reflux, gastrointestinal hypomotility.



   Genitourinary System  : Ureteral spasm, urinary retention, dysuria, urinary frequency, urinary hesitancy, irritative bladder symptom.



   Nervous System  : Blurred vision, diplopia, visual disturbances, confusion, dizziness, depression, drowsiness, sedation, headache, euphoria, facial dyskinesia, false sense of well-being, feeling faint, lightheadedness, general feeling of discomfort or illness, excitability, nervousness, agitation, restlessness, somnolence, insomnia, dyskinesia, irritability, tremor.



   Respiratory  : Dryness of the pharynx and respiratory passages, laryngismus, atelectasis, wheezing, troubled breathing, respiratory depression, hiccups.



   Special Senses  : labyrinthitis, tinnitus, vertigo, hypermetropia, lacrimation increased, mydriasis, photophobia.



   EXCERPT:   Common adverse reactions of TUZISTRA XR include: nausea and vomiting, constipation, abdominal distension, abdominal pain, blurred vision, diplopia, visual disturbances, confusion, dizziness, depression, drowsiness, sedation, headache, euphoria, facial dyskinesia, feeling faint, light-headedness, general feeling of discomfort or illness, excitability, nervousness, agitation, restlessness, somnolence, insomnia, dyskinesia, irritability, tremor.  (6)  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Vernalis Therapeutics, Inc. 1-855-705-9546 and      www.vernalistherapeutics.com      or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or      www.fda.gov/medwatch      .  
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: BOXED WARNING

  BOXED WARNING

   
 WARNING: DEATH RELATED TO ULTRA-RAPID METABOLISM OF CODEINE TO MORPHINERespiratory depression and death have occurred in children who received codeine following tonsillectomy and/or adenoidectomy and had evidence of being ultra-rapid metabolizers of codeine due to a CYP2D6 polymorphism[see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)].   
     
 WARNING: DEATH RELATED TO ULTRA-RAPID METABOLISM OF CODEINE TO MORPHINESee full prescribing information for complete boxed warning. Respiratory depression and death have occurred in children who received codeine following tonsillectomy and/or adenoidectomy and had evidence of being ultra-rapid metabolizers of codeine due to a CYP2D6 polymorphism. (5.1)   
         EXCERPT:   
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Risk of death in ultra-rapid metabolizers: Conversion of codeine into its active metabolite, morphine, may occur more rapidly and completely resulting in higher than expected morphine levels and respiratory depression or death. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Dose-related respiratory depression:  Use with caution. (5.2). 
 *  Drug dependence: Prescribe with caution that is appropriate to the use of other opioids. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Head injury and increased intracranial pressure:  Avoid in patients with head injury, intra-cranial lesions, or increased intracranial pressure. (   5.4   )  
 *  Activities requiring mental alertness:  Avoid engaging in hazardous tasks requiring complete mental alertness such as driving or operating heavy machinery. Avoid concurrent use of alcohol or other central nervous system depressants. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Acute abdominal conditions: Use with caution in patients with acute abdominal conditions.  (5.7)   
 *  Special risk patients:  Caution in elderly patients and those with asthma, hypothyroidism, Addison's disease, prostatic hypertrophy or urethral stricture. (  5.9  ) 
    
 

   5.1  Death Related to Ultra-Rapid Metabolism of Codeine to Morphine



  Respiratory depression and death have occurred in children who received codeine in the postoperative period following tonsillectomy and/or adenoidectomy and had evidence of being ultra-rapid metabolizers of codeine (i.e., multiple copies of the gene for cytochrome P450 isoenzyme 2D6 [CYP2D6] or high morphine concentrations).  Deaths have also occurred in nursing infants who were exposed to high levels of morphine in breast milk because their mothers were ultra-rapid metabolizers of codeine [see     Use in Specific Populations (8.3)     ].  



 Some individuals may be ultra-rapid metabolizers because of a specific CYP2D6 genotype (gene duplications denoted as *1/*1xN or *1/*2xN).  The prevalence of this CYP2D6 phenotype varies widely and has been estimated at 0.5 to 1% in Chinese and Japanese, 0.5 to 1% in Hispanics, 1 to 10% in Caucasians, 3% in African Americans, and 16 to 28% in North Africans, Ethiopians, and Arabs.  Data are not available for other ethnic groups.  These individuals convert codeine into its active metabolite, morphine, more rapidly and completely than other people.  This rapid conversion results in higher than expected serum morphine levels.  Even at labeled dosage regimens, individuals who are ultra-rapid metabolizers may have life-threatening or fatal respiratory depression or experience signs of overdose (such as extreme sleepiness, confusion, or shallow breathing) [see     Overdosage (10)     ].  



 Children with obstructive sleep apnea who are treated with codeine for post-tonsillectomy and/or adenoidectomy pain may be particularly sensitive to the respiratory depressant effects of codeine that has been rapidly metabolized to morphine.  Codeine is contraindicated for postoperative pain management in all pediatric patients undergoing tonsillectomy and/or adenoidectomy [see     Contraindications (4)     ].  



 When prescribing codeine-containing drugs, healthcare professionals should choose the lowest effective dose for the shortest period of time and inform patients and caregivers about these risks and the signs of morphine overdose [see     Use in Specific Populations (8),       Overdosage (10)     ].  



    5.2 Respiratory Depression



  Codeine, one of the active ingredients in TUZISTRA XR, produces dose-related respiratory depression by directly acting on brain stem respiratory centers.  Codeine affects the center that controls respiratory rhythm and may produce irregular and periodic breathing.  Caution should be exercised when TUZISTRA XR is used postoperatively, in patients with pulmonary disease or shortness of breath, or whenever ventilator function is depressed.



 Overdose of codeine in adults has been associated with fatal respiratory depression, and the use of codeine in children has been associated with fatal respiratory depression.  Exercise caution when administering TUZISTRA XR because of the potential for respiratory depression.  If respiratory depression occurs, discontinue TUZISTRA XR and use naloxone hydrochloride when indicated to antagonize the effect and other supportive measures as necessary [see     Overdosage (10)     ].  



    5.3 Drug Dependence



  Codeine can produce drug dependence of the morphine type and, therefore, has the potential for being abused.  Psychological dependence, physical dependence, and tolerance may develop upon repeated administration of TUZISTRA XR.  Prescribe and administer TUZISTRA XR with the same degree of caution appropriate to the use of other opioid drugs [see     Drug Abuse and Dependence (9.2     ,     9.3)     ]  .



    5.2 Head Injury and Increased Intracranial Pressure



  The respiratory depression effects of opioids and their capacity to elevate cerebrospinal fluid pressure may be markedly exaggerated in the presence of head injury, other intracranial lesions, or a pre-existing increase in intracranial pressure.  Furthermore, opioids produce adverse reactions that may obscure the clinical course of patients with head injuries.  The use of TUZISTRA XR should be avoided in these patients.



    5.5 Activities Requiring Mental Alertness



  Codeine and chlorpheniramine, the active ingredients in TUZISTRA XR, may produce marked drowsiness and impair the mental and/or physical abilities required for the performance of potentially hazardous tasks such as driving a car or operating machinery.  Advise patients to avoid engaging in hazardous tasks requiring mental alertness and motor coordination after ingestion of TUZISTRA XR.  Concurrent use of TUZISTRA XR with alcohol or other central nervous system depressants should be avoided because additional impairment of central nervous system performance may occur.



    5.6 Obstruction Bowel Disease



  Chronic use of opioids, including codeine, may result in constipation or obstructive bowel disease especially in patients with underlying intestinal motility disorders.  Use with caution in patients with underlying intestinal motility disorders.



    5.7 Acute Abdominal Conditions



  TUZISTRA XR should be used with caution in patients with acute abdominal conditions since the administration of codeine may obscure the diagnosis or clinical course of patients with acute abdominal conditions.  The concurrent use of other anticholinergics with codeine may produce paralytic ileus [see     Drug Interactions (7.3)     ]  



    5.8 Dosing



  Patients should be advised to measure TUZISTRA XR with an accurate milliliter measuring device. Patients should be informed that a household teaspoon is not an accurate measuring device and could lead to overdosage, which can result in serious adverse reactions [see     Overdosage (10)     ]  .  Patients should be advised to ask their pharmacist to recommend an appropriate measuring device and for instructions for measuring the correct dose.



    5.9 Special Risk Patients



  As with other opioids, TUZISTRA XR should be used with caution in elderly or debilitated patients and those with asthma, persistent or chronic cough, hypothyroidism, Addison's disease, prostatic hypertrophy or urethral stricture. The usual precautions should be observed, and the possibility of respiratory depression should be kept in mind.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
