<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="twinrix" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Following any dose of TWINRIX, the most common (&gt;=10%) solicited injection site reactions were injection site soreness (35% to 41%) and redness (8% to 11%); the most common solicited systemic adverse events were headache (13% to 22%) and fatigue (11% to 14%).  (6.1)  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or  www.vaers.hhs.gov    .



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. As with any vaccine, there is the possibility that broad use of TWINRIX could reveal adverse events not observed in clinical trials.



 Following any dose of TWINRIX, the most common (&gt;=10%) solicited injection site reactions were injection site soreness (35% to 41%) and redness (8% to 11%); the most common solicited systemic adverse events were headache (13% to 22%) and fatigue (11% to 14%).



 The safety of TWINRIX has been evaluated in clinical trials involving the administration of approximately 7,500 doses to more than 2,500 individuals.



 In a US study, 773 subjects (18 to 70 years of age) were randomized 1:1 to receive TWINRIX (0-, 1-, and 6-month schedule) or concurrent administration of ENGERIX-B (0-, 1-, and 6-month schedule) and HAVRIX (0- and 6-month schedule). Solicited local adverse reactions and systemic adverse events were recorded by parents/guardians on diary cards for 4 days (days 0 to 3) after vaccination. Unsolicited adverse events were recorded for 31 days after vaccination. Solicited events reported following the administration of TWINRIX or ENGERIX-B and HAVRIX are presented in Table 1.



 Table 1. Rates of Local Adverse Reactions and Systemic Adverse Events Within 4 Days of Vaccinationa With TWINRIXb or ENGERIX-B and HAVRIXc 
               TWINRIX      ENGERIX-B    HAVRIX       
  Dose 1       Dose 2       Dose 3       Dose 1       Dose 2       Dose 3       Dose 1       Dose 2       
  Local        (N = 385)  %    (N = 382)  %    (N = 374)  %    (N = 382)  %    (N = 376)  %    (N = 369)  %    (N = 382)  %    (N = 369)  %    
  Soreness  Redness  Swelling    37  8  4     35  9  4     41  11  6    41  6  3     25  7  5     30  9  5     53  7  5     47  9  5     
               TWINRIX      ENGERIX-B and  HAVRIX    
               Dose 1       Dose 2       Dose 3       Dose 1d      Dose 2e      Dose 3d      
  Systemic     (N = 385)  %    (N = 382)  %    (N = 374)  %    (N = 382)  %    (N = 376)  %    (N = 369)  %    
  Headache  Fatigue  Diarrhea  Nausea  Fever  Vomiting    22  14  5  4  4  1    15  13  4  3  3  1    13  11  6  2  2  0    19  14  5  7  4  1    12  9  3  3  2  1    14  10  3  5  4  1    
                 a  Within 4 days of vaccination defined as day of vaccination and the next 3 days.
 

   b  389 subjects received at least 1 dose of TWINRIX.



   c  384 subjects received at least 1 dose each of ENGERIX-B and HAVRIX.



   d  Doses 1 and 3 included ENGERIX-B and HAVRIX in the control group receiving separate vaccinations.



   e  Dose 2 included only ENGERIX-B in the control group receiving separate vaccinations.



 Most solicited local adverse reactions and systemic adverse events seen with TWINRIX were considered by the subjects as mild and self-limiting and did not last more than 48 hours.



 In a clinical trial in which TWINRIX was given on a 0-, 7-, and 21- to 30-day schedule followed by a booster dose at 12 months, solicited local adverse reactions or systemic adverse events were comparable to those seen in other clinical trials of TWINRIX given on a 0-, 1-, and 6-month schedule.



 Among 2,299 subjects in 14 clinical trials, the following adverse events were reported to occur within 30 days following vaccination:



     Incidence 1% to 10% of Injections, Seen in Clinical Trials With TWINRIX:    



     Infections and Infestations:    Upper respiratory tract infections.



     General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions  :  Injection site induration.



     Incidence &lt;1% of Injections, Seen in Clinical Trials With TWINRIX:    



     Infections and Infestations:    Respiratory tract illnesses.



     Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:    Anorexia.



     Psychiatric Disorders:    Agitation, insomnia.



     Nervous System Disorders:    Dizziness, migraine, paresthesia, somnolence, syncope.



     Ear and Labyrinth Disorders:    Vertigo.



     Vascular Disorders:    Flushing.



     Gastrointestinal Disorders:    Abdominal pain, vomiting.



     Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:    Erythema, petechiae, rash, sweating, urticaria.



     Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:    Arthralgia, back pain, myalgia.



     General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:    Injection site ecchymosis, injection site pruritus, influenza-like symptoms, irritability, weakness.



     Incidence &lt;1% of Injections, Seen in Clinical Trials With HAVRIX and/or ENGERIX-B:    



     Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:    Lymphadenopathy.  a+b  



     Nervous System Disorders:    Dysgeusia,  a  hypertonia,  a  tingling.  b  



     Eye Disorders:    Photophobia.  a  



     Vascular Disorders:    Hypotension.  b  



     Gastrointestinal Disorders:    Constipation.  b  



     Investigations:    Creatine phosphokinase increased.  a  



   a+b  Following either HAVRIX or ENGERIX-B.



   a  Following HAVRIX.



   b  Following ENGERIX-B.



 Adverse events within 30 days of vaccination in the US clinical trial of TWINRIX given on a 0-, 7-, and 21- to 30-day schedule followed by a booster dose at 12 months were comparable to those reported in other clinical trials.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse events have been identified during postapproval use of TWINRIX, HAVRIX, or ENGERIX-B. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to product exposure.



   Postmarketing Experience with TWINRIX:  The following list includes serious events or events which have suspected causal connection to components of TWINRIX.



     Infections and Infestations  :  Herpes zoster, meningitis.



     Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:    Thrombocytopenia, thrombocytopenic purpura.



     Immune System Disorders:    Allergic reaction, anaphylactoid reaction, anaphylaxis, serum sickness-like syndrome days to weeks after vaccination (including arthralgia/arthritis, usually transient, fever, urticaria, erythema multiforme, ecchymoses, and erythema nodosum).



     Nervous System Disorders:    Bell's palsy, convulsions, encephalitis, encephalopathy, Guillain-Barre syndrome, hypoesthesia, myelitis, multiple sclerosis, neuritis, neuropathy, optic neuritis, paralysis, paresis, transverse myelitis.



     Eye Disorders:    Conjunctivitis, visual disturbances.



     Ear and Labyrinth Disorders:    Earache, tinnitus.



     Cardiac Disorders  :  Palpitations, tachycardia.



     Vascular Disorders:    Vasculitis.



     Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:    Bronchospasm including asthma-like symptoms, dyspnea.



     Gastrointestinal Disorders  :  Dyspepsia.



     Hepatobiliary Disorders:    Hepatitis, jaundice.



     Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:    Alopecia, angioedema, eczema, erythema multiforme, erythema nodosum, hyperhydrosis, lichen planus.



     Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:    Arthritis, muscular weakness.



     General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:    Chills, immediate injection site pain, stinging, and burning sensation, injection site reaction, malaise.



     Investigations:    Abnormal liver function tests.



   Postmarketing Experience With HAVRIX and/or ENGERIX-B:  The following list includes serious events or events which have suspected causal connection to components of HAVRIX and/or ENGERIX-B, not already reported above for TWINRIX.



     Eye Disorders:    Keratitis.  b  



     Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:    Stevens-Johnson syndrome.  b  



     Congenital, Familial and Genetic Disorders:    Congenital abnormality.  a  



   a  Following HAVRIX.



   b  Following ENGERIX-B.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    The tip caps of the prefilled syringes may contain natural rubber latex which may cause allergic reactions in latex-sensitive individuals. (5.1) 
 *    Syncope (fainting) can occur in association with administration of injectable vaccines, including TWINRIX. Procedures should be in place to avoid falling injury and to restore cerebral perfusion following syncope. (5.2) 
    
 

   5.1 Latex



  The tip caps of the prefilled syringes may contain natural rubber latex which may cause allergic reactions in latex-sensitive individuals.



    5.2 Syncope



  Syncope (fainting) can occur in association with administration of injectable vaccines, including TWINRIX. Syncope can be accompanied by transient neurological signs such as visual disturbance, paresthesia, and tonic-clonic limb movements. Procedures should be in place to avoid falling injury and to restore cerebral perfusion following syncope.



    5.3 Preventing and Managing Allergic Vaccine Reactions



  Prior to immunization, the healthcare provider should review the immunization history for possible vaccine sensitivity and previous vaccination-related adverse reactions to allow an assessment of benefits and risks. Appropriate medical treatment and supervision must be available to manage possible anaphylactic reactions following administration of the vaccine. [See Contraindications (4).]  



    5.4 Moderate or Severe Acute Illness



  To avoid diagnostic confusion between manifestations of an acute illness and possible vaccine adverse effects, vaccination with TWINRIX should be postponed in persons with moderate or severe acute febrile illness unless they are at immediate risk of hepatitis A or hepatitis B infection.



    5.5 Altered Immunocompetence



  Immunocompromised persons, including individuals receiving immunosuppressive therapy, may have a diminished immune response to TWINRIX.



    5.6 Multiple Sclerosis



  Results from 2 clinical studies indicate that there is no association between hepatitis B vaccination and the development of multiple sclerosis,  1  and that vaccination with hepatitis B vaccine does not appear to increase the short-term risk of relapse in multiple sclerosis.  2  



    5.7 Limitations of Vaccine Effectiveness



  Hepatitis A and hepatitis B have relatively long incubation periods. The vaccine may not prevent hepatitis A or hepatitis B infection in individuals who have an unrecognized hepatitis A or hepatitis B infection at the time of vaccination. Additionally, vaccination with TWINRIX may not protect all individuals.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
