<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tybost" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reaction is described in greater detail in another section of the labeling:



 *  New Onset or Worsening Renal Impairment When Used with Tenofovir Disoproxil Fumarate [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse drug reactions observed with TYBOST in combination with atazanavir (incidence greater than 10%, all Grades) are jaundice, ocular icterus, and nausea. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Gilead Sciences, Inc. at 1-800-GILEAD-5 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of TYBOST has been established from a Phase 2 trial, Study 105, and a Phase 3 trial, Study 114. In the pooled analysis, 771 HIV-1 infected, antiretroviral treatment-naive adults received for at least 48 weeks:



 *  TYBOST coadministered with atazanavir and tenofovir DF/emtricitabine (administered as TRUVADA) (N=394) or; 
 *  ritonavir coadministered with atazanavir and tenofovir DF/emtricitabine (administered as TRUVADA ) (N=377). 
    The most common adverse reactions (all Grades) and reported in &gt;10% of subjects in the TYBOST group were jaundice (13%), ocular icterus (15%), and nausea (12%); the most common adverse reactions in the ritonavir group were jaundice (11%), ocular icterus (17%), nausea (11%), and diarrhea (11%). The proportion of subjects who discontinued study treatment due to adverse events, regardless of severity, was 7% in both the TYBOST and ritonavir group. Table 3 displays the frequency of adverse reactions (Grades 2-4) occurring in at least 2% of subjects in the TYBOST group in pooled Studies 105 and 114.
 

 Table 3 Selected Adverse ReactionsFrequencies of adverse reactions are based on Grades 2-4 adverse events attributed to study drugs. (Grades 2-4) Reported in &gt;=2% of HIV-1 Infected Treatment-Naive Adults in the TYBOST Coadministered with Atazanavir Group in Studies 105 and 114 (Week 48 pooled Analysis) 
                                     TYBOST Coadministered with Atazanavir + TRUVADAN=394  Ritonavir Coadministered with Atazanavir + TRUVADAN=377   
  
 Jaundice                                           5%                                 3%                   
 Rash                                               5%                                 4%                   
 Ocular icterus                                     3%                                 1%                   
 Nausea                                             2%                                 2%                   
               Nephrolithiasis    
 

 Nephrolithiasis has previously been identified in patients receiving atazanavir. In the pooled analysis of Studies 105 and 114 through 48 weeks, 8 subjects (2%) receiving TYBOST coadministered with atazanavir and TRUVADA developed nephrolithiasis compared with no subjects receiving ritonavir coadministered with atazanavir and TRUVADA. Median time to onset of nephrolithiasis in the TYBOST group was 24 weeks. Causality in these cases could not be determined with certainty, but the majority of renal stone events were not serious and no subject discontinued study drug.



       Less Common Adverse Reactions    



 Selected adverse reactions of at least moderate severity (&gt;= Grade 2) occurring in less than 2% of subjects receiving TYBOST coadministered with atazanavir and TRUVADA are listed below. These events have been included because of the investigator's assessment of potential causal relationship and were considered serious or have been reported in more than one subject treated with TYBOST and with greater frequency compared with ritonavir.



 *      Gastrointestinal Disorders: diarrhea, vomiting, upper abdominal pain 
 *      General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions: fatigue 
 *      Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders: rhabdomyolysis 
 *      Nervous System Disorders: headache 
 *      Psychiatric Disorders: depression, abnormal dreams, insomnia 
 *      Renal and Urinary Disorders: nephropathy, Fanconi syndrome acquired 
    Refer to the prescribing information for atazanavir or darunavir for information regarding adverse reactions with these drugs.
 

     Laboratory Abnormalities:  The frequency of laboratory abnormalities (Grades 3-4) occurring in at least 2% of subjects in the TYBOST group in Studies 105 and 114 is presented in Table 4.



 Table 4 Laboratory Abnormalities (Grades 3-4) in &gt;=2% of HIV-1 Infected Treatment-Naive Adults in the TYBOST Coadministered with Atazanavir Group in Studies 105 and 114 (Week 48 pooled Analysis) 
                                           TYBOST + Atazanavir + TRUVADA   Ritonavir + Atazanavir + TRUVADA   
  
   Laboratory Parameter Abnormality                    N=394                           N=377                
 Total Bilirubin (&gt;2.5 * ULN)                           65%                             56%                 
 Creatine Kinase (&gt;=10.0 * ULN)                          5%                              6%                 
 Serum Amylase(&gt;2.0 * ULN)                               4%                              2%                 
 ALT (&gt;5.0 * ULN)                                        3%                              2%                 
 AST (&gt;5.0 * ULN)                                        3%                              2%                 
 GGT (&gt;5.0 * ULN)                                        2%                              1%                 
 Urine Glucose (Glycosuria) (&gt;=1000 mg/dL)                3%                              1%                 
 Urine RBC (Hematuria) (&gt;75 RBC/HPF)                     3%                              2%                 
               Increase in Serum Creatinine  :  TYBOST causes increases in serum creatinine and decreases in estimated creatinine clearance due to inhibition of tubular secretion of creatinine without affecting actual renal glomerular function  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)  ]  . In Studies 105 and 114, increases in serum creatinine and decreases in estimated creatinine clearance occurred early in treatment with TYBOST, after which they stabilized. The mean (+/- SD) change in estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) by Cockcroft-Gault method after 48 weeks of treatment was -13.4 +/- 15.2 mL/min in the TYBOST group and -9.1 +/- 14.7 mL/min in the ritonavir group.
 

       Serum Lipids:    Changes from baseline in total cholesterol, HDL-cholesterol, LDL-cholesterol, and triglycerides are presented in Table 5. In both groups, mean values for serum lipids remained within the study reference range for each laboratory test. The clinical significance of these changes is unknown.



 Table 5 Lipid Values, Mean Change from Baseline, Reported in HIV-1 Infected Treatment-Naive Adults Receiving TYBOST Coadministered with Atazanavir + TRUVADA or Ritonavir Coadministered with Atazanavir + TRUVADA in Studies 105 and 114 (Week 48 pooled Analysis) 
                               TYBOST + Atazanavir + TRUVADA  Ritonavir + Atazanavir + TRUVADA   
 Baseline                           Week 48             Baseline            Week 48         
 mg/dL                         Change from baseline        mg/dL         Change from baseline   
  
 Total Cholesterol (fasted)        164[N=307]          +4[N=307]           165[N=299]          +8[N=299]        
 HDL-cholesterol (fasted)          44[N=306]           +3[N=306]           43[N=299]           +3[N=299]        
 LDL-cholesterol (fasted)          102[N=307]          +5[N=307]           103[N=300]          +7[N=300]        
 Triglycerides (fasted)            128[N=307]          +15[N=307]          131[N=299]          +29[N=299]       
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Assess creatinine clearance (CLcr) before initiating treatment. (  5.1  ) 
 *  When TYBOST is used in combination with a tenofovir disoproxil fumarate (tenofovir DF) containing regimen, cases of acute renal failure and Fanconi syndrome have been reported. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Use with tenofovir DF: Assess urine glucose and urine protein at baseline and monitor CLcr, urine glucose, and urine protein. Monitor serum phosphorus in patients with or at risk for renal impairment. (  5.2  ) 
 *  TYBOST in combination with more than one antiretroviral that requires pharmacokinetic enhancement (i.e., two protease inhibitors or elvitegravir in combination with a protease inhibitor) is not recommended. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Use with HIV-1 protease inhibitors other than atazanavir or darunavir administered once daily are not recommended. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Coadministration with cobicistat-containing drugs, including STRIBILD  (r)  , is not recommended. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Coadministration with drugs or regimens containing ritonavir is not recommended. (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Effects on Serum Creatinine



  TYBOST decreases estimated creatinine clearance due to inhibition of tubular secretion of creatinine without affecting actual renal glomerular function. This effect should be considered when interpreting changes in estimated creatinine clearance in patients initiating TYBOST, particularly in patients with medical conditions or receiving drugs needing monitoring with estimated creatinine clearance.



 Prior to initiating therapy with TYBOST, assess estimated creatinine clearance [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ]  . Dosage recommendations are not available for drugs that require dosage adjustments in TYBOST-treated patients with renal impairment [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ,  Drug Interactions (7.3)  , and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)  ]  . Consider alternative medications that do not require dosage adjustments in patients with renal impairment.



 Although TYBOST may cause modest increases in serum creatinine and modest declines in estimated creatinine clearance without affecting renal glomerular function, patients who experience a confirmed increase in serum creatinine of greater than 0.4 mg/dL from baseline should be closely monitored for renal safety.



    5.2 New Onset or Worsening Renal Impairment When Used with Tenofovir Disoproxil Fumarate



  Renal impairment, including cases of acute renal failure and Fanconi syndrome, has been reported when TYBOST was used in an antiretroviral regimen that contained tenofovir DF.



 *  Coadministration of TYBOST and tenofovir DF is not recommended in patients who have an estimated creatinine clearance below 70 mL/min because dose adjustment of tenofovir DF is required below 50 mL/min and such dose adjustments have not been established for coadministration with TYBOST [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ] . 
 *  Document urine glucose and urine protein at baseline [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ] and perform routine monitoring of estimated creatinine clearance, urine glucose, and urine protein during treatment when TYBOST is used with tenofovir DF. Measure serum phosphorus in patients with or at risk for renal impairment when used with tenofovir DF. 
 *  Coadministration of TYBOST and tenofovir DF in combination with concomitant or recent use of a nephrotoxic agent is not recommended. 
    In the clinical trials of TYBOST over 48 weeks (N=771), 6 (1.5%) subjects treated with TYBOST coadministered with atazanavir and TRUVADA  (r)  and 6 (1.6%) subjects treated with ritonavir coadministered with atazanavir and TRUVADA discontinued study drug due to a renal adverse event. Five of the 6 subjects (1.3% overall) in the TYBOST group had laboratory findings consistent with proximal renal tubulopathy leading to study drug discontinuation compared to 2 of 6 subjects (0.5% overall) in the ritonavir group. None of the 5 subjects in the TYBOST group had renal impairment at baseline (i.e., estimated creatinine clearance less than 70 mL/min). The laboratory findings in these 5 subjects with evidence of proximal tubulopathy improved but did not completely resolve in all subjects upon discontinuation of TYBOST coadministered with atazanavir and TRUVADA. Renal replacement therapy was not required in any subject.
 

    5.3 Risk of Serious Adverse Reactions or Loss of Virologic Response Due to Drug Interactions



  Initiation of TYBOST, a CYP3A inhibitor, in patients receiving medications metabolized by CYP3A, or initiation of medications metabolized by CYP3A in patients already receiving TYBOST may increase plasma concentration of these medications which may increase the risk of clinically significant adverse reactions (including life-threatening or fatal reactions) associated with the concomitant medications. Coadministration of TYBOST with atazanavir or darunavir in combination with CYP3A inducers may lead to lower exposure of cobicistat and atazanavir or darunavir and loss of efficacy of atazanavir or darunavir and possible resistance. Therefore, consider the potential for drug interactions prior to and during TYBOST therapy; review concomitant medications during TYBOST therapy; and monitor for the adverse reactions associated with the concomitant drugs [see  Contraindications (4)  and  Drug Interactions (7)  ]  .



 TYBOST or ritonavir when administered with either atazanavir or darunavir may result in different drug interactions when used with concomitant medications. Complex or unknown mechanisms of drug interactions preclude extrapolation of ritonavir drug interactions to certain TYBOST interactions [see     Drug Interactions (7)  , and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ].  



    5.4 Antiretrovirals that are Not Recommended



  The following antiretrovirals are not recommended in combination with TYBOST because dosing recommendations for such combinations have not been established and coadministration may result in decreased plasma concentrations of the antiretroviral agents, leading to loss of therapeutic effect and development of resistance:



 *  More than one antiretroviral that requires pharmacokinetic enhancement (i.e., two protease inhibitors or a protease inhibitor in combination with elvitegravir) 
 *  Darunavir in combination with efavirenz, nevirapine, or etravirine 
 *  Atazanavir in combination with etravirine 
 *  Atazanavir in combination with efavirenz in treatment-experienced patients 
 *  Darunavir 600 mg twice daily 
 *  Other HIV-1 protease inhibitors including fosamprenavir, saquinavir, or tipranavir 
    TYBOST in combination with STRIBILD  (r)  fixed-dose combination tablets (elvitegravir, cobicistat, emtricitabine, tenofovir DF) is not recommended because cobicistat is a component of STRIBILD.
 

 TYBOST in combination with lopinavir/ritonavir or regimens containing ritonavir is not recommended due to similar effects of TYBOST and ritonavir on CYP3A.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
