<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tygacil" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;5%) are nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, abdominal pain, headache, and increased SGPT. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer Inc. at 1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  .    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In clinical trials, 2514 patients were treated with TYGACIL. TYGACIL was discontinued due to adverse reactions in 7% of patients compared to 6% for all comparators. Table 1 shows the incidence of treatment-emergent adverse reactions through test of cure reported in &gt;=2% of patients in these trials.



 Table 1. Incidence (%) of Adverse Reactions Through Test of Cure Reported in &gt;= 2% of Patients Treated in Clinical Studies 
 Body System  Adverse Reactions                   TYGACIL(N=2514)               Comparators(N=2307)         
  
   Body as a Whole                                                                                          
   Abdominal pain                                        6                               4                  
   Abscess                                               2                               2                  
   Asthenia                                              3                               2                  
   Headache                                              6                               7                  
   Infection                                             7                               5                  
   Cardiovascular System                                                                                    
   Phlebitis                                             3                               4                  
   Digestive System                                                                                         
   Diarrhea                                              12                              11                 
   Dyspepsia                                             2                               2                  
   Nausea                                                26                              13                 
   Vomiting                                              18                              9                  
   Hemic and Lymphatic System                                                                               
   Anemia                                                5                               6                  
   Metabolic and Nutritional                                                                                
   Alkaline Phosphatase Increased                        3                               3                  
   Amylase Increased                                     3                               2                  
   Bilirubinemia                                         2                               1                  
   BUN Increased                                         3                               1                  
   Healing Abnormal                                      3                               2                  
   Hyponatremia                                          2                               1                  
   Hypoproteinemia                                       5                               3                  
   SGOT Increased                                        4                               5                  
   SGPT Increased                                        5                               5                  
   Respiratory System                                                                                       
   Pneumonia                                             2                               2                  
   Nervous System                                                                                           
   Dizziness                                             3                               3                  
   Skin and Appendages                                                                                      
   Rash                                                  3                               4                  
         In all 13 Phase 3 and 4 trials that included a comparator, death occurred in 4.0% (150/3788) of patients receiving TYGACIL and 3.0% (110/3646) of patients receiving comparator drugs. In a pooled analysis of these trials, based on a random effects model by trial weight, an adjusted risk difference of all-cause mortality was 0.6% (95% CI 0.1, 1.2) between TYGACIL and comparator-treated patients (see  Table 2  ). The cause of the imbalance has not been established. Generally, deaths were the result of worsening infection, complications of infection or underlying co-morbidities.
 

 Table 2. Patients with Outcome of Death by Infection Type 
                           TYGACIL          Comparator     Risk Difference    
 Infection Type              n/N                %                n/N                %             % (95% CI)      
  
 CAP = Community-acquired pneumonia; cIAI = Complicated intra-abdominal infections; cSSSI = Complicated skin and skin structure infections; HAP = Hospital-acquired pneumonia; VAP = Ventilator-associated pneumonia; RP = Resistant pathogens; DFI = Diabetic foot infections.   
 Note: The studies include 300, 305, 900 (cSSSI), 301, 306, 315, 316, 400 (cIAI), 308 and 313 (CAP), 311 (HAP), 307 [Resistant gram-positive pathogen study in patients with MRSA or Vancomycin-Resistant Enterococcus (VRE)], and 319 (DFI with and without osteomyelitis).   
  
 cSSSI                      12/834             1.4              6/813              0.7         0.7 (-0.3, 1.7)    
 cIAI                      42/1382             3.0             31/1393             2.2         0.8 (-0.4, 2.0)    
 CAP                        12/424             2.8              11/422             2.6         0.2 (-2.0, 2.4)    
 HAP                        66/467             14.1             57/467             12.2        1.9 (-2.4, 6.3)    
 Non-VAP                    41/336             12.2             42/345             12.2        0.0 (-4.9, 4.9)    
 VAP                        25/131             19.1             15/122             12.3        6.8 (-2.1, 15.7)   
 RP                         11/128             8.6               2/43              4.7         3.9 (-4.0, 11.9)   
 DFI                        7/553              1.3              3/508              0.6         0.7 (-0.5, 1.8)    
 Overall Adjusted          150/3788            4.0             110/3646            3.0          0.6 (0.1, 1.2)    
            An analysis of mortality in all trials conducted for approved indications - cSSSI, cIAI, and CABP, including post-market trials (315, 400, 900) - showed an adjusted mortality rate of 2.5% (66/2640) for tigecycline and 1.8% (48/2628) for comparator, respectively. The adjusted risk difference for mortality stratified by trial weight was 0.6% (95% CI 0.0, 1.2).
 

 In comparative clinical studies, infection-related serious adverse events were more frequently reported for subjects treated with TYGACIL (7%) versus comparators (6%). Serious adverse events of sepsis/septic shock were more frequently reported for subjects treated with TYGACIL (2%) versus comparators (1%). Due to baseline differences between treatment groups in this subset of patients, the relationship of this outcome to treatment cannot be established  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  .



 The most common treatment-emergent adverse reactions were nausea and vomiting which generally occurred during the first 1 - 2 days of therapy. The majority of cases of nausea and vomiting associated with TYGACIL and comparators were either mild or moderate in severity. In patients treated with TYGACIL, nausea incidence was 26% (17% mild, 8% moderate, 1% severe) and vomiting incidence was 18% (11% mild, 6% moderate, 1% severe).



 In patients treated for complicated skin and skin structure infections (cSSSI), nausea incidence was 35% for TYGACIL and 9% for vancomycin/aztreonam; vomiting incidence was 20% for TYGACIL and 4% for vancomycin/aztreonam. In patients treated for complicated intra-abdominal infections (cIAI), nausea incidence was 25% for TYGACIL and 21% for imipenem/cilastatin; vomiting incidence was 20% for TYGACIL and 15% for imipenem/cilastatin. In patients treated for community-acquired bacterial pneumonia (CABP), nausea incidence was 24% for TYGACIL and 8% for levofloxacin; vomiting incidence was 16% for TYGACIL and 6% for levofloxacin.



 Discontinuation from tigecycline was most frequently associated with nausea (1%) and vomiting (1%). For comparators, discontinuation was most frequently associated with nausea (&lt;1%).



 The following adverse reactions were reported infrequently (&lt;2%) in patients receiving TYGACIL in clinical studies:



   Body as a Whole  : injection site inflammation, injection site pain, injection site reaction, septic shock, allergic reaction, chills, injection site edema, injection site phlebitis



   Cardiovascular System  : thrombophlebitis



   Digestive System  : anorexia, jaundice, abnormal stools



   Metabolic/Nutritional System  : increased creatinine, hypocalcemia, hypoglycemia



   Special Senses  : taste perversion



   Hemic and Lymphatic System  : partial thromboplastin time (aPTT), prolonged prothrombin time (PT), eosinophilia, increased international normalized ratio (INR), thrombocytopenia



   Skin and Appendages  : pruritus



   Urogenital System  : vaginal moniliasis, vaginitis, leukorrhea



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of TYGACIL. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish causal relationship to drug exposure.



 *  anaphylaxis/anaphylactoid reactions 
 *  acute pancreatitis 
 *  hepatic cholestasis, and jaundice 
 *  severe skin reactions, including Stevens-Johnson Syndrome 
 *  symptomatic hypoglycemia in patients with and without diabetes mellitus 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: ALL-CAUSE MORTALITY

    WARNING: ALL-CAUSE MORTALITY  

    An increase in all-cause mortality has been observed in a meta-analysis of Phase 3 and 4 clinical trials in TYGACIL-treated patients versus comparator. The cause of this mortality risk difference of 0.6% (95% CI 0.1, 1.2) has not been established. TYGACIL should be reserved for use in situations when alternative treatments are not suitable   [see   Indications and Usage (1.4)  ,   Warnings and Precautions (5.1  ,   5.2)   and   Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].    



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: ALL-CAUSE MORTALITY  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



   All-cause mortality was higher in patients treated with TYGACIL than comparators in a meta-analysis of clinical trials. The cause of this mortality risk difference of 0.6% (95% CI 0.1, 1.2) has not been established. TYGACIL should be reserved for use in situations when alternative treatments are not suitable   [see   Indications and Usage (1.4)  ,    Warnings and Precautions (5.1  ,   5.2)   and   Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].    
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  A meta-analysis of Phase 3 and 4 clinical trials demonstrated an increase in all-cause mortality in TYGACIL-treated patients compared to controls with a risk difference of 0.6% (95% CI 0.1, 1.2). The cause of this increase has not been established. An increase was also seen in a meta-analysis limited to the approved indications [0.6% (95% CI 0.0, 1.2)]. The greatest difference in mortality was seen in TYGACIL-treated patients with ventilator-associated pneumonia (  5.1  ,  5.2  ). 
 *  Anaphylaxis/anaphylactoid reactions have been reported with TYGACIL, and may be life-threatening. Exercise caution in patients with known hypersensitivity to tetracyclines. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Hepatic dysfunction and liver failure have been reported with TYGACIL. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Pancreatitis, including fatalities, has been reported with TYGACIL. If pancreatitis is suspected, then consider stopping TYGACIL. (  5.5  ) 
 *  TYGACIL may cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. (  5.6  ) 
 *  The use of TYGACIL during tooth development may cause permanent discoloration of the teeth. (  5.7  ) 
 *   Clostridium difficile associated diarrhea: evaluate if diarrhea occurs. (  5.8  ) 
    
 

   5.1 All-Cause Mortality



  An increase in all-cause mortality has been observed in a meta-analysis of Phase 3 and 4 clinical trials in TYGACIL-treated patients versus comparator-treated patients. In all 13 Phase 3 and 4 trials that included a comparator, death occurred in 4.0% (150/3788) of patients receiving TYGACIL and 3.0% (110/3646) of patients receiving comparator drugs. In a pooled analysis of these trials, based on a random effects model by trial weight, the adjusted risk difference of all-cause mortality was 0.6% (95% CI 0.1, 1.2) between TYGACIL and comparator-treated patients. An analysis of mortality in all trials conducted for approved indications (cSSSI, cIAI, and CABP), including post-market trials showed an adjusted mortality rate of 2.5% (66/2640) for tigecycline and 1.8% (48/2628) for comparator, respectively. The adjusted risk difference for mortality stratified by trial weight was 0.6% (95% CI 0.0, 1.2).



 The cause of this mortality difference has not been established. Generally, deaths were the result of worsening infection, complications of infection or underlying co-morbidities. TYGACIL should be reserved for use in situations when alternative treatments are not suitable [see  Indications and Usage (1.4)  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  and  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ].  



    5.2 Mortality Imbalance and Lower Cure Rates in Hospital-Acquired Pneumonia



  A trial of patients with hospital acquired, including ventilator-associated, pneumonia failed to demonstrate the efficacy of TYGACIL. In this trial, patients were randomized to receive TYGACIL (100 mg initially, then 50 mg every 12 hours) or a comparator. In addition, patients were allowed to receive specified adjunctive therapies. The sub-group of patients with ventilator-associated pneumonia who received TYGACIL had lower cure rates (47.9% versus 70.1% for the clinically evaluable population).



 In this trial, greater mortality was seen in patients with ventilator-associated pneumonia who received TYGACIL (25/131 [19.1%] versus 15/122 [12.3%] in comparator-treated patients) [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . Particularly high mortality was seen among TYGACIL-treated patients with ventilator-associated pneumonia and bacteremia at baseline (9/18 [50.0%] versus 1/13 [7.7%] in comparator-treated patients).



    5.3 Anaphylaxis/Anaphylactoid Reactions



  Anaphylaxis/anaphylactoid reactions have been reported with nearly all antibacterial agents, including TYGACIL, and may be life-threatening. TYGACIL is structurally similar to tetracycline-class antibiotics and should be administered with caution in patients with known hypersensitivity to tetracycline-class antibiotics.



    5.4 Hepatic Effects



  Increases in total bilirubin concentration, prothrombin time and transaminases have been seen in patients treated with tigecycline. Isolated cases of significant hepatic dysfunction and hepatic failure have been reported in patients being treated with tigecycline. Some of these patients were receiving multiple concomitant medications. Patients who develop abnormal liver function tests during tigecycline therapy should be monitored for evidence of worsening hepatic function and evaluated for risk/benefit of continuing tigecycline therapy. Adverse events may occur after the drug has been discontinued.



    5.5 Pancreatitis



  Acute pancreatitis, including fatal cases, has occurred in association with tigecycline treatment. The diagnosis of acute pancreatitis should be considered in patients taking tigecycline who develop clinical symptoms, signs, or laboratory abnormalities suggestive of acute pancreatitis. Cases have been reported in patients without known risk factors for pancreatitis. Patients usually improve after tigecycline discontinuation. Consideration should be given to the cessation of the treatment with tigecycline in cases suspected of having developed pancreatitis [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ]  .



    5.6 Use During Pregnancy



   TYGACIL may cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman.  If the patient becomes pregnant while taking tigecycline, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus. Results of animal studies indicate that tigecycline crosses the placenta and is found in fetal tissues. Decreased fetal weights in rats and rabbits (with associated delays in ossification) and fetal loss in rabbits have been observed with tigecycline [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ]  .



    5.7 Tooth Development



   The use of TYGACIL during tooth development (last half of pregnancy, infancy, and childhood to the age of 8 years) may cause permanent discoloration of the teeth  (yellow-gray-brown). Results of studies in rats with TYGACIL have shown bone discoloration. TYGACIL should not be used during tooth development unless other drugs are not likely to be effective or are contraindicated.



    5.8 Clostridium difficile  Associated Diarrhea



   Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea (CDAD) has been reported with use of nearly all antibacterial agents, including TYGACIL, and may range in severity from mild diarrhea to fatal colitis. Treatment with antibacterial agents alters the normal flora of the colon leading to overgrowth of C. difficile  .



  C. difficile  produces toxins A and B which contribute to the development of CDAD. Hypertoxin producing strains of C. difficile  cause increased morbidity and mortality, as these infections can be refractory to antimicrobial therapy and may require colectomy. CDAD must be considered in all patients who present with diarrhea following antibiotic use. Careful medical history is necessary since CDAD has been reported to occur over two months after the administration of antibacterial agents.



 If CDAD is suspected or confirmed, ongoing antibiotic use not directed against C. difficile  may need to be discontinued. Appropriate fluid and electrolyte management, protein supplementation, antibiotic treatment of C. difficile  , and surgical evaluation should be instituted as clinically indicated.



    5.9 Patients With Intestinal Perforation



  Caution should be exercised when considering TYGACIL monotherapy in patients with complicated intra-abdominal infections (cIAI) secondary to clinically apparent intestinal perforation. In cIAI studies (n=1642), 6 patients treated with TYGACIL and 2 patients treated with imipenem/cilastatin presented with intestinal perforations and developed sepsis/septic shock. The 6 patients treated with TYGACIL had higher APACHE II scores (median = 13) versus the 2 patients treated with imipenem/cilastatin (APACHE II scores = 4 and 6). Due to differences in baseline APACHE II scores between treatment groups and small overall numbers, the relationship of this outcome to treatment cannot be established.



    5.10 Tetracycline-Class Effects



  TYGACIL is structurally similar to tetracycline-class antibiotics and may have similar adverse effects. Such effects may include: photosensitivity, pseudotumor cerebri, and anti-anabolic action (which has led to increased BUN, azotemia, acidosis, and hyperphosphatemia). As with tetracyclines, pancreatitis has been reported with the use of TYGACIL [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  .



    5.11 Superinfection



  As with other antibacterial drugs, use of TYGACIL may result in overgrowth of non-susceptible organisms, including fungi. Patients should be carefully monitored during therapy. If superinfection occurs, appropriate measures should be taken.



    5.12 Development of Drug-Resistant Bacteria



  Prescribing TYGACIL in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug-resistant bacteria.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
