<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="tykerb" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common (&gt;20%) adverse reactions during treatment with TYKERB plus capecitabine were diarrhea, palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia, nausea, rash, vomiting, and fatigue. The most common (&gt;=20%) adverse reactions during treatment with TYKERB plus letrozole were diarrhea, rash, nausea, and fatigue. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   HER2-Positive Metastatic Breast Cancer:  The safety of TYKERB has been evaluated in more than 12,000 patients in clinical trials. The efficacy and safety of TYKERB in combination with capecitabine in breast cancer was evaluated in 198 patients in a randomized, Phase 3 trial  [see Clinical Studies (14.1)].  Adverse reactions which occurred in at least 10% of patients in either treatment arm and were higher in the combination arm are shown in Table 1.



 The most common adverse reactions (&gt;20%) during therapy with TYKERB plus capecitabine were gastrointestinal (diarrhea, nausea, and vomiting), dermatologic (palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia and rash), and fatigue. Diarrhea was the most common adverse reaction resulting in discontinuation of study medication.



 The most common Grade 3 and 4 adverse reactions (NCI CTCAE v3) were diarrhea and palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia. Selected laboratory abnormalities are shown in Table 2.



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=10% of Patients 
                                      TYKERB 1,250 mg/day + Capecitabine 2,000 mg/m2/day    Capecitabine 2,500 mg/m2/day    
                                      (N = 198)        (N = 191)     
                                      All Gradesa      Grade 3       Grade 4       All Gradesa    Grade 3    Grade 4    
  Reactions                           %                %             %             %            %         %         
  Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                                        
     Diarrhea                         65               13            1             40           10        0         
     Nausea                           44               2             0             43           2         0         
     Vomiting                         26               2             0             21           2         0         
     Stomatitis                       14               0             0             11           &lt;1        0         
     Dyspepsia                        11               &lt;1            0             3            0         0         
  Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                                                                                  
     Palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia    53               12            0             51           14        0         
     Rashb                            28               2             0             14           1         0         
     Dry skin                         10               0             0             6            0         0         
  General disorders and administrative site conditions                                                                                  
     Mucosal inflammation             15               0             0             12           2         0         
  Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders                                                                                  
     Pain in extremity                12               1             0             7            &lt;1        0         
     Back pain                        11               1             0             6            &lt;1        0         
  Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders                                                                                  
     Dyspnea                          12               3             0             8            2         0         
  Psychiatric disorders                                                                                             
     Insomnia                         10               &lt;1            0             6            0         0         
               a  National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events, version 3.
 

   b  Grade 3 dermatitis acneiform was reported in &lt;1% of patients in the group receiving TYKERB plus capecitabine.



 Table 2. Selected Laboratory Abnormalities 
                    TYKERB 1,250 mg/day + Capecitabine 2,000 mg/m2/day    Capecitabine 2,500 mg/m2/day    
                    All Gradesa            Grade 3           Grade 4           All Gradesa    Grade 3    Grade 4    
  Parameters        %                      %                 %                 %             %          %          
  Hematologic                                                                                                      
     Hemoglobin     56                     &lt;1                0                 53            1          0          
     Platelets      18                     &lt;1                0                 17            &lt;1         &lt;1         
     Neutrophils    22                     3                 &lt;1                31            2          1          
  Hepatic                                                                                                          
     Total Bilirubin    45                     4                 0                 30            3          0          
     AST            49                     2                 &lt;1                43            2          0          
     ALT            37                     2                 0                 33            1          0          
               a  National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events, version 3.
 

   Hormone Receptor-Positive, Metastatic Breast Cancer:  In a randomized clinical trial of patients (N = 1,286) with hormone receptor-positive, metastatic breast cancer, who had not received chemotherapy for their metastatic disease, patients received letrozole with or without TYKERB. In this trial, the safety profile of TYKERB was consistent with previously reported results from trials of TYKERB in the advanced or metastatic breast cancer population. Adverse reactions which occurred in at least 10% of patients in either treatment arm and were higher in the combination arm are shown in Table 3. Selected laboratory abnormalities are shown in Table 4.



 Table 3. Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=10% of Patients 
                                        TYKERB 1,500 mg/day + Letrozole 2.5 mg/day    Letrozole 2.5 mg/day    
                                        (N = 654)       (N = 624)    
                                        All Gradesa     Grade 3      Grade 4      All Gradesa    Grade 3    Grade 4    
  Reactions                             %               %            %            %            %         %         
  Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                                       
     Diarrhea                           64              9            &lt;1           20           &lt;1        0         
     Nausea                             31              &lt;1           0            21           &lt;1        0         
     Vomiting                           17              1            &lt;1           11           &lt;1        &lt;1        
     Anorexia                           11              &lt;1           0            9            &lt;1        0         
  Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                                                                               
     Rashb                              44              1            0            13           0         0         
     Dry skin                           13              &lt;1           0            4            0         0         
     Alopecia                           13              &lt;1           0            7            0         0         
     Pruritus                           12              &lt;1           0            9            &lt;1        0         
     Nail Disorder                      11              &lt;1           0            &lt;1           0         0         
  General disorders and administrative site conditions                                                                               
     Fatigue                            20              2            0            17           &lt;1        0         
     Asthenia                           12              &lt;1           0            11           &lt;1        0         
  Nervous system disorders                                                                                         
     Headache                           14              &lt;1           0            13           &lt;1        0         
  Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders                                                                               
     Epistaxis                          11              &lt;1           0            2            &lt;1        0         
               a  National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events, version 3.
 

   b  In addition to the rash reported under "Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders", 3 additional subjects in each treatment arm had rash under "Infections and infestations"; none were Grade 3 or 4.



 Table 4. Selected Laboratory Abnormalities 
                         TYKERB 1,500 mg/day + Letrozole 2.5 mg/day    Letrozole 2.5 mg/day    
                         All Gradesa          Grade 3         Grade 4         All Gradesa    Grade 3     Grade 4     
  Hepatic Parameters     %                    %               %               %              %           %           
     AST                 53                   6               0               36             2           &lt;1          
     ALT                 46                   5               &lt;1              35             1           0           
     Total Bilirubin     22                   &lt;1              &lt;1              11             1           &lt;1          
               a  National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events, version 3.
 

     Decreases in Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction:  Due to potential cardiac toxicity with HER2 (ErbB2) inhibitors, LVEF was monitored in clinical trials at approximately 8-week intervals. LVEF decreases were defined as signs or symptoms of deterioration in left ventricular cardiac function that are &gt;=Grade 3 (NCI CTCAE), or a &gt;=20% decrease in left ventricular cardiac ejection fraction relative to baseline which is below the institution's lower limit of normal. Among 198 patients who received combination treatment with TYKERB/capecitabine, 3 experienced Grade 2 and one had Grade 3 LVEF adverse reactions (NCI CTCAE v3)  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)].  Among 654 patients who received combination treatment with TYKERB/letrozole, 26 patients experienced Grade 1 or 2 and 6 patients had Grade 3 or 4 LVEF adverse reactions.



   Hepatotoxicity:  TYKERB has been associated with hepatotoxicity  [see Boxed Warning and Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  .



   Interstitial Lung Disease/Pneumonitis:  TYKERB has been associated with interstitial lung disease and pneumonitis in monotherapy or in combination with other chemotherapies  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)]  .



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of TYKERB. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Immune System Disorders:  Hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis  [see Contraindications (4)]  .



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  Nail disorders including paronychia.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: HEPATOTOXICITY

  WARNING: HEPATOTOXICITY

    Hepatotoxicity has been observed in clinical trials and postmarketing experience. The hepatotoxicity may be severe and deaths have been reported. Causality of the deaths is uncertain   [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)].    



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: HEPATOTOXICITY



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



   Hepatotoxicity has been observed in clinical trials and postmarketing experience. The hepatotoxicity may be severe and deaths have been reported. Causality of the deaths is uncertain   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )].    
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Decreases in left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) have been reported. Confirm normal LVEF before starting TYKERB and continue evaluations during treatment. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Lapatinib has been associated with hepatotoxicity. Monitor liver function tests before initiation of treatment, every 4 to 6 weeks during treatment, and as clinically indicated. Discontinue and do not restart TYKERB if patients experience severe changes in liver function tests. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Dose reduction in patients with severe hepatic impairment should be considered. (  2.2  ,  5.3  ,  8.7  ) 
 *    Diarrhea, including severe diarrhea, has been reported during treatment. Manage with anti-diarrheal agents, and replace fluids and electrolytes if severe. (  5.4  ) 
 *    Lapatinib has been associated with interstitial lung disease and pneumonitis. Discontinue TYKERB if patients experience severe pulmonary symptoms. (  5.5  ) 
 *    Lapatinib may prolong the QT interval in some patients. Consider ECG and electrolyte monitoring. (  5.6  ,  12.4  ) 
 *    Severe cutaneous reactions have been reported. Discontinue TYKERB if life-threatening reactions are suspected. (  5.7  ) 
 *    Fetal harm can occur when administered to a pregnant woman. Women should be advised not to become pregnant when taking TYKERB. (  5.8  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Decreased Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction



  TYKERB has been reported to decrease LVEF [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  . In clinical trials, the majority (&gt;57%) of LVEF decreases occurred within the first 12 weeks of treatment; however, data on long-term exposure are limited. Caution should be taken if TYKERB is to be administered to patients with conditions that could impair left ventricular function. LVEF should be evaluated in all patients prior to initiation of treatment with TYKERB to ensure that the patient has a baseline LVEF that is within the institution's normal limits. LVEF should continue to be evaluated during treatment with TYKERB to ensure that LVEF does not decline below the institution's normal limits [see Dosage and Administration (2.2)]  .



    5.2 Hepatotoxicity



  Hepatotoxicity (ALT or AST &gt;3 times the upper limit of normal and total bilirubin &gt;2 times the upper limit of normal) has been observed in clinical trials (&lt;1% of patients) and postmarketing experience. The hepatotoxicity may be severe and deaths have been reported. Causality of the deaths is uncertain. The hepatotoxicity may occur days to several months after initiation of treatment. Liver function tests (transaminases, bilirubin, and alkaline phosphatase) should be monitored before initiation of treatment, every 4 to 6 weeks during treatment, and as clinically indicated. If changes in liver function are severe, therapy with TYKERB should be discontinued and patients should not be retreated with TYKERB [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  .



    5.3 Patients With Severe Hepatic Impairment



  If TYKERB is to be administered to patients with severe pre-existing hepatic impairment, dose reduction should be considered [see Dosage and Administration (2.2) and Use in Specific Populations (8.7)]  . In patients who develop severe hepatotoxicity while on therapy, TYKERB should be discontinued and patients should not be retreated with TYKERB [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  .



    5.4 Diarrhea



  Diarrhea has been reported during treatment with TYKERB [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  . The diarrhea may be severe, and deaths have been reported. Diarrhea generally occurs early during treatment with TYKERB, with almost half of those patients with diarrhea first experiencing it within 6 days. This usually lasts 4 to 5 days. Lapatinib-induced diarrhea is usually low-grade, with severe diarrhea of NCI CTCAE Grades 3 and 4 occurring in &lt;10% and &lt;1% of patients, respectively. Early identification and intervention is critical for the optimal management of diarrhea. Patients should be instructed to report any change in bowel patterns immediately. Prompt treatment of diarrhea with anti-diarrheal agents (such as loperamide) after the first unformed stool is recommended. Severe cases of diarrhea may require administration of oral or intravenous electrolytes and fluids, use of antibiotics such as fluoroquinolones (especially if diarrhea is persistent beyond 24 hours, there is fever, or Grade 3 or 4 neutropenia), and interruption or discontinuation of therapy with TYKERB [see Dosage and Administration (2.2)]  .



    5.5 Interstitial Lung Disease/Pneumonitis



  Lapatinib has been associated with interstitial lung disease and pneumonitis in monotherapy or in combination with other chemotherapies [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  . Patients should be monitored for pulmonary symptoms indicative of interstitial lung disease or pneumonitis. TYKERB should be discontinued in patients who experience pulmonary symptoms indicative of interstitial lung disease/pneumonitis which are &gt;=Grade 3 (NCI CTCAE).



    5.6 QT Prolongation



  QT prolongation was observed in an uncontrolled, open-label, dose-escalation study of lapatinib in advanced cancer patients [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.4)]  . Lapatinib should be administered with caution to patients who have or may develop prolongation of QTc. These conditions include patients with hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia, with congenital long QT syndrome, patients taking anti-arrhythmic medicines or other medicinal products that lead to QT prolongation, and cumulative high-dose anthracycline therapy. Hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia should be corrected prior to lapatinib administration.



     5.7 Severe Cutaneous Reactions  



   Severe cutaneous reactions have been reported with TYKERB. If life-threatening reactions such as erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, or toxic epidermal necrolysis (e.g., progressive skin rash often with blisters or mucosal lesions) are suspected, discontinue treatment with TYKERB.  



    5.8 Use in Pregnancy



  TYKERB can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Based on findings in animals, TYKERB is expected to result in adverse reproductive effects. Lapatinib administered to rats during organogenesis and through lactation led to death of offspring within the first 4 days after birth [see Use in Specific Populations (8.1)]  .



 There are no adequate and well-controlled studies with TYKERB in pregnant women. Women should be advised not to become pregnant when taking TYKERB. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
