<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="typhim" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Adverse event information is derived from clinical trials and worldwide post-marketing experience.



   DATA FROM CLINICAL TRIALS

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reactions rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. The adverse reaction information from clinical trials does, however, provide a basis for identifying the adverse events that appear to be related to vaccine use and for approximating rates.



 Safety of Typhim Vi vaccine, the US licensed liquid formulation, has been assessed in clinical trials in more than 4,000 subjects both in countries of high and low endemicity. In addition, the safety of the lyophilized formulation has been assessed in more than 6,000 individuals. The adverse reactions were predominately minor and transient local reactions. Local reactions such as injection site pain, erythema, and induration almost always resolved within 48 hours of vaccination. Elevated oral temperature, above 38 degrees C (100.4 degrees F), was observed in approximately 1% of vaccinees in all studies. No serious or life-threatening systemic events were reported in these clinical trials. (10) (11)



 Adverse reactions from two trials evaluating Typhim Vi vaccine lots in the US (18- to 40-year-old adults) are summarized in Table 3. No severe or unusual side effects were observed. Most subjects reported pain and/or tenderness (pain upon direct pressure). Local adverse experiences were generally limited to the first 48 hours. (10) (11)



 Table 3 (10) (11): PERCENTAGE OF 18- TO 40-YEAR-OLD US ADULTS PRESENTING WITH LOCAL OR SYSTEMIC REACTIONS WITHIN 48 HOURS AFTER THE FIRST IMMUNIZATION WITH TYPHIM Vi VACCINE 
 REACTION                     Trial 1PlaceboN = 54     Trial 1Typhim Vi vaccineN = 54(1 Lot)  Trial 2Typhim Vi vaccineN = 98(2 Lots combined)   
  
   Local                                                                                                      
   Tenderness                       7 (13.0%)                 53 (98.0%)                 95 (96.9%)           
   Pain                             4 (7.4%)                  22 (40.7%)                 26 (26.5%)           
   Induration                           0                      8 (14.8%)                  5 (5.1%)            
   Erythema                             0                      2 (3.7%)                   5 (5.1%)            
   Systemic                                                                                                   
   Malaise                          8 (14.8%)                 13 (24.0%)                  4 (4.1%)            
   Headache                         7 (13.0%)                 11 (20.4%)                 16 (16.3%)           
   Myalgia                              0                      4 (7.4%)                   3 (3.1%)            
   Nausea                           2 (3.7%)                   1 (1.9%)                   8 (8.2%)            
   Diarrhea                         2 (3.7%)                       0                      3 (3.1%)            
   Feverish (subjective)                0                      6 (11.1%)                  3 (3.1%)            
   Fever &gt;=100 degrees F                0                      1 (1.9%)                       0               
   Vomiting                             0                      1 (1.9%)                       0               
          No studies were conducted in US children. Adverse reactions from a trial in Indonesia in children one to twelve years of age are summarized in Table 4. (10) (11) No severe or unusual side effects were observed.
 

 Table 4 (10) (11): PERCENTAGE OF INDONESIAN CHILDREN ONE TO TWELVE YEARS OF AGE PRESENTING WITH LOCAL OR SYSTEMIC REACTIONS WITHIN 48 HOURS AFTER THE FIRST IMMUNIZATION WITH TYPHIM Vi VACCINE 
 REACTIONS                                                                N = 175                         
  
   Local                                                                                                  
   Soreness                                                              23 (13.0%)                       
   Pain                                                                  25 (14.3%)                       
   Erythema                                                              12 (6.9%)                        
   Induration                                                             5 (2.9%)                        
   Impaired Limb Use                                                         0                            
   Systemic                                                                                               
   Feverishness                                                           5 (2.9%)                        
   Headache                                                                  0                            
   Decreased Activity                                                     3 (1.7%)                        
        In the US Reimmunization Study, subjects who had received Typhim Vi vaccine 27 or 34 months earlier, and subjects who had never previously received a typhoid vaccination, were randomized to placebo or Typhim Vi vaccine, in a double-blind study. Safety data from the US Reimmunization Study are presented in Table 5. (10) (11) (13) In this study 5/30 (17%) primary immunization subjects and 10/45 (22%) reimmunization subjects had a local reaction. No severe or unusual side effects were observed. Most subjects reported pain and/or tenderness (pain upon direct pressure). Local adverse experiences were generally limited to the first 48 hours. (10) (11) (13)
 

 Table 5 (10) (11) (13): US REIMMUNIZATION STUDY, SUBJECTS PRESENTING WITH LOCAL AND SYSTEMIC REACTIONS WITHIN 48 HOURS AFTER IMMUNIZATION WITH TYPHIM Vi VACCINE 
 REACTION                        PLACEBO(N = 32)       FIRST IMMUNIZATION(N = 30)   REIMMUNIZATION(N = 45)     
  
   Local                                                                                                      
   Tenderness                        2 (6%)                    28 (93%)                   44 (98%)            
   Pain                              1 (3%)                    13 (43%)                   25 (56%)            
   Induration                           0                       5 (17%)                    8 (18%)            
   Erythema                             0                       1 (3%)                     5 (11%)            
   Systemic                                                                                                   
   Malaise                           1 (3%)                    11 (37%)                   11 (24%)            
   Headache                          5 (16%)                    8 (27%)                    5 (11%)            
   Myalgia                              0                       2 (7%)                     1 (2%)             
   Nausea                               0                       1 (3%)                     1 (2%)             
   Diarrhea                             0                          0                       1 (2%)             
   Feverish (subjective)                0                       3 (10%)                    2 (4%)             
   Fever &gt;=100 degrees F             1 (3%)                        0                       1 (2%)             
   Vomiting                             0                          0                          0               
            Solicited Injection Site and Systemic Reactions When Given With Menactra Vaccine
   The majority (70%-77%) of solicited injection site reactions at the Typhim Vi and at the Menactra injection sites were reported as Grade 1 and resolved within 3 days post-vaccination. The most common systemic reactions were headache (41% when Menactra and Typhim Vi were given concomitantly; 42% when Typhim Vi was given with Placebo, and 33% when Menactra vaccine was given alone one month after Typhim Vi vaccination) and fatigue (38% when Menactra vaccine and Typhim Vi were given concomitantly; 35% when Typhim Vi was given with Placebo, and 27% when Menactra vaccine was given alone one month after Typhim Vi vaccination). Fever &gt;=40.0 degrees C and seizures were not reported.



   DATA FROM WORLDWIDE POST-MARKETING EXPERIENCE

  In addition to reports in clinical trials, worldwide voluntary adverse events reports received since market introduction of Typhim Vi vaccine are listed below. This list includes serious events and/or events which were included based on severity, frequency of reporting or a plausible causal connection to Typhim Vi vaccine. Because these events were reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to vaccination.



 *  Gastrointestinal disordersNausea, vomiting, diarrhea, abdominal pain 
 *  General disorders and administration site conditionInjection site pain, inflammation, induration, and erythema; lymphadenopathy, fever, asthenia, malaise, flu-like episode 
 *  Immune system disordersAnaphylaxis, allergic-type reactions such as pruritus, rash, urticaria, angioedema, difficulty breathing, hypotension; serum sickness 
 *  Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disordersMyalgia, arthralgia, cervical pain 
 *  Nervous system disordersSyncope with and without convulsions, headache, loss of consciousness, tremor 
 *  Respiratory system disordersAsthma 
      Additional Adverse Events
   Post-marketing reports of glomerulonephritis, neutropenia, bilateral retinitis, and polyarthritis have been reported in patients who had also received other vaccines; however, a causal relationship has not been established.



   REPORTING OF ADVERSE EVENTS

  Reporting by parents and patients of all adverse events occurring after vaccine administration should be encouraged. Adverse events following immunization with vaccine should be reported by the health-care provider to the US Department of Health and Human Services (DHHS) Vaccine Adverse Event Reporting System (VAERS). Reporting forms and information about reporting requirements or completion of the form can be obtained from VAERS through a toll-free number 1-800-822-7967 or visit the VAERS website at http//www.vaers.org. (17)



   Health-care providers also should report these events to the Pharmocovigilance Department, Sanofi Pasteur Inc., Discovery Drive, Swiftwater, PA 18370, or call 1-800-822-2463.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
