<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="uceris1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Systemic glucocorticosteroid use may result in the following:



 *  Hypercorticism and Adrenal Suppression [ See Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )] 
 *  Symptoms of steroid withdrawal in those patients transferring from Systemic Glucocorticosteroid Therapy [ See Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )] 
 *  Immunosuppression [ See Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )] 
 *  Increased Systemic Glucocorticosteroid Susceptibility [ See Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )] 
 *  Other Glucocorticosteroid Effects [ See Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )] 
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 2%) are headache, nausea, decreased blood cortisol, upper abdominal pain, fatigue, flatulence, abdominal distension, acne, urinary tract infection, arthralgia, and constipation. (  6  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Salix Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-800-508-0024 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of UCERIS has been evaluated in controlled and open-label clinical trials which enrolled a combined total of 1,105 patients with ulcerative colitis.



 In two 8-week, placebo-controlled studies in patients with active disease (Study 1 and Study 2), a total of 255 patients received UCERIS 9 mg, 254 patients received UCERIS 6 mg, and 258 patients received placebo. They ranged in age from 18-77 years (mean 43), 56% were male, and 75% were Caucasian. The most common adverse reactions were headache, nausea, decreased blood cortisol, upper abdominal pain, fatigue, flatulence, abdominal distension, acne, urinary tract infection, arthralgia, and constipation. The adverse reactions occurring in 2% or more of patients on therapy with UCERIS 9 mg are summarized in Table 1.



   Table 1. Summary of Adverse Reactions in Two Placebo-Controlled Trials Experienced by at Least 2% of the UCERIS 9 mg Group (Studies 1 and 2)  




                                                                                                                                                                           UCERIS 9 mg (N = 255) n (%)    UCERIS 6 mg (N = 254) n (%)                                                                              Placebo (N = 258) n (%)                                                                                  
  Headache                                                                                                                                                                 29 (11.4)        37 (14.6)                                                                                                27 (10.5)                                                                                                
  Nausea                                                                                                                                                                   13 (5.1)         12 (4.7)                                                                                                 11 (4.3)                                                                                                 
  Decreased Blood Cortisol                                                                                                                                                 11 (4.3)         6 (2.4)                                                                                                  1 (0.4)                                                                                                  
  Upper Abdominal Pain                                                                                                                                                     10 (3.9)         8 (3.1)                                                                                                  5 (1.9)                                                                                                  
  Fatigue                                                                                                                                                                  8 (3.1)          5 (2.0)                                                                                                  5 (1.9)                                                                                                  
  Flatulence                                                                                                                                                               6 (2.4)          8 (3.1)                                                                                                  5 (1.9)                                                                                                  
  Abdominal Distension                                                                                                                                                     6 (2.4)          4 (1.6)                                                                                                  2 (0.8)                                                                                                  
  Acne                                                                                                                                                                     6 (2.4)          2 (0.8)                                                                                                  5 (1.9)                                                                                                  
  Urinary Tract Infection                                                                                                                                                  5 (2.0)          1 (0.4)                                                                                                  1 (0.4)                                                                                                  
  Arthralgia                                                                                                                                                               5 (2.0)          5 (2.0)                                                                                                  4 (1.6)                                                                                                  
  Constipation                                                                                                                                                             5 (2.0)          1 (0.4)                                                                                                  2 (0.8)                                                                                                  
          Of UCERIS 9 mg patients, a total of 15% discontinued treatment due to any adverse event (including adverse reactions) compared with 17% in the placebo group.
 

 Table 2 summarizes the percentages of patients reporting glucocorticoid related effects in the 2 placebo-controlled studies.



   Table 2. Summary of Glucocorticoid Related Effects in Two Placebo-Controlled Trials (Studies 1 and 2)  




                                                                                                                                                                           UCERIS 9 mg (N = 255) n (%)    UCERIS 6 mg (N = 254) n (%)                                                                              Placebo (N = 258) n (%)                                                                                  
  Overall                                                                                                                                                                  26 (10.2)        19 (7.5)                                                                                                 27 (10.5)                                                                                                
  Mood changes                                                                                                                                                             9 (3.5)          10 (3.9)                                                                                                 11 (4.3)                                                                                                 
  Sleep changes                                                                                                                                                            7 (2.7)          10 (3.9)                                                                                                 12 (4.7)                                                                                                 
  Insomnia                                                                                                                                                                 6 (2.4)          6 (2.4)                                                                                                  8 (3.1)                                                                                                  
  Acne                                                                                                                                                                     6 (2.4)          2 (0.8)                                                                                                  5 (1.9)                                                                                                  
  Moon face                                                                                                                                                                3 (1.2)          3 (1.2)                                                                                                  4 (1.6)                                                                                                  
  Fluid retention                                                                                                                                                          2 (0.8)          3 (1.2)                                                                                                  3 (1.2)                                                                                                  
  Hirsutism                                                                                                                                                                1 (0.4)          0                                                                                                        0                                                                                                        
  Striae rubrae                                                                                                                                                            0                0                                                                                                        2 (0.8)                                                                                                  
  Flushing                                                                                                                                                                 0                1 (0.4)                                                                                                  3 (1.2)                                                                                                  
          No clinically significant differences were observed with respect to the overall percentages of patients with any glucocorticoid related effects between UCERIS and placebo after 8 weeks of induction therapy.
 

 Study 3 was an open-label study evaluating UCERIS 9 mg once daily for 8 weeks in 60 patients who had previously completed an 8-week induction study (Study 1), but had not achieved remission. Among patients who took UCERIS 9 mg up to 16 weeks cumulatively across Study 1 and Study 3 combined, similar rates of adverse reactions and glucocorticoid-related effects were seen compared to those who took UCERIS 9 mg for 8 weeks in Study 1.



 In Study 4, the safety of long-term treatment with UCERIS 6 mg was evaluated in a placebo-controlled 12-month maintenance study of 123 patients. Patients who had previously completed 8 weeks of therapy in any induction study (Study 1, 2, or 3) and were in remission were randomized to UCERIS 6 mg or placebo once daily for 12 months. In patients who took UCERIS 6 mg for up to 12 months, similar rates of adverse reactions were seen between placebo and UCERIS 6 mg. After up to 12 months of study treatment, 77% (27/35) of the patients in the UCERIS 6 mg and 74% (29/39) of the patients in the placebo treatment groups had normal bone density scans.



 In Study 4, the glucocorticoid related effects were similar in patients with up to 12 months of therapy with UCERIS 6 mg and placebo (Table 3).



   Table 3. Summary of Glucocorticoid Related Effects Over 12-month Treatment (Study 4)  




                                                      UCERIS 6 mg (N = 62) n (%)    Placebo (N = 61) n (%)                              
  Overall                                             9 (14.5)         7 (11.5)                                            
  Insomnia                                            4 (6.5)          4 (6.6)                                             
  Mood changes                                        4 (6.5)          2 (3.3)                                             
  Moon face                                           3 (4.8)          3 (4.9)                                             
  Sleep changes                                       3 (4.8)          3 (4.9)                                             
  Acne                                                3 (4.8)          0                                                   
  Hirsutism                                           3 (4.8)          0                                                   
  Flushing                                            1 (1.6)          1 (1.6)                                             
  Fluid retention                                     1 (1.6)         1 (1.6)                                              
           6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   In addition to adverse events reported from clinical trials, the following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of oral budesonide. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. These events have been chosen for inclusion due to either their  seriousness, frequency of reporting or causal connection to UCERIS, or a combination of these factors.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders  : diarrhea, rectal bleeding



   General Disorders and Administrative Site Conditions:  peripheral edema



   Immune System Disorders:  anaphylactic reactions



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  muscle cramps/spasms



   Nervous System Disorders:  benign intracranial hypertension, dizziness



   Psychiatric Disorders:  mood swings



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  rash



   Vascular Disorders:  increased blood pressure
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Hypercorticism and adrenal suppression : Since UCERIS is a glucocorticosteroid, follow general warnings concerning glucocorticoids. (  5.1  ) 
 *   Transferring patients from systemic glucocorticoids : Risk of impaired adrenal function when transferring fromglucocorticoid treatment with higher systemic effects to glucocorticoid treatment with lower systemic effects, such as UCERIS.  Taper patients slowly from systemic corticosteroids if transferring to UCERIS. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Immunosuppression : Potential worsening of infections (e.g., existing tuberculosis, fungal, bacterial, viral, or parasitic infection; or ocular herpes simplex). Use with caution in patients with these infections. More serious or even fatal course of chickenpox or measles can occur in susceptible patients. (  5.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypercorticism and Adrenal Axis Suppression



  When glucocorticosteroids are used chronically, systemic effects such as hypercorticism and adrenal suppression may occur. Glucocorticosteroids can reduce the response of the hypothalamus-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis to stress. In situations where patients are subject to surgery or other stress situations, supplementation with a systemic glucocorticosteroid is recommended. Since UCERIS is a glucocorticosteroid, general warnings concerning glucocorticoids should be followed.



    5.2 Transferring Patients from Systemic Glucocorticosteroid Therapy



  Care is needed in patients who are transferred from glucocorticosteroid treatment with higher systemic effects to glucocorticosteroids with lower systemic effects, such as UCERIS, since symptoms attributed to withdrawal of steroid therapy, including those of acute adrenal suppression or benign intracranial hypertension, may develop. Adrenocortical function monitoring may be required in these patients and the dose of glucocorticosteroid treatment with high systemic effects should be reduced cautiously.



    5.3 Immunosuppression



  Patients who are on drugs that suppress the immune system are more susceptible to infection than healthy individuals. Chicken pox and measles, for example, can have a more serious or even fatal course in susceptible patients or patients on immunosuppressant doses of glucocorticosteroids. In patients who have not had these diseases, particular care should be taken to avoid exposure.



 How the dose, route, and duration of glucocorticosteroid administration affect the risk of developing a disseminated infection is not known. The contribution of the underlying disease and/or prior glucocorticosteroid treatment to the risk is also not known. If exposed, therapy with varicella zoster immune globulin (VZIG) or pooled intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG), as appropriate, may be indicated. If exposed to measles, prophylaxis with pooled intramuscular immunoglobulin (IG) may be indicated. (See prescribing information for VZIG and IG.) If chicken pox develops, treatment with antiviral agents may be considered.



 Glucocorticosteroids should be used with caution, if at all, in patients with active or quiescent tuberculosis infection, untreated fungal, bacterial, systemic viral or parasitic infections.



 Replacement of systemic glucocorticosteroids with UCERIS tablets may unmask allergies (e.g., rhinitis and eczema), which were previously controlled by the systemic drug.



    5.4 Increased Systemic Glucocorticoid Susceptibility



  Reduced liver function affects the elimination of glucocorticosteroids, and increased systemic availability of oral budesonide has been demonstrated in patients with liver cirrhosis [See Use in Specific Populations  (  8.6  )].



    5.5 Other Glucocorticosteroid Effects



  Caution should be taken in patients with hypertension, diabetes mellitus, osteoporosis, peptic ulcer, glaucoma or cataracts, or with a family history of diabetes or glaucoma, or with any other condition where glucocorticosteroids may have unwanted effects.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
