<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="ultram" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  ULTRAM  (r)  was administered to 550 patients during the double-blind or open-label extension periods in U.S. studies of chronic nonmalignant pain. Of these patients, 375 were 65 years old or older. Table 2 reports the cumulative incidence rate of adverse reactions by 7, 30 and 90 days for the most frequent reactions (5% or more by 7 days). The most frequently reported events were in the central nervous system and gastrointestinal system. Although the reactions listed in the table are felt to be probably related to ULTRAM  (r)  administration, the reported rates also include some events that may have been due to underlying disease or concomitant medication. The overall incidence rates of adverse experiences in these trials were similar for ULTRAM  (r)  and the active control groups, TYLENOL  (r)  with Codeine #3 (acetaminophen 300 mg with codeine phosphate 30 mg), and aspirin 325 mg with codeine phosphate 30 mg, however, the rates of withdrawals due to adverse events appeared to be higher in the ULTRAM  (r)  groups.



 Table 2: Cumulative Incidence of Adverse Reactions for ULTRAM(r) in Chronic Trials of Nonmalignant Pain (N=427) 
                            Up to 7 Days               Up to 30 Days              Up to 90 Days               
  
 Dizziness/Vertigo          26%                        31%                        33%                         
 Nausea                     24%                        34%                        40%                         
 Constipation               24%                        38%                        46%                         
 Headache                   18%                        26%                        32%                         
 Somnolence                 16%                        23%                        25%                         
 Vomiting                   9%                         13%                        17%                         
 Pruritus                   8%                         10%                        11%                         
 "CNS Stimulation"          7%                         11%                        14%                         
 Asthenia                   6%                         11%                        12%                         
 Sweating                   6%                         7%                         9%                          
 Dyspepsia                  5%                         9%                         13%                         
 Dry Mouth                  5%                         9%                         10%                         
 Diarrhea                   5%                         6%                         10%                         
            
     Incidence 1% to less than 5% possibly causally related  : the following lists adverse reactions that occurred with an incidence of 1% to less than 5% in clinical trials, and for which the possibility of a causal relationship with ULTRAM  (r)  exists.



   Body as a Whole:  Malaise.



   Cardiovascular:  Vasodilation.



   Central Nervous System:  Anxiety, Confusion, Coordination disturbance, Euphoria, Miosis, Nervousness, Sleep disorder.



   Gastrointestinal:  Abdominal pain, Anorexia, Flatulence.



   Musculoskeletal:  Hypertonia.



   Skin:  Rash.



   Special Senses:  Visual disturbance.



   Urogenital:  Menopausal symptoms, Urinary frequency, Urinary retention.



   Incidence less than 1%, possibly causally related:  the following lists adverse reactions that occurred with an incidence of less than 1% in clinical trials of tramadol and/or reported in post-marketing experience with tramadol-containing products.



   Body as a Whole:  Accidental injury, Allergic reaction, Anaphylaxis, Death, Suicidal tendency, Weight loss, Serotonin syndrome (mental status change, hyperreflexia, fever, shivering, tremor, agitation, diaphoresis, seizures and coma).



   Cardiovascular:  Orthostatic hypotension, Syncope, Tachycardia.



   Central Nervous System:  Abnormal gait, Amnesia, Cognitive dysfunction, Delirium, Depression, Difficulty in concentration, Hallucinations, Movement disorder, Paresthesia, Seizure (see    WARNINGS    ), Speech disorder, Tremor.



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  Cases of hypoglycemia have been reported very rarely in patients taking tramadol. Most reports were in patients with predisposing risk factors, including diabetes or renal insufficiency, or in elderly patients.



   Respiratory:  Dyspnea.



   Skin:  Stevens-Johnson syndrome/Toxic epidermal necrolysis, Urticaria, Vesicles.



   Special Senses:  Dysgeusia, Mydriasis.



   Urogenital:  Dysuria, Menstrual disorder.



   

    Other adverse experiences, causal relationship unknown  : A variety of other adverse events were reported infrequently in patients taking ULTRAM  (r)  during clinical trials and/or reported in post-marketing experience. A causal relationship between ULTRAM  (r)  and these events has not been determined. However, the most significant events are listed below as alerting information to the physician.



   Cardiovascular:  Abnormal ECG, Hypertension, Hypotension, Myocardial ischemia, Palpitations, Pulmonary edema, Pulmonary embolism.



   Central Nervous System:  Migraine.



   Gastrointestinal:  Gastrointestinal bleeding, Hepatitis, Stomatitis, Liver failure.



   Laboratory Abnormalities:  Creatinine increase, Elevated liver enzymes, Hemoglobin decrease, Proteinuria.



   Sensory:  Cataracts, Deafness, Tinnitus.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
