<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="ultravist0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;1%) are headache, nausea, , injection site and infusion site reactions, vasodilatation, vomiting, back pain, urinary urgency, chest pain, pain, dysgeusia and abnormal vision. (  6  )



 To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Bayer HealthCare Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-888-842-2937 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect or predict the rates observed in practice.



 The following table of incidence of reactions is based upon controlled clinical trials in which ULTRAVIST Injection was administered to 1142 patients. This listing includes all reported adverse reactions regardless of attribution.



 Adverse reactions are listed by System Organ Class and in decreasing order of occurrence for rates greater than 1% in the ULTRAVIST group: see Table 3.




  Table 3: ADVERSE REACTIONS REPORTED IN &gt; 1% OF PATIENTS WHO RECEIVED ULTRAVIST INJECTION IN CLINICAL TRIALS    
  System Organ Class               Adverse Reaction             ULTRAVIST Injection                   
  N=1142 (%)                       
  Nervous system disorders         Headache                     46 (4)                                
  Dysgeusia                        15 (1.3)                     
  Eye disorders                    Abnormal Vision              12 (1.1)                              
  Cardiac disorders                Chest pain                   18 (1.6)                              
  Vascular disorders               Vasodilatation               30 (2.6)                              
  Gastrointestinal disorders       Nausea                       42 (3.7)                              
  Vomiting                         22 (1.9)                     
  Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders    Back pain                    22 (1.9)                              
  Renal and urinary disorders      Urinary urgency              21 (1.8)                              
  General disorders and administration site conditions    Injection site and infusion site reactions (hemorrhage, hematoma, pain, edema, erythema, rash)    41 (3.7)                              
  Pain                             13 (1.4)                     
         One or more adverse reactions were recorded in 273 of 1142 (24%) patients during the clinical trials, coincident with the administration of ULTRAVIST Injection or within the defined duration of the study follow-up period (24-72 hours). ULTRAVIST Injection is often associated with sensations of warmth and/or pain.
 

 Serious, life-threatening and fatal reactions have been associated with the administration of iodine-containing contrast media, including ULTRAVIST Injection. In clinical trials 7/1142 patients given ULTRAVIST Injection died 5 days or later after drug administration. Also, 10/1142 patients given ULTRAVIST Injection had serious adverse events.



 The following adverse reactions were observed in &lt;=1% of the subjects receiving ULTRAVIST Injection:



   Cardiac disorders  : atrioventricular block (complete), bradycardia, ventricular extrasystole



   Gastrointestinal disorders  : abdominal discomfort, abdominal pain, abdominal pain upper, constipation, diarrhea, dry mouth, dyspepsia, gastrointestinal disorder, gastrointestinal pain, salivation increased, stomach discomfort, rectal tenesmus



   General disorders and administration site conditions  : asthenia, chest discomfort, chills, excessive thirst, extravasation, feeling hot, hyperhidrosis, malaise, edema peripheral, pyrexia



   Immune system disorders  : asthma, face edema



   Investigations  : blood lactate dehydrogenase increased, blood urea increased, hemoglobin increased, white blood cell count increased



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders  : arthralgia, musculoskeletal pain, myasthenia, neck pain, pain in extremity



   Nervous system disorders  : agitation, confusion, convulsion, dizziness, hypertonia, hypesthesia, incoordination, neuropathy, somnolence, speech disorder, tremor, paresthesia, visual field defect



   Psychiatric disorders  : anxiety



   Renal and urinary disorders  : dysuria, renal pain, urinary retention



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders  : apnea, cough increased, dyspnea, hypoxia, pharyngeal edema, pharyngitis, pleural effusion, pulmonary hypertension, respiratory disorder, sore throat



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders  : erythema, pruritus, rash, urticaria



   Vascular disorders  : coronary artery thrombosis, flushing, hypertension, hypotension, peripheral vascular disorder, syncope, vascular anomaly



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of ULTRAVIST Injection. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Adverse reactions reported in foreign postmarketing surveillance and other trials with the use of ULTRAVIST Injection include:



   Cardiac disorders  : cardiac arrest, ventricular fibrillation, atrial fibrillation,    tachycardia, palpitations, congestive heart failure, myocardial infarction, angina pectoris



   Ear and labyrinth disorders:  vertigo, tinnitus



   Endocrine disorders:  hyperthyroidism, thyrotoxic crisis, hypothyroidism; Thyroid function tests indicative of hypothyroidism or transient thyroid suppression have been uncommonly reported following iodinated contrast administration to adult and pediatric patients, including infants. Some patients were treated for hypothyroidism.



   Eye disorders:  mydriasis, lacrimation disorder



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  dysphagia, swelling of salivary glands



   Immune system disorders:  anaphylactoid reaction (including fatal cases), respiratory arrest, anaphylactoid shock, angioedema, laryngeal edema, laryngospasm, bronchospasm, hypersensitivity



   Musculoskeleal and connective tissue disorders:  compartment syndrome in case of extravasation



   Nervous system disorders:  cerebral ischemia/infarction, paralysis, paresis, transient cortical blindness, aphasia, coma, unconsciousness, amnesia, hypotonia, aggravation of myasthenia gravis symptoms



   Renal and urinary disorders:  renal failure, hematuria



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  pulmonary edema, acute respiratory distress syndrome, asthma



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  Stevens-Johnson Syndrome, skin discoloration



   Vascular disorders:  vasospasm



   6.3 Pediatrics

  The overall character, quality, and severity of adverse reactions in pediatric patients are generally similar to those reported in adult patients. Additional adverse reactions reported in pediatric patients from foreign marketing surveillance or other information are: epistaxis, angioedema, migraine, joint disorder (effusion), muscle cramps, mucous membrane disorder (mucosal swelling), conjunctivitis, hypoxia, fixed eruptions, vertigo, diabetes insipidus, and brain edema.  [See Use in Specific Populations (8.4).]  
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: NOT FOR INTRATHECAL USE

  WARNING: NOT FOR INTRATHECAL USE

    Inadvertent intrathecal administration may cause death, convulsions, cerebral hemorrhage, coma, paralysis, arachnoiditis, acute renal failure, cardiac arrest, seizures, rhabdomyolysis, hyperthermia, and brain edema.   [See Contraindications (  4  ).]    



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: NOT FOR INTRATHECAL USE



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



   Inadvertent intrathecal administration may cause death, convulsions, cerebral hemorrhage, coma, paralysis, arachnoiditis, acute renal failure, cardiac arrest, seizures, rhabdomyolysis, hyperthermia, and brain edema.  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Anaphylactoid Reactions: Life-threatening or fatal anaphylactoid reactions may occur during or after ULTRAVIST administration, particularly in patients with allergic disorders. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Acute Renal Failure: Acute renal failure may occur following ULTRAVIST administration, particularly in patients with renal insufficiency, diabetes, multiple myeloma. Exercise caution and use the lowest necessary dose of ULTRAVIST in patients with renal dysfunction. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Cardiovascular Reactions: Hemodynamic disturbances including shock and cardiac arrest may occur during or shortly after administration of ULTRAVIST. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Thromboembolic Complications: Angiography may be associated with local and distal organ damage, ischemia, thromboembolism and organ failure. In angiographic procedures, consider the possibility of dislodging plaques or damaging or perforating the vessel wall. The physicochemical properties of the contrast agent, the dose and the speed of injection can influence the reactions. (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Anaphylactoid Reactions



  Life-threatening or fatal, anaphylactoid reactions, may occur during or after ULTRAVIST administration. Manifestations include respiratory arrest, laryngospasm, bronchospasm, angioedema, and shock. Increased risk is associated with a history of previous reaction to a contrast agent (3-fold), a known sensitivity to iodine and known allergic disorders (that is, bronchial asthma, hay fever and food allergies) or other hypersensitivities (2-fold). Exercise extreme caution when considering the use of iodinated contrast agents in patients with these histories or disorders.



 Emergency facilities and personnel trained in the treatment of anaphylactoid reactions should be available for at least 30 to 60 minutes after ULTRAVIST administration.



    5.2 Contrast Induced Acute Kidney Injury



  Acute kidney injury, including renal failure, may occur after intravascular administration of ULTRAVIST. Risk factors include: pre-existing renal insufficiency, dehydration, diabetes mellitus, congestive heart failure, advanced vascular disease, elderly age, concomitant use of nephrotoxic or diuretic medications, multiple myeloma / paraproteinemia, repetitive and/or large doses of ULTRAVIST.



 Use the lowest necessary dose of ULTRAVIST in patients with renal impairment. Adequately hydrate patients prior to and following ULTRAVIST administration. Patients with congestive heart failure receiving concurrent diuretic therapy may have relative intravascular volume depletion, which may affect the renal response to the contrast agent osmotic load. Observe such patients for several hours following the procedure to detect delayed hemodynamic renal function disturbances.



    5.3 Cardiovascular Reactions



  ULTRAVIST increases the circulatory osmotic load and may induce acute or delayed hemodynamic disturbances in patients with congestive heart failure, severely impaired renal function, combined renal and hepatic disease, combined renal and cardiac disease, particularly when repetitive and/or large doses are administered [see Drug Interactions (  7  )]  .



 Among patients who have had cardiovascular reactions, most deaths occurred from the start of injection to 10 minutes later; the main feature was cardiac arrest with cardiovascular disease as the main underlying factor. Isolated reports of hypotensive collapse and shock have been published.



 The administration of ULTRAVIST may cause pulmonary edema in patients with heart failure. Based upon published reports, deaths from the administration of iodinated contrast agents range from 6.6 per 1 million (0.00066 percent) to 1 in 10,000 patients (0.01 percent). Observe patients with preexisting cardiovascular disease for several hours following ULTRAVIST administration.



    5.4 Thromboembolic Complications



    *    Angiography may be associated with local and distal organ damage, ischemia, thromboembolism and organ failure including stroke, brachial plexus palsy, chest pain, myocardial infarction, sinus arrest, hepato-renal function abnormalities. For these reasons, meticulous angiographic techniques are recommended, including close attention to guide wire and catheter manipulation, use of manifold systems and/or three-way stopcocks, frequent catheter flushing with heparinized saline solutions and minimizing the length of the procedure. In angiographic procedures, consider the possibility of dislodging plaques or damaging or perforating the vessel wall with resultant pseudoaneurysms, hemorrhage at puncture site, dissection of coronary artery during catheter manipulations and contrast agent injection. The physicochemical properties of the contrast agent, the dose and the speed of injection can influence the reactions. Test injections to ensure proper catheter placement are suggested. Increased thrombosis and activation of the complement system has also occurred. Specialized personnel, and adequate equipment and facilities for immediate resuscitation and cardioversion are necessary. Monitor electrocardiograms and vital signs throughout the procedure. 
 *    Exercise care when performing venography in patients with suspected thrombosis, phlebitis, severe ischemic disease, local infection, venous thrombosis or a totally obstructed venous system. 
 *    Clotting may occur when blood remains in contact with syringes containing iodinated contrast agents. 
 *    Avoid angiography whenever possible in patients with homocystinuria because of the risk of inducing thrombosis and embolism [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  )].  
       5.5 Reactions in Patients with Hyperthyroidism, Pheochromocytoma, or Sickle Cell Disease
 

   Thyroid storm in patients with hyperthyroidism.  Thyroid storm has occurred after the intravascular use of iodinated contrast agents in patients with hyperthyroidism, or with an autonomously functioning thyroid nodule. Evaluate the risk in such patients before use of any iodinated contrast agent.



  Hypertensive crises in patients with pheochromocytoma.  Administer iodinated contrast agents with extreme caution in patients with known or suspected of having pheochromocytoma. Inject the minimum amount of contrast necessary. Assess the blood pressure throughout the procedure, and have measures for treatment of a hypertensive crisis readily available.



  Sickle cell disease.  Contrast agents may promote sickling in individuals who are homozygous for sickle cell disease when administered intravascularly.



    5.6 Extravasation



  Extravasation of ULTRAVIST Injection may cause tissue necrosis and/or compartment syndrome, particularly in patients with severe arterial or venous disease.



    5.7 Increased Radiation Exposure



  The decision to use contrast enhancement is associated with risk and increased radiation exposure. Use contrast after a careful evaluation of clinical, other radiologic data, and the results of non-contrast CT findings, taking into account the increased radiation dose and other risks.



    5.8 Interference with Image Interpretation



  As with other iodinated contrast agents, the use of ULTRAVIST Injection may obscure some lesions which were seen on non-contrast CT scans. Calcified lesions are less likely to enhance. The enhancement of tumors after therapy may decrease. The opacification of the inferior vermis following contrast agent administration has resulted in false-positive diagnosis. Cerebral infarctions of recent onset may be better visualized with contrast enhancement. However, older infarctions may be obscured by the contrast agent.



 In patients with normal blood-brain barriers and renal failure, iodinated contrast agents have been associated with blood-brain barrier disruption and accumulation of contrast in the brain. Accumulation of contrast in the brain also occurs in patients where the blood-brain barrier is known or suspected to be disrupted.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
