<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="ultravate0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6.  ADVERSE REACTIONS

    EXCERPT:   The most commonly reported adverse reactions (&gt;=1%) are telangiectasia, application site atrophy, and headache.  (6.1)  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Drug Safety at 1-800-406-7984 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 During randomized, controlled, blinded clinical trials 277 adults with plaque psoriasis were treated with ULTRAVATE lotion twice daily for up to two weeks (up to approximately 50 grams/week).



 Table 1 presents adverse reactions that occurred in at least 1% of subjects treated with ULTRAVATE lotion twice daily for up to two weeks, and more frequently than in vehicle-treated subjects.



   Table 1. Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;= 1% of Subjects Treated with ULTRAVATE Lotion for up to Two Weeks  



 



 Less common adverse reactions (incidence less than 1% but greater than 0.1%) that occurred in subjects treated with ULTRAVATE lotion included application site discoloration, herpes zoster, influenza, nasopharyngitis, otitis media acute, throat infection, wound, and increased blood pressure.



  Table1 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5.  WARNINGS



     EXCERPT:    *  Reversible hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis suppression may occur, with the potential for glucocorticosteroid insufficiency during or after treatment.  (5.1)   
 *  Systemic effects of topical corticosteroids may also include Cushing's syndrome, hyperglycemia, and glucosuria.  (5.1)   
 *  Systemic absorption may require evaluation for HPA axis suppression.  (5.1)   
 *  Use of potent corticosteroids on large areas, for prolonged durations, under occlusive dressings, or on an altered skin barrier may increase systemic exposure.  (5.1)   
 *  Children may be more susceptible to systemic toxicity when treated with topical corticosteroids.  (5.1  ,  8.4)   
 *  Local adverse reactions with topical steroids may include atrophy, striae, irritation, acneiform eruptions, hypopigmentation, and allergic contact dermatitis. Adverse reactions may be more likely to occur with occlusive use or more potent corticosteroids.  (5.2,    5.4)   
 *  Initiate appropriate therapy if concomitant skin infections develop.  (5.3)   
    
 

   5.1  Effects on Endorcrine System



  ULTRAVATE lotion is a topical corticosteroid that has been shown to suppress the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis.



 Systemic effects of topical corticosteroids may include reversible HPA axis suppression, with the potential for glucocorticosteroid insufficiency. This may occur during treatment or upon withdrawal of treatment of the topical corticosteroid.



 The potential for hypothalamic-pituitary adrenal (HPA) suppression with ULTRAVATE lotion was evaluated in a study of 20 adult subjects with moderate to severe plaque psoriasis involving &gt;=20% of their body surface area. ULTRAVATE lotion produced HPA axis suppression when used twice daily for two weeks in 5 out of 20 (25%) adult patients with plaque psoriasis. Recovery of HPA axis function was generally prompt with the discontinuation of treatment [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  )]  .



 Because of the potential for systemic absorption, use of topical corticosteroids, including ULTRAVATE lotion, may require that patients be evaluated periodically for evidence of HPA axis suppression. Factors that predispose a patient using a topical corticosteroid to HPA axis suppression include the use of more potent corticosteroids, use over large surface areas, prolonged use, occlusive use, use on an altered skin barrier, concomitant use of multiple corticosteroid-containing products, liver failure, and young age. An ACTH stimulation test may be helpful in evaluating patients for HPA axis suppression.



 If HPA axis suppression is documented, attempt to gradually withdraw the drug, reduce the frequency of application, or substitute a less potent steroid. Manifestations of adrenal insufficiency may require supplemental systemic corticosteroids. Recovery of HPA axis function is generally prompt and complete upon discontinuation of topical corticosteroids.



 Systemic effects of topical corticosteroids may also include Cushing's syndrome, hyperglycemia, and glucosuria. Use of more than one corticosteroid-containing product at the same time may increase the total systemic exposure to topical corticosteroids.



 Pediatric patients may be more susceptible than adults to systemic toxicity from the use of topical corticosteroids due to their larger surface-to-body mass ratios [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.4  )]  .



    5.2  Local Adverse Reactions



  Local adverse reactions from topical corticosteroids may include atrophy, striae, telangiectasias, burning, itching, irritation, dryness, folliculitis, acneiform eruptions, hypopigmentation, perioral dermatitis, allergic contact dermatitis, secondary infection, and miliaria. These may be more likely to occur with occlusive use, prolonged use, or use of higher potency corticosteroids, including ULTRAVATE lotion. Some local adverse reactions may be irreversible.



    5.3  Concomitant Skin Infections



  Use an appropriate antimicrobial agent if a skin infection is present or develops. If a favorable response does not occur promptly, discontinue use of ULTRAVATE lotion until the infection has been adequately treated.



    5.4  Allergic Contact Dermatitis



  Allergic contact dermatitis with corticosteroids is usually diagnosed by observing failure to heal rather than noting a clinical exacerbation. Consider confirmation of a clinical diagnosis of allergic contact dermatitis by appropriate patch testing. Discontinue ULTRAVATE lotion if allergic contact dermatitis is established.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
