<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="unasyn" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Adult Patients

  UNASYN is generally well tolerated. The following adverse reactions have been reported in clinical trials.



   Local Adverse Reactions

  Pain at IM injection site - 16%



 Pain at IV injection site - 3%



 Thrombophlebitis - 3%



 Phlebitis - 1.2%



   Systemic Adverse Reactions

  The most frequently reported adverse reactions were diarrhea in 3% of the patients and rash in less than 2% of the patients.



 Additional systemic reactions reported in less than 1% of the patients were: itching, nausea, vomiting, candidiasis, fatigue, malaise, headache, chest pain, flatulence, abdominal distension, glossitis, urine retention, dysuria, edema, facial swelling, erythema, chills, tightness in throat, substernal pain, epistaxis and mucosal bleeding.



   Pediatric Patients

  Available safety data for pediatric patients treated with UNASYN demonstrate a similar adverse events profile to those observed in adult patients. Additionally, atypical lymphocytosis has been observed in one pediatric patient receiving UNASYN.



   Adverse Laboratory Changes

  Adverse laboratory changes without regard to drug relationship that were reported during clinical trials were:



   Hepatic:  Increased AST (SGOT), ALT (SGPT), alkaline phosphatase, and LDH.



   Hematologic:  Decreased hemoglobin, hematocrit, RBC, WBC, neutrophils, lymphocytes, platelets and increased lymphocytes, monocytes, basophils, eosinophils, and platelets.



   Blood Chemistry:  Decreased serum albumin and total proteins.



   Renal:  Increased BUN and creatinine.



   Urinalysis:  Presence of RBC's and hyaline casts in urine.



   Postmarketing Experience

  In addition to adverse reactions reported from clinical trials, the following have been identified during post-marketing use of UNASYN or other products containing ampicillin. Because they are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, estimates of frequency cannot be made. These events have been chosen for inclusion due to a combination of their seriousness, frequency, or potential causal connection to UNASYN.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  Hemolytic anemia, thrombocytopenic purpura, and agranulocytosis have been reported. These reactions are usually reversible on discontinuation of therapy and are believed to be hypersensitivity phenomena. Some individuals have developed positive direct Coombs Tests during treatment with UNASYN, as with other beta-lactam antibacterials.



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  Cholestatic hepatitis, cholestasis, hyperbilirubinemia, jaundice, abnormal hepatic function, gastritis, stomatitis, black "hairy" tongue and  Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea. (see    CONTRAINDICATIONS    and    WARNINGS    sections).



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  Injection site reaction



   Immune System Disorders:  Serious and fatal hypersensitivity (anaphylactic) reactions (See    WARNINGS    section).



   Nervous System Disorders:  Convulsion



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:  Tubulointerstitial nephritis



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  Toxic epidermal necrolysis, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and acute generalised exanthematous pustulosis (AGEP), urticaria, erythema multiforme, and exfoliative dermatitis (see    CONTRAINDICATIONS    section).
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
