<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="utibron" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6     ADVERSE REACTIONS

  LABAs, such as indacaterol, one of the active ingredients in UTIBRON NEOHALER, increase the risk of asthma-related death. UTIBRON NEOHALER is not indicated for the treatment of asthma  [see Boxed Warning and Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  .



 The following adverse reactions are described in greater detail in other sections:



 *  Paradoxical bronchospasm [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)] . 
 *  Immediate hypersensitivity reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)] . 
 *  Cardiovascular effects [see Warnings and Precautions (5.6)] . 
 *  Worsening of narrow-angle glaucoma [see Warnings and Precautions (5.8)] . 
 *  Worsening of urinary retention [see Warnings and Precautions (5.9)] . 
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=2% and higher than placebo) are nasopharyngitis and hypertension. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation at 1-888-669-6682 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1     Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, the adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The UTIBRON NEOHALER safety database included 2654 subjects with COPD in two 12-week lung function trials and one 52-week long-term safety study. A total of 712 subjects received treatment with UTIBRON NEOHALER 27.5 mcg/15.6 mcg BID. The safety data described below are based on the two 12-week trials and the one 52-week trial.



   12-Week Trials  



 The incidence of adverse reactions associated with UTIBRON NEOHALER in Table 1 is based on two 12-week, placebo-controlled trials (Trials 1 and 2; N=1,001 and N=1,042, respectively). Of the 2040 subjects, 63% were male and 91% were Caucasian. They had a mean age of 63 years and an average smoking history of 47 pack-years, with 52% identified as current smokers. At screening, the mean post-bronchodilator percent predicted forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1) was 55% (range: 29% to 79%), the mean post-bronchodilator FEV1/forced vital capacity (FVC) ratio was 50% (range: 19% to 71%), and the mean percent reversibility was 23% (range: 0% to 144%).



 The most common adverse reaction (incidence greater than or equal to 2% and higher than placebo) was nasopharyngitis and hypertension.



 The proportion of patients who discontinued treatment due to adverse reactions was 2.95% for the UTIBRON NEOHALER treated patients and 4.13% for placebo-treated patients.



 Subjects received 1 dose twice-daily of the following: UTIBRON NEOHALER 27.5 mcg/15.6 mcg, indacaterol 27.5 mcg, glycopyrrolate 15.6 mcg, or placebo.



 Table 1. Adverse reactions with UTIBRON NEOHALER (greater than or equal to 1% incidence and higher than placebo) in COPD patients 
   Adverse Reaction      UTIBRON NEOHALER27.5/15.6 mcg BID(N=508)n (%)      Indacaterol27.5 mcg BID(N=511)n (%)      Glycopyrrolate15.6 mcg BID(N=513)n (%)      Placebo(N=508)n (%)     
 Nasopharyngitis  21 (4.1)         13 (2.5)         12 (2.3)         9 (1.8)           
 Hypertension     10 (2.0)         5 (1.0)          3 (0.6)          7 (1.4)           
 Back pain        9 (1.8)          7 (1.4)          2 (0.4)          3 (0.6)           
 Oropharyngeal pain  8 (1.6)          4 (0.8)          8 (1.6)          6 (1.2)           
           Other adverse reactions occurring more frequently with UTIBRON NEOHALER than with placebo, but with an incidence of less than 1% include dyspepsia, gastroenteritis, chest pain, fatigue, peripheral edema, rash/pruritus, insomnia, dizziness, bladder obstruction/urinary retention, atrial fibrillation, palpitations, tachycardia.
 

   52-Week Trial  



 In a long-term safety trial, 614 subjects were treated for up to 52 weeks with indacaterol/glycopyrrolate 27.5 mcg/15.6 mcg twice-daily, indacaterol/glycopyrrolate 27.5/31.2 mcg twice-daily or indacaterol 75 mcg once-daily. The demographic and baseline characteristics of the long-term safety trial were similar to those of the placebo-controlled efficacy trials described above. The adverse reactions reported in the long-term safety trial were consistent with those observed in the placebo-controlled trials of 12 weeks. Additional adverse reactions that occurred with a frequency greater than or equal to 2% in the group receiving indacaterol/glycopyrrolate 27.5 mcg/15.6 mcg twice-daily that exceeded the frequency of indacaterol 75 mcg once-daily in this trial were: upper and lower respiratory tract infection, pneumonia, diarrhea, headache, gastroesophageal reflux disease, hyperglycemia, rhinitis.



   6.2     Postmarketing Experience

  The following additional adverse reaction of angioedema has been identified during worldwide post-approval use of indacaterol/glycopyrrolate at higher than the recommended dose. Because this reaction is reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate the frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: ASTHMA-RELATED DEATH

    WARNING: ASTHMA-RELATED DEATH  

    Long-acting beta2-adrenergic agonists (LABAs) increase the risk of asthma-related death. Data from a large placebo-controlled U.S. study that compared the safety of another LABA (salmeterol) or placebo added to usual asthma therapy showed an increase in asthma-related deaths in patients receiving salmeterol. This finding with salmeterol is considered a class effect of all LABAs, including indacaterol, one of the active ingredients in UTIBRON NEOHALER.   



   The safety and efficacy of UTIBRON NEOHALER in patients with asthma have not been established. UTIBRON NEOHALER is not indicated for the treatment of asthma    [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)].  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: ASTHMA-RELATED DEATH  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Long-acting beta2-adrenergic agonists (LABAs), such as indacaterol, one of the active ingredients in UTIBRON NEOHALER, increase the risk of asthma-related death. A placebo-controlled study with another LABA (salmeterol) showed an increase in asthma-related deaths in patients receiving salmeterol. This finding of an increased risk of asthma-related death with salmeterol is considered a class effect of all LABAs, including indacaterol. (5.1) 
 *  The safety and efficacy of UTIBRON NEOHALER in patients with asthma have not been established. UTIBRON NEOHALER is not indicated for the treatment of asthma. (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5     WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Do not initiate in acutely deteriorating COPD or to treat acute symptoms. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Do not use in combination with an additional medicine containing LABA because of risk of overdose. (  5.3  ,  7.1  ) 
 *  If paradoxical bronchospasm occurs, discontinue UTIBRON NEOHALER immediately and institute alternative therapy. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Use with caution in patients with cardiovascular or convulsive disorders, thyrotoxicosis, sensitivity to sympathomimetic drugs, diabetes mellitus, and ketoacidosis. (  5.6  ,  5.7  ,  7.1  ) 
 *  Worsening of narrow-angle glaucoma or urinary retention may occur. Use with caution in patients with narrow-angle glaucoma, prostatic hyperplasia, or bladder-neck obstruction and instruct patients to contact a physician immediately if symptoms occur. (  5.8  ,  5.9  ) 
 *  Be alert to hypokalemia and hyperglycemia. (  5.11  ) 
    
 

   5.1     Asthma-Related Death [see Boxed Warning]



    *  Data from a large placebo-controlled U.S. study in asthma patients showed that LABAs may increase the risk of asthma-related death. Data are not available to determine whether the rate of death in patients with COPD is increased by LABAs. 
 *  A 28-week, placebo-controlled U.S. study comparing the safety of another LABA (salmeterol) with placebo, each added to usual asthma therapy, showed an increase in asthma-related deaths in patients receiving salmeterol (13/13,176 in patients treated with salmeterol versus 3/13,179 in patients treated with placebo; RR 4.37, 95% CI 1.25, 15.34). The increased risk of asthma-related death is considered a class effect of the LABAs, including indacaterol, one of the ingredients in UTIBRON NEOHALER. 
 *  No study adequate to determine whether the rate of asthma-related death is increased in patients treated with UTIBRON NEOHALER has been conducted. The safety and efficacy of UTIBRON NEOHALER in patients with asthma have not been established. UTIBRON NEOHALER is not indicated for the treatment of asthma. 
       5.2     Deterioration of Disease and Acute Episodes
 

  UTIBRON NEOHALER should not be initiated in patients with acutely deteriorating or potentially life-threatening episodes of COPD. UTIBRON NEOHALER has not been studied in patients with acutely deteriorating COPD. The initiation of UTIBRON NEOHALER in this setting is not appropriate.



 UTIBRON NEOHALER should not be used for the relief of acute symptoms, i.e., as rescue therapy for the treatment of acute episodes of bronchospasm. UTIBRON NEOHALER has not been studied in the relief of acute symptoms and extra doses should not be used for that purpose. Acute symptoms should be treated with an inhaled short-acting beta2-agonist.



 When beginning UTIBRON NEOHALER, patients who have been taking oral or inhaled, short-acting beta2-agonists on a regular basis (e.g., 4 times a day) should be instructed to discontinue the regular use of these drugs and use them only for symptomatic relief of acute respiratory symptoms. When prescribing UTIBRON NEOHALER, the healthcare provider should also prescribe an inhaled, short-acting beta2-agonist and instruct the patient on how it should be used. Increasing inhaled beta2-agonist use is a signal of deteriorating disease for which prompt medical attention is indicated.



 COPD may deteriorate acutely over a period of hours or chronically over several days or longer. If UTIBRON NEOHALER no longer controls the symptoms of bronchoconstriction; the patient's inhaled, short-acting beta2-agonist becomes less effective; or the patient needs more inhalation of short-acting beta2-agonist than usual, these may be markers of deterioration of disease. In this setting, a re-evaluation of the patient and the COPD treatment regimen should be undertaken at once. Increasing the daily dose of UTIBRON NEOHALER beyond the recommended dose is not appropriate in this situation.



    5.3     Excessive Use of UTIBRON NEOHALER and Use with Other Long-Acting Beta2-Adrenergic Agonists



  As with other inhaled drugs containing beta2-adrenergics, UTIBRON NEOHALER should not be used more often than recommended, at higher doses than recommended, or in conjunction with other medications containing LABAs, as an overdose may result. Clinically significant cardiovascular effects and fatalities have been reported in association with excessive use of inhaled sympathomimetic drugs. Patients using UTIBRON NEOHALER should not use another medicine containing a LABA for any reason [see Drug Interactions (7.1)]  .



    5.4     Paradoxical Bronchospasm



  As with other inhaled medicines, UTIBRON NEOHALER can produce paradoxical bronchospasm that may be life-threatening. If paradoxical bronchospasm occurs following dosing with UTIBRON NEOHALER, it should be treated immediately with an inhaled, short-acting bronchodilator; UTIBRON NEOHALER should be discontinued immediately and alternative therapy instituted.



    5.5     Immediate Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Immediate hypersensitivity reactions have been reported after administration of indacaterol or glycopyrrolate, the components of UTIBRON NEOHALER. If signs suggesting allergic reactions occur, in particular, angioedema (including difficulties in breathing or swallowing, swelling of tongue, lips and face), urticaria, or skin rash, UTIBRON NEOHALER should be discontinued immediately and alternative therapy instituted. UTIBRON NEOHALER should be used with caution in patients with severe hypersensitivity to milk proteins.



    5.6     Cardiovascular Effects



  Indacaterol, like other beta2-agonists, can produce a clinically significant cardiovascular effect in some patients as measured by increases in pulse rate, systolic or diastolic blood pressure, or symptoms. If such effects occur, UTIBRON NEOHALER may need to be discontinued. In addition, beta-agonists have been reported to produce ECG changes, such as flattening of the T wave, prolongation of the QTc interval, and ST segment depression, although the clinical significance of these findings is unknown.



 Therefore, UTIBRON NEOHALER should be used with caution in patients with cardiovascular disorders, especially coronary insufficiency, cardiac arrhythmias, and hypertension.



    5.7     Coexisting Conditions



  UTIBRON NEOHALER, like all medicines containing sympathomimetic amines, should be used with caution in patients with convulsive disorders or thyrotoxicosis, and in patients who are unusually responsive to sympathomimetic amines. Doses of the related beta2-agonist albuterol, when administered intravenously, have been reported to aggravate preexisting diabetes mellitus and ketoacidosis.



    5.8     Worsening of Narrow-Angle Glaucoma



  UTIBRON NEOHALER should be used with caution in patients with narrow-angle glaucoma. Prescribers and patients should be alert for signs and symptoms of acute narrow-angle glaucoma (e.g., eye pain or discomfort, blurred vision, visual halos or colored images in association with red eyes from conjunctival congestion and corneal edema). Instruct patients to consult a physician immediately should any of these signs or symptoms develop.



    5.9     Worsening of Urinary Retention



  UTIBRON NEOHALER should be used with caution in patients with urinary retention. Prescribers and patients should be alert for signs and symptoms of urinary retention (e.g., difficulty passing urine, painful urination), especially in patients with prostatic hyperplasia or bladder-neck obstruction. Instruct patients to consult a physician immediately should any of these signs or symptoms develop.



    5.10     Hypokalemia and Hyperglycemia



  Beta2-adrenergic agonists may produce significant hypokalemia in some patients, which has the potential to produce adverse cardiovascular effects [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)]  . The decrease in serum potassium is usually transient, not requiring supplementation. Inhalation of high doses of beta2-adrenergic agonists may produce increases in plasma glucose.



 In patients with severe COPD, hypokalemia may be potentiated by hypoxia and concomitant treatment [see Drug Interactions (7.2)]  , which may increase the susceptibility for cardiac arrhythmias.



 In 2 clinical trials of 12-weeks duration evaluating UTIBRON NEOHALER in subjects with COPD, there was no evidence of a treatment effect on serum glucose or potassium.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
