<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="valchlor" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the prescribing information:



 *  Mucosal or eye injury [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ) ] 
 *  Secondary exposure to VALCHLOR [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  ) ] 
 *  Dermatitis [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  ) ] 
 *  Non-melanoma skin cancer [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  ) ] 
    Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.
 

   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5%) are dermatitis, pruritus, bacterial skin infection, skin ulceration or blistering, and hyperpigmentation (  6.1  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Ceptaris Therapeutics, Inc. at 1-855-4-VALCHLOR (1-855-482-5245) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  In a randomized, observer-blinded, controlled trial, VALCHLOR 0.016% (equivalent to 0.02% mechlorethamine HCl) was compared to an Aquaphor  (r)  -based mechlorethamine HCl 0.02% ointment (Comparator) [  see Clinical Studies (  14  )  ]. The maximum duration of treatment was 12 months. Sixty-three percent (63%) of patients in the VALCHLOR arm and 67% in the comparator arm completed 12 months of treatment.



 The body system associated with the most frequent adverse reactions was skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders. The most common adverse reactions (occurring in at least 5% of the patients) are shown in  Table 1  .



 Table 1. Most Commonly Reported (&gt;=5%) Cutaneous Adverse Reactions 
                            VALCHLORN=128% of patients  ComparatorN=127% of patients   
 Any Grade                  Moderately-Severeor Severe  Any Grade                  Moderately-Severeor Severe   
 Dermatitis                 56                         23                         58                         17                          
 Pruritus                   20                         4                          16                         2                           
 Bacterial skin infection   11                         2                          9                          2                           
 Skin ulceration or blistering  6                          3                          5                          2                           
 Skin hyperpigmentation     5                          0                          7                          0                           
      In the clinical trial, moderately-severe to severe skin-related adverse events were managed with treatment reduction, suspension, or discontinuation. Discontinuations due to adverse reactions occurred in 22% of patients treated with VALCHLOR and 18% of patients treated with the comparator. Sixty-seven percent (67%) of the discontinuations for adverse reactions occurred within the first 90 days of treatment. Temporary treatment suspension occurred in 34% of patients treated with VALCHLOR and 20% of patients treated with the comparator. Reductions in dosing frequency occurred in 23% of patients treated with VALCHLOR and 12% of patients treated with the comparator.
 

 Reductions in hemoglobin, neutrophil count, or platelet count occurred in 13% of patients treated with VALCHLOR and 17% treated with Comparator.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Mucosal or eye injury: VALCHLOR exposure to mucous membranes, especially of the eyes, can cause mucosal injury which may be severe. Eye injury may lead to blindness. Immediately irrigate for at least 15 minutes followed by immediate medical consultation (  5.1  ). 
 *  Secondary exposure to VALCHLOR: individuals other than the patient must avoid skin contact with VALCHLOR (  2.2  ,  5.2  ). 
 *  Dermatitis: Monitor patients for redness, swelling, inflammation, itchiness, blisters, ulceration, and secondary skin infections. Stop treatment or reduce dose frequency (  2.1  ,  5.3  ). 
 *  Non-melanoma skin cancer: Monitor patients during and after treatment (  5.4  ). 
 *  Embryo-fetal toxicity: Can cause fetal harm. Advise women of potential hazard to a fetus (  5.5  ,  8.1  ). 
 *  Flammable gel: VALCHLOR is an alcohol-based gel. Avoid fire, flame, and smoking until the gel has dried (  2.2  ,  5.6  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Mucosal or Eye Injury



  Exposure of the eyes to mechlorethamine causes pain, burns, inflammation, photophobia, and blurred vision. Blindness and severe irreversible anterior eye injury may occur. Advise patients that if eye exposure occurs, (1) immediately irrigate for at least 15 minutes with copious amounts of water, normal saline, or a balanced salt ophthalmic irrigating solution and (2) obtain immediate medical care (including ophthalmologic consultation).



 Exposure of mucous membranes such as the oral mucosa or nasal mucosa causes pain, redness, and ulceration, which may be severe. Should mucosal contact occur, immediately irrigate for at least 15 minutes with copious amounts of water, followed by immediate medical consultation.



    5.2 Secondary Exposure to VALCHLOR



  Avoid direct skin contact with VALCHLOR in individuals other than the patient. Risks of secondary exposure include dermatitis, mucosal injury, and secondary cancers. Follow recommended application instructions to prevent secondary exposure [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )  ].



    5.3 Dermatitis



  The most common adverse reaction was dermatitis, which occurred in 56% of the patients [ see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )  ]. Dermatitis was moderately severe or severe in 23% of patients. Monitor patients for redness, swelling, inflammation, itchiness, blisters, ulceration, and secondary skin infections. The face, genitalia, anus, and intertriginous skin are at increased risk of dermatitis. Follow dose modification instructions for dermatitis [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.1  )  ].



    5.4 Non-Melanoma Skin Cancer



  Four percent (4%, 11/255) of patients developed a non-melanoma skin cancer during the clinical trial or during one year of post-treatment follow-up: 2% (3/128) of patients receiving VALCHLOR, and 6% (8/127) of patients receiving the mechlorethamine ointment comparator. Some of these non-melanoma skin cancers occurred in patients who had received prior therapies known to cause non-melanoma skin cancer. Monitor patients for non-melanoma skin cancers during and after treatment with VALCHLOR. Non-melanoma skin cancer may occur on any area of the skin, including untreated areas.



    5.5 Embryo-fetal Toxicity



  Based on its mechanism of action, case reports in humans, and findings in animals, VALCHLOR can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. There are case reports of children born with malformations in pregnant women systemically administered mechlorethamine. Mechlorethamine was teratogenic and embryo-lethal after a single subcutaneous administration to animals. Advise women to avoid becoming pregnant while using VALCHLOR. If this drug is used during pregnancy or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to a fetus [ see Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  )  ].



    5.6 Flammable Gel



  Alcohol-based products, including VALCHLOR, are flammable. Follow recommended application instructions [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.2  )  ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
