<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="valium" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  Side effects most commonly reported were drowsiness, fatigue, muscle weakness, and ataxia. The following have also been reported:



     Central Nervous System:  

  confusion, depression, dysarthria, headache, slurred speech, tremor, vertigo



     Gastrointestinal System:  

  constipation, nausea, gastrointestinal disturbances



     Special Senses:  

  blurred vision, diplopia, dizziness



     Cardiovascular System:  

  hypotension



     Psychiatric and Paradoxical Reactions:  

  stimulation, restlessness, acute hyperexcited states, anxiety, agitation, aggressiveness, irritability, rage, hallucinations, psychoses, delusions, increased muscle spasticity, insomnia, sleep disturbances, and nightmares. Inappropriate behavior and other adverse behavioral effects have been reported when using benzodiazepines. Should these occur, use of the drug should be discontinued. They are more likely to occur in children and in the elderly.



     Urogenital System:  

  incontinence, changes in libido, urinary retention



     Skin and Appendages:  

  skin reactions



     Laboratories:  

  elevated transaminases and alkaline phosphatase



     Other:  

  changes in salivation, including dry mouth, hypersalivation



 Antegrade amnesia may occur using therapeutic dosages, the risk increasing at higher dosages. Amnestic effects may be associated with inappropriate behavior.



 Minor changes in EEG patterns, usually low-voltage fast activity, have been observed in patients during and after Valium therapy and are of no known significance.



 Because of isolated reports of neutropenia and jaundice, periodic blood counts and liver function tests are advisable during long-term therapy.



   Postmarketing Experience

  Injury, Poisoning and Procedural Complications

  There have been reports of falls and fractures in benzodiazepine users. The risk is increased in those taking concomitant sedatives (including alcohol), and in the elderly.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
