<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="valstar" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Approximately 84% of patients who received intravesical VALSTAR in clinical studies experienced local adverse events, but approximately half of the patients reported irritable bladder symptoms prior to treatment. The local adverse reactions associated with VALSTAR usually occur during or shortly after instillation and resolve within 1 to 7 days after the instillate is removed from the bladder.



 TABLE 1 displays the frequency of the local adverse experiences at baseline and during treatment among 170 patients who received 800 mg doses of VALSTAR  (r)  (valrubicin) Sterile Solution for Intravesical Instillation in a multiple-cycle treatment regimen. Only 7 of 143 patients who were scheduled to receive six doses failed to receive all of the planned doses because of the occurrence of local bladder symptoms.




 TABLE 1Occurrence of Local Adverse Reactions Before and DuringTreatment with Intravesical VALSTAR (% of Patients)   
                     Patients Who Received Multiple-CycleTreatment Regimen at 800 mg/dose(N=170)     
    Reaction         BeforeTreatment       During 6-weekCourse of Treatment     
  ANY LOCALBLADDER SYMPTOM   45%              88%              
  Urinary Frequency   30%              61%              
  Dysuria          11%              56%              
  Urinary Urgency   27%              57%              
  Bladder Spasm    3%               31%              
  Hematuria        11%              29%              
  Bladder Pain     6%               28%              
  Urinary Incontinence   7%               22%              
  Cystitis         4%               15%              
  Nocturia         2%               7%               
  Local Burning Symptoms -Procedure Related   0%               5%               
  Urethral Pain    0%               3%               
  Pelvic Pain      1%               1%               
  Hematuria (Gross)   0%               1%               
         Most systemic adverse events associated with use of VALSTAR have been mild in nature and self-limited, resolving within 24 hours after drug administration. TABLE 2 displays the adverse events other than local bladder symptoms that occurred in 1% or more of the 230 patients who received at least one dose of VALSTAR (200 to 900 mg) in a clinical trial. It cannot be determined whether these events are drug-related.
 


 TABLE 2Most Commonly Reported Systemic Adverse ReactionsFollowing Intravesical Administration of VALSTAR (% of Patients)   
    Body SystemPreferred Term       All Patients Who Received VALSTAR(N = 230)     
    Body as a Whole     
    Abdominal Pain   5%               
    Asthenia       4%               
    Back Pain      3%               
    Chest Pain     3%               
    Fever          2%               
    Headache       4%               
    Malaise        4%               
    Cardiovascular     
    Vasodilation   2%               
    Digestive      
    Diarrhea       3%               
    Flatulence     1%               
    Nausea         5%               
    Vomiting       2%               
    Hemic and Lymphatic     
    Anemia         2%               
    Metabolic and Nutritional     
    Hyperglycemia   1%               
    Peripheral Edema   1%               
    Musculoskeletal     
    Myalgia        1%               
    Nervous        
    Dizziness      3%               
    Respiratory     
    Pneumonia      1%               
    Skin and Appendages     
    Rash           3%               
    Urogenital     
    Hematuria (miscroscopic)   3%               
    Urinary Retention   4%               
    Urinary Tract Infection   15%              
        Adverse reactions other than local reactions that occurred in less than 1% of the patients who received VALSTAR intravesically in clinical trials are listed below. This list includes only adverse reactions that were suspected of being related to treatment.
 

   Digestive System:  Tenesmus.  Metabolic and Nutritional:  Nonprotein nitrogen increased.  Skin and Appendages:  Pruritus.  Special Senses:  Taste loss.  Urogenital System:  Local skin irritation, poor urine flow, and urethritis.



 Inadvertent paravenous extravasation of VALSTAR was not associated with skin ulceration or necrosis.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
