<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="valtrex" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Thrombotic Thrombocytopenic Purpura/Hemolytic  Uremic Syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)].  
 *  Acute Renal Failure [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)] . 
 *  Central Nervous System Effects [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)] . 
    The most common adverse reactions reported in at least 1 indication by greater than 10% of adult subjects treated with VALTREX and observed more frequently with VALTREX compared to placebo are headache, nausea, and abdominal pain. The only adverse reaction reported in greater than 10% of pediatric subjects aged less than 18 years was headache.
 

    EXCERPT:    *  The most common adverse reactions reported in at least one indication by greater than 10% of adult subjects treated with VALTREX and more commonly than in subjects treated with placebo are headache, nausea, and abdominal pain. (6.1) 
 *  The only adverse reaction occurring in greater than 10% of pediatric subjects less than 18 years of age was headache. (6.2)  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch. 



 
   Table 2. Incidence (%) of Laboratory Abnormalities in Herpes Zoster and Genital Herpes Trial Populations 
  Laboratory Abnormality    Herpes Zoster    Genital Herpes Treatment    Genital Herpes Suppression    
  VALTREX  1 gram  3 times daily  (n = 967)    Placebo  (n = 195)    VALTREX  1 gram twice daily  (n = 1,194)    VALTREX  500 mg twice daily  (n = 1,159)    Placebo  (n = 439)    VALTREX  1 gram once daily  (n = 269)    VALTREX  500 mg once daily  (n = 266)    Placebo  (n = 134)    
  Hemoglobin  (&lt;0.8 x LLN)    0.8%           0%           0.3%           0.2%           0%           0%             0.8%           0.8%         
  White blood cells  (&lt;0.75 x LLN)    1.3%           0.6%         0.7%           0.6%           0.2%         0.7%           0.8%           1.5%         
  Platelet count (&lt;100,000/mm3)    1.0%           1.2%         0.3%           0.1%           0.7%         0.4%           1.1%           1.5%         
  AST (SGOT)  (&gt;2 x ULN)    1.0%           0%           1.0%           a              0.5%         4.1%           3.8%           3.0%         
  Serum creatinine  (&gt;1.5 x ULN)    0.2%           0%           0.7%           0%             0%           0%             0%             0%           
  a Data were not collected prospectively.    
  LLN = Lower limit of normal.    
  ULN = Upper limit of normal.    
               

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience in Adult Subjects

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Cold Sores (Herpes Labialis):  In clinical trials for the treatment of cold sores, the adverse reactions reported by subjects receiving VALTREX 2 grams twice daily (n = 609) or placebo (n = 609) for 1 day, respectively, included headache (14%, 10%) and dizziness (2%, 1%). The frequencies of abnormal ALT (greater than 2 x ULN) were 1.8% for subjects receiving VALTREX compared with 0.8% for placebo. Other laboratory abnormalities (hemoglobin, white blood cells, alkaline phosphatase, and serum creatinine) occurred with similar frequencies in the 2 groups.



   Genital Herpes:    Initial Episode:  In a clinical trial for the treatment of initial episodes of genital herpes, the adverse reactions reported by greater than or equal to 5% of subjects receiving VALTREX 1 gram twice daily for 10 days (n = 318) or oral acyclovir 200 mg 5 times daily for 10 days (n = 318), respectively, included headache (13%, 10%) and nausea (6%, 6%). For the incidence of laboratory abnormalities seeTable 2.



   Recurrent Episodes:  In 3 clinical trials for the episodic treatment of recurrent genital herpes, the adverse reactions reported by greater than or equal to 5% of subjects receiving VALTREX 500 mg twice daily for 3 days (n = 402), VALTREX 500 mg twice daily for 5 days (n = 1,136) or placebo (n = 259), respectively, included headache (16%, 11%, 14%) and nausea (5%, 4%, 5%). For the incidence of laboratory abnormalities see Table 2.



   Suppressive Therapy: Suppression of Recurrent Genital Herpes in Immunocompetent Adults:  In a clinical trial for the suppression of recurrent genital herpes infections, the adverse reactions reported by subjects receiving VALTREX 1 gram once daily (n = 269), VALTREX 500 mg once daily (n = 266), or placebo (n = 134), respectively, included headache (35%, 38%, 34%), nausea (11%, 11%, 8%), abdominal pain (11%, 9%, 6%), dysmenorrhea (8%, 5%, 4%), depression (7%, 5%, 5%), arthralgia (6%, 5%, 4%), vomiting (3%, 3%, 2%), and dizziness (4%, 2%, 1%). For the incidence of laboratory abnormalities see Table 2.



   Suppression of Recurrent Genital Herpes in HIV-1 Infected Subjects:  In HIV-1 infected subjects, frequently reported adverse reactions for VALTREX (500 mg twice daily; n = 194, median days on therapy = 172) and placebo (n = 99, median days on therapy = 59), respectively, included headache (13%, 8%), fatigue (8%, 5%), and rash (8%, 1%). Post-randomization laboratory abnormalities that were reported more frequently in valacyclovir subjects versus placebo included elevated alkaline phosphatase (4%, 2%), elevated ALT (14%, 10%), elevated AST (16%, 11%), decreased neutrophil counts (18%, 10%), and decreased platelet counts (3%, 0%), respectively.



   Reduction of Transmission:  In a clinical trial for the reduction of transmission of genital herpes, the adverse reactions reported by subjects receiving VALTREX 500 mg once daily (n = 743) or placebo once daily (n = 741), respectively, included headache (29%, 26%), nasopharyngitis (16%, 15%), and upper respiratory tract infection (9%, 10%).



   Herpes Zoster:  In 2 clinical trials for the treatment of herpes zoster, the adverse reactions reported by subjects receiving VALTREX 1 gram 3 times daily for 7 to 14 days (n = 967) or placebo (n = 195), respectively, included nausea (15%, 8%), headache (14%, 12%), vomiting (6%, 3%), dizziness (3%, 2%), and abdominal pain (3%, 2%). For the incidence of laboratory abnormalities see Table 2.



   6.2 Clinical Trials Experience in Pediatric Subjects

  The safety profile of VALTREX has been studied in 177 pediatric subjects aged 1 month to less than 18 years. Sixty-five of these pediatric subjects, aged 12 to less than 18 years, received oral caplets for 1 to 2 days for treatment of cold sores. The remaining 112 pediatric subjects, aged 1 month to less than 12 years, participated in 3 pharmacokinetic and safety trials and received valacyclovir oral suspension. Fifty-one of these 112 pediatric subjects received oral suspension for 3 to 6 days. The frequency, intensity, and nature of clinical adverse reactions and laboratory abnormalities were similar to those seen in adults.



   Pediatric Subjects Aged 12 to Less Than 18 Years (Cold Sores):  In clinical trials for the treatment of cold sores, the adverse reactions reported by adolescent subjects receiving VALTREX 2 grams twice daily for 1 day, or VALTREX 2 grams twice daily for 1 day followed by 1 gram twice daily for 1 day (n = 65, across both dosing groups), or placebo (n = 30), respectively, included headache (17%, 3%) and nausea (8%, 0%).



   Pediatric Subjects Aged 1 Month to Less Than 12 Years:  Adverse events reported in more than 1 subject across the 3 pharmacokinetic and safety trials in children aged 1 month to less than 12 years were diarrhea (5%), pyrexia (4%), dehydration (2%), herpes simplex (2%), and rhinorrhea (2%). No clinically meaningful changes in laboratory values were observed.



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  In addition to adverse events reported from clinical trials, the following events have been identified during postmarketing use of VALTREX. Because they are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, estimates of frequency cannot be made. These events have been chosen for inclusion due to a combination of their seriousness, frequency of reporting, or potential causal connection to VALTREX.



   General:  Facial edema, hypertension, tachycardia.



   Allergic:  Acute hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis, angioedema, dyspnea, pruritus, rash, and urticaria  [see Contraindications (4)]  .



   CNS Symptoms:  Aggressive behavior; agitation; ataxia; coma; confusion; decreased consciousness; dysarthria; encephalopathy; mania; and psychosis, including auditory and visual hallucinations, seizures, tremors  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3), Use in Specific Populations (8.5), (8.6)].  



   Eye:  Visual abnormalities.



   Gastrointestinal:  Diarrhea.



   Hepatobiliary Tract and Pancreas:  Liver enzyme abnormalities, hepatitis.



   Renal:  Renal failure, renal pain (may be associated with renal failure)  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2), Use in Specific Populations (8.5), (8.6)]  .



   Hematologic:  Thrombocytopenia, aplastic anemia, leukocytoclastic vasculitis, TTP/HUS  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  .



   Skin:  Erythema multiforme, rashes including photosensitivity, alopecia.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura/hemolytic uremic syndrome (TTP/HUS): Has occurred in patients with advanced HIV-1 disease and in allogenic bone marrow transplant and renal transplant patients receiving 8 grams per day of VALTREX in clinical trials. Discontinue treatment if clinical symptoms and laboratory findings consistent with TTP/HUS occur. (5.1) 
 *  Acute renal failure: May occur in elderly patients (with or without reduced renal function), patients with underlying renal disease who receive higher than recommended doses of VALTREX for their level of renal function, patients who receive concomitant nephrotoxic drugs, or inadequately hydrated patients. Use with caution in elderly patients and reduce dosage in patients with renal impairment. (2.4, 5.2) 
 *  Central nervous system adverse reactions (e.g., agitation, hallucinations, confusion, and encephalopathy): May occur in both adult and pediatric patients (with or without reduced renal function) and in patients with underlying renal disease who receive higher than recommended doses of VALTREX for their level of renal function. Elderly patients are more likely to have central nervous system adverse reactions. Use with caution in elderly patients and reduce dosage in patients with renal impairment. (2.4, 5.3) 
    
 

   5.1 Thrombotic Thrombocytopenic Purpura/Hemolytic Uremic Syndrome (TTP/HUS)



  TTP/HUS, in some cases resulting in death, has occurred in patients with advanced HIV-1 disease and also in allogeneic bone marrow transplant and renal transplant recipients participating in clinical trials of VALTREX at doses of 8 grams per day. Treatment with VALTREX should be stopped immediately if clinical signs, symptoms, and laboratory abnormalities consistent with TTP/HUS occur.



    5.2 Acute Renal Failure



  Cases of acute renal failure have been reported in:



 *  Elderly patients with or without reduced renal function. Caution should be exercised when administering VALTREX to geriatric patients, and dosage reduction is recommended for those with impaired renal function [see Dosage and Administration (2.4), Use in Specific Populations (8.5)].  
 *  Patients with underlying renal disease who received higher-than-recommended doses of VALTREX for their level of renal function. Dosage reduction is recommended when administering VALTREX to patients with renal impairment [see Dosage and Administration (2.4), Use in Specific Populations (8.6)].  
 *  Patients receiving other nephrotoxic drugs. Caution should be exercised when administering VALTREX to patients receiving potentially nephrotoxic drugs. 
 *  Patients without adequate hydration. Precipitation of acyclovir in renal tubules may occur when the solubility (2.5 mg/mL) is exceeded in the intratubular fluid. Adequate hydration should be maintained for all patients. 
    In the event of acute renal failure and anuria, the patient may benefit from hemodialysis until renal function is restored [see Dosage and Administration (2.4), Adverse Reactions (6.3)]  .
 

    5.3 Central Nervous System Effects



  Central nervous system adverse reactions, including agitation, hallucinations, confusion, delirium, seizures, and encephalopathy, have been reported in both adult and pediatric patients with or without reduced renal function and in patients with underlying renal disease who received higher-than-recommended doses of VALTREX for their level of renal function. Elderly patients are more likely to have central nervous system adverse reactions. VALTREX should be discontinued if central nervous system adverse reactions occur [see Adverse Reactions (6.3), Use in Specific Populations (8.5, 8.6)].  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
