<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="vancomycin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 10%) were nausea (17%), abdominal pain (15%)  ,  and hypokalemia (13%). (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact ANI Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at 1-800-308-6755 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The data described below reflect exposure to Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsules in 260 adult subjects in two Phase 3 clinical trials for the treatment of diarrhea associated with  C. difficile.  In both trials, subjects received Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsules 125 mg orally four times daily. The mean duration of treatment was 9.4 days. The median age of patients was 67, ranging between 19 and 96 years of age. Patients were predominantly Caucasian (93%) and 52% were male.



 Adverse reactions occurring in &gt;= 5% of Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsule-treated subjects are shown in Table 1. The most common adverse reactions associated with Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsules (&gt;= 10%) were nausea, abdominal pain, and hypokalemia.



 Table 1: Common (&gt;= 5%) Adverse Reactionsa for Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsules Reported in Clinical Trials for Treatment of Diarrhea Associated with C. difficile 
    a  Adverse reaction rates were derived from the incidence of treatment-emergent adverse events.   
  
     System/Organ Class              Adverse Reaction                Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsules % (N=260)    
     Gastrointestinal disorders       NauseaAbdominal painVomitingDiarrheaFlatulence       1715998             
     General disorders and administration site conditions       PyrexiaEdema peripheralFatigue       965                 
     Infections and infestations       Urinary tract infection         8                   
     Metabolism and nutrition disorders       Hypokalemia                     13                  
     Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders       Back pain                       6                   
     Nervous system disorders        Headache                        7                   
         Nephrotoxicity (e.g., reports of renal failure, renal impairment, blood creatinine increased) occurred in 5% of subjects treated with Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsules. Nephrotoxicity following Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsules typically first occurred within one week after completion of treatment (median day of onset was Day 16). Nephrotoxicity following Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsules occurred in 6% of subjects &gt;65 years of age and 3% of subjects &lt;=65 years of age (see  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS, Nephrotoxicity  [  5.3  ]).
 

 The incidences of hypokalemia, urinary tract infection, peripheral edema, insomnia, constipation, anemia, depression, vomiting, and hypotension were higher among subjects &gt;65 years of age than in subjects &lt;=65 years of age (see  USE IN SPECIFIC POPULATIONS, Geriatric Use  [  8.5  ]).



 Discontinuation of study drug due to adverse events occurred in 7% of subjects treated with Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsules. The most common adverse events leading to discontinuation of Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsules were  C. difficile  colitis (&lt;1%), nausea (&lt;1%), and vomiting (&lt;1%).



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsules. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



     Ototoxicity  : Cases of hearing loss associated with intravenously administered vancomycin have been reported. Most of these patients had kidney dysfunction or a preexisting hearing loss or were receiving concomitant treatment with an ototoxic drug (see  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS, Ototoxicity  [  5.4  ]). Vertigo, dizziness, and tinnitus have been reported.



     Hematopoietic  : Reversible neutropenia, usually starting 1 week or more after onset of intravenous therapy with vancomycin or after a total dose of more than 25 g, has been reported for several dozen patients. Neutropenia appears to be promptly reversible when vancomycin is discontinued. Thrombocytopenia has been reported.



     Miscellaneous  : Patients have been reported to have had anaphylaxis, drug fever, chills, nausea, eosinophilia, rashes (including exfoliative dermatitis), Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, and rare cases of vasculitis in association with the administration of vancomycin.



 A condition has been reported that is similar to the IV-induced syndrome with symptoms consistent with anaphylactoid reactions, including hypotension, wheezing, dyspnea, urticaria, pruritus, flushing of the upper body ("Red Man Syndrome"), pain and muscle spasm of the chest and back. These reactions usually resolve within 20 minutes but may persist for several hours.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *     Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsules must be given orally for treatment of staphylococcal enterocolitis and C. difficile -associated diarrhea. Orally administered Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsules are not effective for other types of infections. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Clinically significant serum concentrations have been reported in some patients who have taken multiple oral doses of Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsules for active C. difficile -associated diarrhea. Monitoring of serum concentrations may be appropriate in some instances. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Nephrotoxicity has occurred following oral Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsule therapy and can occur either during or after completion of therapy. The risk is increased in geriatric patients. (  5.3  ) Monitor renal function. 
 *    Ototoxicity has occurred in patients receiving Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsules. (  5.4  ) Assessment of auditory function may be appropriate in some instances. 
 *    Prescribing Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsules in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug resistant bacteria. (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Oral Use Only



   This preparation for the treatment of colitis is for oral use only and is not systemically absorbed. Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsules must be given orally for treatment of staphylococcal enterocolitis and Clostridium difficile-  associated diarrhea. Orally administered Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsules are not effective for other types of infections.  



  Parenteral administration of vancomycin is not  effective for treatment of staphylococcal enterocolitis and C. difficile  -associated diarrhea. If parenteral vancomycin therapy is desired, use an intravenous preparation of vancomycin and consult the package insert accompanying that preparation  .



    5.2 Potential for Systemic Absorption



  Clinically significant serum concentrations have been reported in some patients who have taken multiple oral doses of Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsules for active C. difficile  -associated diarrhea. Some patients with inflammatory disorders of the intestinal mucosa also may have significant systemic absorption of vancomycin. These patients may be at risk for the development of adverse reactions associated with higher doses of Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsules; therefore, monitoring of serum concentrations of vancomycin may be appropriate in some instances, e.g., in patients with renal insufficiency and/or colitis or in those receiving concomitant therapy with an aminoglycoside antibiotic.



    5.3 Nephrotoxicity



  Nephrotoxicity (e.g., reports of renal failure, renal impairment, blood creatinine increased) has occurred following oral Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsule therapy in randomized controlled clinical studies, and can occur either during or after completion of therapy. The risk of nephrotoxicity is increased in patients &gt;65 years of age (see ADVERSE REACTIONS, Clinical Trial Experience  [  6.1  ] and USE IN SPECIFIC POPULATIONS, Geriatric Use  [  8.5  ]).



 In patients &gt;65 years of age, including those with normal renal function prior to treatment, renal function should be monitored during and following treatment with Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsules to detect potential vancomycin induced nephrotoxicity.



    5.4 Ototoxicity



  Ototoxicity has occurred in patients receiving vancomycin. It may be transient or permanent. It has been reported mostly in patients who have been given excessive intravenous doses, who have an underlying hearing loss, or who are receiving concomitant therapy with another ototoxic agent, such as an aminoglycoside. Serial tests of auditory function may be helpful in order to minimize the risk of ototoxicity (see ADVERSE REACTIONS, Postmarketing Experience  [  6.2  ]).



    5.5 Superinfection



  Use of Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsules may result in the overgrowth of nonsusceptible bacteria. If superinfection occurs during therapy, appropriate measures should be taken.



    5.6 Development of Drug-Resistant Bacteria



  Prescribing Vancomycin Hydrochloride Capsules in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug resistant bacteria.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
