<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="varivax" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  *  fever &gt;=102.0 degrees F (38.9 degrees C) oral: 14.7% 
 *  injection-site complaints: 19.3% (  6.1  ) 
   Frequently reported (&gt;=10%) adverse reactions in children ages 1 to 12 years include: 
 *  *  fever &gt;=100.0 degrees F (37.8 degrees C) oral: 10.2% 
 *  injection-site complaints: 24.4% (  6.1  ) 
   Frequently reported (&gt;=10%) adverse reactions in adolescents and adults ages 13 years and older include: 
 *  *  varicella-like rash (injection site) 
 *  varicella-like rash (generalized) (  6.1  ) 
   Other reported adverse reactions in all age groups include: 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS or exposure during pregnancy or within three months prior to conception, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or VAERS at 1-800-822-7967 or www.vaers.hhs.gov.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice. Vaccine-related adverse reactions reported during clinical trials were assessed by the study investigators to be possibly, probably, or definitely vaccine-related and are summarized below.



 In clinical trials {2-9}, VARIVAX was administered to over 11,000 healthy children, adolescents, and adults.



 In a double  -  blind, placebo  -  controlled study among 914 healthy children and adolescents who were serologically confirmed to be susceptible to varicella, the only adverse reactions that occurred at a significantly (p&lt;0.05) greater rate in vaccine recipients than in placebo recipients were pain and redness at the injection site {2}.



     Children 1 to 12 Years of Age  



     One-Dose Regimen in Children  



 In clinical trials involving healthy children monitored for up to 42 days after a single dose of VARIVAX, the frequency of fever, injection  -  site complaints, or rashes were reported as shown in Table 1:



 Table 1: Fever, Local Reactions, and Rashes (%) in Children 1 to 12 Years of Age 0 to 42 Days After Receipt of a Single Dose of VARIVAX 
 Reaction    N                               % Experiencing Reaction  Peak Occurrence During Postvaccination Days   
  
 Fever &gt;=102.0 degrees F (38.9 degrees C) Oral  8827                              14.7%           0 to 42          
 Injection-site complaints  8916                              19.3%            0 to 2          
             (pain/soreness, swelling and/or erythema, rash, pruritus, hematoma, induration, stiffness)   
 Varicella-like rash (injection site)  8916                               3.4%           8 to 19          
 Median number of lesions                                      2                              
 Varicella-like rash (generalized)  8916                               3.8%           5 to 26          
 Median number of lesions                                      5                              
           In addition, adverse events occurring at a rate of &gt;=1% are listed in decreasing order of frequency: upper respiratory illness, cough, irritability/nervousness, fatigue, disturbed sleep, diarrhea, loss of appetite, vomiting, otitis, diaper rash/contact rash, headache, teething, malaise, abdominal pain, other rash, nausea, eye complaints, chills, lymphadenopathy, myalgia, lower respiratory illness, allergic reactions (including allergic rash, hives), stiff neck, heat rash/prickly heat, arthralgia, eczema/dry skin/dermatitis, constipation, itching.
 

 Pneumonitis has been reported rarely (&lt;1%) in children vaccinated with VARIVAX.



 Febrile seizures have occurred at a rate of &lt;0.1% in children vaccinated with VARIVAX.



     Two-Dose Regimen in Children  



 Nine hundred eighty-one (981) subjects in a clinical trial received 2 doses of VARIVAX 3 months apart and were actively followed for 42 days after each dose. The 2-dose regimen of varicella vaccine had a safety profile comparable to that of the 1-dose regimen. The overall incidence of injection-site clinical complaints (primarily erythema and swelling) observed in the first 4 days following vaccination was 25.4% Postdose 2 and 21.7% Postdose 1, whereas the overall incidence of systemic clinical complaints in the 42-day follow-up period was lower Postdose 2 (66.3%) than Postdose 1 (85.8%).



     Adolescents (13 Years of Age and Older) and Adults  



 In clinical trials involving healthy adolescents and adults, the majority of whom received two doses of VARIVAX and were monitored for up to 42 days after any dose, the frequencies of fever, injection-site complaints, or rashes are shown in Table 2.



 Table 2: Fever, Local Reactions, and Rashes (%) in Adolescents and Adults 0 to 42 Days After Receipt of VARIVAX 
 Reaction  N                            % PostDose 1  Peak Occurrence inPostvaccination Days            N            % PostDose 2  Peak Occurrence inPostvaccination Days   
  
 Fever &gt;=100.0 degrees F (37.8 degrees C) Oral  1584                         10.2%  14 to 27            956           9.5%    0 to 42    
 Injection-site complaints  1606                         24.4%   0 to 2             955           32.5%   0 to 2     
      (soreness, erythema, swelling, rash, pruritus, pyrexia, hematoma, induration, numbness)   
 Varicella-like rash (injection site)  1606                          3%     6 to 20            955            1%     0 to 6     
 Median number of lesions                                 2                                        2                
 Varicella-like rash (generalized)  1606                         5.5%    7 to 21            955           0.9%    0 to 23    
 Median number of lesions                                 5                                       5.5               
              In addition, adverse events reported at a rate of &gt;=1% are listed in decreasing order of frequency: upper respiratory illness, headache, fatigue, cough, myalgia, disturbed sleep, nausea, malaise, diarrhea, stiff neck, irritability/nervousness, lymphadenopathy, chills, eye complaints, abdominal pain, loss of appetite, arthralgia, otitis, itching, vomiting, other rashes, constipation, lower respiratory illness, allergic reactions (including allergic rash, hives), contact rash, cold/canker sore.
 

   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  Broad use of VARIVAX could reveal adverse events not observed in clinical trials.



 The following additional adverse events, regardless of causality, have been reported during post-marketing use of VARIVAX:



   Body as a Whole  



 Anaphylaxis (including anaphylactic shock) and related phenomena such as angioneurotic edema, facial edema, and peripheral edema.



   Eye Disorders  



 Necrotizing retinitis (in immunocompromised individuals).



   Hemic and Lymphatic System  



 Aplastic anemia; thrombocytopenia (including idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP)).



   Infections and Infestations  



 Varicella (vaccine strain).



   Nervous/Psychiatric  



 Encephalitis; cerebrovascular accident; transverse myelitis; Guillain-Barre syndrome; Bell's palsy; ataxia; non-febrile seizures; aseptic meningitis; dizziness; paresthesia.



   Respiratory  



 Pharyngitis; pneumonia/pneumonitis.



   Skin  



 Stevens-Johnson syndrome; erythema multiforme; Henoch-Schonlein purpura; secondary bacterial infections of skin and soft tissue, including impetigo and cellulitis; herpes zoster.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Evaluate individuals for immune competence prior to administration of VARIVAX if there is a family history of congenital or hereditary immunodeficiency. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Avoid contact with high-risk individuals susceptible to varicella because of possible transmission of varicella vaccine virus. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Defer vaccination for at least 5 months following blood or plasma transfusions, or administration of immune globulins (IG). (  5.5  ,  7.2  ) 
 *  Avoid use of salicylates for 6 weeks following administration of VARIVAX to children and adolescents. (  5.6  ,  7.1  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Management of Allergic Reactions



  Adequate treatment provisions, including epinephrine injection (1:1000), should be available for immediate use should anaphylaxis occur.



    5.2 Family History of Immunodeficiency



  Vaccination should be deferred in patients with a family history of congenital or hereditary immunodeficiency until the patient's immune status has been evaluated and the patient has been found to be immunocompetent.



    5.3 Use in HIV-Infected Individuals



  The Advisory Committee for Immunization Practices (ACIP) has recommendations on the use of varicella vaccine in HIV-infected individuals.



    5.4 Risk of Vaccine Virus Transmission



  Post-marketing experience suggests that transmission of vaccine virus may occur rarely between healthy vaccinees who develop a varicella-like rash and healthy susceptible contacts. Transmission of vaccine virus from a mother who did not develop a varicella-like rash to her newborn infant has been reported.



 Due to the concern for transmission of vaccine virus, vaccine recipients should attempt to avoid whenever possible close association with susceptible high-risk individuals for up to six weeks following vaccination with VARIVAX. Susceptible high-risk individuals include:



 *  Immunocompromised individuals; 
 *  Pregnant women without documented history of varicella or laboratory evidence of prior infection; 
 *  Newborn infants of mothers without documented history of varicella or laboratory evidence of prior infection and all newborn infants born at &lt;28 weeks gestation regardless of maternal varicella immunity. 
       5.5 Immune Globulins and Transfusions
 

  Immunoglobulins should not be given concomitantly with VARIVAX. Vaccination should be deferred for at least 5 months following blood or plasma transfusions, or administration of immune globulin(s) {1}.



 Following administration of VARIVAX, immune globulin(s) should not be given for 2 months thereafter unless its use outweighs the benefits of vaccination {1}. [See  Drug Interactions (7.2)  .]  



    5.6 Salicylate Therapy



  Avoid use of salicylates (aspirin) or salicylate-containing products in children and adolescents 12 months through 17 years of age for six weeks following vaccination with VARIVAX because of the association of Reye syndrome with aspirin therapy and wild-type varicella infection. [See  Drug Interactions (7.1)  .]  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
