<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="varubi" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 5%) are:



 *  Cisplatin Based Highly Emetogenic Chemotherapy: neutropenia and hiccups (   6.1   ) 
 *  Moderately Emetogenic Chemotherapy and Combinations of Anthracycline and Cyclophosphamide: decreased appetite, neutropenia and dizziness (   6.1   ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Tesaro at 1-844-4-TESARO or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The safety of VARUBI was evaluated in approximately 2800 patients in 4 controlled clinical trials in patients receiving emetogenic cancer chemotherapy. VARUBI was given in combination with a 5-HT3 receptor antagonist and dexamethasone. On Day 1 of Cycle 1 of chemotherapy, 1567 patients were treated with VARUBI and 1198 of these patients continued into the optional multiple cycle extension for up to 6 cycles of chemotherapy. The median number of cycles administered 180 mg of VARUBI was four. VARUBI 180 mg was administered to 1294 patients.



 In Cycle 1 adverse reactions were reported in approximately 7% of patients treated with VARUBI compared with approximately 6% of patients treated with control therapy. The most common adverse reactions reported with an incidence of &gt;=3% and greater than control are listed in  Table 2  and  Table 3  .



 Table 2: Most Common Adverse Reactions in Patients Receiving Cisplatin-Based Highly Emetogenic Chemotherapy (Cycle 1)* 
   *  all reactions occurring at &gt;= 3% in the VARUBI group and for which the rate for VARUBI exceeds the rate for control   
  
                              VARUBI Regimen(VARUBI, Dexamethasone, and 5-HT3Receptor Antagonist)N = 624      Control(Placebo, Dexamethasone, and5-HT3Receptor Antagonist)N = 627     
 Neutropenia                9%                         8%                          
 Hiccups                    5%                         4%                          
 Abdominal Pain             3%                         2%                          
     Table 3: Most Common Adverse Reactions in Patients Receiving Moderately Emetogenic Chemotherapy and Combinations of Anthracycline and Cyclophosphamide (Cycle 1)* 
 *all reactions occurring at &gt;= 3% in the VARUBI group and for which the rate for VARUBI exceeds the rate for control.   
  
                              VARUBI Regimen(VARUBI, Dexamethasone, and 5-HT3Receptor Antagonist)N = 670      Control(Placebo, Dexamethasone, and5-HT3Receptor Antagonist)N = 674     
 Decreased appetite         9%                         7%                          
 Neutropenia                7%                         6%                          
 Dizziness                  6%                         4%                          
 Dyspepsia                  4%                         2%                          
 Urinary tract infection    4%                         3%                          
 Stomatitis                 4%                         2%                          
 Anemia                     3%                         2%                          
      Adverse reactions in the multiple-cycle extensions of highly and moderately emetogenic chemotherapy studies for up to 6 cycles of chemotherapy were generally similar to that observed in Cycle 1.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  EXCERPT:   Interaction with CYP2D6 Substrates with a Narrow Therapeutic Index: The inhibitory effect of a single dose of VARUBI on CYP2D6 lasts at least 7 days and may last longer. Avoid use of pimozide; monitor for adverse reactions if concomitant use with other CYP2D6 substrates with a narrow therapeutic index cannot be avoided (   4    ,   5.1    ,   7.1    )



 



   5.1 Interaction with CYP2D6 Substrates with a Narrow Therapeutic Index



  The inhibitory effect of VARUBI on CYP2D6 lasts at least 7 days and may last longer after a single dose administration of VARUBI [see Contraindications (  4  ), Drug Interactions (  7  ), Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  . Avoid use of VARUBI in patients who are receiving pimozide, a CYP2D6 substrate. An increase in plasma concentrations of pimozide may result in QT prolongation. Monitor for adverse reactions if concomitant use of VARUBI and other CYP2D6 substrates with a narrow therapeutic index cannot be avoided.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
