<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="vascepa" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common reported adverse reaction (incidence &gt;2% and greater than placebo) was arthralgia. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Amarin Pharma Inc. at 1-855-VASCEPA (1-855-827-2372) or contact the FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 Adverse reactions reported in at least 2% and at a greater rate than placebo for patients treated with VASCEPA based on pooled data across two clinical studies are listed in Table 1.



 Table 1. Adverse Reactions Occurring at Incidence &gt;2% and Greater than Placebo in Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled TrialsStudies included patients with triglycerides values of 200 to 2000 mg/dL. 
 Adverse Reaction                          Placebo(N=309)   VASCEPA(N=622)    
 n                                                %                n                %          
  
 Arthralgia                                       3               1.0              14               2.3         
           An additional adverse reaction from clinical studies was oropharyngeal pain.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  EXCERPT:   In patients with hepatic impairment, monitor ALT and AST levels periodically during therapy. (  5.1  )



 Use with caution in patients with known hypersensitivity to fish and/or shellfish. (  5.2  )



 



   5.1 Monitoring: Laboratory Tests



  In patients with hepatic impairment, alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) levels should be monitored periodically during therapy with VASCEPA.



    5.2 Fish Allergy



  VASCEPA contains ethyl esters of the omega-3 fatty acid, eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA), obtained from the oil of fish. It is not known whether patients with allergies to fish and/or shellfish are at increased risk of an allergic reaction to VASCEPA. VASCEPA should be used with caution in patients with known hypersensitivity to fish and/or shellfish.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
