<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="vaxchora" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt; 3%) were tiredness (31%), headache (29%), abdominal pain (19%), nausea/vomiting (18%), lack of appetite (17%) and diarrhea (4%). (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact PaxVax, Inc. at 1-800-533-5899 or safety@paxvax.com, or VAERS at 1-800-222-7967 or      www.vaers.hhs.gov.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in clinical trials of a vaccine cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another vaccine and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of VAXCHORA was evaluated in four randomized, placebo-controlled, multicenter clinical trials. A total of 3235 adults 18 through 64 years of age received one dose of VAXCHORA and 562 received placebo [physiologic saline (N=551) or lactose (N=11)]. Overall, the mean age was 32.5 years; 53.8% of trial participants were female; 67.1% were White, 27.3% were Black or African American, 1.8% were Asian, 1.7% were multiracial, 1.3% were other, 0.6% were American Indian or Alaskan Native and 0.3% were Native Hawaiian or Pacific Islander. There were 9.3% Hispanic or Latino participants.



   Solicited Adverse Reactions  



 Adults 18 through 45 years of age received VAXCHORA in a multi-center, double-blind, randomized (8:1), placebo-controlled trial conducted in the United States and Australia (Study 1). The safety analysis set included 2789 VAXCHORA recipients. Solicited adverse reactions were recorded daily for 7 days following vaccination.  Table 1  presents the frequency and severity of solicited adverse reactions observed within 7 days following receipt of VAXCHORA or placebo in Study 1.



   Table 1: Rates of Solicited Adverse Reactions Reported in VAXCHORA Trial Participants 18 to 45 Years of Age During 7 Days Post-Vaccination  




                             Study 1             
                             VAXCHORA             Placebo (Saline)     
     Adverse Reaction        (N=2789)             (N=350)         
                             %                    %               
  
    Tiredness               31.3                 27.4             
       Mild                 18.7                 16.3             
       Moderate             12.0                 9.9              
       SevereSevere category includes both grade 3 (severe) and grade 4 (potentially life-threatening) adverse events.    0.7                  1.2              
    Headache                28.9                 23.6             
       Mild                 18.9                 14.6             
       Moderate             9.6                  8.8              
       Severe               0.5                  0.3              
    Abdominal Pain          18.7                 16.9             
       Mild                 12.1                 12.0             
       Moderate             6.2                  5.0              
       Severe               0.4                  0.0              
    Nausea/Vomiting         18.3                 15.2             
       Mild                 13.3                 11.4             
       Moderate             4.7                  3.8              
       Severe               0.3                  0.0              
    Lack of Appetite        16.5                 16.6             
       Mild                 11.7                 12.2             
       Moderate             4.4                  4.4              
       Severe               0.3                  0.0              
    Diarrhea                3.9                  1.2              
       Mild                 2.4                  0.9              
       Moderate             0.7                  0.3              
       Severe               0.84                 0.0              
    Fever                   0.6                  1.2              
       Mild                 0.2                  0.3              
       Moderate             0.3                  0.9              
       Severe               0.11                 0.0              
           Grading scales are defined as follows:  
 

   Tiredness, Headache, Abdominal Pain, Nausea, Lack of Appetite: Mild = no interference with activity, Moderate = Some interference with activity, Severe = significant, prevents daily activity, Potentially Life Threatening = emergency room (ER) visit or hospitalization.  



   Vomiting: Mild = 1-2 episodes/24 hours, Moderate = &gt;2 episodes/24 hours, Severe = requires intravenous hydration, Potentially Life Threatening = ER visit or hospitalization for hypotensive shock.  



   Diarrhea: Mild = 4 loose stools/24 hours, Moderate = 5 loose stools/24 hours, Severe = &gt;=6 loose stools /24 hours, Potentially Life Threatening = ER visit or hospitalization.  



   Fever: Mild = 38.0-38.4 degrees C/100.4-101.1 degrees F, Moderate = 38.5-38.9 degrees C/101.2- 102.0 degrees F, Severe = 39.0-40.0 degrees C/102.1-104.0 degrees F, Potentially Life Threatening = &gt;40.0  degrees C/104.0  degrees F.  



   Serious Adverse Events  



 In a pooled analysis of the four clinical studies, 0.6% (20/3235) of VAXCHORA recipients and 0.5% (3/562) of placebo recipients reported a serious adverse event within 6 months post-vaccination. None of these events were considered to be related to vaccination.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    The safety and effectiveness of VAXCHORA have not been established in immunocompromised persons. (  5.1  ) 
 *    VAXCHORA may be shed in the stool of recipients for at least 7 days. There is a potential for transmission of the vaccine strain to non- vaccinated close contacts (e.g., household contacts). Use caution when considering whether to administer VAXCHORA to individuals with immunocompromised close contacts. (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Altered Immunocompetence



  The safety and effectiveness of VAXCHORA have not been established in immunocompromised persons [see Immunocompromised Individuals (  8.6  )]  .



    5.2 Shedding and Transmission



  VAXCHORA may be shed in the stool of recipients for at least 7 days. There is a potential for transmission of the vaccine strain to non-vaccinated close contacts (e.g., household contacts) [see Pharmacodynamics (  12.2  )]  . Use caution when considering whether to administer VAXCHORA to individuals with immunocompromised close contacts.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
