<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="vazculep" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Adverse reactions to VAZCULEP are primarily attributable to excessive pharmacologic activity. Adverse reactions reported in published clinical studies, observational trials, and case reports of VAZCULEP are listed below by body system. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to estimate their frequency reliably or to establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Cardiac disorders:  Reflex bradycardia, lowered cardiac output, ischemia, hypertension, arrhythmias



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  Epigastric pain, vomiting, nausea



   Nervous system disorders:  Headache, blurred vision, neck pain, tremors



   Vascular disorders:  Hypertensive crisis



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  Dyspnea



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  Pruritis



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions during treatment: nausea, vomiting, and headache. (  6  )



  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Eclat Pharmaceuticals at 1-877-622-2320 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Extravasation during intravenous administration may cause necrosis or sloughing of tissue (  5.3  ) 
 *   Severe bradycardia and decreased cardiac output (  5.4  ) 
 *   Allergic-type reactions: Sulfite (  5.5  ) 
 *   Concomitant use with oxytocic drugs: Pressor effect of sympathomimetic pressor amines is potentiated (  5.8  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Exacerbation of Angina, Heart Failure, or Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension



  Because of its increasing blood pressure effects, VAZCULEP can precipitate angina in patients with severe arteriosclerosis or history of angina, exacerbate underlying heart failure, and increase pulmonary arterial pressure.



    5.2 Peripheral and Visceral Ischemia



  VAZCULEP can cause excessive peripheral and visceral vasoconstriction and ischemia to vital organs, particularly in patients with extensive peripheral vascular disease.



    5.3 Skin and Subcutaneous Necrosis



  Extravasation of VAZCULEP can cause necrosis or sloughing of tissue. The infusion site should be checked for free flow. Care should be taken to avoid extravasation of VAZCULEP.



    5.4 Bradycardia



  VAZCULEP can cause severe bradycardia and decreased cardiac output.



    5.5 Allergic Reactions



  VAZCULEP contains sodium metabisulfite, a sulfite that may cause allergic-type reactions, including anaphylactic symptoms and life-threatening or less severe asthmatic episodes in certain susceptible people. The overall prevalence of sulfite sensitivity in the general population is unknown and probably low. Sulfite sensitivity is seen more frequently in asthmatic than in nonasthmatic people.



    5.6 Renal Toxicity



  VAZCULEP can increase the need for renal replacement therapy in patients with septic shock. Monitor renal function.



    5.7 Risk of Augmented Pressor Affect in Patients with Autonomic Dysfunction



  The increasing blood pressure response to adrenergic drugs, including VAZCULEP, can be increased in patients with autonomic dysfunction, as may occur with spinal cord injuries.



    5.8 Pressor Effect with Concomitant Oxytocic Drugs



  Oxytocic drugs potentiate the increasing blood pressure effect of sympathomimetic pressor amines including VAZCULEP [see Drug Interactions (  7.1  )]  , with the potential for hemorrhagic stroke.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
