<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="velcade" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are also discussed in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Peripheral Neuropathy [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *  Hypotension [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
 *  Cardiac Toxicity[ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ] 
 *  Pulmonary Toxicity [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   ] 
 *  Posterior Reversible Encephalopathy Syndrome (PRES) [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)   ] 
 *  Gastrointestinal Toxicity [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)   ] 
 *  Thrombocytopenia/Neutropenia [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)   ] 
 *  Tumor Lysis Syndrome [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)   ] 
 *  Hepatic Toxicity [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)   ] 
      EXCERPT:   Most commonly reported adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 20%) in clinical studies include nausea, diarrhea, thrombocytopenia, neutropenia, peripheral neuropathy, fatigue, neuralgia, anemia, leukopenia, constipation, vomiting, lymphopenia, rash, pyrexia, and anorexia. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Millennium Pharmaceuticals at 1-866 VELCADE or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Safety Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



     Summary of Clinical Trial in Patients with Previously Untreated Multiple Myeloma  



 Table 9 describes safety data from 340 patients with previously untreated multiple myeloma who received VELCADE (1.3 mg/m  2  ) administered intravenously in combination with melphalan (9 mg/m  2  ) and prednisone (60 mg/m  2  ) in a prospective randomized study.



 The safety profile of VELCADE in combination with melphalan/prednisone is consistent with the known safety profiles of both VELCADE and melphalan/prednisone.



 Table 9: Most Commonly Reported Adverse Reactions (&gt;= 10% in the VELCADE, Melphalan and Prednisone arm) with Grades 3 and &gt;= 4 Intensity in the Previously Untreated Multiple Myeloma Study 
                                           VELCADE, Melphalan and Prednisone  Melphalan and Prednisone   
                                            (n=340)     (n=337)     
 System Organ Class                          Total     Toxicity Grade, n (%)    Total     Toxicity Grade, n (%)   
   Preferred Term                            n (%)         3          &gt;= 4       n (%)         3          &gt;= 4      
  
   Blood and lymphatic system disorders                                                                             
   Thrombocytopenia                         164 (48)    60 (18)     57 (17)     140 (42)    48 (14)     39 (12)     
   Neutropenia                              160 (47)    101 (30)    33 (10)     143 (42)    77 (23)     42 (12)     
   Anemia                                   109 (32)    41 (12)      4 (1)      156 (46)    61 (18)      18 (5)     
   Leukopenia                               108 (32)    64 (19)      8 (2)      93 (28)     53 (16)      11 (3)     
   Lymphopenia                              78 (23)     46 (14)      17 (5)     51 (15)      26 (8)      7 (2)      
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                                       
   Nausea                                   134 (39)     10 (3)        0        70 (21)     1 (&lt; 1)        0        
   Diarrhea                                 119 (35)     19 (6)      2 (1)       20 (6)     1 (&lt; 1)        0        
   Vomiting                                 87 (26)      13 (4)        0        41 (12)      2 (1)         0        
   Constipation                             77 (23)      2 (1)         0         14 (4)        0           0        
   Abdominal Pain Upper                     34 (10)     1 (&lt; 1)        0         20 (6)        0           0        
   Nervous system disorders                                                                                         
   Peripheral Neuropathy                    156 (46)    42 (12)      2 (1)       4 (1)         0           0        
   Neuralgia                                117 (34)     27 (8)      2 (1)      1 (&lt; 1)        0           0        
   Paresthesia                              42 (12)      6 (2)         0         4 (1)         0           0        
   General disorders and administration site conditions                                                                             
   Fatigue                                  85 (25)      19 (6)      2 (1)      48 (14)      4 (1)         0        
   Asthenia                                 54 (16)      18 (5)        0         23 (7)      3 (1)         0        
   Pyrexia                                  53 (16)      4 (1)         0         19 (6)     1 (&lt; 1)     1 (&lt; 1)     
   Infections and infestations                                                                                      
   Herpes Zoster                            39 (11)      11 (3)        0         9 (3)       4 (1)         0        
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders                                                                               
   Anorexia                                 64 (19)      6 (2)         0         19 (6)        0           0        
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                                                                             
   Rash                                     38 (11)      2 (1)         0         7 (2)         0           0        
   Psychiatric disorders                                                                                            
   Insomnia                                 35 (10)     1 (&lt; 1)        0         21 (6)        0           0        
                 Relapsed Multiple Myeloma Randomized Study of VELCADE versus Dexamethasone  
 

 The safety data described below and in Table 10 reflect exposure to either VELCADE (n=331) or dexamethasone (n=332) in a study of patients with relapsed multiple myeloma. VELCADE was administered intravenously at doses of 1.3 mg/m  2  twice weekly for 2 out of 3 weeks (21-day cycle). After eight 21-day cycles patients continued therapy for three 35-day cycles on a weekly schedule. Duration of treatment was up to 11 cycles (9 months) with a median duration of 6 cycles (4.1 months). For inclusion in the trial, patients must have had measurable disease and 1 to 3 prior therapies. There was no upper age limit for entry. Creatinine clearance could be as low as 20 mL/min and bilirubin levels as high as 1.5 times the upper limit of normal. The overall frequency of adverse reactions was similar in men and women, and in patients &lt; 65 and &gt;= 65 years of age. Most patients were Caucasian [  see  Clinical Studies (14.1)    ].



 Among the 331 VELCADE-treated patients, the most commonly reported (&gt; 20%) adverse reactions overall were nausea (52%), diarrhea (52%), fatigue (39%), peripheral neuropathies (35%), thrombocytopenia (33%), constipation (30%), vomiting (29%), and anorexia (21%). The most commonly reported (&gt; 20%) adverse reaction reported among the 332 patients in the dexamethasone group was fatigue (25%). Eight percent (8%) of patients in the VELCADE-treated arm experienced a Grade 4 adverse reaction; the most common reactions were thrombocytopenia (4%) and neutropenia (2%). Nine percent (9%) of dexamethasone-treated patients experienced a Grade 4 adverse reaction. All individual dexamethasone-related Grade 4 adverse reactions were less than 1%.



     Serious Adverse Reactions and Adverse Reactions Leading to Treatment Discontinuation in the Relapsed Multiple Myeloma Study of VELCADE versus Dexamethasone  



 Serious adverse reactions are defined as any reaction that results in death, is life-threatening, requires hospitalization or prolongs a current hospitalization, results in a significant disability, or is deemed to be an important medical event. A total of 80 (24%) patients from the VELCADE treatment arm experienced a serious adverse reaction during the study, as did 83 (25%) dexamethasone-treated patients. The most commonly reported serious adverse reactions in the VELCADE treatment arm were diarrhea (3%), dehydration, herpes zoster, pyrexia, nausea, vomiting, dyspnea, and thrombocytopenia (2% each). In the dexamethasone treatment group, the most commonly reported serious adverse reactions were pneumonia (4%), hyperglycemia (3%), pyrexia, and psychotic disorder (2% each).



 A total of 145 patients, including 84 (25%) of 331 patients in the VELCADE treatment group and 61 (18%) of 332 patients in the dexamethasone treatment group were discontinued from treatment due to adverse reactions. Among the 331 VELCADE treated patients, the most commonly reported adverse reaction leading to discontinuation was peripheral neuropathy (8%). Among the 332 patients in the dexamethasone group, the most commonly reported adverse reactions leading to treatment discontinuation were psychotic disorder and hyperglycemia (2% each).



 Four deaths were considered to be VELCADE-related in this relapsed multiple myeloma study: 1 case each of cardiogenic shock, respiratory insufficiency, congestive heart failure and cardiac arrest. Four deaths were considered dexamethasone-related: 2 cases of sepsis, 1 case of bacterial meningitis, and 1 case of sudden death at home.



     Most Commonly Reported Adverse Reactions in the Relapsed Multiple Myeloma Study of VELCADE versus Dexamethasone  



 The most common adverse reactions from the relapsed multiple myeloma study are shown in Table 10. All adverse reactions with incidence &gt;= 10% in the VELCADE arm are included.



 Table 10: Most Commonly Reported Adverse Reactions (&gt;= 10% in VELCADE arm), with Grades 3 and 4 Intensity in the Relapsed Multiple Myeloma Study of VELCADE versus Dexamethasone (N=663) 
                         VELCADEN=331   DexamethasoneN=332   
 Preferred Term               All          Grade 3        Grade 4          All          Grade 3        Grade 4      
  
 Adverse Reactions         324 (98)       193 (58)        28 (8)        297 (89)       110 (33)        29 (9)       
 Nausea                    172 (52)         8 (2)            0           31 (9)            0              0         
 Diarrhea NOS              171 (52)        22 (7)            0           36 (11)        2 (&lt; 1)           0         
 Fatigue                   130 (39)        15 (5)            0           82 (25)         8 (2)            0         
 Peripheral neuropathies    115 (35)        23 (7)         2 (&lt; 1)        14 (4)            0           1 (&lt; 1)      
 Thrombocytopenia          109 (33)        80 (24)        12 (4)         11 (3)          5 (2)         1 (&lt; 1)      
 Constipation               99 (30)         6 (2)            0           27 (8)         1 (&lt; 1)           0         
 Vomiting NOS               96 (29)         8 (2)            0           10 (3)         1 (&lt; 1)           0         
 Anorexia                   68 (21)         8 (2)            0            8 (2)         1 (&lt; 1)           0         
 Pyrexia                    66 (20)        2 (&lt; 1)           0           21 (6)         3 (&lt; 1)        1 (&lt; 1)      
 Paresthesia                64 (19)         5 (2)            0           24 (7)            0              0         
 Anemia NOS                 63 (19)        20 (6)         1 (&lt; 1)        21 (6)          8 (2)            0         
 Headache NOS               62 (19)        3 (&lt; 1)           0           23 (7)         1 (&lt; 1)           0         
 Neutropenia                58 (18)        37 (11)         8 (2)         1 (&lt; 1)        1 (&lt; 1)           0         
 Rash NOS                   43 (13)        3 (&lt; 1)           0            7 (2)            0              0         
 Appetite decreased NOS     36 (11)           0              0           12 (4)            0              0         
 Dyspnea NOS                35 (11)        11 (3)         1 (&lt; 1)        37 (11)         7 (2)         1 (&lt; 1)      
 Abdominal pain NOS         35 (11)         5 (2)            0            7 (2)            0              0         
 Weakness                   34 (10)        10 (3)            0           28 (8)          8 (2)            0         
                 Safety Experience from the Phase 2 Open-Label Extension Study in Relapsed Multiple Myeloma  
 

 In the phase 2 extension study of 63 patients, no new cumulative or new long-term toxicities were observed with prolonged VELCADE treatment. These patients were treated for a total of 5.3 to 23 months, including time on VELCADE in the prior VELCADE study [  see  Clinical Studies (14.1)    ].



     Safety Experience from the Phase 3 Open-Label Study of VELCADE Subcutaneous versus Intravenous in Relapsed Multiple Myeloma  



 The safety and efficacy of VELCADE administered subcutaneously were evaluated in one Phase 3 study at the recommended dose of 1.3 mg/m  2  . This was a randomized, comparative study of VELCADE subcutaneous versus intravenous in 222 patients with relapsed multiple myeloma. The safety data described below and in Table 11 reflect exposure to either VELCADE subcutaneous (n=147) or VELCADE intravenous (n=74) [  see  Clinical Studies (14.1)    ].



 Table 11: Most Commonly Reported Adverse Reactions (&gt;= 10%), with Grade 3 and &gt;= 4 Intensity in the Relapsed Multiple Myeloma Study (N=221) of VELCADE Subcutaneous versus Intravenous 
                         Subcutaneous    Intravenous    
                            (N=147)        (N=74)       
 System Organ Class          Total      Toxicity Grade, n (%)      Total      Toxicity Grade, n (%)   
   Preferred Term            n (%)            3            &gt;= 4           n (%)            3            &gt;= 4        
  
 Note: Safety population: 147 patients in the subcutaneous treatment group and 74 patients in the intravenous treatment group who received at least 1 dose of study medication   
  
   Blood and lymphatic system disorders                                                                                               
   Anemia                   28 (19)         8 (5)            0           17 (23)         3 (4)            0         
   Leukopenia               26 (18)         8 (5)            0           15 (20)         4 (5)          1 (1)       
   Neutropenia              34 (23)        15 (10)         4 (3)         20 (27)        10 (14)         3 (4)       
   Thrombocytopenia         44 (30)         7 (5)          5 (3)         25 (34)         7 (9)          5 (7)       
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                                               
   Diarrhea                 28 (19)         1 (1)            0           21 (28)         3 (4)            0         
   Nausea                   24 (16)           0              0           10 (14)           0              0         
   Vomiting                 13 (9)          3 (2)            0           8 (11)            0              0         
   General disorders and administration site conditions                                                                                               
   Asthenia                 10 (7)          1 (1)            0           12 (16)         4 (5)            0         
   Fatigue                  11 (7)          3 (2)            0           11 (15)         3 (4)            0         
   Pyrexia                  18 (12)           0              0            6 (8)            0              0         
   Nervous system disorders                                                                                               
   Neuralgia                34 (23)         5 (3)            0           17 (23)         7 (9)            0         
   Peripheral neuropathies     55 (37)         8 (5)          1 (1)         37 (50)        10 (14)         1 (1)       
             In general, safety data were similar for the subcutaneous and intravenous treatment groups. Differences were observed in the rates of some Grade &gt;= 3 adverse reactions. Differences of &gt;= 5% were reported in neuralgia (3% subcutaneous versus 9% intravenous), peripheral neuropathies (6% subcutaneous versus 15% intravenous), neutropenia (13% subcutaneous versus 18% intravenous), and thrombocytopenia (8% subcutaneous versus 16% intravenous).
 

 A local reaction was reported in 6% of patients in the subcutaneous group, mostly redness. Only 2 (1%) patients were reported as having severe reactions, 1 case of pruritus and 1 case of redness. Local reactions led to reduction in injection concentration in one patient and drug discontinuation in one patient. Local reactions resolved in a median of 6 days.



 Dose reductions occurred due to adverse reactions in 31% of patients in the subcutaneous treatment group compared with 43% of the intravenously-treated patients. The most common adverse reactions leading to a dose reduction included peripheral sensory neuropathy (17% in the subcutaneous treatment group compared with 31% in the intravenous treatment group); and neuralgia (11% in the subcutaneous treatment group compared with 19% in the intravenous treatment group).



     Serious Adverse Reactions and Adverse Reactions Leading to Treatment Discontinuation in the Relapsed Multiple Myeloma Study of VELCADE Subcutaneous versus Intravenous  



 The incidence of serious adverse reactions was similar for the subcutaneous treatment group (20%) and the intravenous treatment group (19%). The most commonly reported serious adverse reactions in the subcutaneous treatment arm were pneumonia and pyrexia (2% each). In the intravenous treatment group, the most commonly reported serious adverse reactions were pneumonia, diarrhea, and peripheral sensory neuropathy (3% each).



 In the subcutaneous treatment group, 27 patients (18%) discontinued study treatment due to an adverse reaction compared with 17 patients (23%) in the intravenous treatment group  .  Among the 147 subcutaneously-treated patients, the most commonly reported adverse reactions leading to discontinuation were peripheral sensory neuropathy (5%) and neuralgia (5%). Among the 74 patients in the intravenous treatment group, the most commonly reported adverse reactions leading to treatment discontinuation were peripheral sensory neuropathy (9%) and neuralgia (9%).



 Two patients (1%) in the subcutaneous treatment group and 1 (1%) patient in the intravenous treatment group died due to an adverse reaction during treatment. In the subcutaneous group the causes of death were one case of pneumonia and one case of sudden death. In the intravenous group the cause of death was coronary artery insufficiency.



     Safety Experience from the Clinical Trial in Patients with Previously Untreated Mantle Cell Lymphoma  



 Table 12 describes safety data from 240 patients with previously untreated mantle cell lymphoma who received VELCADE (1.3 mg/m  2  ) administered intravenously in combination with rituximab (375 mg/m  2  ), cyclophosphamide (750 mg/m  2  ), doxorubicin (50 mg/m  2  ), and prednisone (100 mg/m  2  ) (VcR-CAP) in a prospective randomized study.



 Infections were reported for 31% of patients in the VcR-CAP arm and 23% of the patients in the comparator (rituximab, cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, vincristine, and prednisone [R-CHOP]) arm, including the predominant preferred term of pneumonia (VcR-CAP 8% versus R-CHOP 5%).



 Table 12: Most Commonly Reported Adverse Reactions (&gt;= 5%) with Grades 3 and &gt;= 4 Intensity in the Previously Untreated Mantle Cell Lymphoma Study 
                                           VcR-CAPn=240  R-CHOPn=242   
 System Organ ClassPreferred Term           Alln (%)   ToxicityGrade 3n (%)  ToxicityGrade &gt;=4n (%)   Alln (%)   ToxicityGrade 3n (%)  ToxicityGrade &gt;=4n (%)   
  
 Key: R-CHOP=rituximab, cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, vincristine, and prednisone;   
 VcR-CAP=VELCADE, rituximab, cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, and prednisone.   
  
     Blood and lymphatic system disorders                                                                             
     Neutropenia                            209 (87)    32 (13)     168 (70)    172 (71)    31 (13)     125 (52)    
     Leukopenia                             116 (48)    34 (14)     69 (29)     87 (36)     39 (16)     27 (11)     
     Anemia                                 106 (44)    27 (11)      4 (2)      71 (29)     23 (10)      4 (2)      
     Thrombocytopenia                       172 (72)    59 (25)     76 (32)     42 (17)      9 (4)       3 (1)      
     Febrile neutropenia                    41 (17)     24 (10)      12 (5)     33 (14)      17 (7)      15 (6)     
     Lymphopenia                            68 (28)     25 (10)     36 (15)     28 (12)      15 (6)      2 (1)      
     Nervous system disorders                                                                                       
     Peripheral neuropathy                  71 (30)      17 (7)     1 (&lt; 1)     65 (27)      10 (4)        0        
     Hypoesthesia                            14 (6)      3 (1)         0         13 (5)        0           0        
     Paresthesia                             14 (6)      2 (1)         0         11 (5)        0           0        
     Neuralgia                              25 (10)      9 (4)         0        1 (&lt; 1)        0           0        
     General disorders and administration site conditions                                                                             
     Fatigue                                43 (18)      11 (5)     1 (&lt; 1)     38 (16)      5 (2)         0        
     Pyrexia                                48 (20)      7 (3)         0        23 (10)      5 (2)         0        
     Asthenia                               29 (12)      4 (2)      1 (&lt; 1)      18 (7)     1 (&lt; 1)        0        
     Edema peripheral                        16 (7)     1 (&lt; 1)        0         13 (5)        0           0        
     Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                                     
     Nausea                                 54 (23)     1 (&lt; 1)        0        28 (12)        0           0        
     Constipation                           42 (18)     1 (&lt; 1)        0         22 (9)      2 (1)         0        
     Stomatitis                              20 (8)      2 (1)         0         19 (8)        0        1 (&lt; 1)     
     Diarrhea                               59 (25)      11 (5)        0         11 (5)      3 (1)      1 (&lt; 1)     
     Vomiting                               24 (10)     1 (&lt; 1)        0         8 (3)         0           0        
     Abdominal distension                    13 (5)        0           0         4 (2)         0           0        
     Infections and infestations                                                                                    
     Pneumonia                               20 (8)      8 (3)       5 (2)       11 (5)      5 (2)       3 (1)      
     Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                                                                             
     Alopecia                               31 (13)     1 (&lt; 1)     1 (&lt; 1)     33 (14)      4 (2)         0        
     Metabolism and nutrition disorders                                                                             
     Hyperglycemia                           10 (4)     1 (&lt; 1)        0         17 (7)      10 (4)        0        
     Decreased appetite                     36 (15)      2 (1)         0         15 (6)     1 (&lt; 1)        0        
     Vascular disorders                                                                                             
     Hypertension                            15 (6)     1 (&lt; 1)        0         3 (1)         0           0        
     Psychiatric disorders                                                                                          
     Insomnia                                16 (7)     1 (&lt; 1)        0         8 (3)         0           0        
             The incidence of herpes zoster reactivation was 4.6% in the VcR-CAP arm and 0.8% in the R-CHOP arm. Antiviral prophylaxis was mandated by protocol amendment.
 

 The incidences of Grade &gt;= 3 bleeding events were similar between the 2 arms (3 patients in the VcR-CAP arm and 1 patient in the R-CHOP arm). All of the Grade &gt;= 3 bleeding events resolved without sequelae in the VcR-CAP arm.



 Adverse reactions leading to discontinuation occurred in 8% of patients in VcR-CAP group and 6% of patients in R-CHOP group. In the VcR-CAP group, the most commonly reported adverse reaction leading to discontinuation was peripheral sensory neuropathy (1%; 3 patients). The most commonly reported adverse reaction leading to discontinuation in the R-CHOP group was febrile neutropenia (&lt; 1%; 2 patients).



     Integrated Summary of Safety (Relapsed Multiple Myeloma and Relapsed Mantle Cell Lymphoma)  



 Safety data from phase 2 and 3 studies of single agent VELCADE 1.3 mg/m  2  /dose twice weekly for 2 weeks followed by a 10-day rest period in 1163 patients with previously-treated multiple myeloma (N=1008) and previously-treated mantle cell lymphoma (N=155) were integrated and tabulated. This analysis does not include data from the Phase 3 Open-Label Study of VELCADE subcutaneous versus intravenous in relapsed multiple myeloma. In the integrated studies, the safety profile of VELCADE was similar in patients with multiple myeloma and mantle cell lymphoma.



 In the integrated analysis, the most commonly reported (&gt; 20%) adverse reactions were nausea (49%), diarrhea (46%), asthenic conditions including fatigue (41%) and weakness (11%), peripheral neuropathies (38%), thrombocytopenia (32%), vomiting (28%), constipation (25%), and pyrexia (21%). Eleven percent (11%) of patients experienced at least 1 episode of &gt;= Grade 4 toxicity, most commonly thrombocytopenia (4%) and neutropenia (2%).



 In the Phase 2 relapsed multiple myeloma clinical trials of VELCADE administered intravenously, local skin irritation was reported in 5% of patients, but extravasation of VELCADE was not associated with tissue damage.



     Serious Adverse Reactions and Adverse Reactions Leading to Treatment Discontinuation in the Integrated Summary of Safety  



 A total of 26% of patients experienced a serious adverse reaction during the studies. The most commonly reported serious adverse reactions included diarrhea, vomiting and pyrexia (3% each), nausea, dehydration, and thrombocytopenia (2% each) and pneumonia, dyspnea, peripheral neuropathies, and herpes zoster (1% each).



 Adverse reactions leading to discontinuation occurred in 22% of patients. The reasons for discontinuation included peripheral neuropathy (8%), and fatigue, thrombocytopenia, and diarrhea (2% each).



 In total, 2% of the patients died and the cause of death was considered by the investigator to be possibly related to study drug: including reports of cardiac arrest, congestive heart failure, respiratory failure, renal failure, pneumonia and sepsis.



     Most Commonly Reported Adverse Reactions in the Integrated Summary of Safety  



 The most common adverse reactions are shown in Table 13. All adverse reactions occurring at &gt;= 10% are included. In the absence of a randomized comparator arm, it is often not possible to distinguish between adverse events that are drug-caused and those that reflect the patient's underlying disease. Please see the discussion of specific adverse reactions that follows.



 Table 13: Most Commonly Reported (&gt;= 10% Overall) Adverse Reactions in Integrated Analyses of Relapsed Multiple Myeloma and Relapsed Mantle Cell Lymphoma Studies using the 1.3 mg/m2 Dose (N=1163) 
                         All PatientsN=1163  Multiple MyelomaN=1008  Mantle Cell LymphomaN=155   
 Preferred Term               All        &gt;= Grade 3         All        &gt;= Grade 3         All        &gt;= Grade 3     
  
 Nausea                    567 (49)        36 (3)        511 (51)        32 (3)         56 (36)         4 (3)       
 Diarrhea NOS              530 (46)        83 (7)        470 (47)        72 (7)         60 (39)        11 (7)       
 Fatigue                   477 (41)        86 (7)        396 (39)        71 (7)         81 (52)        15 (10)      
 Peripheral neuropathies    443 (38)       129 (11)       359 (36)       110 (11)        84 (54)        19 (12)      
 Thrombocytopenia          369 (32)       295 (25)       344 (34)       283 (28)        25 (16)        12 (8)       
 Vomiting NOS              321 (28)        44 (4)        286 (28)        40 (4)         35 (23)         4 (3)       
 Constipation              296 (25)        17 (1)        244 (24)        14 (1)         52 (34)         3 (2)       
 Pyrexia                   249 (21)        16 (1)        233 (23)        15 (1)         16 (10)        1 (&lt; 1)      
 Anorexia                  227 (20)        19 (2)        205 (20)        16 (2)         22 (14)         3 (2)       
 Anemia NOS                209 (18)        65 (6)        190 (19)        63 (6)         19 (12)         2 (1)       
 Headache NOS              175 (15)        8 (&lt; 1)       160 (16)        8 (&lt; 1)        15 (10)           0         
 Neutropenia               172 (15)       121 (10)       164 (16)       117 (12)         8 (5)          4 (3)       
 Rash NOS                  156 (13)        8 (&lt; 1)       120 (12)        4 (&lt; 1)        36 (23)         4 (3)       
 Paresthesia               147 (13)        9 (&lt; 1)       136 (13)        8 (&lt; 1)        11 (7)         1 (&lt; 1)      
 Dizziness (excl vertigo)    129 (11)        13 (1)        101 (10)        9 (&lt; 1)        28 (18)         4 (3)       
 Weakness                  124 (11)        31 (3)        106 (11)        28 (3)         18 (12)         3 (2)       
                 Description of Selected Adverse Reactions from the Integrated Phase 2 and 3 Relapsed Multiple Myeloma and Phase 2 Relapsed Mantle Cell Lymphoma Studies  
 

     Gastrointestinal Toxicity  



 A total of 75% of patients experienced at least one gastrointestinal disorder. The most common gastrointestinal disorders included nausea, diarrhea, constipation, vomiting, and appetite decreased. Other gastrointestinal disorders included dyspepsia and dysgeusia. Grade 3 adverse reactions occurred in 14% of patients; &gt;= Grade 4 adverse reactions were &lt;= 1%. Gastrointestinal adverse reactions were considered serious in 7% of patients. Four percent (4%) of patients discontinued due to a gastrointestinal adverse reaction. Nausea was reported more often in patients with multiple myeloma (51%) compared to patients with mantle cell lymphoma (36%).



     Thrombocytopenia  



 Across the studies, VELCADE-associated thrombocytopenia was characterized by a decrease in platelet count during the dosing period (days 1 to 11) and a return toward baseline during the 10-day rest period during each treatment cycle. Overall, thrombocytopenia was reported in 32% of patients. Thrombocytopenia was Grade 3 in 22%, &gt;= Grade 4 in 4%, and serious in 2% of patients, and the reaction resulted in VELCADE discontinuation in 2% of patients [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)    ]. Thrombocytopenia was reported more often in patients with multiple myeloma (34%) compared to patients with mantle cell lymphoma (16%). The incidence of &gt;= Grade 3 thrombocytopenia also was higher in patients with multiple myeloma (28%) compared to patients with mantle cell lymphoma (8%).



     Peripheral Neuropathy  



 Overall, peripheral neuropathies occurred in 38% of patients. Peripheral neuropathy was Grade 3 for 11% of patients and &gt;= Grade 4 for &lt; 1% of patients. Eight percent (8%) of patients discontinued VELCADE due to peripheral neuropathy. The incidence of peripheral neuropathy was higher among patients with mantle cell lymphoma (54%) compared to patients with multiple myeloma (36%).



 In the VELCADE versus dexamethasone phase 3 relapsed multiple myeloma study, among the 62 VELCADE-treated patients who experienced &gt;= Grade 2 peripheral neuropathy and had dose adjustments, 48% had improved or resolved with a median of 3.8 months from first onset.



 In the phase 2 relapsed multiple myeloma studies, among the 30 patients who experienced Grade 2 peripheral neuropathy resulting in discontinuation or who experienced &gt;= Grade 3 peripheral neuropathy, 73% reported improvement or resolution with a median time of 47 days to improvement of one Grade or more from the last dose of VELCADE.



     Hypotension  



 The incidence of hypotension (postural, orthostatic and hypotension NOS) was 8% in patients treated with VELCADE. Hypotension was Grade 1 or 2 in the majority of patients and Grade 3 in 2% and &gt;= Grade 4 in &lt; 1%. Two percent (2%) of patients had hypotension reported as a serious adverse reaction, and 1% discontinued due to hypotension. The incidence of hypotension was similar in patients with multiple myeloma (8%) and those with mantle cell lymphoma (9%). In addition, &lt; 1% of patients experienced hypotension associated with a syncopal reaction.



     Neutropenia  



 Neutrophil counts decreased during the VELCADE dosing period (days 1 to 11) and returned toward baseline during the 10-day rest period during each treatment cycle. Overall, neutropenia occurred in 15% of patients and was Grade 3 in 8% of patients and &gt;= Grade 4 in 2%. Neutropenia was reported as a serious adverse reaction in &lt; 1% of patients and &lt; 1% of patients discontinued due to neutropenia. The incidence of neutropenia was higher in patients with multiple myeloma (16%) compared to patients with mantle cell lymphoma (5%). The incidence of &gt;= Grade 3 neutropenia also was higher in patients with multiple myeloma (12%) compared to patients with mantle cell lymphoma (3%).



     Asthenic conditions (Fatigue, Malaise, Weakness, Asthenia)  



 Asthenic conditions were reported in 54% of patients. Fatigue was reported as Grade 3 in 7% and &gt;= Grade 4 in &lt; 1% of patients. Asthenia was reported as Grade 3 in 2% and &gt;= Grade 4 in &lt; 1% of patients. Two percent (2%) of patients discontinued treatment due to fatigue and &lt; 1% due to weakness and asthenia. Asthenic conditions were reported in 53% of patients with multiple myeloma and 59% of patients with mantle cell lymphoma.



     Pyrexia  



 Pyrexia (&gt; 38oC) was reported as an adverse reaction for 21% of patients. The reaction was Grade 3 in 1% and &gt;= Grade 4 in &lt; 1%. Pyrexia was reported as a serious adverse reaction in 3% of patients and led to VELCADE discontinuation in &lt; 1% of patients. The incidence of pyrexia was higher among patients with multiple myeloma (23%) compared to patients with mantle cell lymphoma (10%). The incidence of &gt;= Grade 3 pyrexia was 1% in patients with multiple myeloma and &lt; 1% in patients with mantle cell lymphoma.



     Herpes Virus Infection  



 Consider using antiviral prophylaxis in subjects being treated with VELCADE. In the randomized studies in previously untreated and relapsed multiple myeloma, herpes zoster reactivation was more common in subjects treated with VELCADE (ranging between 6-11%) than in the control groups (3-4%). Herpes simplex was seen in 1-3% in subjects treated with VELCADE and 1-3% in the control groups. In the previously untreated multiple myeloma study, herpes zoster virus reactivation in the VELCADE, melphalan and prednisone arm was less common in subjects receiving prophylactic antiviral therapy (3%) than in subjects who did not receive prophylactic antiviral therapy (17%).



     Retreatment in Relapsed Multiple Myeloma  



 A single-arm trial was conducted in 130 patients with relapsed multiple myeloma to determine the efficacy and safety of retreatment with intravenous VELCADE. The safety profile of patients in this trial is consistent with the known safety profile of VELCADE-treated patients with relapsed multiple myeloma as demonstrated in Tables 10, 11, and 13; no cumulative toxicities were observed upon retreatment. The most common adverse drug reaction was thrombocytopenia which occurred in 52% of the patients. The incidence of &gt;= Grade 3 thrombocytopenia was 24%. Peripheral neuropathy occurred in 28% of patients, with the incidence of &gt;= Grade 3 peripheral neuropathy reported at 6%. The incidence of serious adverse reactions was 12.3%. The most commonly reported serious adverse reactions were thrombocytopenia (3.8%), diarrhea (2.3%), and herpes zoster and pneumonia (1.5% each).



 Adverse reactions leading to discontinuation occurred in 13% of patients. The reasons for discontinuation included peripheral neuropathy (5%) and diarrhea (3%).



 Two deaths considered to be VELCADE-related occurred within 30 days of the last VELCADE dose; one in a patient with cerebrovascular accident and one in a patient with sepsis.



     Additional Adverse Reactions from Clinical Studies  



 The following clinically important serious adverse reactions that are not described above have been reported in clinical trials in patients treated with VELCADE administered as monotherapy or in combination with other chemotherapeutics. These studies were conducted in patients with hematological malignancies and in solid tumors.



   Blood and lymphatic system disorders:  Anemia, disseminated intravascular coagulation, febrile neutropenia, lymphopenia, leukopenia



   Cardiac disorders:  Angina pectoris, atrial fibrillation aggravated, atrial flutter, bradycardia, sinus arrest, cardiac amyloidosis, complete atrioventricular block, myocardial ischemia, myocardial infarction, pericarditis, pericardial effusion,  Torsades de pointes  , ventricular tachycardia



   Ear and labyrinth disorders:  Hearing impaired, vertigo



   Eye disorders:  Diplopia and blurred vision, conjunctival infection, irritation



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  Abdominal pain, ascites, dysphagia, fecal impaction, gastroenteritis, gastritis hemorrhagic, hematemesis, hemorrhagic duodenitis, ileus paralytic, large intestinal obstruction, paralytic intestinal obstruction, peritonitis, small intestinal obstruction, large intestinal perforation, stomatitis, melena, pancreatitis acute, oral mucosal petechiae, gastroesophageal reflux



   General disorders and administration site conditions:  Chills, edema, edema peripheral, injection site erythema, neuralgia, injection site pain, irritation, malaise, phlebitis



   Hepatobiliary disorders:  Cholestasis, hepatic hemorrhage, hyperbilirubinemia, portal vein thrombosis, hepatitis, liver failure



   Immune system disorders:  Anaphylactic reaction, drug hypersensitivity, immune complex mediated hypersensitivity, angioedema, laryngeal edema



   Infections and infestations:  Aspergillosis, bacteremia, bronchitis, urinary tract infection, herpes viral infection, listeriosis, nasopharyngitis, pneumonia, respiratory tract infection, septic shock, toxoplasmosis, oral candidiasis, sinusitis, catheter related infection



   Injury, poisoning and procedural complications:  Catheter related complication, skeletal fracture, subdural hematoma



   Investigations:  Weight decreased



   Metabolism and nutrition disorders:  Dehydration, hypocalcemia, hyperuricemia, hypokalemia, hyperkalemia, hyponatremia, hypernatremia



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  Arthralgia, back pain, bone pain, myalgia, pain in extremity



   Nervous system disorders    :  Ataxia, coma, dizziness, dysarthria, dysesthesia, dysautonomia, encephalopathy, cranial palsy, grand mal convulsion, headache, hemorrhagic stroke, motor dysfunction, neuralgia, spinal cord compression, paralysis, postherpetic neuralgia, transient ischemic attack



   Psychiatric disorders    :  Agitation, anxiety, confusion, insomnia, mental status change, psychotic disorder, suicidal ideation



   Renal and urinary disorders:  Calculus renal, bilateral hydronephrosis, bladder spasm, hematuria, hemorrhagic cystitis, urinary incontinence, urinary retention, renal failure (acute and chronic), glomerular nephritis proliferative



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  Acute respiratory distress syndrome, aspiration pneumonia, atelectasis, chronic obstructive airways disease exacerbated, cough, dysphagia, dyspnea, dyspnea exertional, epistaxis, hemoptysis, hypoxia, lung infiltration, pleural effusion, pneumonitis, respiratory distress, pulmonary hypertension



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders    :  Urticaria, face edema, rash (which may be pruritic), leukocytoclastic vasculitis, pruritus.



   Vascular disorders    :  Cerebrovascular accident, cerebral hemorrhage, deep venous thrombosis, hypertension, peripheral embolism, pulmonary embolism, pulmonary hypertension



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified from the worldwide postmarketing experience with VELCADE. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure: atrioventricular block complete, cardiac tamponade, ischemic colitis, encephalopathy, dysautonomia, deafness bilateral, disseminated intravascular coagulation, hepatitis, acute pancreatitis, progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML), acute diffuse infiltrative pulmonary disease, PRES (formerly RPLS), toxic epidermal necrolysis, acute febrile neutrophilic dermatosis (Sweet's syndrome), herpes meningoencephalitis, optic neuropathy, blindness and ophthalmic herpes.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Peripheral Neuropathy: Manage with dose modification or discontinuation. (  2.7  ) Patients with preexisting severe neuropathy should be treated with VELCADE only after careful risk-benefit assessment. (  2.7  ,  5.1  ) 
 *  Hypotension: Use caution when treating patients taking anti-hypertensives, with a history of syncope, or with dehydration. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Cardiac Toxicity: Worsening of and development of cardiac failure has occurred. Closely monitor patients with existing heart disease or risk factors for heart disease. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Pulmonary Toxicity: Acute respiratory syndromes have occurred. Monitor closely for new or worsening symptoms. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Posterior Reversible Encephalopathy Syndrome: Consider MRI imaging for onset of visual or neurological symptoms; discontinue VELCADE if suspected. (  5.5  ). 
 *  Gastrointestinal Toxicity: Nausea, diarrhea, constipation, and vomiting may require use of antiemetic and antidiarrheal medications or fluid replacement. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Thrombocytopenia or Neutropenia: Monitor complete blood counts regularly throughout treatment. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Tumor Lysis Syndrome: Closely monitor patients with high tumor burden (  5.8  ). 
 *  Hepatic Toxicity: Monitor hepatic enzymes during treatment.(  5.9  ). 
 *  Embryo-fetal Risk: Women should avoid becoming pregnant while being treated with VELCADE. Advise pregnant women of potential embryo-fetal harm. (  5.10  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Peripheral Neuropathy



  VELCADE treatment causes a peripheral neuropathy that is predominantly sensory; however, cases of severe sensory and motor peripheral neuropathy have been reported. Patients with pre-existing symptoms (numbness, pain or a burning feeling in the feet or hands) and/or signs of peripheral neuropathy may experience worsening peripheral neuropathy (including &gt;= Grade 3) during treatment with VELCADE. Patients should be monitored for symptoms of neuropathy, such as a burning sensation, hyperesthesia, hypoesthesia, paresthesia, discomfort, neuropathic pain or weakness. In the Phase 3 relapsed multiple myeloma trial comparing VELCADE subcutaneous versus intravenous the incidence of Grade &gt;= 2 peripheral neuropathy was 24% for subcutaneous and 39% for intravenous. Grade &gt;= 3 peripheral neuropathy occurred in 6% of patients in the subcutaneous treatment group, compared with 15% in the intravenous treatment group. Starting VELCADE subcutaneously may be considered for patients with pre-existing or at high risk of peripheral neuropathy.



 Patients experiencing new or worsening peripheral neuropathy during VELCADE therapy may require a decrease in the dose and/or a less dose-intense schedule [ see     Dosage and Administration (2.7)    ]. In the VELCADE versus dexamethasone phase 3 relapsed multiple myeloma study, improvement in or resolution of peripheral neuropathy was reported in 48% of patients with &gt;= Grade 2 peripheral neuropathy following dose adjustment or interruption. Improvement in or resolution of peripheral neuropathy was reported in 73% of patients who discontinued due to Grade 2 neuropathy or who had &gt;= Grade 3 peripheral neuropathy in the phase 2 multiple myeloma studies [ see     Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ]. The long-term outcome of peripheral neuropathy has not been studied in mantle cell lymphoma.



    5.2 Hypotension



  The incidence of hypotension (postural, orthostatic, and hypotension NOS) was 8%. These events are observed throughout therapy. Caution should be used when treating patients with a history of syncope, patients receiving medications known to be associated with hypotension, and patients who are dehydrated. Management of orthostatic/postural hypotension may include adjustment of antihypertensive medications, hydration, and administration of mineralocorticoids and/or sympathomimetics [ see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ].



    5.3 Cardiac Toxicity



  Acute development or exacerbation of congestive heart failure and new onset of decreased left ventricular ejection fraction have occurred during VELCADE therapy, including reports in patients with no risk factors for decreased left ventricular ejection fraction. Patients with risk factors for, or existing heart disease should be closely monitored. In the relapsed multiple myeloma study of VELCADE versus dexamethasone, the incidence of any treatment-related cardiac disorder was 8% and 5% in the VELCADE and dexamethasone groups, respectively. The incidence of adverse reactions suggestive of heart failure (acute pulmonary edema, pulmonary edema, cardiac failure, congestive cardiac failure, cardiogenic shock) was &lt;= 1% for each individual reaction in the VELCADE group. In the dexamethasone group the incidence was &lt;= 1% for cardiac failure and congestive cardiac failure; there were no reported reactions of acute pulmonary edema, pulmonary edema, or cardiogenic shock. There have been isolated cases of QT-interval prolongation in clinical studies; causality has not been established.



    5.4 Pulmonary Toxicity



  Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome (ARDS) and acute diffuse infiltrative pulmonary disease of unknown etiology such as pneumonitis, interstitial pneumonia, lung infiltration have occurred in patients receiving VELCADE. Some of these events have been fatal.



 In a clinical trial, the first two patients given high-dose cytarabine (2g/m  2  per day) by continuous infusion with daunorubicin and VELCADE for relapsed acute myelogenous leukemia died of ARDS early in the course of therapy.



 There have been reports of pulmonary hypertension associated with VELCADE administration in the absence of left heart failure or significant pulmonary disease.



 In the event of new or worsening cardiopulmonary symptoms, consider interrupting VELCADE until a prompt and comprehensive diagnostic evaluation is conducted.



    5.5 Posterior Reversible Encephalopathy Syndrome (PRES)



  Posterior Reversible Encephalopathy Syndrome (PRES; formerly termed Reversible Posterior Leukoencephalopathy Syndrome (RPLS)) has occurred in patients receiving VELCADE. PRES is a rare, reversible, neurological disorder which can present with seizure, hypertension, headache, lethargy, confusion, blindness, and other visual and neurological disturbances. Brain imaging, preferably MRI (Magnetic Resonance Imaging), is used to confirm the diagnosis. In patients developing PRES, discontinue VELCADE. The safety of reinitiating VELCADE therapy in patients previously experiencing PRES is not known.



    5.6 Gastrointestinal Toxicity



  VELCADE treatment can cause nausea, diarrhea, constipation, and vomiting [ see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  sometimes requiring use of antiemetic and antidiarrheal medications. Ileus can occur. Fluid and electrolyte replacement should be administered to prevent dehydration. Interrupt VELCADE for severe symptoms.



    5.7 Thrombocytopenia/Neutropenia



  VELCADE is associated with thrombocytopenia and neutropenia that follow a cyclical pattern with nadirs occurring following the last dose of each cycle and typically recovering prior to initiation of the subsequent cycle. The cyclical pattern of platelet and neutrophil decreases and recovery remain consistent in the studies of multiple myeloma and mantle cell lymphoma, with no evidence of cumulative thrombocytopenia or neutropenia in the treatment regimens studied.  



  Monitor complete blood counts (CBC) frequently during treatment with VELCADE. Measure platelet counts prior to each dose of VELCADE. Adjust dose/schedule for thrombocytopenia [ see  Tables 2  and  4  and  Dosage and Administration (2.6)    ]. Gastrointestinal and intracerebral hemorrhage has occurred during thrombocytopenia in association with VELCADE. Support with transfusions and supportive care, according to published guidelines.  



  In the single-agent, relapsed multiple myeloma study of VELCADE versus dexamethasone, the mean platelet count nadir measured was approximately 40% of baseline. The severity of thrombocytopenia related to pretreatment platelet count is shown in Table 8. The incidence of bleeding (&gt;= Grade 3) was 2% on the VELCADE arm and was &lt; 1% in the dexamethasone arm.  



 Table 8: Severity of Thrombocytopenia Related to Pretreatment Platelet Count in the Relapsed Multiple Myeloma Study of VELCADE versus Dexamethasone 
 PretreatmentPlatelet Count  Number of Patients(N=331)   Number (%) of Patientswith Platelet Count&lt; 10,000/uL  Number (%) of Patientswith Platelet Count10,000-25,000/uL   
  
      &gt;= 75,000/uL                  309                        8 (3%)                     36 (12%)            
 &gt;= 50,000/uL-&lt; 75,000/uL              14                       2 (14%)                     11 (79%)            
 &gt;= 10,000/uL-&lt; 50,000/uL              7                        1 (14%)                     5 (71%)             
       In the combination study of VELCADE with rituximab, cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin and prednisone (VcR-CAP) in previously untreated mantle cell lymphoma patients, the incidence of thrombocytopenia (&gt;= Grade 4) was 32% versus 1% for the rituximab, cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, vincristine, and prednisone (R-CHOP) arm as shown in Table 12. The incidence of bleeding events (&gt;= Grade 3) was 1% in the VcR-CAP arm (3 patients) and was &lt; 1% in the R-CHOP arm (1 patient).  
 

  Platelet transfusions were given to 23% of the patients in the VcR-CAP arm and 3% of the patients in the R-CHOP arm.  



  The incidence of neutropenia (&gt;= Grade 4) was 70% in the VcR-CAP arm and was 52% in the R-CHOP arm. The incidence of febrile neutropenia (&gt;= Grade 4) was 5% in the VcR-CAP arm and was 6% in the R-CHOP arm. Myeloid growth factor support was provided at a rate of 78% in the VcR-CAP arm and 61% in the R-CHOP arm.  



    5.8 Tumor Lysis Syndrome



  Tumor lysis syndrome has been reported with VELCADE therapy. Patients at risk of tumor lysis syndrome are those with high tumor burden prior to treatment. Monitor patients closely and take appropriate precautions.



    5.9 Hepatic Toxicity



  Cases of acute liver failure have been reported in patients receiving multiple concomitant medications and with serious underlying medical conditions. Other reported hepatic reactions include hepatitis, increases in liver enzymes, and hyperbilirubinemia. Interrupt VELCADE therapy to assess reversibility. There is limited re-challenge information in these patients.



    5.10 Embryo-fetal Risk



  Women of reproductive potential should avoid becoming pregnant while being treated with VELCADE. Bortezomib administered to rabbits during organogenesis at a dose approximately 0.5 times the clinical dose of 1.3 mg/m  2  based on body surface area caused post-implantation loss and a decreased number of live fetuses [ see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)    ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
