<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="veletri" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  *  -  Dose Initiation and Escalation: Nausea, vomiting, headache, hypotension, flushing, chest pain, anxiety, dizziness, bradycardia, dyspnea, abdominal pain, musculoskeletal pain, and tachycardia (  6.1  ) 
 *  -  Chronic Dosing: Headache, jaw pain, flushing, diarrhea, nausea and vomiting, flu-like symptoms, and anxiety/nervousness (  6.1  ) 
   Most common adverse reactions during: 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, please contact: ACTELION at 1-866-228-3546 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088, or http://www.fda.gov/medwatch  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 During clinical trials, adverse events were classified as follows: (1) adverse events during dose initiation and escalation, (2) adverse events during chronic dosing, and (3) adverse events associated with the drug delivery system.



     Adverse Events during Dose Initiation and Escalation  



 During early clinical trials, epoprostenol was increased in 2-ng/kg/min increments until the patients developed symptomatic intolerance. The most common adverse events and the adverse events that limited further increases in dose were generally related to vasodilation, the major pharmacologic effect of epoprostenol. The most common dose-limiting adverse events (occurring in &gt;=1% of patients) were nausea, vomiting, headache, hypotension, and flushing, but also include chest pain, anxiety, dizziness, bradycardia, dyspnea, abdominal pain, musculoskeletal pain, and tachycardia. Table 9 lists the adverse events reported during dose initiation and escalation in decreasing order of frequency.



 Table 9: Adverse Events during Dose Initiation and Escalation 
 Adverse Events Occurringin &gt;=1% of Patients                          Epoprostenol(n = 391)               
  
 Flushing                                                                      58%                        
 Headache                                                                      49%                        
 Nausea/vomiting                                                               32%                        
 Hypotension                                                                   16%                        
 Anxiety, nervousness, agitation                                               11%                        
 Chest pain                                                                    11%                        
 Dizziness                                                                     8%                         
 Bradycardia                                                                   5%                         
 Abdominal pain                                                                5%                         
 Musculoskeletal pain                                                          3%                         
 Dyspnea                                                                       2%                         
 Back pain                                                                     2%                         
 Sweating                                                                      1%                         
 Dyspepsia                                                                     1%                         
 Hypesthesia/paresthesia                                                       1%                         
 Tachycardia                                                                   1%                         
            Adverse Events during Chronic Administration:  
 

 Interpretation of adverse events is complicated by the clinical features of PAH, which are similar to some of the pharmacologic effects of epoprostenol (e.g., dizziness, syncope). Adverse events which may be related to the underlying disease include dyspnea, fatigue, chest pain, edema, hypoxia, right ventricular failure, and pallor. Several adverse events, on the other hand, can clearly be attributed to epoprostenol. These include hypotension, bradycardia, tachycardia, pulmonary edema, bleeding at various sites, thrombocytopenia, headache, abdominal pain, pain (unspecified), sweating, rash, arthralgia, jaw pain, flushing, diarrhea, nausea and vomiting, flu-like symptoms, anxiety/nervousness, and agitation. In addition, chest pain, fatigue, and pallor have been reported during epoprostenol therapy, and a role for the drug in these events cannot be excluded.



     Adverse Events during Chronic Administration for Idiopathic or Heritable PAH:  



 In an effort to separate the adverse effects of the drug from the adverse effects of the underlying disease, Table 10 lists adverse events that occurred at a rate at least 10% greater on epoprostenol than on conventional therapy in controlled trials for idiopathic or heritable PAH.



 Table 10: Adverse Events Regardless of Attribution Occurring in Patients with Idiopathic or Heritable PAH with &gt;= 10% Difference between Epoprostenol and Conventional Therapy Alone 
 Adverse Event                                  Epoprostenol(n = 52)        Conventional Therapy(n = 54)    
 Occurrence More Common With Epoprostenol   
  
   General                                                                                                  
 Chills/fever/sepsis/flu-like symptoms                  25%                             11%                 
   Cardiovascular                                                                                           
 Tachycardia                                            35%                             24%                 
 Flushing                                               42%                              2%                 
   Gastrointestinal                                                                                         
 Diarrhea                                               37%                              6%                 
 Nausea/vomiting                                        67%                             48%                 
   Musculoskeletal                                                                                          
 Jaw pain                                               54%                              0%                 
 Myalgia                                                44%                             31%                 
 Nonspecific musculoskeletal pain                       35%                             15%                 
   Neurological                                                                                             
 Anxiety/nervousness/tremor                             21%                              9%                 
 Dizziness                                              83%                             70%                 
 Headache                                               83%                             33%                 
 Hypesthesia, hyperesthesia, paresthesia                12%                              2%                 
         Thrombocytopenia has been reported during uncontrolled clinical trials in patients receiving epoprostenol.
 

     Adverse Events during Chronic Administration for PAH/SSD  



 In an effort to separate the adverse effects of the drug from the adverse effects of the underlying disease, Table 11 lists adverse events that occurred at a rate at least 10% greater on epoprostenol in the controlled trial.



 Table 11: Adverse Events Regardless of Attribution Occurring in Patients with PAH/SSD With &gt;=10% Difference Between Epoprostenol and Conventional Therapy Alone 
 Adverse Event                                  Epoprostenol(n = 56)        Conventional Therapy(n = 55)    
  
   Cardiovascular                                                                                           
 Flushing                                               23%                              0%                 
 Hypotension                                            13%                              0%                 
   Gastrointestinal                                                                                         
 Anorexia                                               66%                             47%                 
 Nausea/vomiting                                        41%                             16%                 
 Diarrhea                                               50%                              5%                 
   Musculoskeletal                                                                                          
 Jaw pain                                               75%                              0%                 
 Pain/neck pain/arthralgia                              84%                             65%                 
   Neurological                                                                                             
 Headache                                               46%                              5%                 
   Skin and Appendages                                                                                      
 Skin ulcer                                             39%                             24%                 
 Eczema/rash/urticaria                                  25%                              4%                 
         Although the relationship to epoprostenol administration has not been established, pulmonary embolism has been reported in several patients taking epoprostenol and there have been reports of hepatic failure.
 

     Adverse Events Attributable to the Drug Delivery System  



 Chronic infusions of epoprostenol are delivered using a small, portable infusion pump through an indwelling central venous catheter. During controlled PAH trials of up to 12 weeks' duration, the local infection rate was about 18%, and the rate for pain was about 11%. During long-term follow-up, sepsis was reported at a rate of 0.3 infections/patient per year in patients treated with epoprostenol. This rate was higher than reported in patients using chronic indwelling central venous catheters to administer parenteral nutrition, but lower than reported in oncology patients using these catheters. Malfunctions in the delivery system resulting in an inadvertent bolus of or a reduction in epoprostenol were associated with symptoms related to excess or insufficient epoprostenol, respectively.



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  In addition to adverse reactions reported from clinical trials, the following events have been identified during post-approval use of epoprostenol. Because they are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, estimates of frequency cannot be made. These events have been chosen for inclusion due to a combination of their seriousness, frequency of reporting, or potential causal connection to epoprostenol.



   Blood and Lymphatic:  Anemia, hypersplenism, pancytopenia, splenomegaly.



   Endocrine and Metabolic:  Hyperthyroidism
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  VELETRI should be used only by clinicians experienced in the diagnosis and treatment of pulmonary hypertension. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Reconstitute only as directed, with Sterile Water for Injection or Sodium Chloride 0.9% Injection.(  5.1  ) 
 *  Do not abruptly lower the dose or withdraw dosing. All dosing initiation and changes should be closely monitored. (  5.3  ,  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 General



   Reconstitute VELETRI only as directed using Sterile Water for Injection, USP, or Sodium Chloride 0.9% Injection, USP. Do not mix VELETRI with any other parenteral medications or solutions prior to or during administration.  



 VELETRI should be used only by clinicians experienced in the diagnosis and treatment of pulmonary hypertension. Carefully establish the diagnosis of idiopathic or heritable PAH or PAH/CTD.



    5.2 Dose Initiation



  VELETRI is a potent pulmonary and systemic vasodilator. Initiate VELETRI in a setting with adequate personnel and equipment for physiologic monitoring and emergency care. Dose initiation has been performed during right heart catheterization and without cardiac catheterization. During dose initiation, asymptomatic increases in pulmonary artery pressure coincident with increases in cardiac output occurred rarely. In such cases, consider dose reduction, but such an increase does not imply that chronic treatment is contraindicated.



    5.3 Chronic Use and Dose Adjustment



  During chronic use, deliver VELETRI continuously on an ambulatory basis through a permanent indwelling central venous catheter. Unless contraindicated, administer anticoagulant therapy to patients receiving VELETRI to reduce the risk of pulmonary thromboembolism or systemic embolism through a patent foramen ovale. To reduce the risk of infection, use aseptic technique in the reconstitution and administration of VELETRI and in routine catheter care. Because epoprostenol is metabolized rapidly, even brief interruptions in the delivery of VELETRI may result in symptoms associated with rebound pulmonary hypertension including dyspnea, dizziness, and asthenia. Intravenous therapy with VELETRI will likely be needed for prolonged periods, possibly years, so consider the patient's capacity to accept and care for a permanent intravenous catheter and infusion pump.



 Based on clinical trials, the acute hemodynamic response (reduction in pulmonary artery resistance) to epoprostenol did not correlate well with improvement in exercise tolerance or survival during chronic use of epoprostenol. Adjust dosage of VELETRI during chronic use at the first sign of recurrence or worsening of symptoms attributable to pulmonary hypertension or the occurrence of adverse events associated with epoprostenol [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  ]  . Following dosage adjustments, monitor standing and supine blood pressure and heart rate closely for several hours.



    5.4 Withdrawal Effects



  Abrupt withdrawal (including interruptions in drug delivery) or sudden large reductions in dosage of VELETRI may result in symptoms associated with rebound pulmonary hypertension, including dyspnea, dizziness, and asthenia. In clinical trials, one Class III primary pulmonary hypertension patient's death was judged attributable to the interruption of epoprostenol. Avoid abrupt withdrawal.



    5.5 Sepsis



  See   Adverse Reactions (6.1)    
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
