<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="venlafaxine" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Major Depressive Disorder - Adverse events in short-term studies that occurred in at least 5% of the patients receiving venlafaxine extended-release capsules and at a rate at least twice that of the placebo group were abnormal ejaculation, gastrointestinal complaints (nausea, dry mouth, and anorexia), CNS complaints (dizziness, somnolence, and abnormal dreams), and sweating.



 Social Anxiety Disorder - Adverse events in short-term studies that occurred in at least 5% of the patients receiving venlafaxine extended-release capsules and at a rate at least twice that of the placebo group were asthenia, gastrointestinal complaints (anorexia, dry mouth, nausea), CNS complaints (anxiety, insomnia, libido decreased, nervousness, somnolence, dizziness), abnormalities of sexual function (abnormal ejaculation, orgasmic dysfunction, impotence), yawn, sweating, and abnormal vision.  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Upstate Pharma, LLC at 1-844-599-2273 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Data Sources



 The information included in subsection "Adverse Findings Observed in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Studies with Venlafaxine Hydrochloride Extended-Release Capsules" is based on data from a pool of three 8- and 12-week controlled clinical trials in major depressive disorder (includes two U.S. trials and one European trial), and on data up to 12 weeks from a pool of two controlled clinical trials in Social Anxiety Disorder. Information on additional adverse reactions associated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules in the entire development program for the formulation and with venlafaxine hydrochloride immediate-release tablets is included in the subsection "Other Adverse Reactions Observed During the Premarketing Evaluation of Venlafaxine Hydrochloride Immediate-Release Tablets and Venlafaxine Hydrochloride Extended-Release Capsules" [  see also  Warnings and Precautions (5)    ].



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Adverse Findings Observed in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Studies with Venlafaxine Hydrochloride Extended-Release Capsules



     Adverse Reactions Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment  



     Major Depressive Disorder  : Approximately 11% of the 357 patients who received venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules in placebo-controlled clinical trials for major depressive disorder discontinued treatment due to an adverse reaction, compared with 6% of the 285 placebo-treated patients in those studies. Adverse reactions that led to treatment discontinuation in a least 2% of drug-treated patients were nausea, dizziness, and somnolence.



     Social Anxiety Disorder  : Approximately 17% of the 277 patients who received venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules in placebo-controlled clinical trials for Social Anxiety Disorder discontinued treatment due to an adverse reaction, compared with 5% of the 274 placebo-treated patients in those studies. Adverse reactions that led to treatment discontinuation in a least 2% of drug-treated patients were nausea, insomnia, impotence, headache, dizziness, and somnolence.



     Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of 5% or More  



     Major Depressive Disorder  : Note in particular the following adverse reactions that occurred in at least 5% of the patients receiving venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules and at a rate at least twice that of the placebo group for all placebo-controlled trials for the major depressive disorder indication (see  Table 6  ): Abnormal ejaculation, gastrointestinal complaints (nausea, dry mouth, and anorexia), CNS complaints (dizziness, somnolence, and abnormal dreams), and sweating. In the two U.S. placebo-controlled trials, the following additional reactions occurred in at least 5% of patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules (n = 192) and at a rate at least twice that of the placebo group: Abnormalities of sexual function (impotence in men, anorgasmia in women, and libido decreased), gastrointestinal complaints (constipation and flatulence), CNS complaints (insomnia, nervousness, and tremor), problems of special senses (abnormal vision), cardiovascular effects (hypertension and vasodilatation), and yawning.



     Social Anxiety Disorder  : Note in particular the following adverse reactions that occurred in at least 5% of the patients receiving venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules and at a rate at least twice that of the placebo group for the 2 placebo-controlled trials for the Social Anxiety Disorder indication (see  Table 7  ): Asthenia, gastrointestinal complaints (anorexia, constipation, dry mouth, nausea), CNS complaints (dizziness, insomnia, libido decreased, nervousness, somnolence), abnormalities of sexual function (abnormal ejaculation, impotence, libido decreased, orgasmic dysfunction), yawn, sweating, and abnormal vision.



     Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of 2% or More Among Patients Treated with Venlafaxine Hydrochloride Extended-Release Capsules  



 Tables 6 and 7 enumerate the incidence, rounded to the nearest percent, of adverse reactions that occurred during acute therapy of major depressive disorder (up to 12 weeks; dose range of 75 to 225 mg/day) and of Social Anxiety Disorder (up to 12 weeks; dose range of 75 to 225 mg/day), respectively, in 2% or more of patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules where the incidence in patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules was greater than the incidence for the respective placebo-treated patients. The table shows the percentage of patients in each group who had at least one episode of a reaction at some time during their treatment. Reported adverse reactions were classified using a standard COSTART-based Dictionary terminology.



 The prescriber should be aware that these figures cannot be used to predict the incidence of adverse reactions in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors differ from those which prevailed in the clinical trials. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be compared with figures obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatments, uses and investigators. The cited figures, however, do provide the prescribing physician with some basis for estimating the relative contribution of drug and nondrug factors to the adverse reaction incidence rate in the population studied.



 Table 6 Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reaction Incidence in Short-Term Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials with Venlafaxine Hydrochloride Extended-Release Capsules in Patients with Major Depressive DisorderIncidence, rounded to the nearest %, for reactions reported by at least 2% of patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules, except for reactions which had an incidence equal to or less than placebo.,&lt;1% indicates an incidence greater than zero but less than 1%. 
                                                % Reporting Reaction        
 Body System  Preferred Term               Venlafaxine Hydrochloride Extended-Release Capsules             Placebo               
                                                     (n = 357)                       (n = 285)              
  
   Body as a Whole                                                                                          
   Asthenia                                              8%                              7%                 
   Cardiovascular System                                                                                    
   Vasodilatation                                        4%                              2%                 
   Hypertension                                          4%                              1%                 
   Digestive System                                                                                         
   Nausea                                               31%                             12%                 
   Constipation                                          8%                              5%                 
   Anorexia                                              8%                              4%                 
   Vomiting                                              4%                              2%                 
   Flatulence                                            4%                              3%                 
   Metabolic/Nutritional                                                                                    
   Weight Loss                                           3%                              0%                 
   Nervous System                                                                                           
   Dizziness                                            20%                              9%                 
   Somnolence                                           17%                              8%                 
   Insomnia                                             17%                             11%                 
   Dry Mouth                                            12%                              6%                 
   Nervousness                                          10%                              5%                 
   Abnormal Dreams                                       7%                              2%                 
   Tremor                                                5%                              2%                 
   Depression                                            3%                             &lt;1%                 
   Paresthesia                                           3%                              1%                 
   Libido Decreased                                      3%                             &lt;1%                 
   Agitation                                             3%                              1%                 
   Respiratory System                                                                                       
   Pharyngitis                                           7%                              6%                 
   Yawn                                                  3%                              0%                 
   Skin                                                                                                     
   Sweating                                             14%                              3%                 
   Special Senses                                                                                           
   Abnormal Vision                                       4%                             &lt;1%                 
   Urogenital System                                                                                        
   Abnormal Ejaculation  (male)  ,                      16%                             &lt;1%                 
   Impotence                                             4%                             &lt;1%                 
   Anorgasmia (female)  ,                                3%                             &lt;1%                 
        Table 7 Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reaction Incidence in Short-Term Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials with Venlafaxine Hydrochloride Extended-Release Capsules in Social Anxiety Disorder PatientsAdverse reactions for which the venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules reporting rate was less than or equal to the placebo rate are not included.,&lt;1% means greater than zero but less than 1%. 
                                           % Reporting Reaction          
 Body System  Preferred Term         Venlafaxine Hydrochloride Extended-Release Capsules               Placebo                
                                                 (n = 277)                          (n = 274)               
  
   Body as a Whole                                                                                          
   Headache                                         34%                                33%                  
   Asthenia                                         17%                                8%                   
   Flu Syndrome                                     6%                                 5%                   
   Accidental Injury                                5%                                 3%                   
   Abdominal Pain                                   4%                                 3%                   
   Cardiovascular System                                                                                    
   Hypertension                                     5%                                 4%                   
   Vasodilatation                                   3%                                 1%                   
   Palpitation                                      3%                                 1%                   
   Digestive System                                                                                         
   Nausea                                           29%                                9%                   
   Anorexia                                         20%                                1%                   
   Constipation                                     8%                                 4%                   
   Diarrhea                                         6%                                 5%                   
   Vomiting                                         3%                                 2%                   
   Eructation                                       2%                                 0%                   
   Metabolic/Nutritional                                                                                    
   Weight Loss                                      4%                                 0%                   
   Nervous System                                                                                           
   Insomnia                                         23%                                7%                   
   Dry Mouth                                        17%                                4%                   
   Dizziness                                        16%                                8%                   
   Somnolence                                       16%                                8%                   
   Nervousness                                      11%                                3%                   
   Libido Decreased                                 9%                                 &lt;1%                  
   Anxiety                                          5%                                 3%                   
   Agitation                                        4%                                 1%                   
   Tremor                                           4%                                 &lt;1%                  
   Abnormal Dreams                                  4%                                 &lt;1%                  
   Paresthesia                                      3%                                 &lt;1%                  
   Twitching                                        2%                                 0%                   
   Respiratory System                                                                                       
   Yawn                                             5%                                 &lt;1%                  
   Sinusitis                                        2%                                 1%                   
   Skin                                                                                                     
   Sweating                                         13%                                2%                   
   Special Senses                                                                                           
   Abnormal Vision                                  6%                                 3%                   
   Urogenital System                                                                                        
   Abnormal Ejaculation  ,                          16%                                1%                   
   Impotence                                        10%                                1%                   
   Orgasmic Dysfunction  ,                          8%                                 0%                   
           Vital Sign Changes
 

 Treatment with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules treatment for up to 12 weeks in premarketing placebo-controlled major depressive disorder trials was associated with a mean final on-therapy increase in pulse rate of approximately 2 beats per minute, compared with 1 beat per minute for placebo.



 Treatment with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules for up to 12 weeks in premarketing placebo-controlled Social Anxiety Disorder trials was associated with a mean final on-therapy increase in pulse rate of approximately 4 beats per minute, compared with an increase of 1 beat per minute for placebo. [See    Warnings and Precautions (5.3)    for effects on blood pressure.]



 In a flexible-dose study in MDD, with doses of venlafaxine hydrochloride immediate-release tablets in the range of 200 to 375 mg/day and mean dose greater than 300 mg/day, the mean pulse was increased by about 2 beats per minute compared with a decrease of about 1 beat per minute for placebo. [See    Warnings and Precautions (5.16)    for effects on heart rate.]



   Laboratory Changes



     Serum Cholesterol  



 Venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules treatment for up to 12 weeks in premarketing placebo-controlled trials for major depressive disorder was associated with a mean final on-therapy increase in serum cholesterol concentration of approximately 1.5 mg/dL compared with a mean final decrease of 7.4 mg/dL for placebo. Venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules treatment for up to 12 weeks in other premarketing placebo-controlled trials was associated with mean final on-therapy increases in serum cholesterol concentration of approximately 7.9 mg/dL compared with a mean final decrease of 2.9 mg/dL for placebo.



 Patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride immediate-release tablets for at least 3 months in placebo-controlled 12-month extension trials had a mean final on-therapy increase in total cholesterol of 9.1 mg/dL compared with a decrease of 7.1 mg/dL among placebo-treated patients. This increase was duration dependent over the study period and tended to be greater with higher doses. Clinically relevant increases in serum cholesterol, defined as 1) a final on-therapy increase in serum cholesterol &gt;=50 mg/dL from baseline and to a value &gt;=261 mg/dL, or 2) an average on-therapy increase in serum cholesterol &gt;=50 mg/dL from baseline and to a value &gt;=261 mg/dL, were recorded in 5.3% of venlafaxine-treated patients and 0.0% of placebo-treated patients [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.14)    ].



     Serum Triglycerides  



 Venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules treatment for up to 12 weeks in pooled premarketing trials was associated with a mean final on-therapy increase in fasting serum triglyceride concentration of approximately 8.2 mg/dl, compared with a mean final increase of 0.4 mg/dl for placebo.



   ECG Changes



 In a flexible-dose MDD study with doses of venlafaxine hydrochloride immediate-release tablets in the range of 200 to 375 mg/day and mean dose greater than 300 mg/day, the mean change in heart rate was 8.5 beats per minute compared with 1.7 beats per minute for placebo. [  See  Warnings and Precautions (5.16)    ]



   Other Adverse Reactions Observed During the Premarketing Evaluation of Venlafaxine Hydrochloride Immediate-Release Tablets and Venlafaxine Hydrochloride Extended-Release Capsules



 During its premarketing assessment, multiple doses of venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules were administered to 705 patients in Phase 3 major depressive disorder studies and venlafaxine hydrochloride immediate-release tablets was administered to 96 patients. During its premarketing assessment, multiple doses of venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules were also administered to 3514 patients in other Phase 3 studies. In addition, in premarketing assessment of venlafaxine hydrochloride immediate-release tablets, multiple doses were administered to 2897 patients in Phase 2 to Phase 3 studies for major depressive disorder. The conditions and duration of exposure to venlafaxine in both development programs varied greatly, and included (in overlapping categories) open and double-blind studies, uncontrolled and controlled studies, inpatient (venlafaxine hydrochloride immediate-release tablets only) and outpatient studies, fixed-dose, and titration studies. Adverse reactions associated with this exposure were recorded by clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. Consequently, it is not possible to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse reactions without first grouping similar types of untoward events into a smaller number of standardized reaction categories.



 In the tabulations that follow, reported adverse reactions were classified using a standard COSTART-based Dictionary terminology. The frequencies presented, therefore, represent the proportion of the 7212 patients exposed to multiple doses of either formulation of venlafaxine who experienced a reaction of the type cited on at least one occasion while receiving venlafaxine. All reported reactions are included except those already listed in Tables 6 and 7 and those reactions for which a drug cause was remote. If the COSTART term for a reaction was so general as to be uninformative, it was replaced with a more informative term. It is important to emphasize that, although the reactions reported occurred during treatment with venlafaxine, they were not necessarily caused by it.



 Reactions are further categorized by body system and listed in order of decreasing frequency using the following definitions:  frequent  adverse reactions are defined as those occurring on one or more occasions in at least 1/100 patients;  infrequent  adverse reactions are those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1000 patients;  rare  reactions are those occurring in fewer than 1/1000 patients.



 Body as a whole -  Frequent:  chest pain substernal, chills, fever, neck pain;  Infrequent:  face edema, intentional injury, malaise, moniliasis, neck rigidity, pelvic pain, photosensitivity reaction, suicide attempt, withdrawal syndrome;  Rare:  appendicitis, bacteremia, cellulitis, granuloma.



 Cardiovascular system -  Frequent:  migraine, tachycardia;  Infrequent:  angina pectoris, bradycardia, extrasystoles, hypotension, peripheral vascular disorder (mainly cold feet and/or cold hands), postural hypotension, syncope;  Rare:  aortic aneurysm, arteritis, first-degree atrioventricular block, bigeminy, bundle branch block, capillary fragility, cerebral ischemia, coronary artery disease, congestive heart failure, heart arrest, hematoma, cardiovascular disorder (mitral valve and circulatory disturbance), mucocutaneous hemorrhage, myocardial infarct, pallor, sinus arrhythmia, thrombophlebitis.



 Digestive system -  Frequent:  increased appetite;  Infrequent:  bruxism, colitis, dysphagia, tongue edema, eructation, esophagitis, gastritis, gastroenteritis, gastrointestinal ulcer, gingivitis, glossitis, rectal hemorrhage, hemorrhoids, melena, oral moniliasis, stomatitis, mouth ulceration;  Rare:  abdominal distension, biliary pain, cheilitis, cholecystitis, cholelithiasis, esophageal spasms, duodenitis, hematemesis, gastroesophageal reflux disease, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, gum hemorrhage, hepatitis, ileitis, jaundice, intestinal obstruction, liver tenderness, parotitis, periodontitis, proctitis, salivary gland enlargement, increased salivation, soft stools, tongue discoloration.



 Endocrine system -  Rare:  galactorrhoea, goiter, hyperthyroidism, hypothyroidism, thyroid nodule, thyroiditis.



 Hemic and lymphatic system -  Frequent:  ecchymosis;  Infrequent:  anemia, leukocytosis, leukopenia, lymphadenopathy, thrombocythemia;  Rare:  basophilia, bleeding time increased, cyanosis, eosinophilia, lymphocytosis, multiple myeloma, purpura, thrombocytopenia.



 Metabolic and nutritional -  Frequent:  edema, weight gain;  Infrequent:  alkaline phosphatase increased, dehydration, hypercholesteremia, hyperglycemia, hyperlipidemia, hypokalemia, SGOT (AST) increased, SGPT (ALT) increased, thirst;  Rare:  alcohol intolerance, bilirubinemia, BUN increased, creatinine increased, diabetes mellitus, glycosuria, gout, healing abnormal, hemochromatosis, hypercalcinuria, hyperkalemia, hyperphosphatemia, hyperuricemia, hypocholesteremia, hypoglycemia, hyponatremia, hypophosphatemia, hypoproteinemia, uremia.



 Musculoskeletal system -  Infrequent:  arthritis, arthrosis, bone spurs, bursitis, leg cramps, myasthenia, tenosynovitis;  Rare:  pathological fracture, muscle cramp, muscle spasms, musculoskeletal stiffness, myopathy, osteoporosis, osteosclerosis, plantar fasciitis, rheumatoid arthritis, tendon rupture.



 Nervous system -  Frequent:  amnesia, confusion, depersonalization, hypesthesia, trismus, vertigo;  Infrequent:  akathisia, apathy, ataxia, circumoral paresthesia, CNS stimulation, emotional lability, euphoria, hallucinations, hostility, hyperesthesia, hyperkinesia, hypotonia, incoordination, libido increased, manic reaction, myoclonus, neuralgia, neuropathy, psychosis, seizure, stupor, suicidal ideation;  Rare:  akinesia, alcohol abuse, aphasia, bradykinesia, buccoglossal syndrome, cerebrovascular accident, feeling drunk, loss of consciousness, delusions, dementia, dystonia, energy increased, facial paralysis, abnormal gait, Guillain-Barre Syndrome, homicidal ideation, hyperchlorhydria, hypokinesia, hysteria, impulse control difficulties, motion sickness, neuritis, nystagmus, paranoid reaction, paresis, psychotic depression, reflexes decreased, reflexes increased, torticollis.



 Respiratory system -  Frequent:  cough increased, dyspnea;  Infrequent:  asthma, chest congestion, epistaxis, hyperventilation, laryngismus, laryngitis, pneumonia;  Rare:  atelectasis, hemoptysis, hypoventilation, hypoxia, larynx edema, pleurisy, pulmonary embolus, sleep apnea.



 Skin and appendages -  Frequent:  pruritus;  Infrequent:  acne, alopecia, contact dermatitis, dry skin, eczema, maculopapular rash, psoriasis, urticaria;  Rare:  brittle nails, erythema nodosum, exfoliative dermatitis, lichenoid dermatitis, furunculosis, hirsutism, leukoderma, miliaria, petechial rash, pruritic rash, pustular rash, vesiculobullous rash, seborrhea, skin atrophy, skin hypertrophy, skin striae, sweating decreased.



 Special senses -  Frequent:  abnormality of accommodation, mydriasis, taste perversion;  Infrequent:  conjunctivitis, diplopia, dry eyes, otitis media, parosmia, photophobia, taste loss;  Rare:  blepharitis, cataract, chromatopsia, conjunctival edema, corneal lesion, deafness, exophthalmos, eye hemorrhage, angle-closure glaucoma, retinal hemorrhage, subconjunctival hemorrhage, hyperacusis, keratitis, labyrinthitis, miosis, papilledema, decreased pupillary reflex, otitis externa, scleritis, uveitis, visual field defect.



  Urogenital system -  Frequent:  albuminuria, urination impaired;  Infrequent:  amenorrhea, (Based on the number of men and women as appropriate.) cystitis, dysuria, hematuria, kidney calculus, kidney pain, leukorrhea,menorrhagia,metrorrhagia,nocturia, breast pain, polyuria, pyuria, prostatic disorder (prostatitis, enlarged prostate, and prostate irritability),urinary incontinence, urinary retention, urinary urgency, vaginal hemorrhage,vaginitis;  Rare:  abortion,anuria, breast discharge, breast engorgement, balanitis,breast enlargement, endometriosis,female lactation,fibrocystic breast, calcium crystalluria, cervicitis,orchitis,ovarian cyst,bladder pain, prolonged erection,gynecomastia (male),hypomenorrhea,mastitis, menopause,pyelonephritis, oliguria, salpingitis,urolithiasis, uterine hemorrhage,uterine spasm,vaginal dryness.
 

   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  Voluntary reports of other adverse reactions temporally associated with the use of venlafaxine have been received since market introduction. Because these reactions are reported from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. These reports include the following reactions: agranulocytosis, anaphylaxis, aplastic anemia, catatonia, congenital anomalies, impaired coordination and balance, CPK increased, deep vein thrombophlebitis, delirium, EKG abnormalities such as QT prolongation; cardiac arrhythmias including atrial fibrillation, supraventricular tachycardia, ventricular extrasystoles, and rare reports of ventricular fibrillation and ventricular tachycardia, including torsade de pointes; toxic epidermal necrolysis/Stevens-Johnson Syndrome, erythema multiforme, extrapyramidal symptoms (including dyskinesia and tardive dyskinesia), angle-closure glaucoma, hemorrhage (including eye and gastrointestinal bleeding), hepatic reactions (including GGT elevation; abnormalities of unspecified liver function tests; liver damage, necrosis, or failure; and fatty liver), interstitial lung disease, involuntary movements, LDH increased, neuroleptic malignant syndrome-like reactions (including a case of a 10-year-old who may have been taking methylphenidate, was treated and recovered), neutropenia, night sweats, pancreatitis, pancytopenia, panic, prolactin increased, renal failure, rhabdomyolysis, serotonin syndrome, shock-like electrical sensations or tinnitus (in some cases, subsequent to the discontinuation of venlafaxine or tapering of dose), and syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion (usually in the elderly).
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: SUICIDALITY AND ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS

    WARNING: SUICIDALITY AND ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS  

    Antidepressants increased the risk compared to placebo of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term studies of Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Anyone considering the use of Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets or any other antidepressant in a child, adolescent, or young adult must balance this risk with the clinical need. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction in risk with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older. Depression and certain other psychiatric disorders are themselves associated with increases in the risk of suicide. Patients of all ages who are started on antidepressant therapy should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, or unusual changes in behavior. Families and caregivers should be advised of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber. Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets are not approved for use in pediatric patients. [    See Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   and   Patient Counseling Information (17.1)    ]  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: Suicidality and Antidepressants   



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



   Increased risk of suicidal thinking and behavior in children, adolescents and young adults taking antidepressants for major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets are not approved for use in pediatric patients. (  5.1  )  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Serotonin Syndrome: Serotonin syndrome has been reported with SSRIs and SNRIs, including Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets, both when taken alone, but especially when co-administered with other serotonergic agents (including triptans, tricyclic antidepressants, fentanyl, lithium, tramadol, tryptophan, buspirone and St. John's Wort). If such symptoms occur, discontinue Venlafaxine Extended-Release tablets and initiate supportive treatment. If concomitant use of Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets with other serotonergic drugs is clinically warranted, patients should be made aware of a potential increased risk for serotonin syndrome, particularly during treatment initiation and dose increases. (  5.2  ). 
 *  Suicidality: Monitor for clinical worsening and suicide risk. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Sustained hypertension may occur. Blood pressure monitoring recommended. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Angle Closure Glaucoma: Angle closure glaucoma has occurred in patients with untreated anatomically narrow angles treated with antidepressants. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Abrupt discontinuation or dose reduction: Discontinuation symptoms may occur (generally self-limiting; serious symptoms possible). Dose reduction recommended to be gradual. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Activation of Mania/Hypomania has occurred. (  5.10  ) 
 *  Symptomatic hyponatremia may occur. (  5.11  ) 
 *  Seizures have been reported. Use with caution in patients with seizure history. (  5.12  ) 
 *  Abnormal bleeding (most commonly ecchymosis) has been reported. (  5.13  ) 
 *  Serum cholesterol: Clinically relevant cholesterol increases may occur. Cholesterol measurements should be considered during long-term therapy. (  5.14  ) 
 *  Interstitial lung disease and eosinophilic pneumonia have been reported. (  5.15  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Clinical Worsening and Suicide Risk



  Patients with major depressive disorder (MDD), both adult and pediatric, may experience worsening of their depression and/or the emergence of suicidal ideation and behavior (suicidality) or unusual changes in behavior, whether or not they are taking antidepressant medications, and this risk may persist until significant remission occurs. Suicide is a known risk of depression and certain other psychiatric disorders, and these disorders themselves are the strongest predictors of suicide. There has been a long standing concern, however, that antidepressants may have a role in inducing worsening of depression and the emergence of suicidality in certain patients during the early phases of treatment. Pooled analyses of short-term placebo-controlled trials of antidepressant drugs (SSRIs and others) showed that these drugs increase the risk of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults (ages 18-24) with major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older.



 The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in children and adolescents with MDD, obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD), or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 24 short-term trials of 9 antidepressant drugs in over 4400 patients. The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in adults with MDD or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 295 short-term trials (median duration of 2 months) of 11 antidepressant drugs in over 77,000 patients.



 There was considerable variation in risk of suicidality among drugs, but a tendency toward an increase in the younger patients for almost all drugs studied. There were differences in absolute risk of suicidality across the different indications, with the highest incidence in MDD. The risk differences (drug vs placebo), however, were relatively stable within age strata and across indications. These risk differences (drug-placebo difference in the number of cases of suicidality per 1000 patients treated) are provided in Table 1.



 Table 1 
    Age Range      Drug-Placebo Difference in Number of Cases of Suicidality per 1000 Patients Treated    
  
                                              Increases Compared to Placebo                               
       &lt;18                                         14 additional cases                                    
      18-24                                        5 additional cases                                     
                                              Decreases Compared to Placebo                               
      25-64                                           1 fewer case                                        
      &gt;=65                                            6 fewer cases                                       
        No suicides occurred in any of the pediatric trials. There were suicides in the adult trials, but the number was not sufficient to reach any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.
 

 It is unknown whether the suicidality risk extends to longer-term use, i.e., beyond several months. However, there is substantial evidence from placebo-controlled maintenance trials in adults with depression that the use of antidepressants can delay the recurrence of depression.



  All patients being treated with antidepressants for any indication should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, and unusual changes in behavior, especially during the initial few months of a course of drug therapy, or at times of dose changes, either increases or decreases.  



 The following symptoms, anxiety, agitation, panic attacks, insomnia, irritability, hostility, aggressiveness, impulsivity, akathisia (psychomotor restlessness), hypomania, and mania, have been reported in adult and pediatric patients being treated with antidepressants for major depressive disorder as well as for other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric. Although a causal link between the emergence of such symptoms and either the worsening of depression and/or the emergence of suicidal impulses has not been established, there is concern that such symptoms may represent precursors to emerging suicidality.



 Consideration should be given to changing the therapeutic regimen, including possibly discontinuing the medication, in patients whose depression is persistently worse, or who are experiencing emergent suicidality or symptoms that might be precursors to worsening depression or suicidality, especially if these symptoms are severe, abrupt in onset, or were not part of the patient's presenting symptoms.



 If the decision has been made to discontinue treatment, medication should be tapered, as rapidly as is feasible, but with recognition that abrupt discontinuation can be associated with certain symptoms [ see  Dosage and Administration (2.5 )  and  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)    ].



  Families and caregivers of patients being treated with antidepressants for major depressive disorder or other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric, should be alerted about the need to monitor patients for the emergence of agitation, irritability, unusual changes in behavior, and the other symptoms described above, as well as the emergence of suicidality, and to report such symptoms immediately to health care providers. Such monitoring should include daily observation by families and caregivers.  Prescriptions for Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets should be written for the smallest quantity of tablets consistent with good patient management, in order to reduce the risk of overdose.



 A major depressive episode may be the initial presentation of bipolar disorder. It is generally believed (though not established in controlled trials) that treating such an episode with an antidepressant alone may increase the likelihood of precipitation of a mixed/manic episode in patients at risk for bipolar disorder. Whether any of the symptoms described above represent such a conversion is unknown. However, prior to initiating treatment with an antidepressant, patients with depressive symptoms should be adequately screened to determine if they are at risk for bipolar disorder; such screening should include a detailed psychiatric history, including a family history of suicide, bipolar disorder, and depression. It should be noted that Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets are not approved for use in treating bipolar depression.



    5.2 Serotonin Syndrome



  The development of a potentially life-threatening serotonin syndrome has been reported with SNRIs and SSRIs, including Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets, alone but particularly with concomitant use of other serotonergic drugs (including triptans, tricyclic antidepressants, fentanyl, lithium, tramadol, tryptophan, busipirone, and St. John's Wort), and with drugs that impair metabolism of serotonin (in particular, MAOIs, both those intended to treat psychiatric disorders and also others, such as linezolid and intravenous methylene blue).



 Serotonin syndrome symptoms may include mental status changes (e.g., agitation, hallucinations, delirium, and coma), autonomic instability (e.g., tachycardia, labile blood pressure, dizziness, diaphoresis, flushing, hyperthermia), neuromuscular symptoms (e.g., tremor, rigidity, myoclonus, hyperreflexia, incoordination), seizures, and/or gastrointestinal symptoms (e.g., nausea, vomiting, diarrhea). Patients should be monitored for the emergence of serotonin syndrome.



 The concomitant use of Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets with MAOIs intended to treat psychiatric disorders is contraindicated. Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets should also not be started in a patient who is being treated with MAOIs such as linezolid or intravenous methylene blue. All reports with methylene blue that provided information on the route of administration involved intravenous administration in the dose range of 1 mg/kg to 8 mg/kg. No reports involved the administration of methylene blue by other routes (such as oral tablets or local tissue injection) or at lower doses. There may be circumstances when it is necessary to initiate treatment with a MAOI such as linezolid or intravenous methylene blue in a patient taking Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets. Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets should be discontinued before initiating treatment with the MAOI. [ see  CONTRAINDICATIONS (4.1)  and  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION (2.6  and  2.7)    ].



 If concomitant use of Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets with other serotonergic drugs including triptans, tricyclic antidepressants, fentanyl, lithium, tramadol, buspirone, tryptophan and St. John's Wort is clinically warranted, patients should be aware of a potential increased risk for serotonin syndrome, particularly during treatment initiation and dose increases.



 Treatment with Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets and any concomitant serotonergic agents should be discontinued immediately if the above events occur and supportive symptomatic treatment should be initiated.



    5.3 Sustained Hypertension



  Venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsule treatment is associated with sustained hypertension (defined as treatment-emergent supine diastolic blood pressure (SDBP) &gt;=90 mm Hg and &gt;=10 mm Hg above baseline for 3 consecutive on-therapy visits) (see  Table 2  ).



 An analysis for patients in venlafaxine hydrochloride immediate-release tablet studies meeting criteria for sustained hypertension revealed a dose-dependent increase in the incidence of sustained hypertension for immediate-release venlafaxine hydrochloride (see  Table 3  ).



 An insufficient number of patients received mean doses of venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules over 300 mg/day to fully evaluate the incidence of sustained increases in blood pressure at these higher doses.



 Table 2: Number (%) of Sustained Elevations in SDBP in Venlafaxine Hydrochloride Extended-Release Capsule Premarketing Studies by Indication 
      Major Depressive Disorder(75-375 mg/day)              Other Clinical Trials(75-225 mg/day)          
  
                     19/705 (3)                                         5/771 (0.6)                       
       Table 3: Incidence (%) of Sustained Elevations in SDBP in Venlafaxine Hydrochloride Immediate-Release Tablet Studies 
                 Venlafaxine mg/day                                      Incidence                        
  
                        &lt;100                                                 3%                           
                   &gt;100 to &lt;=200                                             5%                           
                   &gt;200 to &lt;=300                                             7%                           
                        &gt;300                                                13%                           
        In premarketing major depressive disorder studies, 0.7% (5/705) of the venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsule-treated patients discontinued treatment because of elevated blood pressure. Among these patients, most of the blood pressure increases were in a modest range (12 to 16 mm Hg, SDBP). In other clinical studies, 0.6% (5/771) of the venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsule-treated patients discontinued treatment because of elevated blood pressure. In these patients, the blood pressure increases were modest (1 to 24 mm Hg, SDBP).
 

 Sustained increases of SDBP could have adverse consequences. Cases of elevated blood pressure requiring immediate treatment have been reported in post marketing experience. Pre-existing hypertension should be controlled before treatment with venlafaxine. It is recommended that patients receiving venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release tablets have regular monitoring of blood pressure. For patients who experience a sustained increase in blood pressure while receiving venlafaxine, either dose reduction or discontinuation should be considered.



    Elevations in Systolic and Diastolic Blood Pressure  



 In placebo-controlled premarketing studies, there were changes in mean blood pressure (see  Table 4  for mean change in supine systolic and supine diastolic blood pressure). Across most indications, a dose-related increase in supine systolic and diastolic blood pressure was evident in venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsule-treated patients.



 Table 4: Final On-Therapy Mean Changes from Baseline in Supine Systolic and Diastolic Blood Pressure (mm Hg) Results by Indication, Study Duration, and Dose in Placebo-Controlled Trials 
                               Venlafaxine Hydrochloride Extended-Release Capsules mg/day    Placebo      
 &lt;=75                              &gt;75                                    
 SSBP                              SDBP          SSBP          SDBP          SSBP          SDBP       
  
 Major Depressive Disorder8-12 weeks     -0.28          0.37          2.93          3.56         -1.08         -0.10       
 Other Clinical Trials12 weeks     -0.29         -1.26          1.18          1.34         -1.96         -1.22       
             Across all clinical trials, 1.4% of patients in the venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsule-treated groups experienced a &gt;=15 mm Hg increase in supine diastolic blood pressure with blood pressure &gt;=105 mm Hg compared to 0.9% of patients in the placebo groups. Similarly, 1% of patients in the venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsule-treated groups experienced a &gt;=20 mm Hg increase in supine systolic blood pressure with blood pressure &gt;=180 mm Hg compared to 0.3% of patients in the placebo groups.
 

    5.4 Angle Closure Glaucoma



  Angle-Closure Glaucoma: The pupillary dilation that occurs following use of many antidepressant drugs including Venlafaxine may trigger an angle closure attack in a patient with anatomically narrow angles who does not have a patent iridectomy.



    5.5 Discontinuation of Treatment with Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets



  Discontinuation symptoms have been systematically evaluated in patients taking venlafaxine, to include prospective analyses of clinical trials and retrospective surveys of trials in major depressive disorder and social anxiety disorder. Abrupt discontinuation or dose reduction of venlafaxine at various doses has been found to be associated with the appearance of new symptoms, the frequency of which increased with increased dose level and with longer duration of treatment. Reported symptoms include agitation, anorexia, anxiety, confusion, impaired coordination and balance, diarrhea, dizziness, dry mouth, dysphoric mood, fasciculation, fatigue, headaches, hypomania, insomnia, nausea, nervousness, nightmares, sensory disturbances (including shock-like electrical sensations), somnolence, sweating, tremor, vertigo, and vomiting.



 During marketing of venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules, other SNRI's (Serotonin and Norepinephrine Reuptake Inhibitors), and SSRI's (Selective Serotonin Reuptake Inhibitors), there have been spontaneous reports of adverse reactions occurring upon discontinuation of these drugs, particularly when abrupt, including the following: dysphoric mood, irritability, agitation, dizziness, sensory disturbances (e.g. paresthesias such as electric shock sensations), anxiety, confusion, headache, lethargy, emotional lability, insomnia, hypomania, tinnitus, and seizures. While these reactions are generally self-limiting, there have been reports of serious discontinuation symptoms.



 Patients should be monitored for these symptoms when discontinuing treatment with Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets. A gradual reduction in the dose rather than abrupt cessation is recommended whenever possible. If intolerable symptoms occur following a decrease in the dose or upon discontinuation of treatment, then resuming the previously prescribed dose may be considered. Subsequently, the physician may continue decreasing the dose but at a more gradual rate [ see  Dosage and Administration (2.4)    ].



    5.6 Insomnia and Nervousness



  Treatment-emergent insomnia and nervousness were more commonly reported for patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules than with placebo in pooled analyses of short-term major depressive disorder and other clinical studies, as shown in Table 5.



 Table 5 Incidence of Insomnia and Nervousness in Placebo-Controlled Major Depressive Disorder and Other Trials 
                       Major Depressive Disorder      Other Trials       
                       Venlafaxine Hydrochloride Extended-Release Capsules        Placebo         Venlafaxine Hydrochloride Extended-Release Capsules        Placebo          
 Symptom                     n = 357               n = 285               N = 819               n = 695          
  
 Insomnia                      17%                   11%                   24%                    8%            
 Nervousness                   10%                    5%                   10%                    5%            
           Insomnia and nervousness each led to drug discontinuation in 0.9% of the patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules in major depressive disorder studies.
 

 In other clinical trials, insomnia and nervousness led to drug discontinuation in 2% and 1%, respectively, of the patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules up to 12 weeks.



    5.7 Changes in Weight



  Adult Patients: A loss of 5% or more of body weight occurred in 7% of patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules and 2% of placebo-treated patients in the short-term placebo-controlled major depressive disorder trials. The discontinuation rate for weight loss associated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules was 0.1% in major depressive disorder studies. In other placebo-controlled trials, 4% of the patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules and 1% of the placebo-treated patients sustained a loss of 7% or more of body weight during up to 6 months of treatment. None of the patients receiving venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules in other studies discontinued for weight loss.



 The safety and efficacy of venlafaxine therapy in combination with weight loss agents, including phentermine, have not been established. Co-administration of Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets and weight loss agents is not recommended. Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets are not indicated for weight loss alone or in combination with other products.



   Pediatric Patients: Weight loss has been observed in pediatric patients (ages 6-17) receiving venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules. In a pooled analysis of four eight-week, double-blind, placebo-controlled, flexible dose outpatient trials for major depressive disorder (MDD) and another disorder, patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules lost an average of 0.45 kg (n = 333), while placebo-treated patients gained an average of 0.77 kg (n = 333). More patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules than with placebo experienced a weight loss of at least 3.5% in the studies (18% of patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules vs. 3.6% of placebo-treated patients; p&lt;0.001). In a 16-week, double-blind, placebo-controlled, flexible dose outpatient study for another disorder, venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsule-treated patients lost an average of 0.75 kg (n=137), while placebo-treated patients gained an average of 0.76 kg (n=148). More patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules than with placebo experienced a weight loss of at least 3.5% in the study (47% of patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules vs. 14% of placebo-treated patients; p&lt;0.001). Weight loss was not limited to patients with treatment-emergent anorexia [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)    ].



 The risks associated with longer-term use of venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules were assessed in an open-label MDD study of children and adolescents who received venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules for up to six months. The children and adolescents in the study had increases in weight that were less than expected based on data from age- and sex-matched peers. The difference between observed weight gain and expected weight gain was larger for children (&lt;12 years old) than for adolescents (&gt;=12 years old).



    5.8 Changes in Height



  Pediatric Patients: During an eight-week, placebo-controlled non-MDD study, venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsule-treated patients (ages 6-17) grew an average of 0.3 cm (n=122), while placebo-treated patients grew an average of 1.0 cm (n=132); p=0.041. This difference in height increase was most notable in patients younger than twelve. During the eight-week placebo-controlled MDD studies, venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsule-treated patients grew an average of 0.8 cm (n = 146), while placebo-treated patients grew an average of 0.7 cm (n = 147). During a 16-week, placebo-controlled non-MDD study, both the venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsule-treated patients (n=109) and the placebo-treated (n=112) patients each grew an average of 1.0 cm. In the six-month, open-label MDD study, children and adolescents had height increases that were less than expected based on data from age- and sex-matched peers. The difference between observed growth rates and expected growth rates was larger for children (&lt;12 years old) than for adolescents (&gt;=12 years old).



    5.9 Changes in Appetite



  Adult Patients: Treatment-emergent anorexia was more commonly reported for patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules (8%) than for placebo-treated patients (4%) in the pool of short-term, double-blind, placebo-controlled major depressive disorder studies. The discontinuation rate for anorexia associated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules was 1.0% in major depressive disorder studies. Treatment-emergent anorexia was more commonly reported for patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules (20%) than for placebo-treated patients (2%) in the pool of short-term, double-blind, placebo-controlled Social Anxiety Disorder studies. The discontinuation rate for anorexia was 0.4% for patients receiving venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules for up to 12 weeks in Social Anxiety Disorder studies.



   Pediatric Patients: Decreased appetite has been observed in pediatric patients receiving venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules. In placebo-controlled trials in MDD and another disorder, 10% of patients aged 6-17 treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules for up to eight weeks and 3% of patients treated with placebo reported treatment-emergent anorexia (decreased appetite). None of the patients receiving venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules discontinued for anorexia or weight loss. In a placebo-controlled non-MDD trial, 22% and 3% of patients aged 8-17 treated for up to 16 weeks with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules and placebo, respectively, reported treatment-emergent anorexia (decreased appetite). The discontinuation rates for anorexia were 0.7% and 0.0% for patients receiving venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules and placebo, respectively; the discontinuation rates for weight loss were 0.7% for patients receiving either venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules or placebo.



    5.10 Activation of Mania/Hypomania



  During premarketing major depressive disorder studies, mania or hypomania occurred in 0.3% of patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules and 0.0% placebo patients. In premarketing Social Anxiety Disorder studies, no patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules and no placebo-treated patients experienced mania or hypomania. In all premarketing major depressive disorder trials with venlafaxine hydrochloride immediate-release tablets, mania or hypomania occurred in 0.5% of venlafaxine-treated patients compared with 0% of placebo patients. Mania/hypomania has also been reported in a small proportion of patients with mood disorders who were treated with other marketed drugs to treat major depressive disorder. As with all drugs effective in the treatment of major depressive disorder, Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets should be used cautiously in patients with a history of mania.



    5.11 Hyponatremia



  Hyponatremia may occur as a result of treatment with SSRI's and SNRI's, including Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets. In many cases, this hyponatremia appears to be the result of the syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion (SIADH). Cases with serum sodium lower than 110 mmol/L have been reported. Elderly patients may be at greater risk of developing hyponatremia with SSRIs and SNRIs. Also, patients taking diuretics or who are otherwise volume depleted may be at greater risk [ see  Use in Specific Populations (8.5)    ]. Discontinuation of Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets should be considered in patients with symptomatic hyponatremia and appropriate medical intervention should be instituted.



 Signs and symptoms of hyponatremia include headache, difficulty concentrating, memory impairment, confusion, weakness, and unsteadiness, which may lead to falls. Signs and symptoms associated with more severe and/or acute cases have included hallucination, syncope, seizure, coma, respiratory arrest, and death.



    5.12 Seizures



  During premarketing experience, no seizures occurred among 705 patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules in the major depressive disorder studies or among 277 patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules in Social Anxiety Disorder studies. In all premarketing major depressive disorder trials with venlafaxine hydrochloride immediate-release tablets, seizures were reported at various doses in 0.3% (8/3082) of venlafaxine-treated patients. Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets, like many antidepressants, should be used cautiously in patients with a history of seizures and should be discontinued in any patient who develops seizures.



    5.13 Abnormal Bleeding



  SSRIs and SNRIs, including Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets, may increase the risk of bleeding events. Concomitant use of aspirin, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, warfarin, and other anticoagulants may add to this risk. Case reports and epidemiological studies (case-control and cohort design) have demonstrated an association between use of drugs that interfere with serotonin reuptake and the occurrence of gastrointestinal bleeding. Bleeding events related to SSRIs and SNRIs use have ranged from ecchymoses, hematomas, epistaxis, and petechiae to life-threatening hemorrhages.



 Patients should be cautioned about the risk of bleeding associated with the concomitant use of Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets and NSAIDs, aspirin, or other drugs that affect coagulation.



    5.14 Serum Cholesterol Elevation



  Clinically relevant increases in serum cholesterol were recorded in 5.3% of venlafaxine-treated patients and 0.0% of placebo-treated patients treated for at least 3 months in placebo-controlled trials [ see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ]. Measurement of serum cholesterol levels should be considered during long-term treatment.



    5.15 Interstitial Lung Disease and Eosinophilic Pneumonia



  Interstitial lung disease and eosinophilic pneumonia associated with venlafaxine therapy have been rarely reported. The possibility of these adverse reactions should be considered in venlafaxine-treated patients who present with progressive dyspnea, cough or chest discomfort. Such patients should undergo a prompt medical evaluation, and discontinuation of venlafaxine therapy should be considered.



    5.16 Use in Patients With Heart Disease



  Premarketing experience with venlafaxine in patients with concomitant systemic illness is limited. Caution is advised in administering Venlafaxine Extended Release Tablets to patients with diseases or conditions that could affect hemodynamic responses.



 Venlafaxine has not been evaluated or used to any appreciable extent in patients with a recent history of myocardial infarction or unstable heart disease. Patients with these diagnoses were systematically excluded from many clinical studies during venlafaxine's premarketing testing. The electrocardiograms were analyzed for 275 patients who received venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules and 220 patients who received placebo in 8- to 12-week double-blind, placebo-controlled trials in major depressive disorder as well as for 195 patients who received venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules and 228 patients who received placebo in 12-week double-blind, placebo-controlled trials in Social Anxiety Disorder. The mean change from baseline in corrected QT interval (QTc) for patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules in major depressive disorder studies was increased relative to that for placebo-treated patients (increase of 4.7 msec for venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules and decrease of 1.9 msec for placebo). The mean change from baseline in QTc for patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules in the Social Anxiety Disorder studies was increased relative to that for placebo-treated patients (increase of 2.8 msec for venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules and decrease of 2.0 msec for placebo).



 In these same trials, the mean change from baseline in heart rate for patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules in the major depressive disorder studies was significantly higher than that for placebo (a mean increase of 4 beats per minute for venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules and 1 beat per minute for placebo). The mean change from baseline in heart rate for patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules in the Social Anxiety Disorder studies was significantly higher than that for placebo (a mean increase of 5 beats per minute for venlafaxine hydrochloride extended-release capsules and no change for placebo).



 In a flexible-dose study, with doses of venlafaxine hydrochloride immediate-release tablets in the range of 200 to 375 mg/day and mean dose greater than 300 mg/day, patients treated with venlafaxine hydrochloride immediate-release tablets had a mean increase in heart rate of 8.5 beats per minute compared with 1.7 beats per minute in the placebo group.



 As increases in heart rate were observed, caution should be exercised in patients whose underlying medical conditions might be compromised by increases in heart rate (e.g., patients with hyperthyroidism, heart failure, or recent myocardial infarction).



 Evaluation of the electrocardiograms for 769 patients who received venlafaxine hydrochloride immediate-release tablets in 4- to 6-week double-blind, placebo-controlled trials showed that the incidence of trial-emergent conduction abnormalities did not differ from that with placebo.



    5.17 Laboratory Tests



  There are no specific laboratory tests recommended.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
