<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="venofer" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions associated with Venofer are described in other sections  [See Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ,  5.2  and  5.3  )].  



    EXCERPT:    *  The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=2%) following the administration of Venofer are diarrhea, nausea, vomiting, headache, dizziness, hypotension, pruritus, pain in extremity, arthralgia, back pain, muscle cramp, injection site reactions, chest pain, and peripheral edema. (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact American Regent, Inc. at 1-800-734-9236 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or      www.fda.gov/medwatch    .
 

 

  6.1 Adverse Reactions in Clinical Trials

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Adverse Reactions in Adults Patients with CKD

    Adverse Reactions in Adult Patients with CKD  



 The frequency of adverse reactions associated with the use of Venofer has been documented in six clinical trials involving 231 patients with HDD-CKD, 139 patients with NDD-CKD and 75 patients with PDD-CKD. Treatment-emergent adverse reactions reported by &gt;= 2% of treated patients in the six clinical trials for which the rate for Venofer exceeds the rate for comparator are listed by indication in Table 1. Patients with HDD-CKD received 100 mg doses at 10 consecutive dialysis sessions until a cumulative dose of 1000 mg was administered. Patients with NDD-CKD received either 5 doses of 200 mg over 2 weeks or 2 doses of 500 mg separated by fourteen days, and patients with PDD-CKD received 2 doses of 300 mg followed by a dose of 400 mg over a period of 4 weeks.



 Table 1. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;= 2% of Study Populations and for which the Rate for Venofer Exceeds the Rate for Comparator 
   * EPO=Erythropoietin    
  
    Adverse Reactions    (Preferred Term)       HDD-CKD          NDD-CKD          PDD-CKD        
    Venofer          Venofer          Oral Iron        Venofer          EPO* Only      
    (N=231)          (N=139)          (N=139)          (N=75)           (N=46)         
    %                %                %                %                %              
    Subjects with any adverse reaction     78.8             76.3             73.4             72.0             65.2             
    Ear and Labyrinth Disorders                                                                                          
       Ear Pain    0                2.2              0.7              0                0                
    Eye Disorders                                                                                          
       Conjunctivitis   0.4              0                0                2.7              0                
    Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                                          
       Abdominal pain   3.5              1.4              2.9              4.0              6.5              
       Diarrhea    5.2              7.2              10.1             8.0              4.3              
       Dysgeusia   0.9              7.9              0                0                0                
       Nausea      14.7             8.6              12.2             5.3              4.3              
       Vomiting    9.1              5.0              8.6              8.0              2.2              
    General Disorders and                                                                                          
    Administration Site Conditions                                                                                          
       Asthenia    2.2              0.7              2.2              2.7              0                
       Chest pain   6.1              1.4              0                2.7              0                
       Feeling abnormal   3.0              0                0                0                0                
       Infusion site pain or burning   0                5.8              0                0                0                
       Injection site extravasation   0                2.2              0                0                0                
       Peripheral edema   2.6              7.2              5.0              5.3              10.9             
       Pyrexia     3.0              0.7              0.7              1.3              0                
    Infections and Infestations                                                                                          
       Nasopharyngitis, Sinusitis, Upper     respiratory tract infections, Pharyngitis   2.6              2.2              4.3              16.0             4.3              
    Injury, Poisoning and Procedural                                                                                          
    Complications                                                                                          
       Graft complication   9.5              1.4              0                0                0                
    Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders                                                                                          
       Fluid overload   3.0              1.4              0.7              1.3              0                
       Gout        0                2.9              1.4              0                0                
       Hyperglycemia   0                2.9              0                0                2.2              
       Hypoglycemia   0.4              0.7              0.7              4.0              0                
    Musculoskeletal and Connective                                                                                          
    Tissue Disorders                                                                                          
       Arthralgia   3.5              1.4              2.2              4.0              4.3              
       Back pain   2.2              2.2              3.6              1.3              4.3              
       Muscle cramp   29.4             0.7              0.7              2.7              0                
       Myalgia     0                3.6              0                1.3              0                
       Pain in extremity   5.6              4.3              0                2.7              6.5              
    Nervous System Disorders                                                                                          
       Dizziness   6.5              6.5              1.4              1.3              4.3              
       Headache    12.6             2.9              0.7              4.0              0                
    Respiratory, Thoracic and                                                                                          
    Mediastinal Disorders                                                                                          
       Cough       3.0              2.2              0.7              1.3              0                
       Dyspnea     3.5              5.8              1.4              1.3              2.2              
       Nasal congestion   0                1.4              2.2              1.3              0                
    Skin and Subcutaneous                                                                                          
    Tissue Disorders                                                                                          
       Pruritus    3.9              2.2              4.3              2.7              0                
    Vascular Disorders                                                                                          
       Hypertension   6.5              6.5              4.3              8.0              6.5              
       Hypotension   39.4             2.2              0.7              2.7              2.2              
            One hundred thirty (11%) of the 1,151 patients evaluated in the 4 U.S. trials in HDD-CKD patients (studies A, B and the two post marketing studies) had prior other intravenous iron therapy and were reported to be intolerant (defined as precluding further use of that iron product). When these patients were treated with Venofer there were no occurrences of adverse reactions that precluded further use of Venofer  [See Warning and Precautions (  5  )].  
 

   Adverse Reactions in Pediatric Patients with CKD (ages 2 years and older)

    Adverse Reactions in Pediatric Patients with CKD (ages 2 years and older)  



 In a randomized, open-label, dose-ranging trial for iron maintenance treatment with Venofer in pediatric patients with CKD on stable erythropoietin therapy  [see Clinical Studies (  14.6  )]  , at least one treatment-emergent adverse reaction was experienced by 57% (27/47) of the patients receiving Venofer 0.5 mg/kg, 53% (25/47) of the patients receiving Venofer 1.0 mg/kg, and 55% (26/47) of the patients receiving Venofer 2.0 mg/kg.



 A total of 5 (11%) subjects in the Venofer 0.5 mg/kg group, 10 (21%) patients in the Venofer 1.0 mg/kg group, and 10 (21%) patients in the Venofer 2.0 mg/kg group experienced at least 1 serious adverse reaction during the study. The most common treatment-emergent adverse reactions (&gt; 2% of patients) in all patients were headache (6%), respiratory tract viral infection (4%), peritonitis (4%), vomiting (4%), pyrexia (4%), dizziness (4%), cough (4%), renal transplant (4%), nausea (3%), arteriovenous fistula thrombosis (2%), hypotension (2%), and hypertension (2.1%).



   6.2 Adverse Reactions from Post-Marketing Experience

  Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 In the post-marketing safety studies in 1,051 treated patients with HDD-CKD, the adverse reactions reported by &gt; 1% were: cardiac failure congestive, sepsis and dysgeusia.



 The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of Venofer. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure: Anaphylactic-type reactions, shock, loss of consciousness, collapse, bronchospasm, dyspnea, convulsions, light-headedness, confusion, angioedema, swelling of the joints, hyperhidrosis, back pain, bradycardia, and chromaturia.



 Symptoms associated with Venofer total dosage or infusing too rapidly included hypotension, dyspnea, headache, vomiting, nausea, dizziness, joint aches, paresthesia, abdominal and muscle pain, edema, and cardiovascular collapse. These adverse reactions have occurred up to 30 minutes after the administration of Venofer injection. Reactions have occurred following the first dose or subsequent doses of Venofer. Symptoms may respond to intravenous fluids, hydrocortisone, and/or antihistamines. Slowing the infusion rate may alleviate symptoms.



 Injection site discoloration has been reported following extravasation. Assure stable intravenous access to avoid extravasation.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypersensitivity Reactions: Observe for signs and symptoms of hypersensitivity during and after Venofer administration for at least 30 minutes and until clinically stable following completion of each administration. Only administer Venofer when personnel and therapies are immediately available for the treatment of serious hypersensitivity reactions. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Hypotension: Venofer may cause hypotension. Monitor for signs and symptoms of hypotension during and following each administration of Venofer. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Iron Overload: Regularly monitor hematologic responses during Venofer therapy. Do not administer Venofer to patients with iron overload. (  5.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions



   Serious hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylactic-type reactions, some of which have been life-threatening and fatal, have been reported in patients receiving Venofer. Patients may present with shock, clinically significant hypotension, loss of consciousness, and/or collapse. If hypersensitivity reactions or signs of intolerance occur during administration, stop Venofer immediately. Monitor patients for signs and symptoms of hypersensitivity during and after Venofer administration for at least 30 minutes and until clinically stable following completion of the infusion. Only administer Venofer when personnel and therapies are immediately available for the treatment of serious hypersensitivity reactions.  Most reactions associated with intravenous iron preparations occur within 30 minutes of the completion of the infusion [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  and  6.2  )].  



    5.2 Hypotension



  Venofer may cause clinically significant hypotension. Monitor for signs and symptoms of hypotension following each administration of Venofer. Hypotension following administration of Venofer may be related to the rate of administration and/or total dose administered [See Dosage and Administration (  2  ), Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ), and Adverse Reactions (  6.2  )].  



    5.3 Iron Overload



  Excessive therapy with parenteral iron can lead to excess storage of iron with the possibility of iatrogenic hemosiderosis. All adult and pediatric patients receiving Venofer require periodic monitoring of hematologic and iron parameters (hemoglobin, hematocrit, serum ferritin and transferrin saturation). Do not administer Venofer to patients with evidence of iron overload. Transferrin saturation (TSAT) values increase rapidly after intravenous administration of iron sucrose; do not perform serum iron measurements for at least 48 hours after intravenous dosing [See Dosage and Administration (  2  ) and Overdosage (  10  )].  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
