<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="verelan" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 3% and more common than in patients treated with placebo) are headache, infection, constipation, flu syndrome, peripheral edema, dizziness, pharyngitis and sinusitis (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact UCB, Inc. at 1-800-477-7877 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. The adverse reaction information from clinical trials does, however, provide a basis for identifying the adverse events that appear to be related to drug use and for approximating rates.



 Serious adverse reactions are uncommon when verapamil therapy is initiated with upward dose titration within the recommended single and total daily dose. See  Warnings and Precautions (5.1  ,  5.2  ,  5.3  ,  5.4  ,  5.5)  for discussion of heart failure, hypotension, elevated liver enzymes, AV block, and rapid ventricular response. Reversible (upon discontinuation of verapamil) non-obstructive, paralytic ileus has been infrequently reported in association with the use of verapamil.



 The following reactions (  Table 1  ) to orally administered Verelan PM occurred at rates of 2.0% or greater or occurred at lower rates but appeared to be drug-related in clinical trials in hypertension.



 Table 1. Adverse Events Occurring in &gt;= 2% of Verelan PM Patients in Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials 
                       All Doses StudiedN = 297%  PlaceboN = 116%                        All Doses StudiedN = 297%  PlaceboN = 116%   
  
 Headache                   12.1             11.2        Dyspepsia                   2.7              1.7         
 Infection                  12.1              6.9        Rhinitis                    2.7              2.6         
 Constipation                8.8              0.9        Diarrhea                    2.4              1.7         
 Flu Syndrome                3.7              2.6        Pain                        2.4              1.7         
 Peripheral edema            3.7              0.9        Edema                       1.7              0.0         
 Dizziness                   3.0              0.9        Nausea                      1.7              0.0         
 Pharyngitis                 3.0              2.6        Accidental Injury           1.5              0.0         
 Sinusitis                   3.0              2.6                                                                 
            In previous experience with other formulations of verapamil (N=4,954) the following reactions (  Table 2  ) have occurred at rates greater than 1.0% or occurred at lower rates but appeared clearly drug related in clinical trials in 4,954 patients.
 

 Table 2. Adverse Events Occurring in &gt;1% (or lower rates and clearly drug related) of Patients with Other Verapamil Formulations 
 Constipation                            7.3%          Fatigue                                 1.7%           
 Dizziness                               3.3%          Bradycardia (HR&lt;50/min)                 1.4%           
 Nausea                                  2.7%          Rash                                    1.2%           
 Hypotension                             2.5%          AV block (total 1o, 2o, 3o)             1.2%           
 Headache                                2.2%          AV block (2o and 3o)                    0.8%           
 Edema                                   1.9%          Flushing                                0.6%           
 CHF/Pulmonary Edema                     1.8%                                                                 
          In clinical trials related to the control of ventricular response in patients taking digoxin who had atrial fibrillation or atrial flutter, ventricular rate below 50/min at rest occurred in 15% of patients and asymptomatic hypotension occurred in 5% of patients.
 

   6.2 Open Trials / Postmarketing Experience

  The following reactions, reported with orally administered verapamil in 2.0% or less of patients, occurred under conditions (open verapamil trials, postmarketing experience [reactions added since the initial US approval of Verelan PM in 1998 are marked with an asterisk]) where a causal relationship is uncertain; they are listed to alert the physician to a possible relationship:



   Cardiovascular:  angina pectoris, atrioventricular dissociation, ECG Abnormal*, chest pain, claudication, hypertension*, myocardial infarction, palpitations, purpura (vasculitis), syncope.



   Digestive System:  diarrhea, dry mouth, elevated liver enzymes* [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.3)    ], gastrointestinal distress, gingival hyperplasia.



   Hemic and Lymphatic:  ecchymosis or bruising.



   Nervous System:  cerebrovascular accident, confusion, equilibrium disorders, extrapyramidal symptoms, insomnia, muscle cramps, paresthesia, psychotic symptoms, shakiness, somnolence.



   Respiratory:  dyspnea.



   Skin:  arthralgia and rash, exanthema, hair loss, hyperkeratosis, macules, sweating, urticaria, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, erythema multiforme.



   Special Senses:  blurred vision, tinnitus.



   Urogenital:  gynecomastia, galactorrhea/hyperprolactinemia, impotence, increased urination, spotty menstruation.



   Other:  allergy aggravated, asthenia*.



   6.3 Treatment of Acute Cardiovascular Adverse Reactions

  The frequency of cardiovascular adverse reactions that require therapy is rare; hence, experience with their treatment is limited. Whenever severe hypotension or complete AV block occurs following oral administration of verapamil, apply the appropriate emergency measures immediately; e.g., intravenously administered norepinephrine bitartrate, atropine sulfate, isoproterenol HCl (all in the usual doses), or calcium gluconate (10% solution). In patients with hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, use alpha-adrenergic agents (phenylephrine HCl, metaraminol bitartrate, or methoxamine HCl) to maintain blood pressure, and isoproterenol and avoid norepinephrine. If further support is necessary, inotropic agents (dopamine HCl or dobutamine HCl) may be administered. Actual treatment and dosage depends on the severity of the clinical situation and the judgment and experience of the treating physician.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Congestive heart failure or pulmonary edema may develop (  5.1  ) 
 *  Hypotension/dizziness may occur (  5.2  ) 
 *  Elevated transaminases have occurred; monitor liver function (  5.3  ) 
 *  Ventricular fibrillation has occurred in patients with atrial flutter or atrial fibrillation and an accessory bypass tract (  5.4  ) 
 *  Reduce dose or discontinue therapy if marked first-degree AV block or progression to second- or third-degree AV block occurs (  5.5  ) 
 *  Sinus bradycardia, pulmonary edema, severe hypotension, second-degree AV block, sinus arrest and death occurred in patients with hypertrophic cardiomyopathy (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Heart Failure



  Verapamil has a negative inotropic effect which, in most patients, is compensated by its afterload reduction (decreased systemic vascular resistance) properties without a net impairment of ventricular performance. In previous clinical experience with 4,954 patients primarily with immediate-release verapamil, 87 (1.8%) developed congestive heart failure or pulmonary edema. Avoid verapamil in patients with severe left ventricular dysfunction (e.g., ejection fraction less than 30% or moderate to severe symptoms of cardiac failure) and in patients with any degree of ventricular dysfunction if they are receiving a beta-adrenergic blocker [see   Drug Interactions (7.4)    ]. Control patients with milder ventricular dysfunction, if possible, with optimum doses of digitalis and/or diuretics before verapamil treatment is started [see   Drug Interactions (7.5)    ].



    5.2 Hypotension



  Occasionally, the pharmacologic action of verapamil may produce a decrease in blood pressure below normal levels which may result in dizziness or symptomatic hypotension. In hypertensive patients, decreases in blood pressure below normal are unusual. The incidence of hypotension observed in 4,954 patients enrolled in clinical trials of other verapamil formulations was 2.5% [see   Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ]. In clinical studies of Verelan PM, 1.7% of the patients developed significant hypotension. Tilt table testing (60 degrees) was not able to induce orthostatic hypotension.



    5.3 Elevated Liver Enzymes



  Elevations of transaminases with and without concomitant elevations in alkaline phosphatase and bilirubin have been reported. Such elevations have sometimes been transient and may disappear even in the face of continued verapamil treatment.



 Several cases of hepatocellular injury related to verapamil have been proven by rechallenge; half of these had clinical symptoms (malaise, fever, and/or right upper quadrant pain) in addition to elevations of SGOT, SGPT and alkaline phosphatase. Periodic monitoring of liver function in patients receiving verapamil is therefore prudent.



    5.4 Accessory Bypass Tract (Wolff-Parkinson-White or Lown-Ganong Levine)



  Some patients with paroxysmal and/or chronic atrial flutter or atrial fibrillation and a coexisting accessory AV pathway have developed increased antegrade conduction across the accessory pathway bypassing the AV node, producing a very rapid ventricular response or ventricular fibrillation after receiving intravenous verapamil (or digitalis). Although a risk of this occurring with oral verapamil has not been established, such patients receiving oral verapamil may be at risk and its use in these patients is contraindicated [see   Contraindications (4)    ]. Treatment is usually DC-cardioversion. Cardioversion has been used safely and effectively after oral verapamil.



    5.5 Atrioventricular Block



  The effect of verapamil on AV conduction and the SA node may lead to asymptomatic first-degree AV block and transient bradycardia, sometimes accompanied by nodal escape rhythms. PR interval prolongation is correlated with verapamil plasma concentrations, especially during the early titration phase of therapy. Higher degrees of AV block, however, were infrequently (0.8%) observed in previous verapamil clinical trials [see   Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ].



 Marked first-degree block or progressive development to second- or third-degree AV block requires a reduction in dosage or, in rare instances, discontinuation of verapamil and institution of appropriate therapy depending upon the clinical situation.



    5.6 Patients with Hypertrophic Cardiomyopathy



  In 120 patients with hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, idiopathic hypertrophic subaortic stenosis (IHSS) (most of them refractory or intolerant to propranolol) who received therapy with verapamil at doses up to 720 mg/day, a variety of serious adverse effects were seen. Three patients died in pulmonary edema; all had severe left ventricular outflow obstruction and a history of left ventricular dysfunction. Eight other patients had pulmonary edema and/or severe hypotension; abnormally high (over 20 mm Hg) pulmonary capillary wedge pressure and a marked left ventricular outflow obstruction were present in most of these patients. Concomitant administration of quinidine [see   Drug Interactions (7.10)    ] preceded the severe hypotension in 3 of the 8 patients (2 of whom developed pulmonary edema). Sinus bradycardia occurred in 11% of the patients, second-degree AV block in 4% and sinus arrest in 2% [see   Adverse Reactions (6)    ]. It must be appreciated that this group of patients had a serious disease with a high mortality rate. Most adverse effects responded well to dose reduction and only rarely did verapamil have to be discontinued.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
