<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="veregen" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In Phase 3 clinical trials, a total of 397 subjects received Veregen  (r)  three times per day topical application for the treatment of external genital and perianal warts for up to 16 weeks.



 Serious local adverse events of pain and inflammation were reported in two subjects (0.5%), both women.



 In clinical trials, the incidence of patients with local adverse events leading to discontinuation or dose interruption (reduction) was 5% (19/397). These included the following events: application site reactions (local pain, erythema, vesicles, skin erosion/ulceration), phimosis, inguinal lymphadenitis, urethral meatal stenosis, dysuria, genital herpes simplex, vulvitis, hypersensitivity, pruritus, pyodermitis, skin ulcer, erosions in the urethral meatus, and superinfection of warts and ulcers.



 Local and regional reactions (including adenopathy) occurring at &gt;1% in the treated groups are presented in Table 1.



 Table 1: Local and Regional Adverse Reactions During Treatment (% Subjects) 
                            Veregen  (r)    (N = 397)    Vehicle  (N = 207)          
 Erythema                   70                         32                          
 Pruritus                   69                         45                          
 Burning                    67                         31                          
 Pain/discomfort            56                         14                          
 Erosion/Ulceration         49                         10                          
 Edema                      45                         11                          
 Induration                 35                         11                          
 Rash vesicular             20                         6                           
 Regional Lymphadenitis     3                          1                           
 Desquamation               5                          &lt;1                          
 Discharge                  3                          &lt;1                          
 Bleeding                   2                          &lt;1                          
 Reaction                   2                          0                           
 Scar                       1                          0                           
 Irritation                 1                          0                           
 Rash                       1                          0                           
      A total of 266/397 (67%) of subjects in the Veregen  (r)  group had either a moderate or a severe reaction that was considered probably related to the drug, of which 120 (30%) subjects had a severe reaction. Severe reactions occurred in 37% (71/192) of women and in 24% (49/205) of men. The percentage of subjects with at least one severe, related adverse event was 26% (86/328) for subjects with genital warts only, 42% (19/45) in subjects with both genital and perianal warts and 48% (11/23) of subjects with perianal warts only.
 

 Phimosis occurred in 3% of uncircumcised male subjects (5/174) treated with Veregen  (r)  and in 1% (1/99) in vehicle.



 The maximum mean severity of erythema, erosion, edema, and induration was observed by week 2 of treatment.



 Less common local adverse events included urethritis, perianal infection, pigmentation changes, dryness, eczema, hyperesthesia, necrosis, papules, and discoloration. Other less common adverse events included cervical dysplasia, pelvic pain, cutaneous facial rash, and staphylococcemia.



 In a dermal sensitization study of Veregen  (r)  in healthy volunteers, hypersensitivity (type IV) was observed in 5 out of 209 subjects (2.4%) under occlusive conditions.



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions are local skin and application site reactions including (incidence &gt;= 20%) erythema, pruritus, burning, pain/discomfort, erosion/ulceration, edema, induration, and rash vesicular  (6)  .



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact PharmaDerm  (r)  , A Division of Fougera Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-800-645-9833 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  Veregen  (r)  has not been evaluated for the treatment of urethral, intra-vaginal, cervical, rectal, or intra-anal human papilloma viral disease and should not be used for the treatment of these conditions.



 Use of Veregen  (r)  on open wounds should be avoided.



 Patients should be advised to avoid exposure of the genital and perianal area to sun/UV-light as Veregen  (r)  has not been tested under these circumstances.



    EXCERPT:    *  Veregen  (r)  should not be used to treat urethral, intra-vaginal, cervical, rectal, or intra-anal human papilloma viral disease  (5)  . 
 *  Use of Veregen  (r)  on open wounds should be avoided  (5)  . 
 *  Avoid exposure of Veregen  (r)  treated areas to sun/UV-light as Veregen  (r)  has not been tested under these circumstances  (5)  . 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
