<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="vesicare" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (&gt; 4% and &gt; placebo) were dry mouth, and constipation at both 5 mg and 10 mg doses; and urinary tract infection, and blurred vision at the 10 mg dose ( )  6.1    To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Astellas Pharma US, Inc at 1-800-727-7003 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or .  http://www.fda.gov/medwatch    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 VESIcare has been evaluated for safety in 1811 patients in randomized, placebo-controlled trials. Expected adverse reactions of antimuscarinic agents are dry mouth, constipation, blurred vision (accommodation abnormalities), urinary retention, and dry eyes. The incidence of dry mouth and constipation in patients treated with VESIcare was higher in the 10 mg compared to the 5 mg dose group.



 In the four 12-week double-blind clinical trials, severe fecal impaction, colonic obstruction, and intestinal obstruction were reported in one patient each, all in the VESIcare 10 mg group. Angioneurotic edema has been reported in one patient taking VESIcare 5 mg. Compared to 12 weeks of treatment with VESIcare, the incidence and severity of adverse reactions were similar in patients who remained on drug for up to 12 months.



 The most frequent adverse reaction leading to study discontinuation was dry mouth (1.5%). lists the rates of identified adverse reactions, derived from all reported adverse events, in randomized, placebo-controlled trials at an incidence greater than placebo and in 1% or more of patients treated with VESIcare 5 or 10 mg once daily for up to 12 weeks.  Table 1  



 Table 1. Percentages of Patients with Identified Adverse Reactions, Derived from All Adverse Events Exceeding Placebo Rate and Reported by 1% or More Patients for Combined Pivotal Studies 
                                                                      Placebo    (%)      VESIcare    5 mg    (%)      VESIcare    10 mg    (%)     
  
  Number of Patients                                                 1216           578           1233          
  GASTROINTESTINAL DISORDERS                                                                                    
       Dry Mouth                                                     4.2            10.9          27.6          
       Constipation                                                  2.9            5.4           13.4          
       Nausea                                                        2.0            1.7           3.3           
       Dyspepsia                                                     1.0            1.4           3.9           
       Abdominal Pain Upper                                          1.0            1.9           1.2           
       Vomiting NOS                                                  0.9            0.2           1.1           
  INFECTIONS AND INFESTATIONS                                                                                   
       Urinary Tract Infection NOS                                   2.8            2.8           4.8           
       Influenza                                                     1.3            2.2           0.9           
       Pharyngitis NOS                                               1.0            0.3           1.1           
  NERVOUS SYSTEM DISORDERS                                                                                      
       Dizziness                                                     1.8            1.9           1.8           
  EYE DISORDERS                                                                                                 
       Vision Blurred                                                1.8            3.8           4.8           
       Dry Eyes NOS                                                  0.6            0.3           1.6           
  RENAL AND URINARY DISORDERS                                                                                   
       Urinary Retention                                             0.6            0             1.4           
  GENERAL DISORDERS AND ADMINISTRATION SITE CONDITIONS                                                          
       Edema Lower Limb                                              0.7            0.3           1.1           
       Fatigue                                                       1.1            1.0           2.1           
  PSYCHIATRIC DISORDERS                                                                                         
       Depression NOS                                                0.8            1.2           0.8           
  RESPIRATORY, THORACIC AND MEDIASTINAL DISORDERS                                                               
      Cough                                                          0.2            0.2           1.1           
  VASCULAR DISORDERS                                                                                            
      Hypertension NOS                                               0.6            1.4           0.5           
            6.2 Post-Marketing Experience
   Because these spontaneously reported events are from the worldwide postmarketing experience, the frequency of events and the role of solifenacin in their causation cannot be reliably determined.



 The following events have been reported in association with solifenacin use in worldwide postmarketing experience:



 : peripheral edema, hypersensitivity reactions, including angioedema with airway obstruction, rash, pruritus, urticaria, and anaphylactic reaction;    General    



 : headache, confusion, hallucinations, delirium and somnolence;    Central Nervous    



 : QT prolongation; Torsade de Pointes, atrial fibrillation, tachycardia, palpitations;    Cardiovascular    



 : liver disorders mostly characterized by abnormal liver function tests, AST (aspartate aminotransferase), ALT (alanine aminotransferase), GGT (gamma-glutamyl transferase);    Hepatic    



 : renal impairment;    Renal    



 : decreased appetite, hyperkalemia;    Metabolism and nutrition disorders    



 : exfoliative dermatitis and erythema multiforme;    Dermatologic    



 glaucoma;  :  Eye disorders        



 gastroesophageal reflux disease and ileus;  :  Gastrointestinal disorders        



 dysphonia;  :  Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders    



 muscular weakness;  :  Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders    
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Angioedema and anaphylactic reactions: Reports of angioedema of the face, lips and/or larynx, in some cases occurring after the first dose, have been described. Anaphylactic reactions have been reported rarely ( )  5.1   
 *    Urinary Retention: Administer with caution to patients with clinically significant bladder outflow obstruction ( )  5.2   
 *    Gastrointestinal Disorders: Use with caution in patients with decreased gastrointestinal motility ( )  5.3   
 *    Central Nervous System Effects: Somnolence has been reported with VESIcare. Advise patients not to drive or operate heavy machinery until they know how VESIcare affects them ( )  5.4   
 *    Controlled Narrow-Angle Glaucoma: Use with caution in patients being treated for narrow-angle glaucoma ( )  5.5   
 *    QT Prolongation: Use with caution in patients with a known history of QT prolongation or patients who are taking medications known to prolong the QT interval ( )  5.8   
    
 

   5.1 Angioedema and Anaphylactic Reactions



  Angioedema of the face, lips, tongue, and/or larynx have been reported with solifenacin. In some cases angioedema occurred after the first dose. Cases of angioedema have been reported to occur hours after the first dose or after multiple doses. Angioedema associated with upper airway swelling may be life threatening. If involvement of the tongue, hypopharynx, or larynx occurs, solifenacin should be promptly discontinued and appropriate therapy and/or measures necessary to ensure a patent airway should be promptly provided.  Anaphylactic reactions have been reported rarely in patients treated with solifenacin succinate. Solifenacin succinate should not be used in patients with a known or suspected hypersensitivity to solifenacin succinate. In patients who develop anaphylactic reactions, solifenacin succinate should be discontinued and appropriate therapy and/or measures should be taken.



    5.2 Urinary Retention



  VESIcare, like other anticholinergic drugs, should be administered with caution to patients with clinically significant bladder outflow obstruction because of the risk of urinary retention [ ]. see ( )  Contraindications    4    



    5.3 Gastrointestinal Disorders



  VESIcare, like other anticholinergics, should be used with caution in patients with decreased gastrointestinal motility [ ]. see ( )  Contraindications    4    



    5.4 Central Nervous System Effects



  VESIcare is associated with anticholinergic central nervous system (CNS) effects [ ]. A variety of CNS anticholinergic effects have been reported, including headache, confusion, hallucinations and somnolence. Patients should be monitored for signs of anticholinergic CNS effects, particularly after beginning treatment or increasing the dose. Advise patients not to drive or operate heavy machinery until they know how VESIcare affects them. If a patient experiences anticholinergic CNS effects, dose reduction or drug discontinuation should be considered. see ( )  Adverse Reactions    6.2    



    5.5 Controlled Narrow-Angle Glaucoma



  VESIcare should be used with caution in patients being treated for narrow-angle glaucoma [ ]. see ( )  Contraindications    4    



    5.6 Hepatic Impairment



  VESIcare should be used with caution in patients with hepatic impairment. Doses of VESIcare greater than 5 mg are not recommended in patients with moderate hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh B). VESIcare is not recommended for patients with severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh C) [ ]. see ( ) and ( )  Dosage and Administration    2.3    Use in Specific Populations    8.7    



    5.7 Renal Impairment



  VESIcare should be used with caution in patients with renal impairment. Doses of VESIcare greater than 5 mg are not recommended in patients with severe renal impairment (CL &lt;30 mL/min) [ ].cr see ( ) and ( )  Dosage and Administration    2.2    Use in Specific Populations    8.6    



    5.8 Patients with Congenital or Acquired QT Prolongation



  In a study of the effect of solifenacin on the QT interval in 76 healthy women [ ] the QT prolonging effect appeared less with solifenacin 10 mg than with 30 mg (three times the maximum recommended dose), and the effect of solifenacin 30 mg did not appear as large as that of the positive control moxifloxacin at its therapeutic dose. This observation should be considered in clinical decisions to prescribe VESIcare for patients with a known history of QT prolongation or patients who are taking medications known to prolong the QT interval. see ( )  Clinical Pharmacology    12.2    
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
