<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="vfend1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=2%): visual disturbances, fever, nausea, rash, vomiting, chills, headache, liver function test abnormal, tachycardia, hallucinations (  6  )  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer Inc at 1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    



 

  6.1 Overview

  The most frequently reported adverse events (all causalities) in the therapeutic trials were visual disturbances (18.7%), fever (5.7%), nausea (5.4%), rash (5.3%), vomiting (4.4%), chills (3.7%), headache (3.0%), liver function test increased (2.7%), tachycardia (2.4%), hallucinations (2.4%). The treatment-related adverse events which most often led to discontinuation of voriconazole therapy were elevated liver function tests, rash, and visual disturbances  [see  Warning and Precautions (5.2  ,  5.3)  and  Adverse Reactions (6.2  ,  6.3)  ]  .



   6.2 Clinical Trial Experience in Adults

  The data described in Table 3 reflect exposure to voriconazole in 1655 patients in the therapeutic studies. This represents a heterogeneous population, including immunocompromised patients, e.g., patients with hematological malignancy or HIV and non-neutropenic patients. This subgroup does not include healthy subjects and patients treated in the compassionate use and non-therapeutic studies. This patient population was 62% male, had a mean age of 46 years (range 11-90, including 51 patients aged 12-18 years), and was 78% White and 10% Black. Five hundred sixty one patients had a duration of voriconazole therapy of greater than 12 weeks, with 136 patients receiving voriconazole for over six months. Table 3 includes all adverse events which were reported at an incidence of &gt;=2% during voriconazole therapy in the all therapeutic studies population, studies 307/602 and 608 combined, or study 305, as well as events of concern which occurred at an incidence of &lt;2%.



 In study 307/602, 381 patients (196 on voriconazole, 185 on amphotericin B) were treated to compare voriconazole to amphotericin B followed by other licensed antifungal therapy in the primary treatment of patients with acute invasive aspergillosis. The rate of discontinuation from voriconazole study medication due to adverse events was 21.4% (42/196 patients). In study 608, 403 patients with candidemia were treated to compare voriconazole (272 patients) to the regimen of amphotericin B followed by fluconazole (131 patients). The rate of discontinuation from voriconazole study medication due to adverse events was 19.5% out of 272 patients. Study 305 evaluated the effects of oral voriconazole (200 patients) and oral fluconazole (191 patients) in the treatment of esophageal candidiasis. The rate of discontinuation from voriconazole study medication in Study 305 due to adverse events was 7% (14/200 patients). Laboratory test abnormalities for these studies are discussed under Clinical Laboratory Values below.



 Table 3: Treatment Emergent Adverse Events Rate &gt;= 2% on Voriconazole or Adverse Events of Concern in All Therapeutic Studies Population, Studies 307/602-608 Combined, or Study 305. Possibly Related to Therapy or Causality UnknownStudy 307/602: invasive aspergillosis; Study 608: candidemia; Study 305: esophageal candidiasis 
                  All Therapeutic Studies  Studies 307/602 and 608(IV/ oral therapy)  Study 305(oral therapy)   
 VoriconazoleN=1655  VoriconazoleN=468   Ampho BN=185   Ampho B-&gt; FluconazoleN=131  VoriconazoleN=200  FluconazoleN=191   
                      N (%)           N (%)           N (%)            N (%)           N (%)           N (%)        
  
                                                                                                                    
   Special Senses                                                                                                      
 Abnormal vision    310 (18.7)      63 (13.5)        1 (0.5)             0           31 (15.5)        8 (4.2)       
 Photophobia         37 (2.2)        8 (1.7)            0                0            5 (2.5)         2 (1.0)       
 Chromatopsia        20 (1.2)        2 (0.4)            0                0            2 (1.0)            0          
                                                                                                                    
   Body as a Whole                                                                                                      
 Fever               94 (5.7)        8 (1.7)        25 (13.5)         5 (3.8)            0               0          
 Chills              61 (3.7)        1 (0.2)        36 (19.5)         8 (6.1)         1 (0.5)            0          
 Headache            49 (3.0)        9 (1.9)         8 (4.3)          1 (0.8)            0            1 (0.5)       
                                                                                                                    
   Cardiovascular System                                                                                                      
 Tachycardia         39 (2.4)        6 (1.3)         5 (2.7)             0               0               0          
                                                                                                                    
   Digestive System                                                                                                      
 Nausea              89 (5.4)        18 (3.8)       29 (15.7)         2 (1.5)         2 (1.0)         3 (1.6)       
 Vomiting            72 (4.4)        15 (3.2)        18 (9.7)         1 (0.8)         2 (1.0)         1 (0.5)       
 Liver function tests abnormal     45 (2.7)        15 (3.2)        4 (2.2)          1 (0.8)         6 (3.0)         2 (1.0)       
 Cholestatic jaundice     17 (1.0)        8 (1.7)            0             1 (0.8)         3 (1.5)            0          
                                                                                                                    
   Metabolic and Nutritional Systems                                                                                                      
 Alkaline phosphatase increased     59 (3.6)        19 (4.1)        4 (2.2)          3 (2.3)         10 (5.0)        3 (1.6)       
 Hepatic enzymes increased     30 (1.8)        11 (2.4)        5 (2.7)          1 (0.8)         3 (1.5)            0          
 SGOT increased      31 (1.9)        9 (1.9)            0             1 (0.8)         8 (4.0)         2 (1.0)       
 SGPT increased      29 (1.8)        9 (1.9)         1 (0.5)          2 (1.5)         6 (3.0)         2 (1.0)       
 Hypokalemia         26 (1.6)        3 (0.6)        36 (19.5)        16 (12.2)           0               0          
 Bilirubinemia       15 (0.9)        5 (1.1)         3 (1.6)          2 (1.5)         1 (0.5)            0          
 Creatinine increased     4 (0.2)            0           59 (31.9)        10 (7.6)         1 (0.5)            0          
                                                                                                                    
   Nervous System                                                                                                      
 Hallucinations      39 (2.4)        13 (2.8)        1 (0.5)             0               0               0          
                                                                                                                    
   Skin and Appendages                                                                                                      
 Rash                88 (5.3)        20 (4.3)        7 (3.8)          1 (0.8)         3 (1.5)         1 (0.5)       
                                                                                                                    
   Urogenital                                                                                                       
 Kidney function abnormal     10 (0.6)        6 (1.3)        40 (21.6)         9 (6.9)         1 (0.5)         1 (0.5)       
 Acute kidney failure     7 (0.4)         2 (0.4)         11 (5.9)         7 (5.3)            0               0          
                 Visual Disturbances  
 

 Voriconazole treatment-related visual disturbances are common. In therapeutic trials, approximately 21% of patients experienced abnormal vision, color vision change and/or photophobia. Visual disturbances may be associated with higher plasma concentrations and/or doses.



 There have been post-marketing reports of prolonged visual adverse events, including optic neuritis and papilledema  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  .



 The mechanism of action of the visual disturbance is unknown, although the site of action is most likely to be within the retina. In a study in healthy subjects investigating the effect of 28-day treatment with voriconazole on retinal function, voriconazole caused a decrease in the electroretinogram (ERG) waveform amplitude, a decrease in the visual field, and an alteration in color perception. The ERG measures electrical currents in the retina. The effects were noted early in administration of voriconazole and continued through the course of study drug dosing. Fourteen days after end of dosing, ERG, visual fields and color perception returned to normal  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  .



     Dermatological Reactions  



 Dermatological reactions were common in the patients treated with voriconazole. The mechanism underlying these dermatologic adverse events remains unknown.



 Serious cutaneous reactions, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis and erythema multiforme have been reported during treatment with VFEND. If a patient develops an exfoliative cutaneous reaction, VFEND should be discontinued.



 In addition, VFEND has been associated with photosensitivity skin reactions. Patients should avoid strong, direct sunlight during VFEND therapy. In patients with photosensitivity skin reactions, squamous cell carcinoma of the skin and melanoma have been reported during long-term therapy. If a patient develops a skin lesion consistent with squamous cell carcinoma or melanoma, VFEND should be discontinued  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.12)  ]  .



     Less Common Adverse Events  



 The following adverse events occurred in &lt;2% of all voriconazole-treated patients in all therapeutic studies (N=1655). This listing includes events where a causal relationship to voriconazole cannot be ruled out or those which may help the physician in managing the risks to the patients. The list does not include events included in Table 5 above and does not include every event reported in the voriconazole clinical program.



   Body as a Whole:  abdominal pain, abdomen enlarged, allergic reaction, anaphylactoid reaction  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  , ascites, asthenia, back pain, chest pain, cellulitis, edema, face edema, flank pain, flu syndrome, graft versus host reaction, granuloma, infection, bacterial infection, fungal infection, injection site pain, injection site infection/inflammation, mucous membrane disorder, multi-organ failure, pain, pelvic pain, peritonitis, sepsis, substernal chest pain.



   Cardiovascular:  atrial arrhythmia, atrial fibrillation, AV block complete, bigeminy, bradycardia, bundle branch block, cardiomegaly, cardiomyopathy, cerebral hemorrhage, cerebral ischemia, cerebrovascular accident, congestive heart failure, deep thrombophlebitis, endocarditis, extrasystoles, heart arrest, hypertension, hypotension, myocardial infarction, nodal arrhythmia, palpitation, phlebitis, postural hypotension, pulmonary embolus, QT interval prolonged, supraventricular extrasystoles, supraventricular tachycardia, syncope, thrombophlebitis, vasodilatation, ventricular arrhythmia, ventricular fibrillation, ventricular tachycardia (including torsade de pointes)  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  .



   Digestive:  anorexia, cheilitis, cholecystitis, cholelithiasis, constipation, diarrhea, duodenal ulcer perforation, duodenitis, dyspepsia, dysphagia, dry mouth, esophageal ulcer, esophagitis, flatulence, gastroenteritis, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, GGT/LDH elevated, gingivitis, glossitis, gum hemorrhage, gum hyperplasia, hematemesis, hepatic coma, hepatic failure, hepatitis, intestinal perforation, intestinal ulcer, jaundice, enlarged liver, melena, mouth ulceration, pancreatitis, parotid gland enlargement, periodontitis, proctitis, pseudomembranous colitis, rectal disorder, rectal hemorrhage, stomach ulcer, stomatitis, tongue edema.



   Endocrine:  adrenal cortex insufficiency, diabetes insipidus, hyperthyroidism, hypothyroidism.



   Hemic and Lymphatic:  agranulocytosis, anemia (macrocytic, megaloblastic, microcytic, normocytic), aplastic anemia, hemolytic anemia, bleeding time increased, cyanosis, DIC, ecchymosis, eosinophilia, hypervolemia, leukopenia, lymphadenopathy, lymphangitis, marrow depression, pancytopenia, petechia, purpura, enlarged spleen, thrombocytopenia, thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura.



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  albuminuria, BUN increased, creatine phosphokinase increased, edema, glucose tolerance decreased, hypercalcemia, hypercholesteremia, hyperglycemia, hyperkalemia, hypermagnesemia, hypernatremia, hyperuricemia, hypocalcemia, hypoglycemia, hypomagnesemia, hyponatremia, hypophosphatemia, peripheral edema, uremia.



   Musculoskeletal:  arthralgia, arthritis, bone necrosis, bone pain, leg cramps, myalgia, myasthenia, myopathy, osteomalacia, osteoporosis.



   Nervous System:  abnormal dreams, acute brain syndrome, agitation, akathisia, amnesia, anxiety, ataxia, brain edema, coma, confusion, convulsion, delirium, dementia, depersonalization, depression, diplopia, dizziness, encephalitis, encephalopathy, euphoria, Extrapyramidal Syndrome, grand mal convulsion, Guillain-Barre syndrome, hypertonia, hypesthesia, insomnia, intracranial hypertension, libido decreased, neuralgia, neuropathy, nystagmus, oculogyric crisis, paresthesia, psychosis, somnolence, suicidal ideation, tremor, vertigo.



   Respiratory System:  cough increased, dyspnea, epistaxis, hemoptysis, hypoxia, lung edema, pharyngitis, pleural effusion, pneumonia, respiratory disorder, respiratory distress syndrome, respiratory tract infection, rhinitis, sinusitis, voice alteration.



   Skin and Appendages:  alopecia, angioedema, contact dermatitis, discoid lupus erythematosis, eczema, erythema multiforme, exfoliative dermatitis, fixed drug eruption, furunculosis, herpes simplex, maculopapular rash, melanoma, melanosis, photosensitivity skin reaction, pruritus, pseudoporphyria, psoriasis, skin discoloration, skin disorder, skin dry, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, squamous cell carcinoma, sweating, toxic epidermal necrolysis, urticaria.



   Special Senses:  abnormality of accommodation, blepharitis, color blindness, conjunctivitis, corneal opacity, deafness, ear pain, eye pain, eye hemorrhage, dry eyes, hypoacusis, keratitis, keratoconjunctivitis, mydriasis, night blindness, optic atrophy, optic neuritis, otitis externa, papilledema, retinal hemorrhage, retinitis, scleritis, taste loss, taste perversion, tinnitus, uveitis, visual field defect.



   Urogenital:  anuria, blighted ovum, creatinine clearance decreased, dysmenorrhea, dysuria, epididymitis, glycosuria, hemorrhagic cystitis, hematuria, hydronephrosis, impotence, kidney pain, kidney tubular necrosis, metrorrhagia, nephritis, nephrosis, oliguria, scrotal edema, urinary incontinence, urinary retention, urinary tract infection, uterine hemorrhage, vaginal hemorrhage.



   6.3 Clinical Laboratory Values

  The overall incidence of clinically significant transaminase abnormalities in all therapeutic studies was 12.4% (206/1655) of patients treated with voriconazole. Increased incidence of liver function test abnormalities may be associated with higher plasma concentrations and/or doses. The majority of abnormal liver function tests either resolved during treatment without dose adjustment or following dose adjustment, including discontinuation of therapy.



 Voriconazole has been infrequently associated with cases of serious hepatic toxicity including cases of jaundice and rare cases of hepatitis and hepatic failure leading to death. Most of these patients had other serious underlying conditions.



 Liver function tests should be evaluated at the start of and during the course of VFEND therapy. Patients who develop abnormal liver function tests during VFEND therapy should be monitored for the development of more severe hepatic injury. Patient management should include laboratory evaluation of hepatic function (particularly liver function tests and bilirubin). Discontinuation of VFEND must be considered if clinical signs and symptoms consistent with liver disease develop that may be attributable to VFEND  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  .



 Acute renal failure has been observed in severely ill patients undergoing treatment with VFEND. Patients being treated with voriconazole are likely to be treated concomitantly with nephrotoxic medications and have concurrent conditions that may result in decreased renal function. It is recommended that patients are monitored for the development of abnormal renal function. This should include laboratory evaluation, particularly serum creatinine.



 Tables 4 to 6 show the number of patients with hypokalemia and clinically significant changes in renal and liver function tests in three randomized, comparative multicenter studies. In study 305, patients with esophageal candidiasis were randomized to either oral voriconazole or oral fluconazole. In study 307/602, patients with definite or probable invasive aspergillosis were randomized to either voriconazole or amphotericin B therapy. In study 608, patients with candidemia were randomized to either voriconazole or the regimen of amphotericin B followed by fluconazole.



 Table 4: Protocol 305 - Patients with Esophageal Candidiasis Clinically Significant Laboratory Test Abnormalities 
                                      Criteria             Voriconazole                Fluconazole            
                                                              n/N (%)                   n /N (%)              
  
 n = number of patients with a clinically significant abnormality while on study therapy   
 N = total number of patients with at least one observation of the given lab test while on study therapy   
 ULN = upper limit of normal     
  
                                                                                                              
 T. Bilirubin                         &gt;1.5* ULN             8/185 (4.3)                7/186 (3.8)            
 AST                                  &gt;3.0* ULN            38/187 (20.3)              15/186 (8.1)            
 ALT                                  &gt;3.0* ULN            20/187 (10.7)              12/186 (6.5)            
 Alk phos                             &gt;3.0* ULN            19/187 (10.2)              14/186 (7.5)            
         Table 5: Protocol 307/602 - Primary Treatment of Invasive Aspergillosis Clinically Significant Laboratory Test Abnormalities 
                            Criteria                  Voriconazole                   Amphotericin B           
                                                        n/N (%)                         n/N (%)               
  
 n = number of patients with a clinically significant abnormality while on study therapy   
 N = total number of patients with at least one observation of the given lab test while on study therapy   
 ULN = upper limit of normal   
 LLN = lower limit of normal   
  
                                                                                                              
 T. Bilirubin              &gt;1.5* ULN                 35/180 (19.4)                   46/173 (26.6)            
 AST                       &gt;3.0* ULN                 21/180 (11.7)                   18/174 (10.3)            
 ALT                       &gt;3.0* ULN                 34/180 (18.9)                   40/173 (23.1)            
 Alk phos                  &gt;3.0* ULN                 29/181 (16.0)                   38/173 (22.0)            
 Creatinine                &gt;1.3* ULN                 39/182 (21.4)                   102/177 (57.6)           
 Potassium                 &lt;0.9* LLN                 30/181 (16.6)                   70/178 (39.3)            
         Table 6: Protocol 608 - Treatment of Candidemia Clinically Significant Laboratory Test Abnormalities 
                            Criteria                  Voriconazole           Amphotericin B followed by Fluconazole   
                                                        n/N (%)                         n/N (%)               
  
 n = number of patients with a clinically significant abnormality while on study therapy   
 N = total number of patients with at least one observation of the given lab test while on study therapy   
 ULN = upper limit of normal   
 LLN = lower limit of normal   
  
                                                                                                              
 T. Bilirubin              &gt;1.5* ULN                 50/261 (19.2)                   31/115 (27.0)            
 AST                       &gt;3.0* ULN                 40/261 (15.3)                   16/116 (13.8)            
 ALT                       &gt;3.0* ULN                  22/261 (8.4)                   15/116 (12.9)            
 Alk phos                  &gt;3.0* ULN                 59/261 (22.6)                   26/115 (22.6)            
 Creatinine                &gt;1.3* ULN                 39/260 (15.0)                   32/118 (27.1)            
 Potassium                 &lt;0.9* LLN                 43/258 (16.7)                   35/118 (29.7)            
            6.4 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of voriconazole. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Skeletal  : fluorosis and periostitis have been reported during long-term voriconazole therapy  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.13)  ]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Clinically Significant Drug Interactions : Review patient's concomitant medications (  5.1  ,  7  ) 
 *   Hepatic Toxicity : Serious hepatic reactions reported. Evaluate liver function tests at start of and during voriconazole therapy (  5.2  ) 
 *   Visual Disturbances (including optic neuritis and papilledema): Monitor visual function if treatment continues beyond 28 days (  5.3  ) 
 *   Embryo-Fetal Toxicity : Do not administer to pregnant women unless the benefit to the mother outweighs the risk to the fetus. Inform pregnant patient of hazard (  5.4  ,  8.1  ) 
 *   Arrhythmias and QT Prolongation : Correct potassium, magnesium and calcium prior to use; caution patients with proarrhythmic conditions (  5.5  ) 
 *   Infusion Related Reactions (including anaphylaxis) : Stop the infusion (  5.6  ) 
 *   Dermatological Reactions : Discontinue for exfoliative cutaneous reactions or phototoxicity. Avoid sunlight due to risk of photosensitivity (  5.12  ) 
 *   Skeletal Events : Fluorosis and periostitis reported with long-term voriconazole therapy. Discontinue if these events occur (  5.13  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Drug Interactions



  See  Table 7  for a listing of drugs that may significantly alter voriconazole concentrations. Also, see  Table 8  for a listing of drugs that may interact with voriconazole resulting in altered pharmacokinetics or pharmacodynamics of the other drug [see  Contraindications (4)  and  Drug Interactions (7)  ]  .



    5.2 Hepatic Toxicity



   In clinical trials, there have been uncommon cases of serious hepatic reactions during treatment with VFEND (including clinical hepatitis, cholestasis and fulminant hepatic failure, including fatalities).  Instances of hepatic reactions were noted to occur primarily in patients with serious underlying medical conditions (predominantly hematological malignancy). Hepatic reactions, including hepatitis and jaundice, have occurred among patients with no other identifiable risk factors. Liver dysfunction has usually been reversible on discontinuation of therapy [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  and  Adverse Reactions (6.3)  ]  .



  Measure serum transaminase levels and bilirubin at the initiation of VFEND therapy and monitor at least weekly for the first month of treatment. Monitoring frequency can be reduced to monthly during continued use if no clinically significant changes are noted. If liver function tests become markedly elevated compared to baseline, VFEND should be discontinued unless the medical judgment of the benefit-risk of the treatment for the patient justifies continued use [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ,  Dosage and Administration (2.4  ,  2.6)  , and  Adverse Reactions (6.3)  ]  .  



    5.3 Visual Disturbances



   The effect of VFEND on visual function is not known if treatment continues beyond 28 days.  There have been post-marketing reports of prolonged visual adverse events, including optic neuritis and papilledema. If treatment continues beyond 28 days, visual function including visual acuity, visual field and color perception should be monitored [see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ]  .



    5.4 Embryo-Fetal Toxicity



  Voriconazole can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman.



 In animals, voriconazole administration was associated with teratogenicity, embryotoxicity, increased gestational length, dystocia and embryomortality. Please refer to section 8.1 (Use in Pregnancy) for additional details.



 If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be informed of the potential hazard to the fetus.



    5.5 Arrhythmias and QT Prolongation



  Some azoles, including voriconazole, have been associated with prolongation of the QT interval on the electrocardiogram. During clinical development and post-marketing surveillance, there have been rare cases of arrhythmias, (including ventricular arrhythmias such as torsade de pointes  ), cardiac arrests and sudden deaths in patients taking voriconazole. These cases usually involved seriously ill patients with multiple confounding risk factors, such as history of cardiotoxic chemotherapy, cardiomyopathy, hypokalemia and concomitant medications that may have been contributory.



  Voriconazole should be administered with caution to patients with potentially proarrhythmic conditions, such as:  



 *   Congenital or acquired QT-prolongation  
 *   Cardiomyopathy, in particular when heart failure is present  
 *   Sinus bradycardia  
 *   Existing symptomatic arrhythmias  
 *   Concomitant medicinal product that is known to prolong QT interval [see  Contraindications (4)  ,  Drug Interactions (7)  , and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]   
     Rigorous attempts to correct potassium, magnesium and calcium should be made before starting and during voriconazole therapy [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .  
 

    5.6 Infusion Related Reactions



  During infusion of the intravenous formulation of voriconazole in healthy subjects, anaphylactoid-type reactions, including flushing, fever, sweating, tachycardia, chest tightness, dyspnea, faintness, nausea, pruritus and rash, have occurred uncommonly. Symptoms appeared immediately upon initiating the infusion. Consideration should be given to stopping the infusion should these reactions occur.



    5.7 Laboratory Tests



  Electrolyte disturbances such as hypokalemia, hypomagnesemia and hypocalcemia should be corrected prior to initiation of and during VFEND therapy.



 Patient management should include laboratory evaluation of renal (particularly serum creatinine) and hepatic function (particularly liver function tests and bilirubin).



    5.8 Patients With Hepatic Impairment



  It is recommended that the standard loading dose regimens be used but that the maintenance dose be halved in patients with mild to moderate hepatic cirrhosis (Child-Pugh Class A and B) receiving VFEND [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  and  Dosage and Administration (2.6)  ]  .



 VFEND has not been studied in patients with severe cirrhosis (Child-Pugh Class C). VFEND has been associated with elevations in liver function tests and clinical signs of liver damage, such as jaundice, and should only be used in patients with severe hepatic insufficiency if the benefit outweighs the potential risk. Patients with hepatic insufficiency must be carefully monitored for drug toxicity.



    5.9 Patients With Renal Impairment



  In patients with moderate to severe renal dysfunction (creatinine clearance &lt;50 mL/min), accumulation of the intravenous vehicle, SBECD, occurs. Oral voriconazole should be administered to these patients, unless an assessment of the benefit/risk to the patient justifies the use of intravenous voriconazole. Serum creatinine levels should be closely monitored in these patients, and if increases occur, consideration should be given to changing to oral voriconazole therapy [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  and  Dosage and Administration (2.7)  ]  .



    5.10 Monitoring of Renal Function



  Acute renal failure has been observed in patients undergoing treatment with VFEND. Patients being treated with voriconazole are likely to be treated concomitantly with nephrotoxic medications and have concurrent conditions that may result in decreased renal function.



 Patients should be monitored for the development of abnormal renal function. This should include laboratory evaluation, particularly serum creatinine.



    5.11 Monitoring of Pancreatic Function



  Patients with risk factors for acute pancreatitis (e.g., recent chemotherapy, hematopoietic stem cell transplantation [HSCT]) should be monitored for the development of pancreatitis during VFEND treatment.



    5.12 Dermatological Reactions



  Serious exfoliative cutaneous reactions, such as Stevens-Johnson syndrome, have been reported during treatment with VFEND. If a patient develops an exfoliative cutaneous reaction, VFEND should be discontinued.



 VFEND has been associated with photosensitivity skin reaction. Patients, including children, should avoid exposure to direct sunlight during VFEND treatment and should use measures such as protective clothing and sunscreen with high sun protection factor (SPF). If phototoxic reactions occur, the patient should be referred to a dermatologist and VFEND discontinuation should be considered. If VFEND is continued despite the occurrence of phototoxicity-related lesions, dermatologic evaluation should be performed on a systematic and regular basis to allow early detection and management of premalignant lesions. Squamous cell carcinoma of the skin and melanoma have been reported during long-term VFEND therapy in patients with photosensitivity skin reactions. If a patient develops a skin lesion consistent with premalignant skin lesions, squamous cell carcinoma or melanoma, VFEND should be discontinued.



  The frequency of phototoxicity reactions is higher in the pediatric population. Because squamous cell carcinoma has been reported in patients who experience photosensitivity reactions, stringent measures for photoprotection are warranted in children. In children experiencing photoaging injuries such as lentigines or ephelides, sun avoidance and dermatologic follow-up are recommended even after treatment discontinuation.  



    5.13 Skeletal Adverse Events



  Fluorosis and periostitis have been reported during long-term voriconazole therapy. If a patient develops skeletal pain and radiologic findings compatible with fluorosis or periostitis, voriconazole should be discontinued [see  Adverse Reactions (6.4)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
