<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="vicoprofen" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  VICOPROFEN was administered to approximately 300 pain patients in a safety study that employed dosages and a duration of treatment sufficient to encompass the recommended usage (see  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION  ). Adverse event rates generally increased with increasing daily dose. The event rates reported below are from approximately 150 patients who were in a group that received one tablet of VICOPROFEN an average of three to four times daily. The overall incidence rates of adverse experiences in the trials were fairly similar for this patient group and those who received the comparison treatment, acetaminophen 600 mg with codeine 60 mg.



 The following lists adverse events that occurred with an incidence of 1% or greater in clinical trials of VICOPROFEN, without regard to the causal relationship of the events to the drug. To distinguish different rates of occurrence in clinical studies, the adverse events are listed as follows:



   name of adverse event = less than 3%  



   adverse events marked with an asterisk * = 3% to 9%  



   adverse event rates over 9% are in parentheses.  



   Body as a Whole

  Abdominal pain*; Asthenia*; Fever; Flu syndrome; Headache (27%); Infection*; Pain.



   Cardiovascular

  Palpitations; Vasodilation.



   Central Nervous System

  Anxiety*; Confusion; Dizziness (14%); Hypertonia; Insomnia*; Nervousness*; Paresthesia; Somnolence (22%); Thinking abnormalities.



   Digestive

  Anorexia; Constipation (22%); Diarrhea*; Dry mouth*; Dyspepsia (12%); Flatulence*; Gastritis; Melena; Mouth ulcers; Nausea (21%); Thirst; Vomiting*.



   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders

  Edema*.



   Respiratory

  Dyspnea; Hiccups; Pharyngitis; Rhinitis.



   Skin and Appendages

  Pruritus*; Sweating*.



   Special Senses

  Tinnitus.



   Urogenital

  Urinary frequency.



   Incidence less than 1%

  Body as a Whole

  Allergic reaction.



   Cardiovascular

  Arrhythmia; Hypotension; Tachycardia.



   Central Nervous System

  Agitation; Abnormal dreams; Decreased libido; Depression; Euphoria; Mood changes; Neuralgia; Slurred speech; Tremor, Vertigo.



   Digestive

  Chalky stool; "Clenching teeth"; Dysphagia; Esophageal spasm; Esophagitis; Gastroenteritis; Glossitis; Liver enzyme elevation.



   Metabolic and Nutritional

  Weight decrease.



   Musculoskeletal

  Arthralgia; Myalgia.



   Respiratory

  Asthma; Bronchitis; Hoarseness; Increased cough; Pulmonary congestion; Pneumonia; Shallow breathing; Sinusitis.



   Skin and Appendages

  Rash; Urticaria.



   Special Senses

  Altered vision; Bad taste; Dry eyes.



   Urogenital

  Cystitis; Glycosuria; Impotence; Urinary incontinence; Urinary retention.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
