<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="vidaza" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are described in other labeling sections:



 *  Anemia, neutropenia and thrombocytopenia [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ) ] 
 *  Hepatic coma [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  ) ] 
 *  Elevated serum creatinine, renal failure, and renal tubular acidosis [ see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  ) ] 
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;30%) by SC route are: nausea, anemia, thrombocytopenia, vomiting, pyrexia, leukopenia, diarrhea, injection site erythema, constipation, neutropenia and ecchymosis. Most common adverse reactions by IV route also included petechiae, rigors, weakness and hypokalemia (  6.1  ).
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Celgene Corporation at 1-888-423-5436 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

    Most Commonly Occurring Adverse Reactions (SC or IV Route):  nausea, anemia, thrombocytopenia, vomiting, pyrexia, leukopenia, diarrhea, injection site erythema, constipation, neutropenia, ecchymosis. The most common adverse reactions by IV route also included petechiae, rigors, weakness and hypokalemia.



     Adverse Reactions Most Frequently (&gt;2%) Resulting in Clinical Intervention (SC or IV Route):  Discontinuation: leukopenia, thrombocytopenia, neutropenia.Dose Held: leukopenia, neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, pyrexia, pneumonia, febrile neutropenia.Dose Reduced: leukopenia, neutropenia, thrombocytopenia.



   6.1 Adverse Reactions in Clinical Trials

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The data described below reflect exposure to VIDAZA in 443 MDS patients from 4 clinical studies. Study 1 was a supportive-care controlled trial (SC administration), Studies 2 and 3 were single arm studies (one with SC administration and one with IV administration), and Study 4 was an international randomized trial (SC administration) [  see Clinical Studies (  14  )  ].



 In Studies 1, 2 and 3, a total of 268 patients were exposed to VIDAZA, including 116 exposed for 6 cycles (approximately 6 months) or more and 60 exposed for greater than 12 cycles (approximately one year). VIDAZA was studied primarily in supportive-care controlled and uncontrolled trials (n=150 and n=118, respectively). The population in the subcutaneous studies (n=220) was 23 to 92 years old (mean 66.4 years), 68% male, and 94% white, and had MDS or AML. The population in the IV study (n=48) was 35 to 81 years old (mean 63.1 years), 65% male, and 100% white. Most patients received average daily doses between 50 and 100 mg/m  2  .



 In Study 4, a total of 175 patients with higher-risk MDS (primarily RAEB and RAEB-T subtypes) were exposed to VIDAZA. Of these patients, 119 were exposed for 6 or more cycles, and 63 for at least 12 cycles. The mean age of this population was 68.1 years (ranging from 42 to 83 years), 74% were male, and 99% were white. Most patients received daily VIDAZA doses of 75 mg/m  2  .



   Table 1  presents adverse reactions occurring in at least 5% of patients treated with VIDAZA (SC) in Studies 1 and 2. It is important to note that duration of exposure was longer for the VIDAZA-treated group than for the observation group: patients received VIDAZA for a mean of 11.4 months while mean time in the observation arm was 6.1 months.



  
 Table 1: Most Frequently Observed Adverse Reactions (&gt;= 5.0% in All SC VIDAZA Treated Patients; Studies 1 and 2)   
                                                 Number (%) of Patients      
   System Organ Class     Preferred Term    a      All VIDAZA    b    (N=220)      Observation    c    (N=92)     
  
  a Multiple terms of the same preferred terms for a patient are only counted once within each treatment group.    
  b Includes adverse reactions from all patients exposed to VIDAZA, including patients after crossing over from observations.    
  c Includes adverse reactions from observation period only; excludes any adverse events after crossover to VIDAZA.    
  
   Blood and lymphatic system disorders                                                                   
      Anemia                                   153 (69.5)                   59 (64.1)                     
      Anemia aggravated                        12 (5.5)                     5 (5.4)                       
      Febrile neutropenia                      36 (16.4)                    4 (4.3)                       
      Leukopenia                               106 (48.2)                   27 (29.3)                     
      Neutropenia                              71 (32.3)                    10 (10.9)                     
      Thrombocytopenia                         144 (65.5)                   42 (45.7)                     
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                             
      Abdominal tenderness                     26 (11.8)                    1 (1.1)                       
      Constipation                             74 (33.6)                    6 (6.5)                       
      Diarrhea                                 80 (36.4)                    13 (14.1)                     
      Gingival bleeding                        21 (9.5)                     4 (4.3)                       
      Loose stools                             12 (5.5)                     0                             
      Mouth hemorrhage                         11 (5.0)                     1 (1.1)                       
      Nausea                                   155 (70.5)                   16 (17.4)                     
      Stomatitis                               17 (7.7)                     0                             
      Vomiting                                 119 (54.1)                   5 (5.4)                       
   General disorders and administration site conditions                                  
      Chest pain                               36 (16.4)                    5 (5.4)                       
      Injection site bruising                  31 (14.1)                    0                             
      Injection site erythema                  77 (35.0)                    0                             
      Injection site granuloma                 11 (5.0)                     0                             
      Injection site pain                      50 (22.7)                    0                             
      Injection site pigmentation changes      11 (5.0)                     0                             
      Injection site pruritus                  15 (6.8)                     0                             
      Injection site reaction                  30 (13.6)                    0                             
      Injection site swelling                  11 (5.0)                     0                             
      Lethargy                                 17 (7.7)                     2 (2.2)                       
      Malaise                                  24 (10.9)                    1 (1.1)                       
      Pyrexia                                  114 (51.8)                   28 (30.4)                     
   Infections and infestations                                                                            
      Nasopharyngitis                          32 (14.5)                    3 (3.3)                       
      Pneumonia                                24 (10.9)                    5 (5.4)                       
      Upper respiratory tract infection        28 (12.7)                    4 (4.3)                       
   Injury, poisoning, and procedural complications                                                               
      Post procedural hemorrhage               13 (5.9)                     1 (1.1)                       
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders                                                                     
      Anorexia                                 45 (20.5)                    6 (6.5)                       
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders                                  
      Arthralgia                               49 (22.3)                    3 (3.3)                       
      Chest wall pain                          11 (5.0)                     0                             
      Myalgia                                  35 (15.9)                    2 (2.2)                       
   Nervous system disorders                                                                               
      Dizziness                                41 (18.6)                    5 (5.4)                       
      Headache                                 48 (21.8)                    10 (10.9)                     
   Psychiatric disorders                                                                                  
      Anxiety                                  29 (13.2)                    3 (3.3)                       
      Insomnia                                 24 (10.9)                    4 (4.3)                       
   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders                                                               
      Dyspnea                                  64 (29.1)                    11 (12.0)                     
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                                                                 
      Dry skin                                 11 (5.0)                     1 (1.1)                       
      Ecchymosis                               67 (30.5)                    14 (15.2)                     
      Erythema                                 37 (16.8)                    4 (4.3)                       
      Rash                                     31 (14.1)                    9 (9.8)                       
      Skin nodule                              11 (5.0)                     1 (1.1)                       
      Urticaria                                13 (5.9)                     1 (1.1)                       
   Vascular disorders                                                                                     
      Hematoma                                 19 (8.6)                     0                             
      Hypotension                              15 (6.8)                     2 (2.2)                       
      Petechiae                                52 (23.6)                    8 (8.7)                       
           Table 2  presents adverse reactions occurring in at least 5% of patients treated with VIDAZA in Study 4. Similar to Studies 1 and 2 described above, duration of exposure to treatment with VIDAZA was longer (mean 12.2 months) compared with best supportive care (mean 7.5 months).
 

  
 Table 2: Most Frequently Observed Adverse Reactions (&gt;= 5.0% in the VIDAZA Treated Patients and the Percentage with NCI CTC Grade 3/4 Reactions; Study 4)   
                                                 Number (%) of Patients     
                                                 Any Grade       Grade 3/4      
   System Organ Class     Preferred Term    a      VIDAZA(N=175)      Best Supportive Care Only(N=102)      VIDAZA(N=175)      Best Supportive Care Only(N=102)     
  
  a Multiple reports of the same preferred term from a patient were only counted once within each treatment.    
  
   Blood and lymphatic system disorders                                                                       
      Anemia                                   90 (51.4)       45 (44.1)       24 (13.7)      9 (8.8)         
      Febrile neutropenia                      24 (13.7)       10 (9.8)        22 (12.6)      7 (6.9)         
      Leukopenia                               32 (18.3)       2 (2.0)         26 (14.9)      1 (1.0)         
      Neutropenia                              115 (65.7)      29 (28.4)       107 (61.1)     22 (21.6)       
      Thrombocytopenia                         122 (69.7)      35 (34.3)       102 (58.3)     29 (28.4)       
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                                 
      Abdominal pain                           22 (12.6)       7 (6.9)         7 (4.0)        0               
      Constipation                             88 (50.3)       8 (7.8)         2 (1.1)        0               
      Dyspepsia                                10 (5.7)        2 (2.0)         0              0               
      Nausea                                   84 (48.0)       12 (11.8)       3 (1.7)        0               
      Vomiting                                 47 (26.9)       7 (6.9)         0              0               
   General disorders and administration site conditions                                                                   
      Fatigue                                  42 (24.0)       12 (11.8)       6 (3.4)        2 (2.0)         
      Injection site bruising                  9 (5.1)         0               0              0               
      Injection site erythema                  75 (42.9)       0               0              0               
      Injection site hematoma                  11 (6.3)        0               0              0               
      Injection site induration                9 (5.1)         0               0              0               
      Injection site pain                      33 (18.9)       0               0              0               
      Injection site rash                      10 (5.7)        0               0              0               
      Injection site reaction                  51 (29.1)       0               1 (0.6)        0               
      Pyrexia                                  53 (30.3)       18 (17.6)       8 (4.6)        1 (1.0)         
   Infections and infestations                                                                                
      Rhinitis                                 10 (5.7)        1 (1.0)         0              0               
      Upper respiratory tract infection        16 (9.1)        4 (3.9)         3 (1.7)        0               
      Urinary tract infection                  15 (8.6)        3 (2.9)         3 (1.7)        0               
   Investigations                                                                                             
      Weight decreased                         14 (8.0)        0               1 (0.6)        0               
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders                                                                         
      Hypokalemia                              11 (6.3)        3 (2.9)         3 (1.7)        3 (2.9)         
   Nervous system disorders                                                                                   
      Lethargy                                 13 (7.4)        2 (2.0)         0              1 (1.0)         
   Psychiatric disorders                                                                                      
      Anxiety                                  9 (5.1)         1 (1.0)         0              0               
      Insomnia                                 15 (8.6)        3 (2.9)         0              0               
   Renal and urinary disorders                                                                                
      Hematuria                                11 (6.3)        2 (2.0)         4 (2.3)        1 (1.0)         
   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders                                                                   
      Dyspnea                                  26 (14.9)       5 (4.9)         6 (3.4)        2 (2.0)         
      Dyspnea exertional                       9 (5.1)         1 (1.0)         0              0               
      Pharyngolaryngeal pain                   11 (6.3)        3 (2.9)         0              0               
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                                                                     
      Erythema                                 13 (7.4)        3 (2.9)         0              0               
      Petechiae                                20 (11.4)       4 (3.9)         2 (1.1)        0               
      Pruritus                                 21 (12.0)       2 (2.0)         0              0               
      Rash                                     18 (10.3)       1 (1.0)         0              0               
   Vascular disorders                                                                                         
      Hypertension                             15 (8.6)        4 (3.9)         2 (1.1)        2 (2.0)         
           In Studies 1, 2 and 4 with SC administration of VIDAZA, adverse reactions of neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, anemia, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, constipation, and injection site erythema/reaction tended to increase in incidence with higher doses of VIDAZA. Adverse reactions that tended to be more pronounced during the first 1 to 2 cycles of SC treatment compared with later cycles included thrombocytopenia, neutropenia, anemia, nausea, vomiting, injection site erythema/pain/bruising/reaction, constipation, petechiae, dizziness, anxiety, hypokalemia, and insomnia. There did not appear to be any adverse reactions that increased in frequency over the course of treatment.
 

 Overall, adverse reactions were qualitatively similar between the IV and SC studies. Adverse reactions that appeared to be specifically associated with the IV route of administration included infusion site reactions (e.g. erythema or pain) and catheter site reactions (e.g. infection, erythema, or hemorrhage).



 In clinical studies of either SC or IV VIDAZA, the following serious adverse reactions occurring at a rate of &lt; 5% (and not described in  Tables 1  or  2  ) were reported:



   Blood and lymphatic system disorders:  agranulocytosis, bone marrow failure, pancytopenia splenomegaly.



   Cardiac disorders:  atrial fibrillation, cardiac failure, cardiac failure congestive, cardio-respiratory arrest, congestive cardiomyopathy.



   Eye disorders:  eye hemorrhage



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  diverticulitis, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, melena, perirectal abscess.



   General disorders and administration site conditions:  catheter site hemorrhage, general physical health deterioration, systemic inflammatory response syndrome.



   Hepatobiliary disorders:  cholecystitis.



   Immune system disorders:  anaphylactic shock, hypersensitivity.



   Infections and infestations:  abscess limb, bacterial infection, cellulitis, blastomycosis, injection site infection, Klebsiella sepsis, neutropenic sepsis, pharyngitis streptococcal, pneumonia Klebsiella, sepsis, septic shock, Staphylococcal bacteremia, Staphylococcal infection, toxoplasmosis.



   Metabolism and nutrition disorders:  dehydration.



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  bone pain aggravated, muscle weakness, neck pain.



   Neoplasms benign, malignant and unspecified:  leukemia cutis.



   Nervous system disorders:  cerebral hemorrhage, convulsions, intracranial hemorrhage.



   Renal and urinary disorders:  loin pain, renal failure.



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  hemoptysis, lung infiltration, pneumonitis, respiratory distress.



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  pyoderma gangrenosum, rash pruritic, skin induration.



   Surgical and medical procedures:  cholecystectomy.



   Vascular disorders:  orthostatic hypotension.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postmarketing use of VIDAZA. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 *  -  Interstitial lung disease 
 *  -  Tumor lysis syndrome 
 *  -  Injection site necrosis 
 *  -  Sweet's syndrome (acute febrile neutrophilic dermatosis) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Anemia, neutropenia and thrombocytopenia: Monitor complete blood counts frequently (CBC) (  5.1  ). 
 *  Hepatotoxicity: Patients with severe preexisting hepatic impairment are at higher risk for toxicity (  5.2  ). 
 *  Renal impairment: Monitor patients with renal impairment for toxicity since azacitidine and its metabolites are primarily excreted by the kidneys (  5.3  ). 
 *  Monitor liver chemistries and serum creatinine prior to initiation of therapy and with each cycle (  2.1  ). 
 *  VIDAZA may cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Women of childbearing potential should be apprised of the potential hazard to a fetus (  5.4  ,  8.1  ). 
 *  Men should be advised not to father a child while receiving VIDAZA (  5.5  ,  13.1  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Anemia, Neutropenia and Thrombocytopenia



  VIDAZA causes anemia, neutropenia and thrombocytopenia. Monitor complete blood counts frequently for response and/or toxicity, at a minimum, prior to each dosing cycle. After administration of the recommended dosage for the first cycle, adjust dosage for subsequent cycles based on nadir counts and hematologic response [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.3  )  ].



    5.2 VIDAZA Toxicity in Patients with Severe Pre-existing Hepatic Impairment



  Because azacitidine is potentially hepatotoxic in patients with severe pre-existing hepatic impairment, caution is needed in patients with liver disease. Patients with extensive tumor burden due to metastatic disease have been reported to experience progressive hepatic coma and death during azacitidine treatment, especially in such patients with baseline albumin &lt;30 g/L. Azacitidine is contraindicated in patients with advanced malignant hepatic tumors [ see Contraindications (  4.1  )  ].



 Safety and effectiveness of VIDAZA in patients with MDS and hepatic impairment have not been studied as these patients were excluded from the clinical trials.



    5.3 Renal Toxicity



  Renal toxicity ranging from elevated serum creatinine to renal failure and death have been reported in patients treated with intravenous azacitidine in combination with other chemotherapeutic agents for nonMDS conditions. In addition, renal tubular acidosis, defined as a fall in serum bicarbonate to &lt;20 mEq/L in association with an alkaline urine and hypokalemia (serum potassium &lt;3 mEq/L) developed in 5 patients with CML treated with azacitidine and etoposide. If unexplained reductions in serum bicarbonate &lt;20 mEq/L or elevations of BUN or serum creatinine occur, the dosage should be reduced or held [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.4  )  ].



 Patients with renal impairment may be at increased risk for renal toxicity. Also, azacitidine and its metabolites are primarily excreted by the kidney. Therefore, these patients should be closely monitored for toxicity [ see Dosage and Administration (  2.4  ,  2.5  )  ]. Patients with MDS and renal impairment were excluded from the clinical studies.



    5.4 Use in Pregnancy



  VIDAZA may cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Azacitidine caused congenital malformations in animals. Women of childbearing potential should be advised to avoid pregnancy during treatment with VIDAZA. There are no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women using VIDAZA. If this drug is used during pregnancy or if a patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus [ see Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  )  ].



    5.5 Use in Males



  Men should be advised to not father a child while receiving treatment with VIDAZA. In animal studies, pre-conception treatment of male mice and rats resulted in increased embryofetal loss in mated females [ see Nonclinical Toxicology (  13  )  ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
