<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="vimovo" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions in clinical trials (&gt;5%): erosive gastritis, dyspepsia, gastritis, diarrhea, gastric ulcer, upper abdominal pain, nausea  (6.1)  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact AstraZeneca at 1-800-236-9933 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The adverse reactions reported below are specific to the clinical trials with VIMOVO. See also the full prescribing information for naproxen and esomeprazole magnesium products.



 The safety of VIMOVO was evaluated in clinical studies involving 2317 patients (aged 27 to 90 years) and ranging from 3-12 months. Patients received either 500 mg/20 mg of VIMOVO twice daily (n=1157), 500 mg of enteric-coated naproxen twice daily (n=426), or placebo (n=246). The average number of VIMOVO doses taken over 12 months was 696  +  44.



 The table below lists all adverse reactions, regardless of causality, occurring in &gt;2% of patients receiving VIMOVO from two clinical studies (Study 1 and Study 2). Both of these studies were randomized, multi-center, double-blind, parallel studies. The majority of patients were female (67%), white (86%). The majority of patients were 50-69 years of age (83%). Approximately one quarter were on low-dose aspirin.



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions occurring in patients &gt;2% Study 1 and Study 2 (endoscopic studies) 
  Preferred term (sorted by SOC)                    VIMOVO 500 mg/20 mg twice daily  (n=428)  %    EC-Naproxen 500 mg twice daily  (n=426)  %    
  Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                                               
  Gastritis Erosive                                 19                                   38                                
  Dyspepsia                                         18                                   27                                
  Gastritis                                         17                                   14                                
  Diarrhea                                          6                                    5                                 
  Gastric Ulcer                                     6                                    24                                
  Abdominal Pain Upper                              6                                    9                                 
  Nausea                                            5                                    5                                 
  Hiatus Hernia                                     4                                    6                                 
  Abdominal Distension                              4                                    4                                 
  Flatulence                                        4                                    3                                 
  Esophagitis                                       4                                    8                                 
  Constipation                                      3                                    3                                 
  Abdominal pain                                    2                                    2                                 
  Erosive Duodenitis                                2                                    12                                
  Abdominal pain lower                              2                                    3                                 
  Duodenitis                                        1                                    7                                 
  Gastritis hemorrhagic                             1                                    2                                 
  Gastroesophageal reflux disease                   &lt;1                                   4                                 
  Duodenal ulcer                                    &lt;1                                   5                                 
  Erosive esophagitis                               &lt;1                                   6                                 
  Infections and infestations                                                                                              
  Upper respiratory tract infection                 5                                    4                                 
  Bronchitis                                        2                                    2                                 
  Urinary tract infection                           2                                    1                                 
  Sinusitis                                         2                                    2                                 
  Nasopharyngitis                                   &lt;1                                   2                                 
  Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders                                                                           
  Arthralgia                                        1                                    2                                 
  Nervous system disorders                                                                                                 
  Headache                                          3                                    1                                 
  Dysgeusia                                         2                                    1                                 
  Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders                                                                           
  Cough                                             2                                    3                                 
         In Study 1 and Study 2, patients taking VIMOVO had fewer premature discontinuations due to adverse reactions compared to patients taking enteric-coated naproxen alone (7.9% vs. 12.5% respectively). The most common reasons for discontinuations due to adverse events in the VIMOVO treatment group were upper abdominal pain (1.2%, n=5), duodenal ulcer (0.7%, n=3) and erosive gastritis (0.7%, n=3). Among patients receiving enteric-coated naproxen, the most common reasons for discontinuations due to adverse events were duodenal ulcer 5.4% (n=23), dyspepsia 2.8% (n=12) and upper abdominal pain 1.2% (n=5). The proportion of patients discontinuing treatment due to any upper gastrointestinal adverse events (including duodenal ulcers) in patients treated with VIMOVO was 4% compared to 12% for patients taking enteric-coated naproxen.
 

 The table below lists all adverse reactions, regardless of causality, occurring in &gt;2% of patients from 2 clinical studies conducted in patients with osteoarthritis of the knee (Study 3 and Study 4).



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions occurring in patients &gt;2% (Study 3 and Study 4) 
  Preferred term (sorted by SOC)                          VIMOVO 500 mg/20 mg twice daily  (n=490)  %    Placebo  (n=246)  %    
  Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                                                 
  Dyspepsia                                               8                                      12          
  Diarrhea                                                6                                      4           
  Abdominal Pain Upper                                    4                                      3           
  Constipation                                            4                                      1           
  Nausea                                                  4                                      4           
  Nervous System Disorders                                                                                   
  Dizziness                                               3                                      2           
  Headache                                                3                                      5           
  General disorders and administration site conditions                                                       
  Peripheral edema                                        3                                      1           
  Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders                                                            
  Cough                                                   1                                      3           
  Infections and infestations                                                                                
  Sinusitis                                               1                                      2           
         The percentage of subjects who withdrew from the VIMOVO treatment group in these studies due to treatment-emergent adverse events was 7%. There were no preferred terms in which more than 1% of subjects withdrew from any treatment group.
 

 The long-term safety of VIMOVO was evaluated in an open-label clinical trial of 239 patients, of which 135 patients received 500 mg/20 mg of VIMOVO for 12 months. There were no differences in frequency or types of adverse reactions seen in the long-term safety study compared to shorter-term treatment in the randomized controlled studies.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  Naproxen



 The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of naproxen. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. These reports are listed below by body system:



   Body as a Whole:  anaphylactic reactions, angioneurotic edema, menstrual disorders, pyrexia (chills and fever)



   Cardiovascular:  congestive heart failure, vasculitis, hypertension, pulmonary edema



   Gastrointestinal:  gastrointestinal bleeding and/or perforation, hematemesis, pancreatitis, vomiting, colitis, exacerbation of inflammatory bowel disease (ulcerative colitis, Crohn's disease), nonpeptic gastrointestinal ulceration, ulcerative stomatitis, esophagitis, peptic ulceration



   Hepatobiliary:  jaundice, abnormal liver function tests, hepatitis (some cases have been fatal)



   Hemic and Lymphatic:  eosinophilia, leukopenia, melena, thrombocytopenia, agranulocytosis, granulocytopenia, hemolytic anemia, aplastic anemia



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  hyperglycemia, hypoglycemia



   Nervous System:  inability to concentrate, depression, dream abnormalities, insomnia, malaise, myalgia, muscle weakness, aseptic meningitis, cognitive dysfunction, convulsions



   Respiratory:  eosinophilic pneumonitis, asthma



   Dermatologic:  alopecia, urticaria, skin rashes, toxic epidermal necrolysis, erythema multiforme, erythema nodosum, fixed drug eruption, lichen planus, pustular reaction, systemic lupus erythematoses, bullous reactions, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome, photosensitive dermatitis, photosensitivity reactions, including rare cases resembling porphyria cutanea tarda (pseudoporphyria) or epidermolysis bullosa. If skin fragility, blistering or other symptoms suggestive of pseudoporphyria occur, treatment should be discontinued and the patient monitored.



   Special Senses:  hearing impairment, corneal opacity, papillitis, retrobulbar optic neuritis, papilledema



   Urogenital:  glomerular nephritis, hematuria, hyperkalemia, interstitial nephritis, nephrotic syndrome, renal disease, renal failure, renal papillary necrosis, raised serum creatinine



   Reproduction (female):  infertility



 Esomeprazole



 The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of esomeprazole. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. These reports are listed below by body system:



   Blood and Lymphatic:  agranulocytosis, pancytopenia;



   Eye:  blurred vision;



   Gastrointestinal:  pancreatitis; stomatitis; microscopic colitis



   Hepatobiliary:  hepatic failure, hepatitis with or without jaundice;



   Immune System:  anaphylactic reaction/shock;



   Infections and Infestations:  GI candidiasis,  Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea;



   Metabolism and Nutritional Disorders:  hypomagnesemia



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue:  muscular weakness, myalgia, bone fracture;



   Nervous System:  hepatic encephalopathy, taste disturbance;



   Psychiatric:  aggression, agitation, depression, hallucination;



   Renal and Urinary:  interstitial nephritis;



   Reproductive System and Breast:  gynecomastia;



   Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal:  bronchospasm;



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue:  alopecia, erythema multiforme, hyperhidrosis, photosensitivity, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis (some fatal).
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL RISKS

  WARNING: CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL RISKS

    Cardiovascular Risk  



 *  Non-Steroidal Anti-inflammatory Drugs (NSAIDs), a component of VIMOVO, may cause an increased risk of serious cardiovascular thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. This risk may increase with duration of use. Patients with cardiovascular disease or risk factors for cardiovascular disease may be at greater risk [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  VIMOVO is contraindicated for the treatment of peri-operative pain in the setting of coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery [see Contraindications (4), and Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
      Gastrointestinal Risk  
 

 *  NSAIDs, including naproxen, a component of VIMOVO, cause an increased risk of serious gastrointestinal adverse events including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach or intestines, which can be fatal. These events can occur at any time during use and without warning symptoms. Elderly patients are at greater risk for serious gastrointestinal events [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)]. 
      EXCERPT:     WARNING: CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL RISKS  
 

     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning     



   Cardiovascular Risk  



 *  Naproxen, a component of VIMOVO, may cause an increased risk of serious cardiovascular thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. This risk may increase with duration of use. Patients with cardiovascular disease or risk factors for cardiovascular disease may be at greater risk. (5.1) 
 *  VIMOVO is contraindicated for the treatment of peri-operative pain in the setting of coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery. (4, 5.1) 
      Gastrointestinal Risk  
 

 *  NSAIDs, including naproxen, a component of VIMOVO, cause an increased risk of serious gastrointestinal adverse events including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach or intestines, which can be fatal. These events can occur at any time during use and without warning symptoms. Elderly patients are at greater risk for serious gastrointestinal (GI) events. (5.4) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Serious and potentially fatal cardiovascular (CV) thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke. Patients with known CV disease/risk factors may be at greater risk  (5.1)   
 *    New onset or worsening of pre-existing hypertension. Blood pressure should be monitored closely during treatment with VIMOVO (  5.2  ,  7.1  ,  7.6  ) 
 *    Congestive heart failure and edema. VIMOVO should be used with caution in patients with fluid retention or heart failure  (5.3)   
 *    Serious gastrointestinal (GI) adverse events, which can be fatal. The risk is greater in patients with a prior history of ulcer disease or GI bleeding, and in patients at high risk for GI events, especially the elderly. VIMOVO should be used with caution in these patients (  5.4  ,  8.5  ) 
 *    Symptomatic response to esomeprazole does not preclude the presence of gastric malignancy (  5.4  ) 
 *    Atrophic gastritis has been noted on biopsy with long-term omeprazole therapy  (5.4)   
 *    Treatment should be withdrawn when active and clinically significant bleeding from any source occurs  (5.5)   
 *    Renal papillary necrosis and other renal injury with long-term use. Use VIMOVO with caution in the elderly, those with impaired renal function, hypovolemia, salt depletion, heart failure, liver dysfunction, and those taking diuretics, or ACE-inhibitors. Not recommended for patients with moderate or severe renal impairment (  2  ,  5.6  ,  5.7  ,  7.1  ,  7.6  ,  8.7  ) 
 *    Anaphylactic reactions. Do not use VIMOVO in patients with the aspirin triad  (5.8)   
 *    Serious skin adverse reactions such as exfoliative dermatitis, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and toxic epidermal necrolysis, which can be fatal and can occur without warning. Discontinue VIMOVO at first appearance of skin rash or any other sign of hypersensitivity  (5.9)   
 *    Elevated liver enzymes and, rarely, severe hepatic reactions. Discontinue use immediately if abnormal liver enzymes persist or worsen (  5.11  ,  8.6  ,  12.3  ) 
 *    Should be avoided in patients with severe hepatic impairment (e.g., Child-Pugh C) (  2  ,  5.11  ,  8.6  ,  12.3  ) 
 *    PPI therapy may be associated with increased risk of Clostridium difficile associated diarrhea.  (5.16)   
 *    Avoid concomitant use of esomeprazole with clopidogrel  (5.17)   
 *    Long-term and multiple daily dose PPI therapy is associated with an increased risk for osteoporosis-related fractures of the hip, wrist or spine  (5.18)   
 *    Interactions with diagnostic investigations for Neuroendocrine Tumors: Increases in intragastric pH may result in hypergastrinemia, enterochromaffin-like cell hyperplasia, and increased Chromogranin A levels which may interfere with diagnostic investigations for neuroendocrine tumors.  (5.20)   
 *    Hypomagnesemia has been reported rarely with prolonged treatment with PPIs  (5.21)   
 *    Avoid concomitant use of VIMOVO with St John's Wort or rifampin due to the potential reduction in esomeprazole levels. (  5.22  ,  7.16  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Cardiovascular Thrombotic Events



  Clinical trials of several COX-2 selective and nonselective NSAIDs of up to three years duration have shown an increased risk of serious cardiovascular (CV) thrombotic events, myocardial infarction, and stroke, which can be fatal. All NSAIDS, both COX-2 selective and nonselective, may have a similar risk. Patients with known CV disease or risk factors for CV disease may be at greater risk. To minimize the potential risk for an adverse CV event in patients treated with an NSAID, the lowest effective dose should be used for the shortest duration possible. Physicians and patients should remain alert for the development of such events, even in the absence of previous CV symptoms. Patients should be informed about the signs and/or symptoms of serious CV events and the steps to take if they occur.



 There is no consistent evidence that concurrent use of aspirin mitigates the increased risk of serious CV thrombotic events associated with NSAID use.



 Two large, controlled, clinical trials of a COX-2 selective NSAID for the treatment of pain in the first 10-14 days following CABG surgery found an increased incidence of myocardial infarction and stroke [see   Contraindications (4)    ].



    5.2 Hypertension



  NSAIDs, including naproxen, a component of VIMOVO, can lead to onset of new hypertension or worsening of pre-existing hypertension, either of which may contribute to the increased incidence of CV events. Patients taking thiazides or loop diuretics may have impaired response to these therapies when taking NSAIDs. NSAIDs should be used with caution in patients with hypertension. Blood pressure (BP) should be monitored closely during the initiation of NSAID treatment and throughout the course of therapy [see Drug Interactions (  7.1  ,     7.6     )  ].



    5.3 Congestive Heart Failure and Edema



  Fluid retention, edema, and peripheral edema have been observed in some patients taking NSAIDs and should be used with caution in patients with fluid retention or heart failure.



    5.4 Gastrointestinal Effects - Risk of Ulceration, Bleeding, and Perforation



  NSAIDs, including naproxen, a component of VIMOVO, can cause serious gastrointestinal (GI) adverse events including inflammation, bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach, small intestine, or large intestine, which can be fatal. While VIMOVO has been shown to significantly decrease the occurrence of gastric ulcers compared to naproxen alone, ulceration and associated complications can still occur.



 These serious adverse events can occur at any time, with or without warning symptoms, in patients treated with NSAIDs. Only one in five patients who develop a serious upper GI adverse event on NSAID therapy is symptomatic. Upper GI ulcers, gross bleeding, or perforation caused by NSAIDs occur in approximately 1% of patients treated for 3-6 months, and in about 2-4% of patients treated for one year. These trends continue with longer duration of use, increasing the likelihood of developing a serious GI event at some time during the course of therapy. However, even short-term therapy is not without risk. The utility of periodic laboratory monitoring has not been demonstrated, nor has it been adequately assessed.



 VIMOVO should be prescribed with caution in those with a prior history of ulcer disease or gastrointestinal bleeding. Patients with a prior history of peptic ulcer disease and/or gastrointestinal bleeding who use NSAIDs have a greater than 10-fold increased risk of developing a GI bleed compared to patients with neither of these risk factors. Other factors that increase the risk for GI bleeding in patients treated with NSAIDs include concomitant use of oral corticosteroids or anticoagulants or antiplatelets (including low-dose aspirin), longer duration of NSAID therapy, smoking, use of alcohol, older age, and poor general health status. Most spontaneous reports of fatal GI events are in elderly or debilitated patients, and therefore special care should be taken in treating this population.



 To minimize the potential risk for an adverse GI event in patients treated with an NSAID or NSAID-containing product, the lowest effective dose should be used for the shortest possible duration. Patients and physicians should remain alert for signs and symptoms of GI ulceration and bleeding during NSAID therapy and promptly initiate additional evaluation and treatment if a serious GI adverse event is suspected. This should include discontinuation of the NSAID until a serious GI adverse event is ruled out. For high risk patients, alternate therapies that do not involve NSAIDs should be considered.



 Epidemiological studies of the case-control and cohort design have demonstrated an association between use of psychotropic drugs that interfere with serotonin reuptake and the occurrence of upper gastrointestinal bleeding. In two studies, concurrent use of an NSAID, COX-2 inhibitor, or aspirin potentiated the risk of bleeding [see Drug Interactions (  7.2  ,     7.10     )  ]. Although these studies focused on upper gastrointestinal bleeding, bleeding at other sites cannot be ruled out.



 NSAIDs should be given with care to patients with a history of inflammatory bowel disease (ulcerative colitis, Crohn's disease) as their condition may be exacerbated.



 Gastrointestinal symptomatic response to therapy with VIMOVO does not preclude the presence of gastric malignancy.



 Atrophic gastritis has been noted occasionally in gastric corpus biopsies from patients treated long-term with omeprazole, of which esomeprazole is an enantiomer and a component of VIMOVO.



    5.5 Active Bleeding



  When active and clinically significant bleeding from any source occurs in patients receiving VIMOVO, the treatment should be withdrawn.



    5.6 Renal Effects



  Long-term administration of NSAIDs has resulted in renal papillary necrosis and other renal injury. Renal toxicity has also been seen in patients in whom renal prostaglandins have a compensatory role in the maintenance of renal perfusion. In these patients, administration of an NSAID may cause a dose-dependent reduction in prostaglandin formation and, secondarily, in renal blood flow, which may precipitate overt renal decompensation. Patients at greatest risk of this reaction are those with impaired renal function, hypovolemia, heart failure, liver dysfunction, salt depletion, those taking diuretics and ACE inhibitors, and the elderly. Discontinuation of NSAID therapy is usually followed by recovery to the pretreatment state.



    5.7 Advanced Renal Disease



  No information is available from controlled clinical studies regarding the use of VIMOVO in patients with advanced renal disease. Therefore, treatment with VIMOVO is not recommended in these patients with advanced renal disease. If VIMOVO therapy must be initiated, close monitoring of the patient's renal function is advisable [see Dosage and  Administration (2),    Use in Specific Populations (8.7)    and   Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)    ].



    5.8 Anaphylactic Reactions



  Anaphylactic reactions may occur in patients without known prior exposure to either component of VIMOVO. NSAIDs should not be given to patients with the aspirin triad. This symptom complex typically occurs in asthmatic patients who experience rhinitis with or without nasal polyps, or who exhibit severe, potentially fatal bronchospasm after taking aspirin or other NSAIDs [see   Contraindications (4)    ]. Emergency help should be sought in cases where an anaphylactic reaction occurs. Anaphylactic reactions, like anaphylaxis, may have a fatal outcome.



    5.9 Skin Reactions



  NSAIDs can cause serious skin adverse events such as exfoliative dermatitis, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and toxic epidermal necrolysis, which can be fatal. These serious events may occur without warning. Patients should be informed about the signs and symptoms of serious skin manifestations and use of the drug should be discontinued at the first appearance of skin rash or any other sign of hypersensitivity.



    5.10 Pregnancy



  Pregnancy Category C



 In late pregnancy, as with other NSAIDs, naproxen, a component of VIMOVO, should be avoided because it may cause premature closure of the ductus arteriosus [see   Contraindications (4)    , and   Use in Specific Populations (8.1)].    



    5.11 Hepatic Effects



  Borderline elevations of one or more liver tests may occur in up to 15% of patients taking NSAIDs including naproxen, a component of VIMOVO. Hepatic abnormalities may be the result of hypersensitivity rather than direct toxicity. These laboratory abnormalities may progress, may remain essentially unchanged, or may be transient with continued therapy. The SGPT (ALT) test is probably the most sensitive indicator of liver dysfunction. Notable elevations of ALT or AST (approximately three or more times the upper limit of normal) have been reported in approximately 1% of patients in clinical trials with NSAIDs. In addition, rare cases of severe hepatic reactions, including jaundice and fatal fulminant hepatitis, liver necrosis and hepatic failure, some of them with fatal outcomes, have been reported.



 A patient with symptoms and/or signs suggesting liver dysfunction, or in whom an abnormal liver test has occurred, should be evaluated for evidence of the development of more severe hepatic reaction while on therapy with VIMOVO.



 If clinical signs and symptoms consistent with liver disease develop, or if systemic manifestations occur (eg, eosinophilia, rash, etc.), VIMOVO should be discontinued.



 Chronic alcoholic liver disease and probably other diseases with decreased or abnormal plasma proteins (albumin) reduce the total plasma concentration of naproxen, but the plasma concentration of unbound naproxen is increased. Caution is advised when high doses are required and some adjustment of dosage may be required in these patients. It is prudent to use the lowest effective dose for the shortest possible duration of adequate treatment.



 VIMOVO should be avoided in patients with severe hepatic impairment [see   Dosage and Administration (2)  , Use in  Specific Populations (8.6),    and   Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)]    .



    5.12 Hematological Effects



  Anemia is sometimes seen in patients receiving NSAIDs. This may be due to fluid retention, occult or gross GI blood loss, or an incompletely described effect upon erythropoiesis. Patients on long-term treatment with NSAIDs should have their hemoglobin or hematocrit checked if they exhibit any signs or symptoms of anemia.



 NSAIDs inhibit platelet aggregation and have been shown to prolong bleeding time in some patients. Unlike aspirin, their effect on platelet function is quantitatively less, of shorter duration, and reversible. Patients receiving VIMOVO who may be adversely affected by alterations in platelet function, such as those with coagulation disorders or patients receiving anticoagulants or antiplatelets, should be carefully monitored.



    5.13 Pre-existing Asthma



  Patients with asthma may have aspirin-sensitive asthma. The use of aspirin in patients with aspirin-sensitive asthma has been associated with severe bronchospasm, which can be fatal. Since cross reactivity, including bronchospasm, between aspirin and other NSAIDs has been reported in such aspirin-sensitive patients, VIMOVO should not be administered to patients with this form of aspirin sensitivity and should be used with caution in patients with pre-existing asthma.



    5.14 Concomitant NSAID Use



  VIMOVO contains naproxen as one of its active ingredients. It should not be used with other naproxen-containing products since they all circulate in the plasma as the naproxen anion.



 The concomitant use of VIMOVO with any dose of a non-aspirin NSAID should be avoided due to the potential for increased risk of adverse reactions.



    5.15 Corticosteroid Treatment



  VIMOVO cannot be expected to substitute for corticosteroids or to treat corticosteroid insufficiency. Abrupt discontinuation of corticosteroids may lead to disease exacerbation. Patients on prolonged corticosteroid therapy should have their therapy tapered slowly if a decision is made to discontinue corticosteroids and the patient should be observed closely for any evidence of adverse effects, including adrenal insufficiency and exacerbation of symptoms of arthritis.



    5.16 Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea



   Published observational studies suggest that PPI therapy like VIMOVO may be associated with an increased risk of Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea, especially in hospitalized patients. This diagnosis should be considered for diarrhea that does not improve [ see  Adverse Reactions (6.2)    ].  



  Patients should use the lowest dose and shortest duration of PPI therapy appropriate to the condition being treated [ see  Dosage and Administration (2)    ].  



    5.17 Interaction with Clopidogrel



   Avoid concomitant use of esomeprazole with clopidogrel. Clopidogrel is a prodrug. Inhibition of platelet aggregation by clopidogrel is entirely due to an active metabolite. The metabolism of clopidogrel to its active metabolite can be impaired by use with concomitant medications, such as esomeprazole, that inhibit CYP2C19 activity. Concomitant use of clopidogrel with 40 mg esomeprazole reduces the pharmacological activity of clopidogrel. When using esomeprazole, a component of VIMOVO, consider alternative anti-platelet therapy [ see  Drug Interactions (7.16)    and Pharmacokinetics (12.3)    ]  



    5.18 Bone Fracture



   Several published observational studies suggest that proton pump inhibitor (PPI) therapy may be associated with an increased risk for osteoporosis-related fractures of the hip, wrist, or spine. The risk of fracture was increased in patients who received high-dose, defined as multiple daily doses, and long-term PPI therapy (a year or longer). Patients should use the lowest dose and shortest duration of PPI therapy appropriate to the condition being treated. Patients at risk for osteoporosis-related fractures should be managed according to the established treatment guidelines. [ see Dosage and Administration (2) and Adverse Reactions (6.2)  ].  



  VIMOVO (a combination PPI/NSAID) is approved for use twice a day and does not allow for administration of a lower daily dose of the PPI. [ see       Dosage and Administration (2)     ].  



    5.19 Masking of Inflammation and Fever



  The pharmacological activity of VIMOVO in reducing fever and inflammation may diminish the utility of these diagnostic signs in detecting complications of presumed noninfectious, noninflammatory painful conditions.



    5.20 Laboratory Tests



  Because serious GI tract ulcerations and bleeding can occur without warning symptoms, physicians should monitor for signs or symptoms of GI bleeding. Patients on long-term treatment with NSAIDs should have their CBC and a chemistry profile checked periodically. If clinical signs and symptoms consistent with liver or renal disease develop, systemic manifestations occur (eg, eosinophilia, rash, etc.) or if abnormal liver tests persist or worsen, VIMOVO should be discontinued.



 Patients with initial hemoglobin values of 10 g or less who are to receive long-term therapy should have hemoglobin values determined periodically.



 Serum chromogranin A (CgA) levels increase secondary to drug-induced decreases in gastric acidity. The increased CgA level may cause false positive results in diagnostic investigations for neuroendocrine tumors. Providers should temporarily stop esomeprazole treatment before assessing CgA levels and consider repeating the test if initial CgA levels are high. If serial tests are performed (e.g. for monitoring), the same commercial laboratory should be used for testing, as reference ranges between tests may vary [see   Pharmacodynamics (12.2)    ].



    5.21 Hypomagnesemia



  Hypomagnesemia, symptomatic and asymptomatic, has been reported rarely in patients treated with PPIs for at least three months, in most cases after a year of therapy. Serious adverse events include tetany, arrhythmias, and seizures. In most patients, treatment of hypomagnesemia required magnesium replacement and discontinuation of the PPI.



 For patients expected to be on prolonged treatment or who take PPIs with medications such as digoxin or drugs that may cause hypomagnesemia (e.g., diuretics), health care professionals may consider monitoring magnesium levels prior to initiation of PPI treatment and periodically. [see   Adverse Reactions (6.2)    ].



    5.22 Concomitant use of St John's Wort or Rifampin with VIMOVO



  Drugs that induce CYP2C19 or CYP3A4 (such as St John's Wort or rifampin) can substantially decrease esomeprazole concentrations. Avoid concomitant use of VIMOVO with St John's Wort or rifampin [see   Drug Interactions (7.15)    ].



    5.23 Concomitant use of VIMOVO with Methotrexate



   Literature suggests that concomitant use of PPIs with methotrexate (primarily at high dose; see methotrexate prescribing information) may elevate and prolong serum levels of methotrexate and/or its metabolite, possibly leading to methotrexate toxicities. In high-dose methotrexate administration a temporary withdrawal of the PPI may be considered in some patients. [ see Drug Interactions (7.8)  ]  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
