<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="viramune2" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6  ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  Adult patients: The most common adverse reaction is rash. During the lead-in period with immediate-release VIRAMUNE, the incidence of Grade 2 or higher drug-related rash in adults is 3%. After the lead-in period the incidence of Grade 2 or higher drug-related rash in subjects taking VIRAMUNE XR is 3%. The incidence of Grade 2 or higher drug-related clinical hepatitis after the lead-in phase was 2%.  (6.1)   
 *  Pediatric patients: The incidence of Grade 2 or higher drug-related rash was 1%.  (6.2)   
        To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Boehringer Ingelheim Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at (800) 542-6257 or (800) 459-9906 TTY, or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.    
 

 

  6.1  Clinical Trial Experience in Adult Patients

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The most serious adverse reactions associated with nevirapine are hepatitis, hepatic failure, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, and hypersensitivity reactions. Hepatitis/hepatic failure may be isolated or associated with signs of hypersensitivity which may include severe rash or rash accompanied by fever, general malaise, fatigue, muscle or joint aches, blisters, oral lesions, conjunctivitis, facial edema, eosinophilia, granulocytopenia, lymphadenopathy, or renal dysfunction [    see  Boxed Warning  and Warnings and Precautions  (5.1  ,  5.2)      ].



 The most common clinical toxicity of nevirapine is rash, which can be severe or life-threatening [    see  Boxed Warning  and Warnings and Precautions  (5.2)      ]. Rash occurs most frequently within the first 6 weeks of therapy. Rashes are usually mild to moderate, maculopapular erythematous cutaneous eruptions, with or without pruritus, located on the trunk, face and extremities.



 The safety database in VIRAMUNE XR clinical trials contains data from 800 subjects treated with VIRAMUNE XR and 654 subjects treated with immediate release VIRAMUNE.



     Trial 1100.1486 (VERxVE)  

  In Trial 1100.1486 (VERxVE) treatment-naive subjects received a lead-in dose of immediate-release VIRAMUNE 200 mg once daily for 14 days (n=1068) and then were randomized to receive either immediate-release VIRAMUNE 200 mg twice daily (n=506) or VIRAMUNE XR 400 mg once daily (n=505). All subjects received tenofovir + emtricitabine as background therapy. Subjects were enrolled with CD4  +  counts less than 250 cells/mm  3  for women and less than 400 cells/mm  3  for men [    see Indications and Usage  (1)      ]. Data on potential symptoms of hepatic events were prospectively collected in this trial. The safety data include all subject visits up to the time of the last subject's completion of the 96 week endpoint in the trial (mean observation period 98 weeks).



 After the lead-in period, the incidence of any hepatic event was 9% in the immediate-release VIRAMUNE group and 6% in the VIRAMUNE XR group; the incidence of symptomatic hepatic events (anorexia, jaundice, vomiting) was 3% and 2%, respectively. The incidence of GRADE 3 or 4 ALT/AST elevation was 8% in both the immediate-release VIRAMUNE group and VIRAMUNE XR group. Overall, there was a comparable incidence of symptomatic hepatic events among men and women enrolled in VERxVE.



 Severe or life-threatening rash considered to be related to nevirapine treatment occurred in 1% of subjects during the lead-in phase with immediate-release VIRAMUNE, and in 1% of subjects in either treatment group during the randomization phase. In addition, six cases of Stevens-Johnson syndrome were reported in the trial; all but one occurred within the first 30 days of nevirapine treatment.



 No Grade 2 or above adverse reactions judged to be related to treatment by the investigator occurred in more than 2% of subjects during the 14-day lead-in with immediate-release VIRAMUNE (200 mg once daily), with the exception of rash which occurred in 4% of subjects.



 Adverse reactions of at least moderate intensity (Grades 2 or above) 2% or more of treatment-naive subjects receiving either immediate-release VIRAMUNE or VIRAMUNE XR after randomization in Trial 1100.1486 are shown in Table 2.



 Table 2 Selected Clinical Adverse Drug Reactions* of at least Moderate Intensity (Grade 2 or above) Occurring in 2% or more of Adult Subjects- Week 96 Analysis of Trial 1100.14861 
   *  Excludes laboratory abnormalities reported as ADRs  1  Mean observation period 98 weeks.  2  Rash includes terms rash, rash maculo-papular, erythema nodosum, rash erythematous, rash papular, skin reaction, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, drug rash with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms (DRESS).  3  Clinical hepatitis includes terms hepatitis, hepatotoxicity, hepatitis acute, liver disorder, hepatitis toxic, hepatic failure, jaundice.   
  
     Adverse Drug Reaction                                         VIRAMUNE Immediate-ReleaseN=506 (%)          VIRAMUNE XRN=505 (%)       
 Rash  2                                                                4                     5             
 Diarrhea                                                               4                     4             
 Headache                                                               4                     4             
 Clinical Hepatitis  3                                                  4                     2             
 Abdominal Pain                                                         2                     3             
 Arthralgia                                                             2                     2             
 Pyrexia                                                                2                     1             
 Nausea                                                                 2                     1             
 Fatigue                                                                2                     2             
          Laboratory Abnormalities  
   Liver enzyme test abnormalities (AST, ALT) were observed in subjects receiving VIRAMUNE XR. Asymptomatic elevations in GGT occur frequently but are not a contraindication to continue therapy with nevirapine in the absence of elevations in other liver enzyme tests. Laboratory abnormalities that occurred in trial 1100.1486 are shown in Table 3.



 Table 3 Grade 2 to Grade 4 Laboratory Abnormalities that Represent a Worsening from Baseline Observed in at least 5% of Subjects in Either Treatment Group - Trial 1100.1486 
     Laboratory Parameter (unit)                Limit                VIRAMUNE Immediate-Release (%)(N=506)          VIRAMUNE XR (%)(N=505)       
  
       Chemistry                                                                                              
 SGPT/ALT (U/L)                                                                                               
 Grade 2                          2.6-5.0 x ULN                   13                         10               
 Grade 3                         5.1-10.0 x ULN                    3                          4               
 Grade 4                           &gt;10.0 x ULN                     4                          2               
 SGOT/AST (U/L)                                                                                               
 Grade 2                          2.6-5.0 x ULN                    9                          7               
 Grade 3                         5.1-10.0 x ULN                    2                          3               
 Grade 4                           &gt;10.0 x ULN                     2                          2               
 Amylase (U/L)                                                                                                
 Grade 2                          1.6-2.0 x ULN                    4                          5               
 Grade 3                          2.1-5.0 x ULN                    4                          2               
 Grade 4                           &gt;5.0 x ULN                      0                         &lt;1               
 Phosphate (mg/dL)                                                                                            
 Grade 2                          2.0-2.4 x ULN                   38                         33               
 Grade 3                          1.0-1.9 x ULN                    6                          7               
 Grade 4                           &lt;1.0 x ULN                     &lt;1                          0               
       Hematology                                                                                             
 Neutrophils                                                                                                  
 Grade 2                         750-999/mm  3                     7                          4               
 Grade 3                         500-749/mm  3                     2                          2               
 Grade 4                          &lt;500/mm  3                       1                          1               
       Lipids                                                                                                 
 LDL (mg/dL)                                                                                                  
 Grade 2                          160-190 mg/dL                   15                         15               
 Grade 3                           &gt;190 mg/dL                      5                          5               
 Cholesterol (mg/dL)                                                                                          
 Grade 2                          240-300 mg/dL                   18                         19               
 Grade 3                           &gt;300 mg/dL                      4                          3               
          Trial 1100.1526 (TRANxITION)  
   In Trial 1100.1526 (TRANxITION) subjects on immediate-release VIRAMUNE 200 mg twice daily for at least 18 weeks were randomized to either receive VIRAMUNE XR 400 mg once daily (n=295) or remain on their immediate-release VIRAMUNE treatment (n=148). Adverse reactions observed for VIRAMUNE XR subjects (48 week analysis) were similar to those observed in trial 1100.1486, as displayed in Table 1.



   6.2  Clinical Trial Experience in Pediatric Patients

  Adverse reactions were assessed in Trial 1100.1518, an open-label, multiple-dose, non-randomized, cross-over trial to evaluate the safety and steady-state pharmacokinetic parameters of VIRAMUNE XR tablets in HIV-1-infected pediatric subjects 3 to less than 18 years of age. Safety was further examined in an optional extension phase of the trial. Forty subjects who completed the pharmacokinetic part of the trial were treated with VIRAMUNE XR once daily in combination with other antiretrovirals for a median duration of 33 weeks. The most frequently reported adverse reactions related to VIRAMUNE XR in pediatric subjects were similar to those observed in adults. In pediatric subjects the incidence of Grade 2 or higher drug-related rash was 1%. There were no adverse reactions of Grade 2 or above which were considered to be related to treatment by the investigator that occurred in more than 1% of subjects [  see Use in Specific Populations  (8.4)  , Clinical Pharmacology  (12.3)  , and Clinical Studies  (14.2)    ].



   6.3  Post-Marketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of immediate-release VIRAMUNE. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 *       Body as a Whole:  fever, somnolence, drug withdrawal [  see Drug Interactions  (7)    ], redistribution/accumulation of body fat [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.6)    ] 
 *       Gastrointestinal:  vomiting 
 *       Liver and Biliary:  jaundice, fulminant and cholestatic hepatitis, hepatic necrosis, hepatic failure 
 *       Hematology:  anemia, eosinophilia, neutropenia 
 *       Investigations:  decreased serum phosphorus 
 *       Musculoskeletal:  arthralgia, rhabdomyolysis associated with skin and/or liver reactions 
 *       Neurologic:  paraesthesia 
 *       Skin and Appendages:  allergic reactions including anaphylaxis, angioedema, bullous eruptions, ulcerative stomatitis and urticaria have all been reported. In addition, hypersensitivity syndrome and hypersensitivity reactions with rash associated with constitutional findings such as fever, blistering, oral lesions, conjunctivitis, facial edema, muscle or joint aches, general malaise, fatigue, or significant hepatic abnormalities [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.1)    ] plus one or more of the following: hepatitis, eosinophilia, granulocytopenia, lymphadenopathy, and/or renal dysfunction have been reported. 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: LIFE-THREATENING (INCLUDING FATAL) HEPATOTOXICITY and SKIN REACTIONS

  WARNING: LIFE-THREATENING (INCLUDING FATAL) HEPATOTOXICITY and SKIN REACTIONS

      HEPATOTOXICITY:    



   Severe, life-threatening, and in some cases fatal hepatotoxicity, particularly in the first 18 weeks, has been reported in patients treated with nevirapine. In some cases, patients presented with non-specific prodromal signs or symptoms of hepatitis and progressed to hepatic failure. These events are often associated with rash. Female gender and higher CD4  +   cell counts at initiation of therapy place patients at increased risk; women with CD4  +   cell counts greater than 250 cells/mm  3  , including pregnant women receiving nevirapine in combination with other antiretrovirals for the treatment of HIV-1 infection, are at the greatest risk. However, hepatotoxicity associated with nevirapine use can occur in both genders, all CD4  +   cell counts and at any time during treatment. Hepatic failure has also been reported in patients without HIV taking nevirapine for post-exposure prophylaxis (PEP). Use of nevirapine for occupational and non-occupational PEP is contraindicated [      see Contraindications   (4.2)        ]. Patients with signs or symptoms of hepatitis, or with increased transaminases combined with rash or other systemic symptoms, must discontinue nevirapine and seek medical evaluation immediately   [    see Warnings and Precautions   (5.1)      ].



     SKIN REACTIONS:    



     Severe, life-threatening skin reactions, including fatal cases, have occurred in patients treated with nevirapine. These have included cases of Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, and hypersensitivity reactions characterized by rash, constitutional findings, and organ dysfunction. Patients developing signs or symptoms of severe skin reactions or hypersensitivity reactions must discontinue nevirapine and seek medical evaluation immediately. Transaminase levels should be checked immediately for all patients who develop a rash in the first 18 weeks of treatment. The 14-day lead-in period with immediate-release VIRAMUNE 200 mg daily dosing has been observed to decrease the incidence of rash and must be followed      [    see Warnings and Precautions   (5.2)      ].



     MONITORING:    



     Patients must be monitored intensively during the first 18 weeks of therapy with nevirapine to detect potentially life-threatening hepatotoxicity or skin reactions. Extra vigilance is warranted during the first 6 weeks of therapy, which is the period of greatest risk of these events. Do not restart nevirapine following clinical hepatitis, or transaminase elevations combined with rash or other systemic symptoms, or following severe skin rash or hypersensitivity reactions. In some cases, hepatic injury has progressed despite discontinuation of treatment.     



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: LIFE-THREATENING (INCLUDING FATAL) HEPATOTOXICITY and SKIN REACTIONS



 



       See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.      



 *  Fatal and non-fatal hepatotoxicity (5.1) 
 *  Fatal and non-fatal skin reactions (5.2) 
        Discontinue immediately if experiencing:    
 

 *  Signs or symptoms of hepatitis (5.1) 
 *  Increased transaminases combined with rash or other systemic symptoms (5.1) 
 *  Severe skin or hypersensitivity reactions (5.2) 
 *  Any rash with systemic symptoms (5.2) 
        Monitoring during the first 18 weeks of therapy is essential. Extra vigilance is warranted during the first 6 weeks of therapy, which is the period of greatest risk of these events   (5)  .    
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5  WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  The most serious adverse reactions associated with nevirapine are hepatitis/hepatic failure, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, and hypersensitivity reactions. Hepatitis/hepatic failure may be associated with signs of hypersensitivity which can include severe rash or rash accompanied by fever, general malaise, fatigue, muscle or joint aches, blisters, oral lesions, conjunctivitis, facial edema, eosinophilia, granulocytopenia, lymphadenopathy, or renal dysfunction.



   The first 18 weeks of therapy with nevirapine are a critical period during which intensive clinical and laboratory monitoring of patients is required to detect potentially life-threatening hepatic events and skin reactions.    The optimal frequency of monitoring during this time period has not been established. Some experts recommend clinical and laboratory monitoring more often than once per month, and in particular, include monitoring of liver enzyme tests prior to beginning the 14-day lead-in period with immediate-release VIRAMUNE, prior to initiation of VIRAMUNE XR (during the lead-in period), and at two weeks after initiation of VIRAMUNE XR therapy. After the initial 18-week period, frequent clinical and laboratory monitoring should continue throughout VIRAMUNE XR treatment. In addition, the 14-day lead-in period with immediate-release VIRAMUNE has been demonstrated to reduce the frequency of rash [  see Dosage and Administration  (2.2  ,  2.5)      ].



 Patients already on a regimen of immediate-release VIRAMUNE twice daily who switch to VIRAMUNE XR therapy should continue with their ongoing clinical and laboratory monitoring.



    EXCERPT:    *  Hepatotoxicity: Fatal and non-fatal hepatotoxicity has been reported. Monitor liver function tests before and during therapy. Permanently discontinue nevirapine if clinical hepatitis or transaminase elevations combined with rash or other systemic symptoms occur. Do not restart nevirapine after recovery.  (5.1)   
 *  Rash: Fatal and non-fatal skin reactions, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, and hypersensitivity reactions, have been reported. Permanently discontinue nevirapine if severe skin reactions or hypersensitivity reactions occur. Check transaminase levels immediately for all patients who develop a rash in the first 18 weeks of treatment.  (5.2)   
 *  Monitor patients for immune reconstitution syndrome and fat redistribution.  (5.5  ,  5.6)   
    
 

   5.1  Hepatotoxicity and Hepatic Impairment



  Severe, life-threatening, and in some cases fatal hepatotoxicity, including fulminant and cholestatic hepatitis, hepatic necrosis and hepatic failure, have been reported in patients treated with nevirapine.



 The risk of symptomatic hepatic events regardless of severity is greatest in the first 6 weeks of therapy. The risk continued to be greater in the nevirapine groups in controlled clinical trials through 18 weeks of treatment. However, hepatic events may occur at any time during treatment. In some cases, patients presented with non-specific, prodromal signs or symptoms of fatigue, malaise, anorexia, nausea, jaundice, liver tenderness or hepatomegaly, with or without initially abnormal serum transaminase levels. Rash was observed in approximately half of the patients with symptomatic hepatic adverse events. Fever and flu-like symptoms accompanied some of these hepatic events. Some events, particularly those with rash and other symptoms, have progressed to hepatic failure with transaminase elevation, with or without hyperbilirubinemia, hepatic encephalopathy, prolonged partial thromboplastin time, or eosinophilia. Rhabdomyolysis has been observed in some patients experiencing skin and/or liver reactions associated with nevirapine use. Patients with signs or symptoms of hepatitis must be advised to discontinue nevirapine and immediately seek medical evaluation, which should include liver enzyme tests.



   Transaminases should be checked immediately if a patient experiences signs or symptoms suggestive of hepatitis and/or hypersensitivity reaction. Transaminases should also be checked immediately for all patients who develop a rash in the first 18 weeks of treatment. Physicians and patients should be vigilant for the appearance of signs or symptoms of hepatitis, such as fatigue, malaise, anorexia, nausea, jaundice, bilirubinuria, acholic stools, liver tenderness, or hepatomegaly. The diagnosis of hepatotoxicity should be considered in this setting, even if transaminases are initially normal or alternative diagnoses are possible    [  see  Boxed Warning  , Dosage and Administration  (2.4)  , and Patient Counseling Information  (17.1)      ].



 If clinical hepatitis or transaminase elevations combined with rash or other systemic symptoms occur, permanently discontinue nevirapine. Do not restart nevirapine after recovery. In some cases, hepatic injury progresses despite discontinuation of treatment.



 The patients at greatest risk of hepatic events, including potentially fatal events, are women with high CD4  +  cell counts. In a retrospective analysis of pooled clinical trials with immediate-release VIRAMUNE, during the first 6 weeks of treatment women had a 3-fold higher risk than men for symptomatic, often rash-associated, hepatic events (6% versus 2%). Patients with higher CD4  +  cell counts at initiation of nevirapine therapy are at higher risk for symptomatic hepatic events. Women with CD4  +  cell counts greater than 250 cells/mm  3  had a 12-fold higher risk of symptomatic hepatic adverse events compared to women with CD4  +  cell counts less than 250 cells/mm  3  (11% versus 1%). An increased risk was observed in men with CD4  +  cell counts greater than 400 cells/mm  3  (6% versus 1% for men with CD4  +  cell counts less than 400 cells/mm  3  ). However, all patients, regardless of gender, CD4  +  cell count, or antiretroviral treatment history, should be monitored for hepatotoxicity since symptomatic hepatic adverse events have been reported at all CD4  +  cell counts. Co-infection with hepatitis B or C and/or increased transaminase elevations at the start of therapy with nevirapine are associated with a greater risk of later symptomatic events (6 weeks or more after starting nevirapine) and asymptomatic increases in AST or ALT.



 In addition, serious hepatotoxicity (including liver failure requiring transplantation in one instance) has been reported in HIV-1 uninfected individuals receiving multiple doses of immediate-release VIRAMUNE in the setting of post-exposure prophylaxis (PEP), an unapproved use. Use of VIRAMUNE XR for occupational and non-occupational PEP is contraindicated [  see Contraindications  (4.2)      ].



 Increased nevirapine trough concentrations have been observed in some patients with hepatic fibrosis or cirrhosis. Therefore, carefully monitor patients with either hepatic fibrosis or cirrhosis for evidence of drug-induced toxicity. Do not administer nevirapine to patients with moderate or severe (Child-Pugh Class B or C, respectively) hepatic impairment [  see Contraindications  (4.1)  , Use in Specific Populations  (8.7)  , and Clinical Pharmacology  (12.3)      ]. VIRAMUNE XR has not been evaluated in subjects with hepatic impairment.



    5.2  Skin Reactions



  Severe and life-threatening skin reactions, including fatal cases, have been reported in patients taking nevirapine. These have occurred most frequently during the first 6 weeks of therapy. These have included cases of Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, and hypersensitivity reactions characterized by rash, constitutional findings, and organ dysfunction including hepatic failure. Rhabdomyolysis has been observed in some patients experiencing skin and/or liver reactions associated with nevirapine use.



 Patients developing signs or symptoms of severe skin reactions or hypersensitivity reactions (including, but not limited to, severe rash or rash accompanied by fever, general malaise, fatigue, muscle or joint aches, blisters, oral lesions, conjunctivitis, facial edema, and/or hepatitis, eosinophilia, granulocytopenia, lymphadenopathy, and renal dysfunction) must permanently discontinue nevirapine and seek medical evaluation immediately [  see  Boxed Warning  and Patient Counseling Information  (17.1)      ]. Do not restart nevirapine following severe skin rash, skin rash combined with increased transaminases or other symptoms, or hypersensitivity reaction.



 If patients present with a suspected nevirapine-associated rash, measure transaminases immediately. Permanently discontinue nevirapine in patients with rash-associated transaminase elevations [  see Warnings and Precautions  (5.1)      ].



 Patients must initiate therapy with immediate-release VIRAMUNE daily for the first 14 days. This lead-in period has been shown to reduce the frequency of rash. Discontinue nevirapine if a patient experiences severe rash or any rash accompanied by constitutional findings. Do not initiate VIRAMUNE XR if a patient experiencing a mild to moderate rash without constitutional symptoms during the 14-day immediate-release VIRAMUNE lead-in period of 200 mg/day (150 mg/m  2  /day in pediatric patients) until the rash has resolved. The total duration of the immediate-release VIRAMUNE lead-in dosing period must not exceed 28 days at which point an alternative regimen should be sought [  see Dosage and Administration  (2.5)      ]. Patients must be monitored closely if isolated rash of any severity occurs. Delay in stopping nevirapine treatment after the onset of rash may result in a more serious reaction.



 Women appear to be at higher risk than men of developing rash with nevirapine.



 In a clinical trial of immediate-release VIRAMUNE, concomitant prednisone use (40 mg per day for the first 14 days of nevirapine administration) was associated with an increase in incidence and severity of rash during the first 6 weeks of nevirapine therapy. Therefore, use of prednisone to prevent nevirapine-associated rash is not recommended.



    5.3  Resistance



  VIRAMUNE XR must not be used as a single agent to treat HIV-1 or added on as a sole agent to a failing regimen. Resistant virus emerges rapidly when nevirapine is administered as monotherapy. The choice of new antiretroviral agents to be used in combination with nevirapine should take into consideration the potential for cross resistance. When discontinuing an antiretroviral regimen containing VIRAMUNE XR, the long half-life of nevirapine should be taken into account; if antiretrovirals with shorter half-lives than nevirapine are stopped concurrently, low plasma concentrations of nevirapine alone may persist for a week or longer and virus resistance may subsequently develop [  see Microbiology  (12.4)      ].



    5.4  Drug Interactions



  See Table 4 for listings of established and potential drug interactions [  see Drug Interactions  (7)      ].



 Concomitant use of St. John's wort (  Hypericum perforatum    ) or St. John's wort-containing products and nevirapine is not recommended. Co-administration of St. John's wort with non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NNRTIs), including nevirapine, is expected to substantially decrease NNRTI concentrations and may result in sub-optimal levels of nevirapine and lead to loss of virologic response and possible resistance to nevirapine or to the class of NNRTIs.



 Co-administration of nevirapine and efavirenz is not recommended as this combination has been associated with an increase in adverse reactions and no improvement in efficacy.



    5.5  Immune Reconstitution Syndrome



   Immune reconstitution syndrome has been reported in patients treated with combination antiretroviral therapy, including nevirapine. During the initial phase of combination antiretroviral treatment, patients whose immune system responds may develop an inflammatory response to indolent or residual opportunistic infections (such as  Mycobacterium avium    infection, cytomegalovirus,  Pneumocystis jiroveci    pneumonia, or tuberculosis), which may necessitate further evaluation and treatment.  



  Autoimmune disorders (such as Graves' disease, polymyositis, and Guillain-Barre syndrome) have also been reported to occur in the setting of immune reconstitution, however, the time to onset is more variable, and can occur many months after initiation of treatment.  



    5.6  Fat Redistribution



  Redistribution/accumulation of body fat including central obesity, dorsocervical fat enlargement (buffalo hump), peripheral wasting, facial wasting, breast enlargement, and "cushingoid appearance" have been observed in patients receiving antiretroviral therapy. The mechanism and long-term consequences of these events are currently unknown. A causal relationship has not been established.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
