<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="viramune0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6   ADVERSE REACTIONS

   EXCERPT:    *  The most common adverse reaction is rash. In adults the incidence of rash is 15% versus 6% with placebo, with Grade 3/4 rash occurring in 2% of subjects.  (6.1)   
 *  In pediatric subjects the incidence of rash (all causality) was 21%.  (6.2)   
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Boehringer Ingelheim Pharmaceuticals, Inc. at (800) 542-6257 or (800) 459-9906 TTY, or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1   Clinical Trial Experience in Adult Patients

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 The most serious adverse reactions associated with VIRAMUNE are hepatitis, hepatic failure, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, and hypersensitivity reactions. Hepatitis/hepatic failure may be isolated or associated with signs of hypersensitivity which may include severe rash or rash accompanied by fever, general malaise, fatigue, muscle or joint aches, blisters, oral lesions, conjunctivitis, facial edema, eosinophilia, granulocytopenia, lymphadenopathy, or renal dysfunction  [see  Boxed Warning  and Warnings and Precautions  (5.1  ,  5.2)  ]  .



   

      Hepatic Reaction    



 In controlled clinical trials, symptomatic hepatic events regardless of severity occurred in 4% (range 0% to 11%) of subjects who received VIRAMUNE and 1% of subjects in control groups. Female gender and higher CD4  +  cell counts (greater than 250 cells/mm  3  in women and greater than 400 cells/mm  3  in men) place patients at increased risk of these events  [see  Boxed Warning  and Warnings and Precautions  (5.1)  ]  .



 Asymptomatic transaminase elevations (AST or ALT greater than 5X ULN) were observed in 6% (range 0% to 9%) of subjects who received VIRAMUNE and 6% of subjects in control groups. Co-infection with hepatitis B or C and/or increased transaminase elevations at the start of therapy with VIRAMUNE are associated with a greater risk of later symptomatic events (6 weeks or more after starting VIRAMUNE) and asymptomatic increases in AST or ALT.



 Liver enzyme abnormalities (AST, ALT, GGT) were observed more frequently in subjects receiving VIRAMUNE than in controls (see  Table 3  ).



   

      Skin Reaction    



 The most common clinical toxicity of VIRAMUNE is rash, which can be severe or life-threatening  [see  Boxed Warning  and Warnings and Precautions  (5.2)  ]  . Rash occurs most frequently within the first 6 weeks of therapy. Rashes are usually mild to moderate, maculopapular erythematous cutaneous eruptions, with or without pruritus, located on the trunk, face and extremities. In controlled clinical trials (Trials 1037, 1038, 1046, and 1090), Grade 1 and 2 rashes were reported in 13% of subjects receiving VIRAMUNE compared to 6% receiving placebo during the first 6 weeks of therapy. Grade 3 and 4 rashes were reported in 2% of VIRAMUNE recipients compared to less than 1% of subjects receiving placebo. Women tend to be at higher risk for development of VIRAMUNE-associated rash  [see  Boxed Warning  and Warnings and Precautions  (5.2)  ]  .



 Treatment-related, adverse experiences of moderate or severe intensity observed in greater than 2% of subjects receiving VIRAMUNE in placebo-controlled trials are shown in Table 2.



 Table 2 Percentage of Subjects with Moderate or Severe Drug-Related Events in Adult Placebo-Controlled Trials 
   1  Background therapy included 3TC for all subjects and combinations of NRTIs and PIs. Subjects had CD4  +  cell counts less than 200 cells/mm  3  .  2  Background therapy included ZDV and ZDV+ddI; VIRAMUNE monotherapy was administered in some subjects. Subjects had CD4  +  cell count greater than or equal to 200 cells/mm  3  .   
  
                              Trial 1090  1              Trials 1037, 1038, 1046  2       
                              VIRAMUNE                   Placebo                    VIRAMUNE                   Placebo                   
                              (n=1121)                   (n=1128)                   (n=253)                    (n=203)                   
 Median exposure (weeks)    58                         52                         28                         28                          
 Any adverse event          15%                        11%                        32%                        13%                         
 Rash                       5                          2                          7                          2                           
 Nausea                     1                          1                          9                          4                           
 Granulocytopenia           2                          3                          &lt;1                         0                           
 Headache                   1                          &lt;1                         4                          1                           
 Fatigue                    &lt;1                         &lt;1                         5                          4                           
 Diarrhea                   &lt;1                         1                          2                          1                           
 Abdominal pain             &lt;1                         &lt;1                         2                          0                           
 Myalgia                    &lt;1                         0                          1                          2                           
        
       Laboratory Abnormalities    



 Liver enzyme test abnormalities (AST, ALT) were observed more frequently in subjects receiving VIRAMUNE than in controls (Table 3). Asymptomatic elevations in GGT occur frequently but are not a contraindication to continue VIRAMUNE therapy in the absence of elevations in other liver enzyme tests. Other laboratory abnormalities (bilirubin, anemia, neutropenia, thrombocytopenia) were observed with similar frequencies in clinical trials comparing VIRAMUNE and control regimens (see Table 3).



 Table 3 Percentage of Adult Subjects with Laboratory Abnormalities 
   1  Background therapy included 3TC for all subjects and combinations of NRTIs and PIs. Subjects had CD4  +  cell counts less than 200 cells/mm  3  .  2  Background therapy included ZDV and ZDV+ddI; VIRAMUNE monotherapy was administered in some subjects. Subjects had CD4  +  cell count greater than or equal to 200 cells/mm  3  .   
  
                              Trial 1090  1              Trials 1037, 1038, 1046  2       
                              VIRAMUNE                   Placebo                    VIRAMUNE                   Placebo                   
   Laboratory Abnormality      (n=1121)                   (n=1128)                   (n=253)                    (n=203)                   
   Blood Chemistry                                                                                                                       
   SGPT (ALT) &gt;250 U/L      5                          4                          14                         4                           
   SGOT (AST) &gt;250 U/L      4                          3                          8                          2                           
   Bilirubin &gt;2.5 mg/dL     2                          2                          2                          2                           
   Hematology                                                                                                                            
   Hemoglobin &lt;8.0 g/dL     3                          4                          0                          0                           
   Platelets &lt;50,000/mm  3    1                          1                          &lt;1                         2                           
   Neutrophils &lt;750/mm  3    13                         14                         4                          1                           
        6.2   Clinical Trial Experience in Pediatric Patients
   Adverse events were assessed in BI Trial 1100.1032 (ACTG 245), a double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of VIRAMUNE (n=305) in which pediatric subjects received combination treatment with VIRAMUNE. In this trial two subjects were reported to experience Stevens-Johnson syndrome or Stevens-Johnson/toxic epidermal necrolysis transition syndrome. Safety was also assessed in trial BI 1100.882 (ACTG 180), an open-label trial of VIRAMUNE (n=37) in which subjects were followed for a mean duration of 33.9 months (range: 6.8 months to 5.3 years, including long-term follow-up in 29 of these subjects in trial BI 1100.892). The most frequently reported adverse events related to VIRAMUNE in pediatric subjects were similar to those observed in adults, with the exception of granulocytopenia, which was more commonly observed in children receiving both zidovudine and VIRAMUNE. Cases of allergic reaction, including one case of anaphylaxis, were also reported.



 The safety of VIRAMUNE was also examined in BI Trial 1100.1368, an open-label, randomized clinical trial performed in South Africa in which 123 HIV-1 infected treatment-naive subjects between 3 months and 16 years of age received combination treatment with VIRAMUNE oral suspension, lamivudine and zidovudine for 48 weeks  [see Use In Specific Populations  (8.4)  and Clinical Pharmacology  (12.3)  ]  . Rash (all causality) was reported in 21% of the subjects, 4 (3%) of whom discontinued drug due to rash. All 4 subjects experienced the rash early in the course of therapy (less than 4 weeks) and resolved upon nevirapine discontinuation. Other clinically important adverse events (all causality) include neutropenia (9%), anemia (7%), and hepatotoxicity (2%)  [see Use in Specific Populations  (8.4)  and Clinical Studies  (14.2)  ]  .



 Safety information on use of VIRAMUNE in combination therapy in pediatric subjects 2 weeks to less than 3 months of age was assessed in 36 subjects from the BI 1100.1222 (PACTG 356) trial. No unexpected safety findings were observed although granulocytopenia was reported more frequently in this age group compared to the older pediatric age groups and adults.



   6.3   Post-Marketing Experience

  In addition to the adverse events identified during clinical trials, the following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of VIRAMUNE. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 *      Body as a Whole: fever, somnolence, drug withdrawal [see Drug Interactions  (7)  ] , redistribution/accumulation of body fat [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.6)  ]  
 *      Gastrointestinal: vomiting 
 *      Liver and Biliary: jaundice, fulminant and cholestatic hepatitis, hepatic necrosis, hepatic failure 
 *      Hematology: anemia, eosinophilia, neutropenia 
 *      Investigations: decreased serum phosphorus 
 *      Musculoskeletal: arthralgia, rhabdomyolysis associated with skin and/or liver reactions 
 *      Neurologic: paraesthesia 
 *      Skin and Appendages: allergic reactions including anaphylaxis, angioedema, bullous eruptions, ulcerative stomatitis and urticaria have all been reported. In addition, hypersensitivity syndrome and hypersensitivity reactions with rash associated with constitutional findings such as fever, blistering, oral lesions, conjunctivitis, facial edema, muscle or joint aches, general malaise, fatigue, or significant hepatic abnormalities, drug reaction with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms (DRESS) [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.1)  ] plus one or more of the following: hepatitis, eosinophilia, granulocytopenia, lymphadenopathy, and/or renal dysfunction have been reported. 
    In post-marketing surveillance anemia has been more commonly observed in children although development of anemia due to concomitant medication use cannot be ruled out.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: LIFE-THREATENING (INCLUDING FATAL) HEPATOTOXICITY and SKIN

REACTIONS

  WARNING: LIFE-THREATENING (INCLUDING FATAL) HEPATOTOXICITY and SKIN

REACTIONS

    HEPATOTOXICITY:  



   Severe, life-threatening,

and in some cases fatal hepatotoxicity, particularly in the first

18 weeks, has been reported in patients treated with VIRAMUNE. In

some cases, patients presented with non-specific prodromal signs or

symptoms of hepatitis and progressed to hepatic failure. These events

are often associated with rash. Female gender and higher CD4  +   cell counts at initiation of therapy place patients

at increased risk; women with CD4  +   cell

counts greater than 250 cells/mm  3  , including

pregnant women receiving VIRAMUNE in combination with other antiretrovirals

for the treatment of HIV-1 infection, are at the greatest risk. However,

hepatotoxicity associated with VIRAMUNE use can occur in both genders,

all CD4  +   cell counts and at any time during

treatment. Hepatic failure has also been reported in patients without

HIV taking VIRAMUNE for post-exposure prophylaxis (PEP). Use of VIRAMUNE

for occupational and non-occupational PEP is contraindicated   [see Contraindications   (4.2)  ]  . Patients with signs or symptoms of hepatitis, or with increased

transaminases combined with rash or other systemic symptoms, must

discontinue VIRAMUNE and seek medical evaluation immediately   [see Warnings and Precautions   (5.1)  ]  .  



   SKIN

REACTIONS:  



   Severe,

life-threatening skin reactions, including fatal cases, have occurred

in patients treated with VIRAMUNE. These have included cases of Stevens-Johnson

syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, and hypersensitivity reactions

characterized by rash, constitutional findings, and organ dysfunction.

Patients developing signs or symptoms of severe skin reactions or

hypersensitivity reactions must discontinue VIRAMUNE and seek medical

evaluation immediately. Transaminase levels should be checked immediately

for all patients who develop a rash in the first 18 weeks of treatment.

The 14-day lead-in period with VIRAMUNE 200 mg daily dosing has been

observed to decrease the incidence of rash and must be followed   [see Warnings and Precautions   (5.2)  ]  .  



   MONITORING:  



   Patients must be monitored

intensively during the first 18 weeks of therapy with VIRAMUNE to

detect potentially life-threatening hepatotoxicity or skin reactions.

Extra vigilance is warranted during the first 6 weeks of therapy,

which is the period of greatest risk of these events. Do not restart

VIRAMUNE following clinical hepatitis, or transaminase elevations

combined with rash or other systemic symptoms, or following severe

skin rash or hypersensitivity reactions. In some cases, hepatic injury

has progressed despite discontinuation of treatment.   



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: LIFE-THREATENING (INCLUDING FATAL)

HEPATOTOXICITY and SKIN REACTIONS



     See full prescribing information

for complete boxed warning.    



 *  Fatal and non-fatal hepatotoxicity (5.1) 
 *  Fatal and non-fatal skin reactions (5.2) 
      Discontinue immediately if experiencing:  
 

 *  Signs or symptoms of hepatitis (5.1) 
 *  Increased transaminases combined with rash or other systemic symptoms (5.1) 
 *  Severe skin or hypersensitivity reactions (5.2) 
 *  Any rash with systemic symptoms (5.2) 
      Monitoring during the first 18 weeks
 of therapy is essential. Extra vigilance is warranted during the first

6 weeks of therapy, which is the period of greatest risk of these

events.   (5)    
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5   WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  The most serious adverse reactions associated with VIRAMUNE are hepatitis/hepatic failure, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, and hypersensitivity reactions. Hepatitis/hepatic failure may be associated with signs of hypersensitivity which can include severe rash or rash accompanied by fever, general malaise, fatigue, muscle or joint aches, blisters, oral lesions, conjunctivitis, facial edema, eosinophilia, granulocytopenia, lymphadenopathy, or renal dysfunction.



  The first 18 weeks of therapy with VIRAMUNE are a critical period during which intensive clinical and laboratory monitoring of patients is required to detect potentially life-threatening hepatic events and skin reactions.  The optimal frequency of monitoring during this time period has not been established. Some experts recommend clinical and laboratory monitoring more often than once per month, and in particular, include monitoring of liver enzyme tests at baseline, prior to dose escalation and at two weeks post-dose escalation. After the initial 18-week period, frequent clinical and laboratory monitoring should continue throughout VIRAMUNE treatment. In addition, the 14-day lead-in period with VIRAMUNE 200 mg daily dosing has been demonstrated to reduce the frequency of rash [see Dosage and Administration  (2.1)  ]  .



    EXCERPT:    *  Hepatotoxicity: Fatal and non-fatal hepatotoxicity has been reported. Monitor liver function tests before and during therapy. Permanently discontinue nevirapine if clinical hepatitis or transaminase elevations combined with rash or other systemic symptoms occur. Do not restart nevirapine after recovery.  (5.1)   
 *  Rash: Fatal and non-fatal skin reactions, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, and hypersensitivity reactions, have been reported. Permanently discontinue nevirapine if severe skin reactions or hypersensitivity reactions occur. Check transaminase levels immediately for all patients who develop a rash in the first 18 weeks of treatment.  (5.2)   
 *  Monitor patients for immune reconstitution syndrome and fat redistribution.  (5.5  ,  5.6)   
    
 

   5.1   Hepatotoxicity and Hepatic Impairment



  Severe, life-threatening, and in some cases fatal hepatotoxicity, including fulminant and cholestatic hepatitis, hepatic necrosis and hepatic failure, have been reported in patients treated with VIRAMUNE. In controlled clinical trials, symptomatic hepatic events regardless of severity occurred in 4% (range 0% to 11%) of subjects who received VIRAMUNE and 1% of subjects in control groups.



 The risk of symptomatic hepatic events regardless of severity was greatest in the first 6 weeks of therapy. The risk continued to be greater in the VIRAMUNE groups compared to controls through 18 weeks of treatment. However, hepatic events may occur at any time during treatment. In some cases, subjects presented with non-specific, prodromal signs or symptoms of fatigue, malaise, anorexia, nausea, jaundice, liver tenderness or hepatomegaly, with or without initially abnormal serum transaminase levels. Rash was observed in approximately half of the subjects with symptomatic hepatic adverse events. Fever and flu-like symptoms accompanied some of these hepatic events. Some events, particularly those with rash and other symptoms, have progressed to hepatic failure with transaminase elevation, with or without hyperbilirubinemia, hepatic encephalopathy, prolonged partial thromboplastin time, or eosinophilia. Rhabdomyolysis has been observed in some patients experiencing skin and/or liver reactions associated with VIRAMUNE use. Patients with signs or symptoms of hepatitis must be advised to discontinue VIRAMUNE and immediately seek medical evaluation, which should include liver enzyme tests.



  Transaminases should be checked immediately if a patient experiences signs or symptoms suggestive of hepatitis and/or hypersensitivity reaction. Transaminases should also be checked immediately for all patients who develop a rash in the first 18 weeks of treatment. Physicians and patients should be vigilant for the appearance of signs or symptoms of hepatitis, such as fatigue, malaise, anorexia, nausea, jaundice, bilirubinuria, acholic stools, liver tenderness or hepatomegaly. The diagnosis of hepatotoxicity should be considered in this setting, even if transaminases are initially normal or alternative diagnoses are possible   [see  Boxed Warning  and Dosage and Administration  (2.3)  ]  .



 If clinical hepatitis or transaminase elevations combined with rash or other systemic symptoms occur, permanently discontinue VIRAMUNE. Do not restart VIRAMUNE after recovery. In some cases, hepatic injury progresses despite discontinuation of treatment.



 The patients at greatest risk of hepatic events, including potentially fatal events, are women with high CD4  +  cell counts. In general, during the first 6 weeks of treatment, women have a 3-fold higher risk than men for symptomatic, often rash-associated, hepatic events (6% versus 2%), and patients with higher CD4  +  cell counts at initiation of VIRAMUNE therapy are at higher risk for symptomatic hepatic events with VIRAMUNE. In a retrospective review, women with CD4  +  cell counts greater than 250 cells/mm  3  had a 12-fold higher risk of symptomatic hepatic adverse events compared to women with CD4  +  cell counts less than 250 cells/mm  3  (11% versus 1%). An increased risk was observed in men with CD4  +  cell counts greater than 400 cells/mm  3  (6% versus 1% for men with CD4  +  cell counts less than 400 cells/mm  3  ). However, all patients, regardless of gender, CD4  +  cell count, or antiretroviral treatment history, should be monitored for hepatotoxicity since symptomatic hepatic adverse events have been reported at all CD4  +  cell counts. Co-infection with hepatitis B or C and/or increased transaminase elevations at the start of therapy with VIRAMUNE are associated with a greater risk of later symptomatic events (6 weeks or more after starting VIRAMUNE) and asymptomatic increases in AST or ALT.



 In addition, serious hepatotoxicity (including liver failure requiring transplantation in one instance) has been reported in HIV-1 uninfected individuals receiving multiple doses of VIRAMUNE in the setting of post-exposure prophylaxis (PEP), an unapproved use. Use of VIRAMUNE for occupational and non-occupational PEP is contraindicated [see Contraindications  (4.2)  ]  .



 Increased nevirapine trough concentrations have been observed in some patients with hepatic fibrosis or cirrhosis. Therefore, carefully monitor patients with either hepatic fibrosis or cirrhosis for evidence of drug-induced toxicity. Do not administer nevirapine to patients with moderate or severe (Child-Pugh Class B or C, respectively) hepatic impairment [see Contraindications  (4.1)  , Use in Specific Populations  (8.7)  , and Clinical Pharmacology  (12.3)  ]  .



    5.2   Skin Reactions



  Severe and life-threatening skin reactions, including fatal cases, have been reported, occurring most frequently during the first 6 weeks of therapy. These have included cases of Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, and hypersensitivity reactions characterized by rash, constitutional findings, and organ dysfunction including hepatic failure. Rhabdomyolysis has been observed in some patients experiencing skin and/or liver reactions associated with VIRAMUNE use. In controlled clinical trials, Grade 3 and 4 rashes were reported during the first 6 weeks in 2% of VIRAMUNE recipients compared to less than 1% of placebo subjects.



 Patients developing signs or symptoms of severe skin reactions or hypersensitivity reactions (including, but not limited to, severe rash or rash accompanied by fever, general malaise, fatigue, muscle or joint aches, blisters, oral lesions, conjunctivitis, facial edema, and/or hepatitis, eosinophilia, granulocytopenia, lymphadenopathy, and renal dysfunction) must permanently discontinue VIRAMUNE and seek medical evaluation immediately [see  Boxed Warning  ]  . Do not restart VIRAMUNE following severe skin rash, skin rash combined with increased transaminases or other symptoms, or hypersensitivity reaction.



 If patients present with a suspected VIRAMUNE-associated rash, measure transaminases immediately. Permanently discontinue VIRAMUNE in patients with rash-associated transaminase elevations [see Warnings and Precautions  (5.1)  ]  .



 Therapy with VIRAMUNE must be initiated with a 14-day lead-in period of 200 mg per day (150 mg/m  2  per day in pediatric patients), which has been shown to reduce the frequency of rash. Discontinue VIRAMUNE if a patient experiences severe rash or any rash accompanied by constitutional findings. Do not increase VIRAMUNE dose to a patient experiencing a mild to moderate rash without constitutional symptoms during the 14-day lead-in period of 200 mg per day (150 mg/m  2  /day in pediatric patients) until the rash has resolved. The total duration of the once-daily lead-in dosing period must not exceed 28 days at which point an alternative regimen should be sought [see Dosage and Administration  (2.4)  ]  . Patients must be monitored closely if isolated rash of any severity occurs. Delay in stopping VIRAMUNE treatment after the onset of rash may result in a more serious reaction.



 Women appear to be at higher risk than men of developing rash with VIRAMUNE.



 In a clinical trial, concomitant prednisone use (40 mg per day for the first 14 days of VIRAMUNE administration) was associated with an increase in incidence and severity of rash during the first 6 weeks of VIRAMUNE therapy. Therefore, use of prednisone to prevent VIRAMUNE-associated rash is not recommended.



    5.3   Resistance



  VIRAMUNE must not be used as a single agent to treat HIV-1 or added on as a sole agent to a failing regimen. Resistant virus emerges rapidly when nevirapine is administered as monotherapy. The choice of new antiretroviral agents to be used in combination with nevirapine should take into consideration the potential for cross resistance. When discontinuing an antiretroviral regimen containing VIRAMUNE, the long half-life of nevirapine should be taken into account; if antiretrovirals with shorter half-lives than VIRAMUNE are stopped concurrently, low plasma concentrations of nevirapine alone may persist for a week or longer and virus resistance may subsequently develop [see Microbiology  (12.4)  ]  .



    5.4   Drug Interactions



  See Table 4 for listings of established and potential drug interactions [see Drug Interactions  (7)  ]  .



 Concomitant use of St. John's wort ( Hypericum perforatum  ) or St. John's wort-containing products and VIRAMUNE is not recommended. Co-administration of St. John's wort with non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NNRTIs), including VIRAMUNE, is expected to substantially decrease NNRTI concentrations and may result in sub-optimal levels of VIRAMUNE and lead to loss of virologic response and possible resistance to VIRAMUNE or to the class of NNRTIs. Co-administration of VIRAMUNE and efavirenz is not recommended as this combination has been associated with an increase in adverse reactions and no improvement in efficacy.



    5.5   Immune Reconstitution Syndrome



  Immune reconstitution syndrome has been reported in patients treated with combination antiretroviral therapy, including VIRAMUNE. During the initial phase of combination antiretroviral treatment, patients whose immune system responds may develop an inflammatory response to indolent or residual opportunistic infections (such as Mycobacterium avium  infection, cytomegalovirus, Pneumocystis jiroveci  pneumonia, or tuberculosis), which may necessitate further evaluation and treatment.



 Autoimmune disorders (such as Graves' disease, polymyositis, and Guillain-Barre syndrome) have also been reported to occur in the setting of immune reconstitution, however, the time to onset is more variable, and can occur many months after initiation of treatment.



    5.6   Fat Redistribution



  Redistribution/accumulation of body fat including central obesity, dorsocervical fat enlargement (buffalo hump), peripheral wasting, facial wasting, breast enlargement, and "cushingoid appearance" have been observed in patients receiving antiretroviral therapy. The mechanism and long-term consequences of these events are currently unknown. A causal relationship has not been established.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
