<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="visipaque" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE EVENTS

  VISIPAQUE (iodixanol) injection was administered to 1244 patients. The comparators administered to 861 patients included low osmolar nonionic, and high and low osmolar ionic contrast media. For complete demographics, see  CLINICAL TRIALS  section.



 Serious, life-threatening and fatal reactions have been associated with the administration of iodine-containing contrast media, including VISIPAQUE Injection. In clinical trials, 3/1244 patients given VISIPAQUE Injection and 1/861 patients given a comparator died within 5 days or later after drug administration. Also, 7/1244 patients given VISIPAQUE Injection and 8/861 given a comparator had serious adverse events. Rare reports of anaphylaxis have been documented during postmarket surveillance.



 As with other contrast agents, VISIPAQUE is often associated with sensations of discomfort, warmth or pain. In a subgroup of 1259 patients, for whom data are available; similar percentages of patients (30%) who received VISIPAQUE or a comparator had application site discomfort, pain, warmth or cold. VISIPAQUE had a trend toward fewer patient reports of moderate or severe pain or warmth; however, whether or not this related to the dose, rate of administration, site of injection or concentration has not been determined.



 The following table of incidence of events is based upon blinded, controlled clinical trials with VISIPAQUE Injection in controlled clinical studies in which VISIPAQUE (1244 patients) was compared with low osmolar nonionic (iohexol, iopromide), a low osmolar ionic (ioxaglate), and a high osmolar ionic (diatrizoate) contrast agents. This listing includes all reported adverse events regardless of attribution. Adverse events (AEs) are listed by body system and in decreasing order of occurrence greater than 0.5% in the VISIPAQUE group.



 As the table shows, one or more adverse events were recorded in 248 of 1244 (20%) patients during the clinical trials, with the administration of VISIPAQUE Injection or within the defined duration of the study follow-up period (24 to 72 hours). In intravenous and intra-arterial procedures, the incidence and type adverse reaction was similar to those of the studied nonionic comparators (iohexol). In a 757 patient subgroup for which data are available, women reported more adverse events 83/299 (27.8%) than men 77/458 (16.2%). Women reported more chest pain (9/299 or 3%) than men (4/458 or 0.8%).



 EACH ADVERSE EVENT REPORTED IN CONTROLLED CLINICAL TRIALS IN GREATER THAN 0.5% OF THE ADULT VISIPAQUE INJECTION PATIENTS 
 NUMBER OF PATIENTS EXPOSED  VISIPAQUEN=1244             Pooled ComparatorsN=861    
  
 (a) Does not include application site.   
  
 Number of Patients With Any Adverse Event  248 (19.9%)                       194 (22.5%)          
 Body As a Whole            Patients With Any Event            41 (3.3%)                  22 (2.6%)           
 Edema (any location)       7 (0.6%)                            0 (0%)             
 Cardiovascular             Patients With Any Event            37 (3.0%)                  39 (4.5%)           
 Angina Pectoris/Chest Pain  28 (2.2%)                          22 (2.6%)           
 Gastrointestinal           Patients WIth Any Event            51 (4.1%)                  46 (5.3%)           
 Diarrhea                   7 (0.6%)                           6 (0.7%)            
 Nausea                     35 (2.8%)                          32 (3.7%)           
 Vomiting                   10 (0.8%)                          11 (1.3%)           
 Nervous System             Patients With Any Event           101 (8.1%)                  60 (7.0%)           
 Agitation, Anxiety, Insomnia, Nervousness  10 (0.8%)                           0 (0%)             
 Dizziness                  8 (0.7%)                           8 (0.9%)            
 Headache/Migraine          31 (2.5%)                          15 (1.7%)           
 Paresthesia                12 (1.0%)                          1 (0.1%)            
 Sensory Disturbance        10 (0.8%)                          9 (1.0%)            
 Syncope                    8 (0.6%)                           1 (0.1%)            
 Vertigo                    30 (2.4%)                          20 (2.3%)           
 Skin                       Patients With Any Event (a)          42 (4.6%)                  18 (2.1%)           
 Nonurticarial Rash or Erythema  26 (2.1%)                          4 (0.5%)            
 Pruritus                   20 (1.6%)                          3 (0.3%)            
 Urticaria                  6 (0.5%)                           10 (1.2%)           
 Special Senses             Patients With Any Event            57 (4.6%)                  38 (4.4%)           
 Parosmia                   6 (0.5%)                           4 (0.5%)            
 Taste Perversion           43 (3.5%)                          32 (3.7%)           
 Scotoma                    14 (1.1%)                          2 (0.2%)            
          The following selected adverse events were reported in &lt;=0.5% of the 1244 patients in controlled clinical trials who received VISIPAQUE Injection.
 

   Body as a Whole-General Disorders:  back pain, fatigue, malaise.



   Cardiovascular Disorders:  arrhythmias, cardiac failure, conduction abnormalities, hypotension, myocardial infarction.



   Nervous System:  cerebral vascular disorder, convulsions, hypoesthesia, stupor, confusion.



   Gastrointestinal System Disorders:  dyspepsia.



   Hypersensitivity Disorders:  pharyngeal edema.



   RespiratorySystem Disorders:  asthma, bronchitis, dyspnea, pulmonary edema, rhinitis.



   Renal System Disorders:  abnormal renal function, acute renal failure, hematuria.



   Peripheral Vascular Disorders:  flushing, peripheral ischemia.



   Skin and Appendage Disorders:  hematoma, increased sweating.



   Special Senses, Other Disorders:  tinnitus.



   Vision Disorders:  abnormal vision.



 Additional adverse events reported in other clinical studies and in foreign postmarketing surveillance and foreign clinical trials with the use of VISIPAQUE Injection are: anaphylactic reactions, anaphylactoid reactions, hypoglycemia, amnesia, cardiac arrest, hypertension, dyskinesia, hemorrhage not otherwise specified, polymyalgia rheumatica, pulmonary embolism, respiratory depression, and cortical blindness.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
