<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="vistogard" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions occurring in &gt;2% of patients receiving VISTOGARD included vomiting, nausea, and diarrhea. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Wellstat Therapeutics Corporation at (1-800-914-0071) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions and using a wide range of doses, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of VISTOGARD was assessed in 135 patients (median age 59 years, 56% male) treated in 2 single-arm, open-label, multi-center trials. VISTOGARD was administered at 10 grams orally every 6 hours for 20 doses or at a body surface area adjusted dosage of 6.2 grams/m  2  /dose for 20 doses in four patients between 1 and 7 years of age. The median duration of exposure was 4.8 days, with a median of 20 doses (range 1 to 23). VISTOGARD was discontinued for adverse reactions in two (1.4%) patients. Serious adverse reactions and Grade &gt;=3 adverse reactions were seen in one patient receiving VISTOGARD (Grade 3 nausea and vomiting). Table 2 summarizes the adverse reactions that occurred in greater than 2% of patients in Studies 1 and 2 combined.



 Table 2 Adverse Reactions in &gt; 2% of Patients Receiving VISTOGARD in Studies 1 and 2 
                  Adverse Reaction                                     N=135 Patients                     
  
                      Vomiting                                            13 (10%)                        
                       Nausea                                              7 (5%)                         
                      Diarrhea                                             4 (3%)                         
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  None.



   EXCERPT:   None. (  5  )
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
