<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="vistide" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

    *  1.   Nephrotoxicity: Renal toxicity, as manifested by &gt;= 2+ proteinuria, serum creatinine elevations of &gt;= 0.4 mg/dL, or decreased creatinine clearance &lt;= 55 mL/min, occurred in 79 of 135 (59%) patients receiving VISTIDE at a maintenance dose of 5 mg/kg every other week. Maintenance dose reductions from 5 mg/kg to 3 mg/kg due to proteinuria or serum creatinine elevations were made in 12 of 41 (29%) patients who had not received prior therapy for CMV retinitis (Study 106) and in 19 of 74 (26%) patients who had received prior therapy for CMV retinitis (Study 107). Prior foscarnet use has been associated with an increased risk of nephrotoxicity; therefore, such patients must be monitored closely (see  CONTRAINDICATIONS  ,  WARNINGS  ,  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION  ). 
 *  2.   Neutropenia: In clinical trials, at the 5 mg/kg maintenance dose, a decrease in absolute neutrophil count to &lt;= 500 cells/mm  3  occurred in 24% of patients. Granulocyte colony stimulating factor (GCSF) was used in 39% of patients. 
 *  3.   Decreased Intraocular Pressure/Ocular Hypotony  : Among the subset of patients monitored for intraocular pressure changes, a &gt;= 50% decrease from baseline intraocular pressure was reported in 17 of 70 (24%) patients at the 5 mg/kg maintenance dose. Severe hypotony (intraocular pressure of 0-1 mm Hg) has been reported in 3 patients. Risk of ocular hypotony may be increased in patients with preexisting diabetes mellitus. 
 *  4.   Anterior Uveitis/Iritis: Uveitis or iritis has been reported in clinical trials and during postmarketing in patients receiving VISTIDE therapy. Uveitis or iritis was reported in 15 of 135 (11%) patients receiving 5 mg/kg maintenance dosing. Treatment with topical corticosteroids with or without topical cycloplegic agents may be considered. Patients should be monitored for signs and symptoms of uveitis/iritis during VISTIDE therapy. 
 *  5.   Metabolic Acidosis  : A diagnosis of Fanconi's syndrome, as manifested by multiple abnormalities of proximal renal tubular function, was reported in 1% of patients. Decreases in serum bicarbonate to &lt;= 16 mEq/L occurred in 16% of cidofovir-treated patients. Cases of metabolic acidosis in association with liver dysfunction and pancreatitis resulting in death have been reported in patients receiving VISTIDE. 
    In clinical trials, VISTIDE was withdrawn due to adverse events in 39% of patients treated with 5 mg/kg every other week as maintenance therapy.
 

 The incidence of adverse reactions reported as serious in three controlled clinical studies in patients with CMV retinitis, regardless of presumed relationship to drug, is listed in Table 4.



 Table 4. Serious Clinical Adverse Events or Laboratory Abnormalities Occurring in &gt; 5% of Patients 
                                                                     N = 135# patients (%)   
  
 Proteinuria (&gt;= 100 mg/dL)                                                 68                (50)          
 Neutropenia (&lt;= 500 cells/mm  3  )                                         33                (24)          
 Decreased Intraocular Pressure                                             17                (24)          
 Decreased Serum Bicarbonate (&lt;= 16 mEq/L)                                  21                (16)          
 Fever                                                                      19                (14)          
 Infection                                                                  16                (12)          
 Creatinine Elevation (&gt;= 2.0 mg/dL)                                        16                (12)          
 Pneumonia                                                                  12                 (9)          
 Dyspnea                                                                    11                 (8)          
 Nausea with Vomiting                                                       10                 (7)          
         The most frequently reported adverse events regardless of relationship to study drugs (cidofovir or probenecid) or severity are shown in Table 5.
 

 The following additional list of adverse events/intercurrent illnesses have been observed in clinical studies of VISTIDE and are listed below regardless of causal relationship to VISTIDE. Evaluation of these reports was difficult because of the diverse manifestations of the underlying disease and because most patients received numerous concomitant medicines.



   Body as a Whole  : abdominal pain, accidental injury, AIDS, allergic reaction, back pain, catheter blocked, cellulitis, chest pain, chills and fever, cryptococcosis, cyst, death, face edema, flu-like syndrome, hypothermia, injection site reaction, malaise, mucous membrane disorder, neck pain, overdose, photosensitivity reaction, sarcoma, sepsis



   Cardiovascular System  : cardiomyopathy, cardiovascular disorder, congestive heart failure, hypertension, hypotension, migraine, pallor, peripheral vascular disorder, phlebitis, postural hypotension, shock, syncope, tachycardia, vascular disorder, edema



   Digestive System  : cholangitis, colitis, constipation, esophagitis, dyspepsia, dysphagia, fecal incontinence, flatulence, gastritis, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, gingivitis, hepatitis, hepatomegaly, hepatosplenomegaly, jaundice, abnormal liver function, liver damage, liver necrosis, melena, pancreatitis, proctitis, rectal disorder, stomatitis, aphthous stomatitis, tongue discoloration, mouth ulceration, tooth caries



   Endocrine System:  adrenal cortex insufficiency



   Hemic &amp; Lymphatic System  : hypochromic anemia, leukocytosis, leukopenia, lymphadenopathy, lymphoma like reaction, pancytopenia, splenic disorder, splenomegaly, thrombocytopenia, thrombocytopenic purpura



   Metabolic &amp; Nutritional System  : cachexia, dehydration, edema, hypercalcemia, hyperglycemia, hyperkalemia, hyperlipemia, hypocalcemia, hypoglycemia, hypoglycemic reaction, hypokalemia, hypomagnesemia, hyponatremia, hypophosphatemia, hypoproteinemia, increased alkaline phosphatase, increased BUN, increased lactic dehydrogenase, increased SGOT, increased SGPT, peripheral edema, respiratory alkalosis, thirst, weight loss, weight gain



   Musculoskeletal System  : arthralgia, arthrosis, bone necrosis, bone pain, joint disorder, leg cramps, myalgia, myasthenia, pathological fracture



   Nervous System  : abnormal dreams, abnormal gait, acute brain syndrome, agitation, amnesia, anxiety, ataxia, cerebrovascular disorder, confusion, convulsion, delirium, dementia, depression, dizziness, drug dependence, dry mouth, encephalopathy, facial paralysis, hallucinations, hemiplegia, hyperesthesia, hypertonia, hypotony, incoordination, increased libido, insomnia, myoclonus, nervousness, neuropathy, paresthesia, personality disorder, somnolence, speech disorder, tremor, twitching, vasodilatation, vertigo



   Respiratory System  : asthma, bronchitis, epistaxis, hemoptysis, hiccup, hyperventilation, hypoxia, increased sputum, larynx edema, lung disorder, pharyngitis, pneumothorax, rhinitis, sinusitis



   Skin &amp; Appendages  : acne, angioedema, dry skin, eczema, exfoliative dermatitis, furunculosis, herpes simplex, nail disorder, pruritus, rash, seborrhea, skin discoloration, skin disorder, skin hypertrophy, skin ulcer, sweating, urticaria



   Special Senses  : abnormal vision, amblyopia, blindness, cataract, conjunctivitis, corneal lesion, corneal opacity, diplopia, dry eyes, ear disorder, ear pain, eye disorder, eye pain, hyperacusis, iritis, keratitis, miosis, otitis externa, otitis media, refraction disorder, retinal detachment, retinal disorder, taste perversion, tinnitus, uveitis, visual field defect, hearing loss



   Urogenital System  : decreased creatinine clearance, dysuria, glycosuria, hematuria, kidney stone, mastitis, metorrhagia, nocturia, polyuria, prostatic disorder, toxic nephrophathy, urethritis, urinary casts, urinary incontinence, urinary retention, urinary tract infection



 Table 5. All Clinical Adverse Events, Laboratory Abnormalities or Intercurrent Illnesses Regardless of Severity Occurring in &gt; 15% of Patients 
                                                                     N = 115# patients (%)   
  
 Any Adverse Event                                                          115               (100)         
 Proteinuria (&gt;= 30 mg/dL)                                                  101               (88)          
 Nausea +/- Vomiting                                                        79                (69)          
 Fever                                                                      67                (58)          
 Neutropenia (&lt; 750 cells/mm  3  )                                          50                (43)          
 Asthenia                                                                   50                (43)          
 Headache                                                                   34                (30)          
 Rash                                                                       34                (30)          
 Infection                                                                  32                (28)          
 Alopecia                                                                   31                (27)          
 Diarrhea                                                                   30                (26)          
 Pain                                                                       29                (25)          
 Creatinine Elevation (&gt; 1.5 mg/dL)                                         28                (24)          
 Anemia                                                                     28                (24)          
 Anorexia                                                                   26                (23)          
 Dyspnea                                                                    26                (23)          
 Chills                                                                     25                (22)          
 Increased Cough                                                            22                (19)          
 Oral Moniliasis                                                            21                (18)          
           Reporting of Adverse Reactions
   Malignancies or serious adverse reactions that occur in patients who have received VISTIDE should be reported to Gilead in writing to the Director of Clinical Research, Gilead Sciences, Inc., 333 Lakeside Drive, Foster City, CA 94404 or by calling 1-800-GILEAD-5 (445-3235), or to FDA MedWatch 1-800-FDA-1088/fax 1-800-FDA-0178.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING

  WARNING

    RENAL IMPAIRMENT IS THE MAJOR TOXICITY OF VISTIDE. CASES OF ACUTE RENAL FAILURE RESULTING IN DIALYSIS AND/OR CONTRIBUTING TO DEATH HAVE OCCURRED WITH AS FEW AS ONE OR TWO DOSES OF VISTIDE. TO REDUCE POSSIBLE NEPHROTOXICITY, INTRAVENOUS PREHYDRATION WITH NORMAL SALINE AND ADMINISTRATION OF PROBENECID MUST BE USED WITH EACH VISTIDE INFUSION. RENAL FUNCTION (SERUM CREATININE AND URINE PROTEIN) MUST BE MONITORED WITHIN 48 HOURS PRIOR TO EACH DOSE OF VISTIDE AND THE DOSE OF VISTIDE MODIFIED FOR CHANGES IN RENAL FUNCTION AS APPROPRIATE (SEE   DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION  ). VISTIDE IS CONTRAINDICATED IN PATIENTS WHO ARE RECEIVING OTHER NEPHROTOXIC AGENTS.  



   NEUTROPENIA HAS BEEN OBSERVED IN ASSOCIATION WITH VISTIDE TREATMENT. THEREFORE, NEUTROPHIL COUNTS SHOULD BE MONITORED DURING VISTIDE THERAPY.  



   VISTIDE IS INDICATED ONLY FOR THE TREATMENT OF CMV RETINITIS IN PATIENTS WITH ACQUIRED IMMUNODEFICIENCY SYNDROME.  



   IN ANIMAL STUDIES CIDOFOVIR WAS CARCINOGENIC, TERATOGENIC AND CAUSED HYPOSPERMIA (SEE   CARCINOGENESIS, MUTAGENESIS, &amp; IMPAIRMENT OF FERTILITY  ).  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
