<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="visudyne" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Severe chest pain, vasovagal and hypersensitivity reactions have been reported. Vasovagal and hypersensitivity reactions on rare occasions can be severe. These reactions may include syncope, sweating, dizziness, rash, dyspnea, flushing and changes in blood pressure and heart rate. General symptoms can include headache, malaise, urticaria, and pruritus.



 The most frequently reported adverse events to Visudyne  (r)  (verteporfin for injection) are injection site reactions (including pain, edema, inflammation, extravasation, rashes, hemorrhage and discoloration) and visual disturbances (including blurred vision, flashes of light, decreased visual acuity and visual field defects, including scotoma). These events occurred in approximately 10%-30% of patients. The following events, listed by Body System, were reported more frequently with Visudyne therapy than with placebo therapy and occurred in 1%-10% of patients:



   Ocular Treatment Site:  Blepharitis, cataracts, conjunctivitis/conjunctival injection, dry eyes, ocular itching, severe vision decrease with or without subretinal/retinal or vitreous hemorrhage



   Body as a Whole:  Asthenia, fever, flu syndrome, infusion related pain primarily presenting as back pain, photosensitivity reactions



   Cardiovascular:  Atrial fibrillation, hypertension, peripheral vascular disorder, varicose veins



   Dermatologic:  Eczema



   Digestive:  Constipation, gastrointestinal cancers, nausea



   Hemic and Lymphatic:  Anemia, white blood cell count decreased, white blood cell count increased



   Hepatic:  Elevated liver function tests



   Metabolic/Nutritional:  Albuminuria, creatinine increased



   Musculoskeletal:  Arthralgia, arthrosis, myasthenia



   Nervous System:  Hypesthesia, sleep disorder, vertigo



   Respiratory:  Cough, pharyngitis, pneumonia



   Special Senses:  Cataracts, decreased hearing, diplopia, lacrimation disorder



   Urogenital:  Prostatic disorder



 Severe vision decrease, equivalent of &gt;=4 lines, within 7 days after treatment has been reported in 1%-5% of patients. Partial recovery of vision was observed in some patients. Photosensitivity reactions usually occurred in the form of skin sunburn following exposure to sunlight. The higher incidence of back pain in the Visudyne group occurred primarily during infusion.



 The following adverse events have occurred either at low incidence (&lt;1%) during clinical trials or have been reported during the use of Visudyne in clinical practice where these events were reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size and frequency of occurrence cannot be determined precisely. They have been chosen for inclusion based on factors such as seriousness, frequency of reporting, possible causal connection to Visudyne, or a combination of these factors:



   Ocular Treatment Site:  Retinal detachment (nonrhegmatogenous), retinal or choroidal vessel nonperfusion, retinal pigment epithelial tear



   Non-ocular Events:  Chest pain and other musculoskeletal pain during infusion
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
