<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="vivelle" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  See  BOXED WARNINGS, WARNINGS  and  PRECAUTIONS.  



       Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice. The adverse reaction information from clinical trials does, however, provide a basis for identifying the adverse events that appear to be related to drug use and for approximating rates.



       The following adverse events have been reported with Vivelle-Dot  (r)  (estradiol transdermal system) therapy:



 Table 3 Summary of Most Frequently Reported Adverse Experiences/Medical Events Regardless of Relationship Reported at a Frequency &gt;=5% 
                  Vivelle0.025 mg/day    (N=47)N (%)  Vivelle0.0375 mg/day    (N=130)N (%)  Vivelle0.05 mg/day    (N=103)N (%)  Vivelle0.075 mg/day    (N=46)N (%)  Vivelle0.1 mg/day    (N=132)N (%)  Placebo(N=157)N (%)   
   Gastrointestinal disorders     
 Constipation     2 (4.3)          5 (3.8)          4 (3.9)          3 (6.5)          2 (1.5)          4 (2.5)           
 Dyspepsia        4 (8.5)          12 (9.2)         3 (2.9)          2 (4.3)          0                10 (6.4)          
 Nausea           2 (4.3)          8 (6.2)          4 (3.9)          0                7 (5.3)          5 (3.2)           
   General disorders and    administration site    conditions  ***   
 Influenza-like illness  3 (6.4)          6 (4.6)          8 (7.8)          0                3 (2.3)          10 (6.4)          
 Pain NOS*        0                8 (6.2)          0                2 (4.3)          7 (5.3)          7 (4.5)           
   Infections and infestations     
 Influenza        4 (8.5)          4 (3.1)          6 (5.8)          0                10 (7.6)         14 (8.9)          
 Nasopharyngitis  3 (6.4)          16 (12.3)        10 (9.7)         9 (19.6)         11 (8.3)         24 (15.3)         
 Sinusitis NOS*   4 (8.5)          17 (13.1)        13 (12.6)        3 (6.5)          7 (5.3)          16 (10.2)         
 Upper respiratory tractinfection NOS*  3 (6.4)          8 (6.2)          11 (10.7)        4 (8.7)          6 (4.5)          9 (5.7)           
   Investigations     
 Weight increased  4 (8.5)          5 (3.8)          2 (1.9)          2 (4.3)          0                3 (1.9)           
   Musculoskeletal and connective    tissue disorders     
 Arthralgia       0                11 (8.5)         4 (3.9)          2 (4.3)          5 (3.8)          9 (5.7)           
 Back pain        4 (8.5)          10 (7.7)         9 (8.7)          4 (8.7)          14 (10.6)        10 (6.4)          
 Neck pain        3 (6.4)          4 (3.1)          4 (3.9)          0                6 (4.5)          2 (1.3)           
 Pain in limb     0                10 (7.7)         7 (6.8)          2 (4.3)          6 (4.5)          9 (5.7)           
   Nervous system disorders     
 Headache NOS*    7 (14.9)         35 (26.9)        32 (31.1)        23 (50.0)        34 (25.8)        37 (23.6)         
 Sinus headache   0                12 (9.2)         5 (4.9)          5 (10.9)         2 (1.5)          8 (5.1)           
   Psychiatric disorders     
 Anxiety NEC**    3 (6.4)          5 (3.8)          0                0                2 (1.5)          4 (2.5)           
 Depression       5 (10.6)         4 (3.1)          7 (6.8)          0                4 (3.0)          6 (3.8)           
 Insomnia         3 (6.4)          6 (4.6)          4 (3.9)          2 (4.3)          2 (1.5)          9 (5.7)           
   Reproductive system and    breast disorders     
 Breast tenderness  8 (17.0)         10 (7.7)         8 (7.8)          3 (6.5)          17 (12.9)        0                 
 Dysmenorrhea     0                0                0                3 (6.5)          0                0                 
 Intermenstrualbleeding  3 (6.4)          9 (6.9)          6 (5.8)          0                14 (10.6)        7 (4.5)           
   Respiratory, thoracic and    mediastinal disorders     
 Sinus congestion  0                4 (3.1)          3 (2.9)          3 (6.5)          6 (4.5)          7 (4.5)           
    Vascular disorders     
 Hot flushes NOS*  3 (6.4)          0                3 (2.9)          0                0                6 (3.8)           
 Hypertension NOS*  2 (4.3)          0                3 (2.9)          0                0                2 (1.3)           
                 Represents milligrams of estradiol delivered daily by each system
 

 * NOS represents not otherwise specified



 ** NEC represents not elsewhere classified



 *** Application site erythema and application site irritation were observed in a small number of patients (3.2% or less of patients across treatment groups.)



       The following additional adverse reactions have been reported with estrogen and/or progestin therapy:



   1.          Genitourinary system.  Changes in vaginal bleeding pattern and abnormal withdrawal bleeding or flow; breakthrough bleeding; spotting; dysmenorrhea, increase in size of uterine leiomyomata; vaginitis, including vaginal candidiasis; change in amount of cervical secretion; changes in cervical ectropion; ovarian cancer; endometrial hyperplasia; endometrial cancer.



   2.          Breasts.  Tenderness, enlargement, pain, nipple discharge, galactorrhea; fibrocystic breast changes; breast cancer.



   3.          Cardiovascular.  Deep and superficial venous thrombosis; pulmonary embolism; thrombophlebitis; myocardial infarction; stroke; increase in blood pressure.



   4.          Gastrointestinal.  Nausea, vomiting; abdominal cramps, bloating; cholestatic jaundice; increased incidence of gallbladder disease; pancreatitis, enlargement of hepatic hemangiomas.



   5.          Skin.  Chloasma or melasma, which may persist when drug is discontinued; erythema multiforme; erythema nodosum; hemorrhagic eruption; loss of scalp hair; hirsutism; pruritus, rash.



   6.          Eyes.  Retinal vascular thrombosis; intolerance to contact lenses.



   7.          Central nervous system.  Headache; migraine; dizziness; mental depression; chorea; nervousness; mood disturbances; irritability; exacerbation of epilepsy, dementia.



   8.          Miscellaneous.  Increase or decrease in weight; reduced carbohydrate tolerance; aggravation of porphyria; edema; arthralgias; leg cramps; changes in libido; anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reactions including urticaria and angioedema; hypocalcemia; exacerbation of asthma; increased triglycerides.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

  

  

       

   ESTROGENS INCREASE THE RISK OF ENDOMETRIAL CANCER  



 Close clinical surveillance of all women taking estrogens is important. Adequate diagnostic measures, including endometrial sampling when indicated, should be undertaken to rule out malignancy in all cases of undiagnosed persistent or recurring abnormal vaginal bleeding. There is no evidence that the use of "natural" estrogens results in a different endometrial risk profile than synthetic estrogens at equivalent estrogen doses. (See   WARNINGS, Malignant Neoplasms,     Endometrial Cancer  .)



 

       

 

       

 

       

   CARDIOVASCULAR AND OTHER RISKS  



 Estrogens with or without progestins should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease. (See   WARNINGS, Cardiovascular Disorders.  )



 

       

 The Women's Health Initiative (WHI) study reported increased risks of myocardial infarction, stroke, invasive breast cancer, pulmonary emboli, and deep vein thrombosis in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age), during 5 years of treatment with oral conjugated estrogens (CE 0.625 mg) combined with medroxyprogesterone acetate (MPA 2.5 mg) relative to placebo (see   CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY  ,   Clinical Studies  ).



 The Women's Health Initiative Memory Study (WHIMS), a substudy of WHI, reported increased risk of developing probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age or older during 4 years of treatment with oral conjugated estrogens plus medroxyprogesterone acetate relative to placebo. It is unknown whether this finding applies to younger postmenopausal women or to women taking estrogen alone therapy. (See   CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY, Clinical Studies  .)



 

       

 Other doses of oral conjugated estrogens with medroxyprogesterone acetate, and other combinations and dosage forms of estrogens and progestins were not studied in the WHI clinical trials and, in the absence of comparable data, these risks should be assumed to be similar.  Because of these risks, estrogens with or without progestins should be prescribed at the lowest effective doses and for the shortest duration consistent with treatment goals and risks for the individual woman.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
