<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="vivitrol" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Serious adverse reactions that may be associated with VIVITROL therapy in clinical use include: severe injection site reactions, eosinophilic pneumonia, serious allergic reactions, unintended precipitation of opioid withdrawal, accidental opioid overdose and depression and suicidality.



 The adverse events seen most frequently in association with VIVITROL therapy for alcohol dependence (ie, those occurring in &gt;= 5% and at least twice as frequently with VIVITROL than placebo) include nausea, vomiting, injection site reactions (including induration, pruritus, nodules and swelling), muscle cramps, dizziness or syncope, somnolence or sedation, anorexia, decreased appetite or other appetite disorders.



 The adverse events seen most frequently in association with VIVITROL therapy in opioid-dependent patients (ie, those occurring in &gt;= 2% and at least twice as frequently with VIVITROL than placebo) were hepatic enzyme abnormalities, injection site pain, nasopharyngitis, insomnia, and toothache.



   EXCERPT:   The adverse events seen most frequently in association with VIVITROL therapy for alcohol dependence (i.e, those occurring in &gt;=5% and at least twice as frequently with VIVITROL than placebo) include nausea, vomiting, injection site reactions (including induration, pruritus, nodules and swelling), muscle cramps, dizziness or syncope, somnolence or sedation, anorexia, decreased appetite or other appetite disorders (  6  ).



 The adverse events seen most frequently in association with VIVITROL therapy in opioid-dependent patients (i.e., those occurring in &gt;=2% of patients treated with VIVITROL and at least twice as frequently with VIVITROL than placebo) were hepatic enzyme abnormalities, injection site pain, nasopharyngitis, insomnia, and toothache (  6  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Alkermes, Inc. at 1-800-VIVITROL (1-800-848-4876) and/or email: usmedinfo@alkermes.com or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  .



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In all controlled and uncontrolled trials during the premarketing development of VIVITROL, more than 1100 patients with alcohol and/or opioid dependence have been treated with VIVITROL. Approximately 700 patients have been treated for 6 months or more, and more than 400 for 1 year or longer.



     Adverse Events Leading to Discontinuation of Treatment  



     Alcohol Dependence  



 In controlled trials of 6 months or less in alcohol-dependent patients, 9% of alcohol-dependent patients treated with VIVITROL discontinued treatment due to an adverse event, as compared to 7% of the alcohol-dependent patients treated with placebo. Adverse events in the VIVITROL 380-mg group that led to more dropouts than in the placebo-treated group were injection site reactions (3%), nausea (2%), pregnancy (1%), headache (1%), and suicide-related events (0.3%). In the placebo group, 1% of patients withdrew due to injection site reactions, and 0% of patients withdrew due to the other adverse events.



     Opioid Dependence  



 In a controlled trial of 6 months, 2% of opioid-dependent patients treated with VIVITROL discontinued treatment due to an adverse event, as compared to 2% of the opioid-dependent patients treated with placebo.



     Common Adverse Reactions  



     Alcohol Dependence  



   Table 1  lists all treatment-emergent clinical adverse reactions, regardless of causality, occurring in &gt;=5% of patients with alcohol dependence, for which the incidence was greater in the combined VIVITROL group than in the placebo group. A majority of patients treated with VIVITROL in clinical studies had adverse reactions with a maximum intensity of "mild" or "moderate".



 Table 1: Treatment-emergent Adverse Reactions (Reactions in &gt;=5% of patients with alcohol dependence treated with VIVITROL and occurring more frequently in the combined VIVITROL group than in the placebo group) 
          a) Includes the preferred terms: diarrhea NOS; frequent bowel movements; gastrointestinal upset; loose stools    
          b) Includes the preferred terms: abdominal pain NOS; abdominal pain upper; stomach discomfort; abdominal pain lower    
          c) Includes the preferred terms: nasopharyngitis; pharyngitis streptococcal; pharyngitis NOS    
          d) Includes the preferred terms: anxiety NEC; anxiety aggravated; agitation; obsessive compulsive disorder; panic attack; nervousness; posttraumatic stress    
          e) Includes the preferred terms: malaise; fatigue (these two comprise the majority of cases); lethargy; sluggishness    
          f) Includes the preferred terms: muscle cramps; spasms; tightness; twitching; stiffness; rigidity    
          g) Includes the preferred terms: rash NOS; rash papular; heat rash    
          h) Includes the preferred terms: headache NOS; sinus headache; migraine; frequent headaches    
  
   Body System             Adverse Reaction / Preferred Term      Placebo      Naltrexone for extended-release injectable suspension     
   N=214                   400 mgN=25              380 mgN=205      190 mgN=210      AllN=440     
   N                       %                       N      %      N      %      N       %      N       %     
 Gastrointestinal Disorders  Nausea                  24     11    8      32     68      33     53      25     129     29      
 Vomiting NOS            12                      6      3     12     28     14      22     10      53     12       
 Diarrhea  a)            21                      10     3     12     27     13      27     13      57     13       
 Abdominal pain  b)      17                      8      4     16     23     11      23     11      50     11       
 Dry Mouth               9                       4      6     24     10     5       8      4       24     5        
 Infections &amp; Infestations  Pharyngitis  c)         23     11    0      0      22      11     35      17     57      13      
 Psychiatric Disorders   Insomnia, sleep disorder  25     12    2      8      29      14     27      13     58      13      
 Anxiety  d)             17                      8      2     8      24     12      16     8       42     10       
 Depression              9                       4      0     0      17     8       7      3       24     5        
 General Disorders &amp; Administration Site Conditions  Any ISR                 106    50    22     88     142     69     121     58     285     65      
 Injection site tenderness  83                      39     18    72     92     45      89     42      199    45       
 Injection site induration  18                      8      7     28     71     35      52     25      130    30       
 Injection site pain     16                      7      0     0      34     17      22     10      56     13       
 Other ISR (primarily nodules, swelling)  8                       4      8     32     30     15      16     8       54     12       
 Injection site pruritus  0                       0      0     0      21     10      13     6       34     8        
 Injection site ecchymosis  11                      5      0     0      14     7       9      4       23     5        
 Asthenic conditions  e)    26                      12     3     12     47     23      40     19      90     20       
 Musculoskeletal &amp; Connective Tissue Disorders  Arthralgia, arthritis, joint stiffness  11     5     1      4      24      12     12      6      37      9       
 Back pain, back stiffness  10                      5      1     4      12     6       14     7       27     6        
 Muscle cramps  f)       3                       1      0     0      16     8       5      2       21     5        
 Skin &amp; Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  Rash  g)                8      4     3      12     12      6      10      5      25      6       
 Nervous System Disorders  Headache  h)            39     18    9      36     51      25     34      16     94      21      
 Dizziness, syncope      9                       4      4     16     27     13      27     13      58     13       
 Somnolence, sedation    2                       1      3     12     8      4       9      4       20     5        
 Metabolism &amp; Nutrition Disorders  Anorexia, appetite decreased NOS, appetite disorder NOS  6      3     5      20     30      14     13      6      48      11      
                      Opioid Dependence  
 

 In the open-label, long-term safety study conducted in the US, the commonly reported adverse reactions among the opioid-dependent patients in the study were similar to those commonly observed events in the alcohol-dependent populations in VIVITROL clinical trials as displayed in  Table 1  , above. For example, injection site reactions of all types, nausea and diarrhea occurred in more than 5% of patients on VIVITROL in the open-label study. In contrast, 48% percent, of the opioid-dependent patients had at least one adverse event in the "Infections and Infestations" Body System. Adverse Reactions/Preferred Terms of nasopharyngitis, upper respiratory tract infection, urinary tract infection, and sinusitis were most commonly reported.



 In the placebo-controlled study in opioid-dependent patients conducted in Russia, the overall frequency of adverse events was lower than in the U.S. population described above.  Table 2  lists treatment-emergent clinical adverse events, regardless of causality, occurring in &gt;=2% of patients with opioid dependence, for which the incidence was greater in the VIVITROL group than in the placebo group. All adverse events were assessed as having a maximum intensity of "mild" or "moderate."



 Table 2: Treatment-emergent Clinical Adverse Events (Events in &gt;=2% of patients with opioid dependence treated with VIVITROL and occurring more frequently in the VIVITROL group than in the placebo group) 
   Body System                 Adverse Event / Preferred Term      PlaceboN=124      VIVITROL 380 mgN=126     
   n                           %                     n             %           
 Investigations              Alanine aminotransferase increased  7             6            16              13               
 Aspartate aminotransferase increased  3                     2             13           10               
 Gamma-glutamyltransferase increased  4                     3             9            7                
 Infections and Infestations  Nasopharyngitis       3             2            9               7                
 Influenza                   5                     4             6            5                
 Psychiatric Disorders       Insomnia              1             1            8               6                
 Vascular Disorders          Hypertension          4             3            6               5                
 General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions  Injection site pain   1             1            6               5                
 Gastrointestinal Disorders  Toothache             2             2            5               4                
 Nervous System Disorders    Headache              3             2            4               3                
                Laboratory Tests  
 

   Eosinophil Count:



 In clinical trials, subjects on VIVITROL had increases in eosinophil counts relative to subjects on placebo. With continued use of VIVITROL, eosinophil counts returned to normal over a period of several months.



 Platelet Count:



 VIVITROL 380 mg was associated with a decrease in platelet count. In clinical trials, alcohol-dependent patients treated with VIVITROL experienced a mean maximal decrease in platelet count of 17.8 x 10  3  /muL, compared to 2.6 x 10  3  /muL in placebo patients.



 After 24 weeks of treatment, opioid-dependent patients treated with VIVITROL experienced a mean maximal decrease in platelet count of 62.8 x 10  3  /muL, compared to 39.9 x 10  3  /muL in placebo patients. In randomized controlled trials, VIVITROL was not associated with an increase in bleeding-related adverse events.



   Hepatic Enzyme Elevations:



 In short-term, controlled trials, in alcohol-dependent patients, the incidence of AST elevations associated with VIVITROL treatment was similar to that observed with oral naltrexone treatment (1.5% each) and slightly higher than observed with placebo treatment (0.9%).



 In the 6-month controlled trial conducted in opioid-dependent subjects, 89% had a baseline diagnosis of hepatitis C infection, and 41% had a baseline diagnosis of HIV infection. There were frequently observed elevated liver enzyme levels (ALT, AST, and GGT); these were more commonly reported as adverse events in the VIVITROL 380-mg group than in the placebo group. Patients could not enroll in this trial if they had a baseline ALT or AST value that was more than three times the upper limit of normal. More patients treated with VIVITROL in this study experienced treatment-emergent elevations in transaminases to more than three times the upper limit of normal than patients treated with placebo. Shifts to more than three times the upper limit of normal occurred in 20% of patients treated with VIVITROL as compared with 13% of placebo patients. Shifts in values of AST to more than three times the upper limit were also more common in the VIVITROL (14%) arm compared with the placebo (11%) arm. Opioid-dependent patients treated with VIVITROL experienced a mean maximal increase from baseline ALT levels of 61 IU/L compared with 48 IU/L in placebo patients. Similarly for AST, opioid-dependent patients treated with VIVITROL experienced a mean maximal increase from baseline AST levels of 40 IU/L compared with 31 IU/L in placebo patients.



   Creatinine Phosphokinase:



 In short-term controlled trials in alcohol-dependent patients, more patients treated with VIVITROL 380 mg (11%) and oral naltrexone (17%) shifted from normal creatinine phosphokinase (CPK) levels before treatment to abnormal CPK levels at the end of the trials, compared to placebo patients (8%). In open-label trials, 16% of patients dosed for more than 6 months had increases in CPK. For both the oral naltrexone and VIVITROL 380-mg groups, CPK abnormalities were most frequently in the range of 1-2 x ULN. However, there were reports of CPK abnormalities as high as 4x ULN for the oral naltrexone group, and 35 x ULN for the VIVITROL 380-mg group. Overall, there were no differences between the placebo and naltrexone (oral or injectable) groups with respect to the proportions of patients with a CPK value at least three times the upper limit of normal. No factors other than naltrexone exposure were associated with the CPK elevations.



 More opioid-dependent patients treated with VIVITROL 380-mg (39%) shifted from normal creatinine phosphokinase (CPK) levels before treatment to abnormal CPK levels during the study as compared to patients treated with placebo (32%). There were reports of CPK abnormalities as high as 41.8 x ULN for the placebo group, and 22.1 x ULN for the VIVITROL 380-mg group.



     Other Events Observed During the VIVITROL Clinical Studies  



 The following is a list of treatment-emergent adverse reactions reported by alcohol- and/or opioid-dependent subjects treated with VIVITROL in all clinical trials. The listing does not include those events already listed in the previous tables or elsewhere in labeling, those events for which a drug cause was remote, those events that were so general as to be uninformative, and those events reported only once that did not have a substantial probability of being acutely life-threatening.



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders  - lymphadenopathy (including cervical adenitis), white blood cell count increased



   Cardiac Disorders  - angina pectoris, angina unstable, atrial fibrillation, cardiac failure congestive, coronary artery atherosclerosis, myocardial infarction, palpitations



   Eye Disorders  - conjunctivitis, vision blurred



   Gastrointestinal Disorders  - abdominal discomfort, colitis, constipation, flatulence, gastroesophageal reflux disease, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, hemorrhoids, pancreatitis acute, paralytic ileus, perirectal abscess



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions  - chest pain, chest tightness, chills, face edema, irritability, lethargy, pyrexia, rigors



   Hepatobiliary Disorders  - cholecystitis acute, cholelithiasis



   Immune System Disorders  - seasonal allergy, hypersensitivity reaction (including angioneurotic edema and urticaria)



   Infections and Infestations  - bronchitis, gastroenteritis, laryngitis, pneumonia, sinusitis, tooth abscess, upper respiratory tract infection, urinary tract infection, advanced HIV disease in HIV-infected patients



   Investigations -  weight decreased, weight increased



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders  - appetite increased, dehydration, heat exhaustion, hypercholesterolemia



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders  -joint stiffness, muscle spasms, myalgia, pain in limb



   Nervous System Disorders  - cerebral arterial aneurysm, convulsions, disturbance in attention, dysgeusia, mental impairment, migraine, ischemic stroke, paresthesia



   Pregnancy, Puerperium, and Perinatal Conditions  - abortion missed



   Psychiatric Disorders  - abnormal dreams, agitation, alcohol withdrawal syndrome, euphoric mood, delirium, libido decreased



   Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal Disorders  - chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, dyspnea, pharyngolaryngeal pain, sinus congestion



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders  -night sweats, pruritus, sweating increased



   Vascular Disorders  -deep venous thrombosis, hot flushes, pulmonary embolism



   6.2 Postmarketing Reports

    Hypersensitivity Reactions including Anaphylaxis  



 Hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis have been reported during postmarketing surveillance.



   Reports From Other Intramuscular Drug Products Containing Polylactide-co-glycolide (PLG) Microspheres  



   Retinal Artery Occlusion  



 Retinal artery occlusion after injection with another drug product containing polylactide-co-glycolide (PLG) microspheres has been reported very rarely during postmarketing surveillance. This event has been reported in the presence of abnormal arteriovenous anastomosis. No cases of retinal artery occlusion have been reported during VIVITROL clinical trials or postmarketing surveillance. VIVITROL should be administered by intramuscular (IM) injection into the gluteal muscle, and care must be taken to avoid inadvertent injection into a blood vessel  [see Dosage and Administration (  2  )]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Vulnerability to Opioid Overdose: Following VIVITROL treatment opioid tolerance is reduced from pretreatment baseline, and patients are vulnerable to potentially fatal overdose at the end of a dosing interval, after missing a dose, or after discontinuing VIVITROL treatment. Attempts to overcome blockade may also lead to fatal overdose (  5.1  ). 
 *   Injection Site Reactions: In some cases, injection site reactions may be very severe. Some cases of injection site reactions required surgical intervention (  5.2  ). 
 *   Precipitation of Opioid Withdrawal: Opioid-dependent and opioid-using patients, including those being treated for alcohol dependence, should be opioid-free before starting VIVITROL treatment, and should notify healthcare providers of any recent opioid use. An opioid-free duration of a minimum of 7-10 days is recommended for patients to avoid precipitation of opioid withdrawal that may be severe enough to require hospitalization. (  5.3  ). 
 *   Hepatotoxicity: Cases of hepatitis and clinically significant liver dysfunction were observed in association with VIVITROL treatment during the clinical development program and in the postmarketing period. Discontinue use of VIVITROL in the event of symptoms or signs of acute hepatitis (  5.4  ). 
 *   Depression and Suicidality: Monitor patients for the development of depression or suicidal thinking (  5.5  ). 
 *   When Reversal of VIVITROL Blockade Is Required for Pain Management: In an emergency situation in patients receiving VIVITROL, suggestions for pain management include regional analgesia or use of non-opioid analgesics (  5.6  ). 
    
 

      5.1 Vulnerability to Opioid Overdose



  After opioid detoxification, patients are likely to have reduced tolerance to opioids. VIVITROL blocks the effects of exogenous opioids for approximately 28 days after administration. However, as the blockade wanes and eventually dissipates completely, patients who have been treated with VIVITROL may respond to lower doses of opioids than previously used, just as they would have shortly after completing detoxification. This could result in potentially life-threatening opioid intoxication (respiratory compromise or arrest, circulatory collapse, etc.) if the patient uses previously tolerated doses of opioids. Cases of opioid overdose with fatal outcomes have been reported in patients who used opioids at the end of a dosing interval, after missing a scheduled dose, or after discontinuing treatment.



    Patients should be alerted that they may be more sensitive to opioids, even at lower doses, after VIVITROL treatment is discontinued, especially at the end of a dosing interval (i.e., near the end of the month that VIVITROL was administered), or after a dose of VIVITROL is missed. It is important that patients inform family members and the people closest to the patient of this increased sensitivity to opioids and the risk of overdose [see Patient Counseling Information (  17  )].  



    There is also the possibility that a patient who is treated with VIVITROL could overcome the opioid blockade effect of VIVITROL. Although VIVITROL is a potent antagonist with a prolonged pharmacological effect, the blockade produced by VIVITROL is surmountable. The plasma concentration of exogenous opioids attained immediately following their acute administration may be sufficient to overcome the competitive receptor blockade. This poses a potential risk to individuals who attempt, on their own, to overcome the blockade by administering large amounts of exogenous opioids. Any attempt by a patient to overcome the antagonism by taking opioids is especially dangerous and may lead to life-threatening opioid intoxication or fatal overdose. Patients should be told of the serious consequences of trying to overcome the opioid blockade   [see Patient Counseling Information (  17  )]  .



       5.2 Injection Site Reactions



     VIVITROL injections may be followed by pain, tenderness, induration, swelling, erythema, bruising, or pruritus; however, in some cases injection site reactions may be very severe. In the clinical trials, one patient developed an area of induration that continued to enlarge after 4 weeks, with subsequent development of necrotic tissue that required surgical excision. In the postmarketing period, additional cases of injection site reaction with features including induration, cellulitis, hematoma, abscess, sterile abscess, and necrosis, have been reported. Some cases required surgical intervention, including debridement of necrotic tissue. Some cases resulted in significant scarring. The reported cases occurred primarily in female patients.



    VIVITROL is administered as an intramuscular gluteal injection, and inadvertent subcutaneous injection of VIVITROL may increase the likelihood of severe injection site reactions. The needles provided in the carton are customized needles. VIVITROL must not be injected using any other needle. The needle lengths (either 1.5 inches or 2 inches) may not be adequate in every patient because of body habitus. Body habitus should be assessed prior to each injection for each patient to assure that the proper needle is selected and that the needle length is adequate for intramuscular administration. For patients with a larger amount of subcutaneous tissue overlying the gluteal muscle, the administering healthcare provider may utilize the supplied 2-inch needle with needle protection device to help ensure that the injectate reaches the intramuscular mass. For very lean patients, the 1.5-inch needle may be appropriate to prevent the needle contacting the periosteum. Either needle may be used for patients with average body habitus. Healthcare providers should ensure that the VIVITROL injection is given correctly, and should consider alternate treatment for those patients whose body habitus precludes an intramuscular gluteal injection with one of the provided needles.



    Patients should be informed that any concerning injection site reactions should be brought to the attention of the healthcare provider [see Patient Counseling Information (  17  )]  . Patients exhibiting signs of abscess, cellulitis, necrosis, or extensive swelling should be evaluated by a physician to determine if referral to a surgeon is warranted.



       5.3 Precipitation of Opioid Withdrawal



  The symptoms of spontaneous opioid withdrawal (which are associated with the discontinuation of opioid in a dependent individual) are uncomfortable, but they are not generally believed to be severe or necessitate hospitalization. However, when withdrawal is precipitated abruptly by the administration of an opioid antagonist to an opioid-dependent patient  , the resulting withdrawal syndrome can be severe enough to require hospitalization. Review of postmarketing cases of precipitated opioid withdrawal in association with naltrexone treatment has identified cases with symptoms of withdrawal severe enough to require hospital admission, and in some cases, management in the intensive care unit.



 To prevent occurrence of precipitated withdrawal in patients dependent on opioids, or exacerbation of a pre-existing subclinical withdrawal syndrome, opioid-dependent patients, including those being treated for alcohol dependence, should be opioid-free (including tramadol) before starting VIVITROL treatment. An opioid-free interval of a minimum of 7-10 days is recommended for patients previously dependent on short-acting opioids. Patients transitioning from buprenorphine or methadone may be vulnerable to precipitation of withdrawal symptoms for as long as two weeks.



 If a more rapid transition from agonist to antagonist therapy is deemed necessary and appropriate by the healthcare provider, monitor the patient closely in an appropriate medical setting where precipitated withdrawal can be managed.



 In every case, healthcare providers should always be prepared to manage withdrawal symptomatically with non-opioid medications because there is no completely reliable method for determining whether a patient has had an adequate opioid-free period. A naloxone challenge test may be helpful; however, a few case reports have indicated that patients may experience precipitated withdrawal despite having a negative urine toxicology screen or tolerating a naloxone challenge test (usually in the setting of transitioning from buprenorphine treatment). Patients should be made aware of the risks associated with precipitated withdrawal and encouraged to give an accurate account of last opioid use. Patients treated for alcohol dependence with VIVITROL should also be assessed for underlying opioid dependence and for any recent use of opioids prior to initiation of treatment with VIVITROL. Precipitated opioid withdrawal has been observed in alcohol-dependent patients in circumstances where the prescriber had been unaware of the additional use of opioids or co-dependence on opioids.



       5.4 Hepatotoxicity



  Cases of hepatitis and clinically significant liver dysfunction were observed in association with VIVITROL exposure during the clinical development program and in the postmarketing period. Transient, asymptomatic hepatic transaminase elevations were also observed in the clinical trials and postmarketing period. Although patients with clinically significant liver disease were not systematically studied, clinical trials did include patients with asymptomatic viral hepatitis infections. When patients presented with elevated transaminases, there were often other potential causative or contributory etiologies identified, including pre-existing alcoholic liver disease, hepatitis B and/or C infection, and concomitant usage of other potentially hepatotoxic drugs. Although clinically significant liver dysfunction is not typically recognized as a manifestation of opioid withdrawal, opioid withdrawal that is precipitated abruptly may lead to systemic sequelae including acute liver injury.



 Patients should be warned of the risk of hepatic injury and advised to seek medical attention if they experience symptoms of acute hepatitis. Use of VIVITROL should be discontinued in the event of symptoms and/or signs of acute hepatitis.



    5.5 Depression and Suicidality



  Alcohol- and opioid-dependent patients, including those taking VIVITROL, should be monitored for the development of depression or suicidal thinking. Families and caregivers of patients being treated with VIVITROL should be alerted to the need to monitor patients for the emergence of symptoms of depression or suicidality, and to report such symptoms to the patient's healthcare provider.



    Alcohol Dependence  



 In controlled clinical trials of VIVITROL administered to adults with alcohol dependence, adverse events of a suicidal nature (suicidal ideation, suicide attempts, completed suicides) were infrequent overall, but were more common in patients treated with VIVITROL than in patients treated with placebo (1% vs 0). In some cases, the suicidal thoughts or behavior occurred after study discontinuation, but were in the context of an episode of depression that began while the patient was on study drug. Two completed suicides occurred, both involving patients treated with VIVITROL.



 Depression-related events associated with premature discontinuation of study drug were also more common in patients treated with VIVITROL (~1%) than in placebo-treated patients (0).



 In the 24-week, placebo-controlled pivotal trial in 624 alcohol-dependent patients, adverse events involving depressed mood were reported by 10% of patients treated with VIVITROL 380 mg, as compared to 5% of patients treated with placebo injections.



    Opioid Dependence  



 In an open-label, long-term safety study conducted in the US, adverse events of a suicidal nature (depressed mood, suicidal ideation, suicide attempt) were reported by 5% of opioid-dependent patients treated with VIVITROL 380 mg (n=101) and 10% of opioid-dependent patients treated with oral naltrexone (n=20). In the 24-week, placebo-controlled pivotal trial that was conducted in Russia in 250 opioid-dependent patients, adverse events involving depressed mood or suicidal thinking were not reported by any patient in either treatment group (VIVITROL 380 mg or placebo).



    5.6 When Reversal of VIVITROL Blockade Is Required for Pain Management



  In an emergency situation in patients receiving VIVITROL, suggestions for pain management include regional analgesia or use of non-opioid analgesics. If opioid therapy is required as part of anesthesia or analgesia, patients should be continuously monitored in an anesthesia care setting by persons not involved in the conduct of the surgical or diagnostic procedure. The opioid therapy must be provided by individuals specifically trained in the use of anesthetic drugs and the management of the respiratory effects of potent opioids, specifically the establishment and maintenance of a patent airway and assisted ventilation.



 Irrespective of the drug chosen to reverse VIVITROL blockade, the patient should be monitored closely by appropriately trained personnel in a setting equipped and staffed for cardiopulmonary resuscitation.



    5.7 Eosinophilic Pneumonia



  In clinical trials with VIVITROL, there was one diagnosed case and one suspected case of eosinophilic pneumonia. Both cases required hospitalization, and resolved after treatment with antibiotics and corticosteroids. Similar cases have been reported in postmarketing use. Should a person receiving VIVITROL develop progressive dyspnea and hypoxemia, the diagnosis of eosinophilic pneumonia should be considered [see Adverse Reactions (  6  )]  . Patients should be warned of the risk of eosinophilic pneumonia, and advised to seek medical attention should they develop symptoms of pneumonia. Clinicians should consider the possibility of eosinophilic pneumonia in patients who do not respond to antibiotics.



    5.8 Hypersensitivity Reactions Including Anaphylaxis



  Cases of urticaria, angioedema, and anaphylaxis have been observed with use of VIVITROL in the clinical trial setting and in postmarketing use. Patients should be warned of the risk of hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis. In the event of a hypersensitivity reaction, patients should be advised to seek immediate medical attention in a healthcare setting prepared to treat anaphylaxis. The patient should not receive any further treatment with VIVITROL.



    5.9 Intramuscular Injections



  As with any intramuscular injection, VIVITROL should be administered with caution to patients with thrombocytopenia or any coagulation disorder (eg, hemophilia and severe hepatic failure).



    5.10 Alcohol Withdrawal



  Use of VIVITROL does not eliminate nor diminish alcohol withdrawal symptoms.



    5.11 Interference with Laboratory Tests



  VIVITROL may be cross-reactive with certain immunoassay methods for the detection of drugs of abuse (specifically opioids) in urine. For further information, reference to the specific immunoassay instructions is recommended.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
