<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="vivlodex" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Cardiovascular Thrombotic Events [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *  GI Bleeding, Ulceration and Perforation [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
 *  Hepatotoxicity [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ] 
 *  Hypertension [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   ] 
 *  Heart Failure and Edema [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)   ] 
 *  Renal Toxicity and Hyperkalemia [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)   ] 
 *  Anaphylactic Reactions [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)   ] 
 *  Serious Skin Reactions [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)   ] 
 *  Hematologic Toxicity [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.11)   ] 
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=2% in controlled clinical trials of VIVLODEX 5 mg or 10 mg group) are diarrhea, nausea, abdominal discomfort. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Iroko Pharmaceuticals, LLC at 1-877-757-0676 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Adverse Reactions in Patients with Osteoarthritis Pain  



 Eight hundred sixty-eight (868) patients with osteoarthritis pain, ranging in age from 40 - 87 years, were enrolled in two Phase 3 clinical trials and received VIVLODEX 5 mg or 10 mg once daily. Fifty percent (50%) of patients were aged 61 years or older.



 Two hundred sixty-nine (269) patients received VIVLODEX 5 mg or 10 mg once daily in the 12-week, double-blind, placebo-controlled, clinical trial of osteoarthritis pain of the knee or hip. The most frequent adverse reactions in this study are summarized in Table 1.



 Table 1 Summary of Adverse Reactions (&gt;=2%) - 12-Week Phase 3 Study in Patients With Osteoarthritis Pain 
 Adverse Reactions                      VIVLODEX5 mg or 10 mgN=269                PlaceboN=133              
  
 Diarrhea                                           3%                                 1%                   
 Nausea                                             2%                                  0                   
 Abdominal Discomfort                               2%                                  0                   
         Six hundred (600) patients received VIVLODEX 10 mg once daily in a 52-week, open-label, clinical trial in osteoarthritis pain of the knee or hip. Of these, 390 (65%) patients completed the trial. The most frequent adverse reactions in this study are summarized in Table 2.
 

 Table 2 Summary of Adverse Reactions (&gt;=2%) - 52-Week Open-Label Study in Patients With Osteoarthritis Pain 
 Adverse Reactions                                                  VIVLODEX 10 mgN=600                   
  
 Arthralgia                                                                  6%                           
 Urinary Tract Infection                                                     6%                           
 Osteoarthritis                                                              5%                           
 Hypertension                                                                4%                           
 Diarrhea                                                                    4%                           
 Headache                                                                    4%                           
 Upper Respiratory Tract Infection                                           4%                           
 Back Pain                                                                   4%                           
 Nasopharyngitis                                                             4%                           
 Bronchitis                                                                  3%                           
 Sinusitis                                                                   3%                           
 Constipation                                                                3%                           
 Dyspepsia                                                                   3%                           
 Nausea                                                                      2%                           
 Edema Peripheral                                                            2%                           
 Pain in Extremity                                                           2%                           
        Additional adverse reactions reported for meloxicam:
 


                                                 
   Body as a Whole                              allergic reaction, face edema, fatigue, fever, hot flushes, malaise, syncope, weight decrease, weight increase   
   Cardiovascular                               angina pectoris, cardiac failure, hypertension, hypotension, myocardial infarction, vasculitis   
   Central and Peripheral Nervous System        convulsions, paresthesia, tremor, vertigo                 
   Gastrointestinal                             colitis, dry mouth, duodenal ulcer, eructation, esophagitis, gastric ulcer, gastritis, gastroesophageal reflux, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, hematemesis, hemorrhagic duodenal ulcer, hemorrhagic gastric ulcer, intestinal perforation, melena, pancreatitis, perforated duodenal ulcer, perforated gastric ulcer, stomatitis ulcerative   
   Heart Rate and Rhythm                        arrhythmia, palpitation, tachycardia                      
   Hematologic                                  agranulocytosis, leukopenia, purpura, thrombocytopenia    
   Immune System                                anaphylactoid reactions (including shock)                 
   Liver and Biliary System                     ALT increased, AST increased, bilirubinemia, GGT increased, hepatitis, jaundice, liver failure   
   Metabolic and Nutritional                    dehydration                                               
   Psychiatric                                  abnormal dreaming, alterations in mood (such as mood elevation), anxiety, appetite increased, confusion, depression, nervousness, somnolence,   
   Respiratory                                  asthma, bronchospasm, dyspnea                             
   Skin and Appendages                          alopecia, angioedema, bullous eruption, erythema multiforme, exfoliative dermatitis, photosensitivity reaction, pruritus, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, sweating increased, urticaria   
   Special Senses                               abnormal vision, conjunctivitis, taste perversion, tinnitus   
   Urinary System                               albuminuria, acute urinary retention, BUN increased, creatinine increased, hematuria, interstitial nephritis, renal failure,   
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: RISK OF SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL EVENTS

    WARNING: RISK OF SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL EVENTS  

  EXCERPT:     WARNING: RISK OF SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR AND GASTROINTESTINAL EVENTS  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) cause an increased risk of serious cardiovascular thrombotic events, including myocardial infarction and stroke, which can be fatal. This risk may occur early in treatment and may increase with duration of use. (5.1) 
 *  VIVLODEX is contraindicated in the setting of coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery. (4, 5.1) 
 *  NSAIDs cause an increased risk of serious gastrointestinal (GI) adverse events including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach or intestines, which can be fatal. These events can occur at any time during use and without warning symptoms. Elderly patients and patients with a prior history of peptic ulcer disease and/or GI bleeding are at greater risk for serious GI events. (5.2) 
    
 

    Cardiovascular Thrombotic Events  



 *  Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) cause an increased risk of serious cardiovascular thrombotic events, including myocardial infarction and stroke, which can be fatal. This risk may occur early in treatment and may increase with duration of use [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *  VIVLODEX is contraindicated in the setting of coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery [see Contraindications (4), Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
        Gastrointestinal Bleeding, Ulceration, and Perforation  
 

 *  NSAIDs cause an increased risk of serious gastrointestinal (GI) adverse events including bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the stomach or intestines, which can be fatal. These events can occur at any time during use and without warning symptoms. Elderly patients and patients with a prior history of peptic ulcer disease and/or GI bleeding are at greater risk for serious GI events [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]. 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Hepatotoxicity : Inform patients of warning signs and symptoms of hepatotoxicity. Discontinue if abnormal liver tests persist or worsen or if clinical signs and symptoms of liver disease develop (  5.3  ) 
 *   Hypertension : Patients taking some antihypertensive medications may have impaired response to these therapies when taking NSAIDs. Monitor blood pressure (  5.4  ,  7  ) 
 *   Heart Failure and Edema : Avoid use of VIVLODEX in patients with severe heart failure unless benefits are expected to outweigh risk of worsening heart failure (  5.5  ) 
 *   Renal Toxicity : Monitor renal function in patients with renal or hepatic impairment, heart failure, dehydration, or hypovolemia. Avoid use of VIVLODEX in patients with advanced renal disease unless benefits are expected to outweigh risk of worsening renal function (  5.6  ) 
 *   Anaphylactic Reactions : Seek emergency help if an anaphylactic reaction occurs (  5.7  ) 
 *   Exacerbation of Asthma Related to Aspirin Sensitivity : VIVLODEX is contraindicated in patients with aspirin-sensitive asthma. Monitor patients with preexisting asthma (without aspirin sensitivity) (  5.8  ) 
 *   Serious Skin Reactions : Discontinue VIVLODEX at first appearance of skin rash or other signs of hypersensitivity (  5.9  ) 
 *   Premature Closure of Fetal Ductus Arteriosus : Avoid use in pregnant women starting at 30 weeks gestation (  5.10  ,  8.1  ) 
 *   Hematologic Toxicity : Monitor hemoglobin or hematocrit in patients with any signs or symptoms of anemia (  5.11  ,  7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Cardiovascular Thrombotic Events



  Clinical trials of several COX-2 selective and nonselective NSAIDs of up to three years duration have shown an increased risk of serious cardiovascular (CV) thrombotic events, including myocardial infarction (MI) and stroke, which can be fatal. Based on available data, it is unclear that the risk for CV thrombotic events is similar for all NSAIDs. The relative increase in serious CV thrombotic events over baseline conferred by NSAID use appears to be similar in those with and without known CV disease or risk factors for CV disease. However, patients with known CV disease or risk factors had a higher absolute incidence of excess serious CV thrombotic events, due to their increased baseline rate. Some observational studies found that this increased risk of serious CV thrombotic events began as early as the first weeks of treatment. The increase in CV thrombotic risk has been observed most consistently at higher doses.



 To minimize the potential risk for an adverse CV event in NSAID-treated patients, use the lowest effective dose for the shortest duration possible. Physicians and patients should remain alert for the development of such events, throughout the entire treatment course, even in the absence of previous CV symptoms. Patients should be informed about the symptoms of serious CV events and the steps to take if they occur.



 There is no consistent evidence that concurrent use of aspirin mitigates the increased risk of serious CV thrombotic events associated with NSAID use. The concurrent use of aspirin and an NSAID, such as meloxicam, increases the risk of serious gastrointestinal (GI) events [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ].



    Status Post Coronary Artery Bypass Graft (CABG) Surgery  



 Two large, controlled clinical trials of a COX-2 selective NSAID for the treatment of pain in the first 10-14 days following CABG surgery found an increased incidence of myocardial infarction and stroke. NSAIDs are contraindicated in the setting of CABG [ see  Contraindications (4)    ].



    Post-MI Patients  



 Observational studies conducted in the Danish National Registry have demonstrated that patients treated with NSAIDs in the post-MI period were at increased risk of reinfarction, CV-related death, and all-cause mortality beginning in the first week of treatment. In this same cohort, the incidence of death in the first year post-MI was 20 per 100 person years in NSAID-treated patients compared to 12 per 100 person years in non-NSAID exposed patients. Although the absolute rate of death declined somewhat after the first year post-MI, the increased relative risk of death in NSAID users persisted over at least the next four years of follow-up.



 Avoid the use of VIVLODEX in patients with a recent MI unless the benefits are expected to outweigh the risk of recurrent CV thrombotic events. If VIVLODEX is used in patients with a recent MI, monitor patients for signs of cardiac ischemia.



    5.2 Gastrointestinal Bleeding, Ulceration, and Perforation



  NSAIDs, including meloxicam, cause serious gastrointestinal (GI) adverse events including inflammation, bleeding, ulceration, and perforation of the esophagus, stomach, small intestine, or large intestine, which can be fatal. These serious adverse events can occur at any time, with or without warning symptoms, in patients treated with VIVLODEX. Only one in five patients who develop a serious upper GI adverse event on NSAID therapy is symptomatic. Upper GI ulcers, gross bleeding, or perforation caused by NSAIDs occurred in approximately 1% of patients treated for 3-6 months, and in about 2%-4% of patients treated for one year. However, even short-term NSAID therapy is not without risk.



    Risk Factors for GI Bleeding, Ulceration, and Perforation  



 Patients with a prior history of peptic ulcer disease and/or GI bleeding who used NSAIDs had a greater than 10-fold increased risk for developing a GI bleed compared to patients without these risk factors. Other factors that increase the risk for GI bleeding in patients treated with NSAIDs include longer duration of NSAID therapy; concomitant use of oral corticosteroids, aspirin, anticoagulants, or selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs); smoking; use of alcohol; older age; and poor general health status. Most postmarketing reports of fatal GI events occurred in elderly or debilitated patients. Additionally, patients with advanced liver disease and/or coagulopathy are at increased risk for GI bleeding.



    Strategies to Minimize the GI Risks in NSAID-treated patients:  



 *  Use the lowest effective dosage for the shortest possible duration. 
 *  Avoid administration of more than one NSAID at a time. 
 *  Avoid use in patients at higher risk unless benefits are expected to outweigh the increased risk of bleeding. For high risk patients, as well as those with active GI bleeding, consider alternate therapies other than NSAIDs. 
 *  Remain alert for signs and symptoms of GI ulceration and bleeding during NSAID therapy. 
 *  If a serious GI adverse event is suspected, promptly initiate evaluation and treatment, and discontinue VIVLODEX until a serious GI adverse event is ruled out. 
 *  In the setting of concomitant use of low-dose aspirin for cardiac prophylaxis, monitor patients more closely for evidence of GI bleeding [ see  Drug Interactions (7)   ]. 
       5.3 Hepatotoxicity
 

  Elevations of ALT or AST (three or more times the upper limit of normal [ULN]) have been reported in approximately 1% of NSAID-treated patients in clinical trials. In addition, rare, sometimes fatal, cases of severe hepatic injury, including fulminant hepatitis, liver necrosis, and hepatic failure have been reported.



 Elevations of ALT or AST (less than three times ULN) may occur in up to 15% of patients treated with NSAIDs including meloxicam.



 Inform patients of the warning signs and symptoms of hepatotoxicity (e.g., nausea, fatigue, lethargy, diarrhea, pruritus, jaundice, right upper quadrant tenderness, and "flulike" symptoms). If clinical signs and symptoms consistent with liver disease develop, or if systemic manifestations occur (e.g., eosinophilia, rash, etc.), discontinue VIVLODEX immediately, and perform a clinical evaluation of the patient.



    5.4 Hypertension



  NSAIDs, including VIVLODEX, can lead to new onset or worsening of pre-existing hypertension, either of which may contribute to the increased incidence of CV events. Patients taking angiotensin converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors, thiazide diuretics, or loop diuretics may have impaired response to these therapies when taking NSAIDs [ see  Drug Interactions (7)    ].



 Monitor blood pressure (BP) during the initiation of NSAID treatment and throughout the course of therapy.



    5.5 Heart Failure and Edema



  The Coxib and traditional NSAID Trialists' Collaboration meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials demonstrated an approximately two-fold increase in hospitalizations for heart failure in COX-2 selective-treated patients and nonselective NSAID-treated patients compared to placebo-treated patients. In a Danish National Registry study of patients with heart failure, NSAID use increased the risk of MI, hospitalization for heart failure, and death.



 Additionally, fluid retention and edema have been observed in some patients treated with NSAIDs. Use of meloxicam may blunt the CV effects of several therapeutic agents used to treat these medical conditions (e.g., diuretics, ACE inhibitors, or angiotensin receptor blockers [ARBs]) [ see  Drug Interactions (7)    ].



 Avoid the use of VIVLODEX in patients with severe heart failure unless the benefits are expected to outweigh the risk of worsening heart failure. If VIVLODEX is used in patients with severe heart failure, monitor patients for signs of worsening heart failure.



    5.6 Renal Toxicity and Hyperkalemia



   Renal Toxicity  



 Long-term administration of NSAIDs has resulted in renal papillary necrosis and other renal injury. Renal toxicity has also been seen in patients in whom renal prostaglandins have a compensatory role in the maintenance of renal perfusion. In these patients, administration of an NSAID may cause a dose-dependent reduction in prostaglandin formation and, secondarily, in renal blood flow, which may precipitate overt renal decompensation. Patients at greatest risk of this reaction are those with impaired renal function, dehydration, hypovolemia, heart failure, liver dysfunction, those taking diuretics and ACE inhibitors or ARBs, and the elderly. Discontinuation of NSAID therapy was usually followed by recovery to the pretreatment state.



 No information is available from controlled clinical studies regarding the use of VIVLODEX in patients with advanced renal disease. The renal effects of VIVLODEX may hasten the progression of renal dysfunction in patients with pre-existing renal disease.



 Correct volume status in dehydrated or hypovolemic patients prior to initiating VIVLODEX. Monitor renal function in patients with renal or hepatic impairment, heart failure, dehydration, or hypovolemia during use of VIVLODEX [ see  Drug Interactions (7)    ] .  Avoid the use of VIVLODEX in patients with advanced renal disease unless the benefits are expected to outweigh the risk of worsening renal function. If VIVLODEX is used in patients with advanced renal disease, monitor patients for signs of worsening renal function.



    Hyperkalemia  



 Increases in serum potassium concentration, including hyperkalemia, have been reported with use of NSAIDs, even in some patients without renal impairment. In patients with normal renal function, these effects have been attributed to a hyporeninemic-hypoaldosteronism state.



    5.7 Anaphylactic Reactions



  Meloxicam has been associated with anaphylactic reactions in patients with and without known hypersensitivity to meloxicam and in patients with aspirin-sensitive asthma [ see  Contraindications (4)  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)    ].



 Seek emergency help if an anaphylactic reaction occurs.



    5.8 Exacerbation of Asthma Related to Aspirin Sensitivity



  A subpopulation of patients with asthma may have aspirin-sensitive asthma which may include chronic rhinosinusitis complicated by nasal polyps; severe, potentially fatal bronchospasm; and/or intolerance to aspirin and other NSAIDs. Because cross-reactivity between aspirin and other NSAIDs has been reported in such aspirin-sensitive patients, VIVLODEX is contraindicated in patients with this form of aspirin sensitivity [ see  Contraindications (4)    ]. When VIVLODEX is used in patients with preexisting asthma (without known aspirin sensitivity), monitor patients for changes in the signs and symptoms of asthma.



    5.9 Serious Skin Reactions



  NSAIDs, including meloxicam, can cause serious skin adverse reactions such as exfoliative dermatitis, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome (SJS), and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), which can be fatal. These serious events may occur without warning. Inform patients about the signs and symptoms of serious skin reactions, and to discontinue the use of VIVLODEX at the first appearance of skin rash or any other sign of hypersensitivity. VIVLODEX is contraindicated in patients with previous serious skin reactions to NSAIDs [ see  Contraindications (4)    ].



    5.10 Premature Closure of Fetal Ductus Arteriosus



  Meloxicam may cause premature closure of the fetal ductus arteriosus. Avoid use of NSAIDs, including VIVLODEX, in pregnant women starting at 30 weeks of gestation (third trimester) [ see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)    ].



    5.11 Hematologic Toxicity



  Anemia has occurred in NSAID-treated patients. This may be due to occult or gross blood loss, fluid retention, or an incompletely described effect upon erythropoiesis. If a patient treated with VIVLODEX has any signs or symptoms of anemia, monitor hemoglobin or hematocrit.



 NSAIDs, including VIVLODEX, may increase the risk of bleeding events. Concomitant use of warfarin and other anticoagulants, antiplatelet agents (e.g., aspirin), and serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) and serotonin norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs) may increase this risk. Monitor these patients for signs of bleeding [ see  Drug Interactions (7)    ].



    5.12 Masking of Inflammation and Fever



  The pharmacological activity of VIVLODEX in reducing inflammation, and possibly fever, may diminish the utility of diagnostic signs in detecting infections.



    5.13 Laboratory Monitoring



  Because serious GI bleeding, hepatotoxicity, and renal injury can occur without warning symptoms or signs, consider monitoring patients on long-term NSAID treatment with a CBC and a chemistry profile periodically [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2  ,  5.3  ,  5.6)    ].
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
