<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="vivotif" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    Adverse Reactions

  More than 1.4 million doses of Ty21a have been administered in controlled clinical trials and more than 150 million doses of Vivotif (Typhoid Vaccine Live Oral Ty21a) have been marketed world-wide. Active surveillance for adverse reactions of enteric-coated capsules was performed in a pilot study (  21  ) and in a subgroup of a large field trial (  14  ) involving a total of 483 individuals receiving 3 vaccine doses. The overall symptom rates from both studies when vaccinated with capsules were combined and shown to be: abdominal pain (6.4%), nausea (5.8%), headache (4.8%), fever (3.3%), diarrhea (2.9%), vomiting (1.5%) and skin rash (1.0%). Only the incidence of nausea occurred at a statistically higher frequency in the vaccinated group as compared to the placebo group (  14  ). Administration of vaccine doses more than 5- fold higher than the currently recommended dose caused only mild reactions in an open study involving 155 healthy adult males (  16  ).



 Post-marketing surveillance has revealed that adverse reactions are infrequent and mild (  17  ). Adverse reactions reported to the manufacturer during 1991-1995, during which time over 60 million doses (capsules) were administered, included: diarrhea (N = 45), abdominal pain (N = 42), nausea (N = 35), fever (N = 34), headache (N = 26), skin rash (N = 26), vomiting (N = 18), or urticaria in the trunk and/or extremities (N = 13). One isolated, non-fatal anaphylactic shock considered to be an allergic reaction to the vaccine was reported.



 To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact PaxVax, Inc. at 1-800-533-5899 or  http://www.paxvax.com  ; or contact the Vaccine Adverse Event Reporting System (VAERS) at 1-800-822-7967 or  http://www.fda.gov/vaers  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
