<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="vraylar" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6. ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Increased Mortality in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis [see  Boxed Warning  and Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *  Cerebrovascular Adverse Reactions, Including Stroke, in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *  Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  
 *  Tardive Dyskinesia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *  Late Occurring Adverse Reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *  Metabolic Changes [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *  Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
 *  Orthostatic Hypotension and Syncope [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  
 *  Seizures [  see Warnings and Precautions (  5.9  )]  
 *  Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.10  )]  
 *  Body Temperature Dysregulation [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.11  )]  
 *  Dysphagia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.12  )]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 5% and at least twice the rate of placebo) were (  6.1  ):
 

 *  Schizophrenia: extrapyramidal symptoms and akathisia 
 *  Bipolar mania: extrapyramidal symptoms, akathisia, dyspepsia, vomiting, somnolence, and restlessness 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Actavis at 1-800-272-5525 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The information below is derived from the clinical trial database for VRAYLAR, consisting of 1733 patients with schizophrenia (aged 18 to 65) and 1025 patients with manic or mixed episodes associated with bipolar I disorder (aged 18 to 65) exposed to one or more doses with a total experience of 566.5 patient-years. Of these patients, 1317 participated in placebo-controlled, 6-week schizophrenia trials with doses ranging from 1.5 mg to 12 mg/day and 623 participated in placebo-controlled, 3-week bipolar mania trials with doses ranging from 3 mg to 12 mg/day. A total of 364 VRAYLAR-treated patients had at least 24 weeks of exposure and 239 VRAYLAR-treated patients had at least 48 weeks of exposure.



     Patients with Schizophrenia  



 The following findings are based on four placebo-controlled, 6-week schizophrenia trials with VRAYLAR doses ranging from 1.5 to 12 mg once daily.



   Adverse Reactions Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment:  There was no single adverse reaction leading to discontinuation that occurred at a rate of &gt;= 2% in VRAYLAR-treated patients and at least twice the rate of placebo.



   Common Adverse Reactions (&gt;= 5% and at least twice the rate of placebo):  extrapyramidal symptoms and akathisia.



 Adverse Reactions with an incidence of &gt;= 2% and greater than placebo, at any dose are shown in    Table 3    .



 Table 3. Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;= 2% of VRAYLAR-treated Patients and &gt; Placebo-treated Adult Patients in 6-Week Schizophrenia Trials 
  Note: Figures rounded to the nearest integer    
  * Data shown by modal daily dose, defined as most frequently administered dose per patient    
  a Tachycardia terms: heart rate increased, sinus tachycardia, tachycardia    
  b Fatigue terms: asthenia, fatigue      
  c Extrapyramidal Symptoms terms: bradykinesia, cogwheel rigidity, drooling, dyskinesia, dystonia, extrapyramidal disorder, hypokinesia, masked facies, muscle rigidity, muscle tightness, Musculoskeletal stiffness, oculogyric crisis, oromandibular dystonia, parkinsonism, salivary hypersecretion, tardive dyskinesia, torticollis, tremor, trismus    
  d Somnolence terms: hypersomnia, sedation, somnolence    
  e Insomnia terms: initial insomnia, insomnia, middle insomnia, terminal insomnia    
  f Hypertension terms: blood pressure diastolic increased, blood pressure increased, blood pressure systolic increased, hypertension    
  gAbdominal pain terms: abdominal discomfort, abdominal pain, abdominal pain lower, abdominal pain upper, gastrointestinal pain    
  hDiarrhea terms: diarrhea, frequent bowel movements    
  iHepatic enzyme increase terms: alanine aminotransferase increased, aspartate aminotransferase increased, hepatic enzyme increased    
  jHeadache terms: headache, tension headache    
  
   System Organ Class /    Preferred Term    Placebo(N= 584)(%)    VRAYLAR      *       
 1.5 - 3 mg/day(N=539)(%)                4.5 - 6 mg/day(N=575)(%)  9 - 12 mg/day(N=203)(%)   
   Cardiac Disorders                      
 Tachycardia  a                          1               2                2                 3                 
   Gastrointestinal Disorders             
 Abdominal pain  g                       5               3                4                 7                 
 Constipation                            5               6                7                 10                
 Diarrhea  h                             3               1                4                 5                 
 Dry Mouth                               2               1                2                 3                 
 Dyspepsia                               4               4                5                 5                 
 Nausea                                  5               5                7                 8                 
 Toothache                               4               3                3                 6                 
 Vomiting                                3               4                5                 5                 
   General Disorders/Administration Site Conditions     
 Fatigue  b                              1               1                3                 2                 
   Infections and infestations            
 Nasopharyngitis                         1               1                1                 2                 
 Urinary tract infection                 1               1                &lt;1                2                 
   Investigations                         
 Blood creatine phosphokinase increased  1               1                2                 3                 
 Hepatic enzyme increased  i             &lt;1              1                1                 2                 
 Weight increased                        1               3                2                 3                 
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders     
 Decreased appetite                      2               1                3                 2                 
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders     
 Arthralgia                              1               2                1                 2                 
 Back pain                               2               3                3                 1                 
 Pain in extremity                       3               2                2                 4                 
   Nervous System Disorders               
 Akathisia                               4               9                13                14                
 Extrapyramidal Symptoms  c              8               15               19                20                
 Headache  j                             13              9                11                18                
 Somnolence  d                           5               5                8                 10                
 Dizziness                               2               3                5                 5                 
   Psychiatric Disorders                  
 Agitation                               4               3                5                 3                 
 Insomnia  e                             11              12               13                11                
 Restlessness                            3               4                6                 5                 
 Anxiety                                 4               6                5                 3                 
   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders     
 Cough                                   2               1                2                 4                 
   Skin and subcutaneous disorders        
 Rash                                    1               &lt;1               1                 2                 
   Vascular Disorders                     
 Hypertension  f                         1               2                3                 6                 
               Patients with Bipolar Mania  
 

 The following findings are based on three placebo-controlled, 3-week bipolar mania trials with VRAYLAR doses ranging from 3 to 12 mg once daily.



   Adverse Reactions Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment:  The only adverse reaction leading to discontinuation that occurred at a rate of &gt;= 2% in VRAYLAR-treated patients and at least twice the rate of placebo was akathisia (2%). Overall, 12% of the patients who received VRAYLAR discontinued treatment due to an adverse reaction, compared with 7% of placebo-treated patients in these trials.



   Common Adverse Reactions (&gt;= 5% and at least twice the rate of placebo):  extrapyramidal symptoms, akathisia, dyspepsia, vomiting, somnolence, and restlessness.



 Adverse Reactions with an incidence of &gt;= 2% and greater than placebo at any dose are shown in    Table 4    .



 Table 4. Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;= 2% of VRAYLAR-treated Patients and &gt; Placebo-treated Adult Patients in 3-Week Bipolar Mania Trials 
  Note: Figures rounded to the nearest integer    
  *Data shown by modal daily dose, defined as most frequently administered dose per patient    
  a Abdominal pain terms: abdominal discomfort, abdominal pain, abdominal pain upper, abdominal tenderness,    
  b Diarrhea: diarrhea, frequent bowel movements    
  c Fatigue terms: asthenia, fatigue           
  d Hepatic enzymes increased terms: alanine aminotransferase increased, aspartate aminotransferase increased, hepatic enzyme increased, transaminases increased    
  e Extrapyramidal Symptoms terms: bradykinesia, drooling, dyskinesia, dystonia, extrapyramidal disorder, hypokinesia, muscle rigidity, muscle tightness, musculoskeletal stiffness, oromandibular dystonia, parkinsonism, salivary hypersecretion, tremor    
  f Somnolence terms: hypersomnia, sedation, somnolence    
  g Insomnia terms: initial insomnia, insomnia, middle insomnia    
  h Hypertension terms: blood pressure diastolic increased, blood pressure increased, hypertension    
  I Tachycardia terms: heart rate increased, sinus tachycardia, tachycardia    
  j Pyrexia terms: body temperature increased, pyrexia    
  k Headache terms: headache, tension headache    
  
   System Organ Class /    Preferred Term     Placebo(N= 442)(%)    VRAYLAR      *       
 3 - 6 mg/day(N=263)(%)                       9 - 12 mg/day(N=360)(%)   
   Cardiac Disorders                           
 Tachycardia  i                               1                   2                    1                     
   Eye Disorders                               
 Vision blurred                               1                   4                    4                     
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                  
 Nausea                                       7                   13                   11                    
 Constipation                                 5                   6                    11                    
 Vomiting                                     4                   10                   8                     
 Dry mouth                                    2                   3                    2                     
 Dyspepsia                                    4                   7                    9                     
 Abdominal pain  a                            5                   6                    8                     
 Diarrhea  b                                  5                   5                    6                     
 Toothache                                    2                   4                    3                     
   General Disorders/Administration Site Conditions     
 Fatigue  c                                   2                   4                    5                     
 Pyrexia  j                                   2                   1                    4                     
   Investigations                              
 Blood creatine phosphokinase increased       2                   2                    3                     
 Hepatic enzymes increased  d                 &lt;1                  1                    3                     
 Weight increased                             2                   2                    3                     
   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders          
 Decreased appetite                           3                   3                    4                     
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders     
 Pain in extremity                            2                   4                    2                     
 Back pain                                    1                   1                    3                     
   Nervous System Disorders                    
 Akathisia                                    5                   20                   21                    
 Extrapyramidal Symptoms  e                   12                  26                   29                    
 Headache  k                                  13                  14                   13                    
 Dizziness                                    4                   7                    6                     
 Somnolence  f                                4                   7                    8                     
   Psychiatric Disorders                       
 Insomnia  g                                  7                   9                    8                     
 Restlessness                                 2                   7                    7                     
   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders     
 Oropharyngeal pain                           2                   1                    3                     
   Vascular Disorders                          
 Hypertension  h                              1                   5                    4                     
              Dystonia  
 

 Symptoms of dystonia, prolonged abnormal contractions of muscle groups, may occur in susceptible individuals during the first few days of treatment. Dystonic symptoms include: spasm of the neck muscles, sometimes progressing to tightness of the throat, swallowing difficulty, difficulty breathing, and/or protrusion of the tongue. Although these symptoms can occur at low doses, they occur more frequently and with greater severity with high potency and higher doses of first-generation antipsychotic drugs. An elevated risk of acute dystonia is observed in males and younger age groups.



     Extrapyramidal Symptoms (EPS) and Akathisia  



 In schizophrenia and bipolar mania trials, data were objectively collected using the Simpson Angus Rating Scale (SAS) for treatment-emergent EPS (parkinsonism) (SAS total score &lt;= 3 at baseline and &gt; 3 post-baseline) and the Barnes Akathisia Scale (BARS) for treatment-emergent akathisia (BARS total score &lt;= 2 at baseline and &gt; 2 post-baseline).



 In 6-week schizophrenia trials, the incidence of reported events related to extrapyramidal symptoms (EPS), excluding akathisia and restlessness was 17% for VRAYLAR-treated patients versus 8% for placebo-treated patients. These events led to discontinuation in 0.3% of VRAYLAR-treated patients versus 0.2% of placebo-treated patients. The incidence of akathisia was 11% for VRAYLAR-treated patients versus 4% for placebo-treated patients. These events led to discontinuation in 0.5% of VRAYLAR-treated patients versus 0.2% of placebo-treated patients. The incidence of EPS is shown in    Table 5    .



 Table 5. Incidence of EPS Compared to Placebo in 6-Week Schizophrenia Studies 
  Note: Figures rounded to the nearest integer    
  *Data shown by modal daily dose, defined as most frequently administered dose per patient    
  ** Dystonia includes adverse event terms: dystonia, oculogyric crisis, oromandibular dystonia, trismus , torticollis    
  S Parkinsonism includes adverse event terms: bradykinesia, cogwheel rigidity, drooling, dyskinesia, extrapyramidal disorder, hypokinesia, masked facies, muscle rigidity, muscle tightness, parkinsonism, tremor, salivary hypersecretion    
  
   Adverse Event Term              Placebo(N= 584)(%)    VRAYLAR      *       
 1.5 - 3 mg/day(N=539)(%)          4.5 - 6 mg/day(N=575)(%)  9-12 mg/day(N=203)(%)   
   All EPS events                  14              24                  32                  33                
   All EPS events,    excluding    Akathisia/Restlessness    8               15                  19                  20                
 Akathisia                         4               9                   13                  14                
 Dystonia  **                      &lt;1              2                   2                   2                 
 Parkinsonism  S                   7               13                  16                  18                
 Restlessness                      3               4                   6                   5                 
 Musculoskeletal stiffness         1               1                   3                   1                 
           In 3-week bipolar mania trials, the incidence of reported events related to extrapyramidal symptoms (EPS), excluding akathisia and restlessness, was 28% for VRAYLAR-treated patients versus 12% for placebo-treated patients. These events led to a discontinuation in 1% of VRAYLAR-treated patients versus 0.2% of placebo-treated patients. The incidence of akathisia was 20% for VRAYLAR-treated patients versus 5% for placebo-treated patients. These events led to discontinuation in 2% of VRAYLAR-treated patients versus 0% of placebo-treated patients. The incidence of EPS is provided in    Table 6    .
 

 Table 6. Incidence of EPS Compared to Placebo in 3-Week Bipolar Mania Trials 
  Note: Figures rounded to the nearest integer    
  *Data shown by modal daily dose, defined as most frequently administered dose per patient    
  ** Dystonia includes adverse event terms: dystonia, oromandibular dystonia    
  S Parkinsonism includes adverse event terms: bradykinesia, drooling, dyskinesia, extrapyramidal disorder,    
  hypokinesia, muscle rigidity, muscle tightness, parkinsonism, salivary hypersecretion, tremor    
  
   Adverse Event Term                     Placebo(N= 442)(%)     VRAYLAR      *       
 3 - 6 mg/day(N=263)(%)                   9 - 12 mg/day(N=360)(%)   
   All EPS events                         18                   41                   45                      
   All EPS events,    excluding    Akathisia/Restlessness    12                   26                   29                      
 Akathisia                                5                    20                   21                      
 Dystonia  **                             1                    5                    3                       
 Parkinsonism  S                          10                   21                   26                      
 Restlessness                             2                    7                    7                       
 Musculoskeletal stiffness                1                    2                    2                       
              Cataracts  
 

 In the long-term uncontrolled schizophrenia (48-week) and bipolar mania (16-week) trials, the incidence of cataracts was 0.1% and 0.2%, respectively. The development of cataracts was observed in nonclinical studies [  see Nonclinical Toxicology (  13.2  )  ]. The possibility of lenticular changes or cataracts cannot be excluded at this time.



     Vital Signs Changes  



 There were no clinically meaningful differences between VRAYLAR-treated patients and placebo-treated patients in mean change from baseline to endpoint in supine blood pressure parameters except for an increase in supine diastolic blood pressure in the 9 - 12 mg/day VRAYLAR-treated schizophrenia patients.



 Pooled data from 6-week schizophrenia and 3-week bipolar mania trials are shown in    Tables 7  and  8  .  



 Table 7. Mean Change in Blood Pressure at Endpoint in 6-Week Schizophrenia Trials 
  * Data shown by modal daily dose, defined as most frequently administered dose per patient    
  
                                  Placebo (N=574)    VRAYLAR      *       
 1.5 - 3 mg/day(N=512)            4.5 - 6 mg/day(N=570)  9- 12 mg/day(N=203)   
 Supine Systolic Blood Pressure (mmHg)  +0.9          +0.6             +1.3                  +2.1                  
 Supine Diastolic Blood Pressure (mmHg)  +0.4          +0.2             +1.6                  +3.4                  
          Table 8. Mean Change in Blood Pressure at Endpoint in 3-Week Bipolar Mania Trials 
  * Data shown by modal daily dose, defined as most frequently administered dose per patient    
  
                                                   Placebo(N=439)    VRAYLAR      *       
 3 - 6 mg/day(N=259)                               9 - 12 mg/day(N=360)   
 Supine Systolic Blood Pressure (mmHg)             -0.5            +0.8               +1.8                  
 Supine Diastolic Blood Pressure (mmHg)            +0.9            +1.5               +1.9                  
              Changes in Laboratory Tests  
 

 The proportions of patients with transaminase elevations of &gt;=3 times the upper limits of the normal reference range in 6-week schizophrenia trials ranged between 1% and 2% for VRAYLAR-treated patients, increasing with dose, and was 1% for placebo-treated patients. The proportions of patients with transaminase elevations of &gt;=3 times the upper limits of the normal reference range in 3-week bipolar mania trials ranged between 2% and 4% for VRAYLAR-treated patients depending on dose group administered and 2% for placebo-treated patients.



 The proportions of patients with elevations of creatine phosphokinase (CPK) greater than 1000 U/L in 6-week schizophrenia trials ranged between 4% and 6% for VRAYLAR-treated patients, increasing with dose, and was 4% for placebo-treated patients. The proportions of patients with elevations of CPK greater than 1000 U/L in 3-week bipolar mania trials was about 4% in cariprazine and placebo-treated patients.



     Other Adverse Reactions Observed During the Pre-marketing Evaluation of VRAYLAR  



 Adverse reactions listed below were reported by patients treated with VRAYLAR at doses of &gt;= 1.5 mg once daily within the database of 2758 VRAYLAR-treated patients. The reactions listed are those that could be of clinical importance, as well as reactions that are plausibly drug-related on pharmacologic or other grounds. Reactions that appear elsewhere in the VRAYLAR label are not included.



 Reactions are further categorized by organ class and listed in order of decreasing frequency, according to the following definition: those occurring in at least 1/100 patients (frequent) [only those not already listed in the tabulated results from placebo-controlled studies appear in this listing]; those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1000 patients (infrequent); and those occurring in fewer than 1/1000 patients (rare).



   Gastrointestinal Disorders:    Infrequent    : gastroesophageal reflux disease, gastritis  



   Hepatobiliary Disorders:    Rare:    hepatitis  



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:    Frequent    : decreased appetite;    Infrequent    : hyponatremia  



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:    Rare    : rhabdomyolysis  



   Nervous System Disorders:    Rare    : ischemic stroke  



   Psychiatric Disorders:    Infrequent:    suicide attempts, suicide ideation;    Rare    : completed suicide  



   Renal and Urinary Disorders:    Infrequent    : pollakiuria  



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:    Infrequent:    hyperhidrosis  
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS



  WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS



    Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. VRAYLAR (cariprazine) is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis     [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]    .  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS  



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. 
 *  VRAYLAR is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis. (5.1) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5. WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Cerebrovascular Adverse Reactions in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis: Increased incidence of cerebrovascular adverse reactions (e.g., stroke, transient ischemic attack) (  5.2  ) 
 *   Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome: Manage with immediate discontinuation and close monitoring (  5.3  ) 
 *   Tardive Dyskinesia : Discontinue if appropriate (  5.4  ) 
 *   Late-Occurring Adverse Reactions: Because of VRAYLAR's long half-life, monitor for adverse reactions and patient response for several weeks after starting VRAYLAR and with each dosage change (  5.5  ) 
 *   Metabolic Changes : Monitor for hyperglycemia/diabetes mellitus, dyslipidemia and weight gain (  5.6  ) 
 *   Orthostatic Hypotension : Monitor heart rate and blood pressure and warn patients with known cardiovascular or cerebrovascular disease, and risk of dehydration or syncope (  5.8  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Increased Mortality in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis



  Antipsychotic drugs increase the all-cause risk of death in elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis. Analyses of 17 dementia-related psychosis placebo-controlled trials (modal duration of 10 weeks and largely in patients taking atypical antipsychotic drugs) revealed a risk of death in the drug-treated patients of between 1.6 to 1.7 times that in placebo-treated patients. Over the course of a typical 10-week controlled trial, the rate of death in drug-treated patients was about 4.5%, compared to a rate of about 2.6% in placebo-treated patients.



 Although the causes of death were varied, most of the deaths appeared to be either cardiovascular (e.g., heart failure, sudden death) or infectious (e.g., pneumonia) in nature. VRAYLAR is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis [see  Boxed Warning  , Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  .



    5.2 Cerebrovascular Adverse Reactions, Including Stroke, in Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis



  In placebo-controlled trials in elderly subjects with dementia, patients randomized to risperidone, aripiprazole, and olanzapine had a higher incidence of stroke and transient ischemic attack, including fatal stroke. VRAYLAR is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis [see  Boxed Warning  , Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  .



    5.3 Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS)



  Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS), a potentially fatal symptom complex, has been reported in association with administration of antipsychotic drugs. Clinical manifestations of NMS are hyperpyrexia, muscle rigidity, delirium, and autonomic instability. Additional signs may include elevated creatine phosphokinase, myoglobinuria (rhabdomyolysis), and acute renal failure.



 If NMS is suspected, immediately discontinue VRAYLAR and provide intensive symptomatic treatment and monitoring.



    5.4 Tardive Dyskinesia



  Tardive dyskinesia, a syndrome consisting of potentially irreversible, involuntary, dyskinetic movements, may develop in patients treated with antipsychotic drugs, including VRAYLAR. The risk appears to be highest among the elderly, especially elderly women, but it is not possible to predict which patients are likely to develop the syndrome. Whether antipsychotic drug products differ in their potential to cause tardive dyskinesia is unknown.



 The risk of tardive dyskinesia and the likelihood that it will become irreversible increase with the duration of treatment and the cumulative dose. The syndrome can develop after a relatively brief treatment period, even at low doses. It may also occur after discontinuation of treatment.



 There is no known treatment for tardive dyskinesia, although the syndrome may remit, partially or completely, if antipsychotic treatment is discontinued. Antipsychotic treatment itself, however, may suppress (or partially suppress) the signs and symptoms of the syndrome, possibly masking the underlying process. The effect that symptomatic suppression has upon the long-term course of tardive dyskinesia is unknown.



 Given these considerations, VRAYLAR should be prescribed in a manner most likely to reduce the risk of tardive dyskinesia. Chronic antipsychotic treatment should generally be reserved for patients: 1) who suffer from a chronic illness that is known to respond to antipsychotic drugs; and 2) for whom alternative, effective, but potentially less harmful treatments are not available or appropriate. In patients who do require chronic treatment, use the lowest dose and the shortest duration of treatment producing a satisfactory clinical response should be sought. Periodically reassess the need for continued treatment.



 If signs and symptoms of tardive dyskinesia appear in a patient on VRAYLAR, drug discontinuation should be considered. However, some patients may require treatment with VRAYLAR despite the presence of the syndrome.



    5.5 Late-Occurring Adverse Reactions



  Adverse events may first appear several weeks after the initiation of VRAYLAR treatment, probably because plasma levels of cariprazine and its major metabolites accumulate over time. As a result, the incidence of adverse reactions in short-term trials may not reflect the rates after longer term exposures [see Dosage and Administration (  2.1  ), Adverse Reactions (  6.1  ), Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )].  



 Monitor for adverse reactions, including EPS or akathisia, and patient response for several weeks after a patient has begun VRAYLAR and after each dosage increase. Consider reducing the dose or discontinuing the drug.



    5.6 Metabolic Changes



  Atypical antipsychotic drugs, including VRAYLAR, have caused metabolic changes, including hyperglycemia, diabetes mellitus, dyslipidemia, and weight gain. Although all of the drugs in the class to date have been shown to produce some metabolic changes, each drug has its own specific risk profile.



    Hyperglycemia and Diabetes Mellitus  



 Hyperglycemia, in some cases extreme and associated with ketoacidosis or hyperosmolar coma or death, has been reported in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics. Assess fasting plasma glucose before or soon after initiation of antipsychotic medication, and monitor periodically during long-term treatment.



    Schizophrenia  



 In the 6-week, placebo-controlled trials of adult patients with schizophrenia, the proportion of patients with shifts in fasting glucose from normal (&lt;100 mg/dL) to high (&gt;=126 mg/dL) and borderline (&gt;=100 and &lt;126 mg/dL) to high were similar in patients treated with VRAYLAR and placebo. In the long-term, open-label schizophrenia studies, 4% patients with normal hemoglobin A1c baseline values developed elevated levels ( &gt;=6.5%).



    Bipolar Mania  



 In the 3-week, placebo-controlled trials of adult patients with bipolar disorder, the proportion of patients with shifts in fasting glucose from normal (&lt;100 mg/dL) to high (&gt;=126 mg/dL) and borderline (&gt;=100 and &lt;126 mg/dL) to high were similar in patients treated with VRAYLAR and placebo. In the long-term, open-label bipolar disorder studies, 4% patients with normal hemoglobin A1c baseline values developed elevated levels (&gt;=6.5%).



    Dyslipidemia  



 Atypical antipsychotics cause adverse alterations in lipids. Before or soon after initiation of antipsychotic medication, obtain a fasting lipid profile at baseline and monitor periodically during treatment.



    Schizophrenia  



 In the 6-week, placebo-controlled trials of adult patients with schizophrenia, the proportion of patients with shifts in fasting total cholesterol, LDL, HDL and triglycerides were similar in patients treated with VRAYLAR and placebo.



    Bipolar Mania  



 In the 3-week, placebo-controlled trials of adult patients with bipolar disorder, the proportion of patients with shifts in fasting total cholesterol, LDL, HDL and triglycerides were similar in patients treated with VRAYLAR and placebo.



    Weight Gain  



 Weight gain has been observed with use of atypical antipsychotics, including VRAYLAR. Monitor weight at baseline and frequently thereafter.   Tables 1  and  2    show the change in body weight occurring from baseline to endpoint in 6-week schizophrenia and 3-week bipolar mania trials.



 Table 1. Change in Body Weight (kg) in 6-Week Schizophrenia Trials 
  *Data shown by modal daily dose, defined as most frequently administered dose per patient    
  
                                                                  VRAYLAR     *       
                                                     Placebo(N=573)  1.5 - 3 mg/day(N=512)  4.5 - 6 mg/day(N=570)  9 - 12mg/day(N=203)   
 Mean Change at Endpoint                             +0.3        +0.8        +1              +1               
 Proportion of Patients with Weight Increase (&gt;= 7% )  5%          8%          8%              17%              
          Table 2. Change in Body Weight (kg) in 3-Week Bipolar Mania Trials 
  *Data shown by modal daily dose, defined as most frequently administered dose per patient    
  
                                                                            VRAYLAR     *       
                                                             Placebo(N=439)  3 - 6 mg/day(N=259)  9 - 12 mg/day (N=360)   
 Mean Change at Endpoint                                     +0.2          +0.5           +0.6              
 Proportion of Patients with Weight Increase (&gt;= 7% )        2%            1%             3%                
          In long-term, uncontrolled trials with VRAYLAR in schizophrenia, the mean changes from baseline in weight at 12, 24, and 48 weeks were 1.2 kg, 1.7 kg, and 2.5 kg, respectively.
 

    5.7 Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis



  Leukopenia and neutropenia have been reported during treatment with antipsychotic agents, including VRAYLAR. Agranulocytosis (including fatal cases) has been reported with other agents in the class.



 Possible risk factors for leukopenia and neutropenia include pre-existing low white blood cell count (WBC) or absolute neutrophil count (ANC) and history of drug-induced leukopenia or neutropenia. In patients with a pre-existing low WBC or ANC or a history of drug-induced leukopenia or neutropenia, perform a complete blood count (CBC) frequently during the first few months of therapy. In such patients, consider discontinuation of VRAYLAR at the first sign of a clinically significant decline in WBC in the absence of other causative factors.



 Monitor patients with clinically significant neutropenia for fever or other symptoms or signs of infection and treat promptly if such symptoms or signs occur. Discontinue VRAYLAR in patients with absolute neutrophil count &lt; 1000/mm  3  and follow their WBC until recovery.



    5.8 Orthostatic Hypotension and Syncope



  Atypical antipsychotics cause orthostatic hypotension and syncope. Generally, the risk is greatest during initial dose titration and when increasing the dose. Symptomatic orthostatic hypotension was infrequent in trials of VRAYLAR and was not more frequent on VRAYLAR than placebo. Syncope was not observed.



 Orthostatic vital signs should be monitored in patients who are vulnerable to hypotension (e.g., elderly patients, patients with dehydration, hypovolemia, and concomitant treatment with antihypertensive medications), patients with known cardiovascular disease (history of myocardial infarction, ischemic heart disease, heart failure, or conduction abnormalities), and patients with cerebrovascular disease. VRAYLAR has not been evaluated in patients with a recent history of myocardial infarction or unstable cardiovascular disease. Such patients were excluded from pre-marketing clinical trials.



    5.9 Seizures



  Like other antipsychotic drugs, VRAYLAR may cause seizures. This risk is greatest in patients with a history of seizures or with conditions that lower the seizure threshold. Conditions that lower the seizure threshold may be more prevalent in older patients.



    5.10 Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment



  VRAYLAR, like other antipsychotics, has the potential to impair judgment, thinking, or motor skills.



 In 6-week schizophrenia trials, somnolence (hypersomnia, sedation, and somnolence) was reported in 7% of VRAYLAR-treated patients compared to 6% of placebo-treated patients. In 3-week bipolar mania trials, somnolence was reported in 8% of VRAYLAR-treated patients compared to 4% of placebo-treated patients.



 Patients should be cautioned about operating hazardous machinery, including motor vehicles, until they are reasonably certain that therapy with VRAYLAR does not affect them adversely.



    5.11 Body Temperature Dysregulation



  Atypical antipsychotics may disrupt the body's ability to reduce core body temperature. Strenuous exercise, exposure to extreme heat, dehydration, and anticholinergic medications may contribute to an elevation in core body temperature; use VRAYLAR with caution in patient who may experience these conditions.



    5.12 Dysphagia



  Esophageal dysmotility and aspiration have been associated with antipsychotic drug use. Dysphagia has been reported with VRAYLAR. VRAYLAR and other antipsychotic drugs should be used cautiously in patients at risk for aspiration.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
