<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="vyvanse" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling



 *  Serious Cardiovascular Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Blood Pressure and Heart Rate Increases [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Psychiatric Adverse Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Suppression of Growth [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Peripheral Vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=5% and at a rate at least twice placebo) in children, adolescents, and/or adults with ADHD were anorexia, anxiety, decreased appetite, decreased weight, diarrhea, dizziness, dry mouth, irritability, insomnia, nausea, upper abdominal pain, and vomiting (  6.1  )
 

 Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 5% and at a rate at least twice placebo) in adults with BED were dry mouth, insomnia, decreased appetite, increased heart rate, constipation, feeling jittery, and anxiety (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Shire US Inc. at 1-800-828-2088 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder  



 The safety data in this section is based on data from the 4-week parallel-group controlled clinical studies of VYVANSE in pediatric and adult patients with ADHD  [see  Clinical Studies (14.1)  ]  .



     Adverse Reactions Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment in ADHD Clinical Trials  



 In the controlled trial in patients ages 6 to 12 years (Study 1), 9% (20/218) of VYVANSE-treated patients discontinued due to adverse reactions compared to 1% (1/72) of placebo-treated patients. The most frequent adverse reactions leading to discontinuation (i.e. leading to discontinuation in at least 1% of VYVANSE-treated patients and at a rate at least twice that of placebo) were ECG voltage criteria for ventricular hypertrophy, tic, vomiting, psychomotor hyperactivity, insomnia, and rash [2 instances for each adverse reaction, i.e., 2/218 (1%)].



 In the controlled trial in patients ages 13 to 17 years (Study 4), 4% (10/233) of VYVANSE-treated patients discontinued due to adverse reactions compared to 1% (1/77) of placebo-treated patients. The most frequent adverse reactions leading to discontinuation were irritability (3/233; 1%), decreased appetite (2/233; 1%), and insomnia (2/233; 1%).



 In the controlled adult trial (Study 7), 6% (21/358) of VYVANSE-treated patients discontinued due to adverse reactions compared to 2% (1/62) of placebo-treated patients. The most frequent adverse reactions leading to discontinuation (i.e. leading to discontinuation in at least 1% of VYVANSE-treated patients and at a rate at least twice that of placebo) were insomnia (8/358; 2%), tachycardia (3/358; 1%), irritability (2/358; 1%), hypertension (4/358; 1%), headache (2/358; 1%), anxiety (2/358; 1%), and dyspnea (3/358; 1%).



 The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=5% and at a rate at least twice placebo) reported in children, adolescents, and/or adults were anorexia, anxiety, decreased appetite, decreased weight, diarrhea, dizziness, dry mouth, irritability, insomnia, nausea, upper abdominal pain, and vomiting.



     Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of 2% or More Among VYVANSE Treated Patients with ADHD in Clinical Trials  



 Adverse reactions reported in the controlled trials in pediatric patients ages 6 to 12 years (Study 1), adolescent patients ages 13 to 17 years (Study 4), and adult patients (Study 7) treated with VYVANSE or placebo are presented in Tables 1, 2, and 3 below.



 Table 1 Adverse Reactions Reported by 2% or More of Children (Ages 6 to 12 Years) with ADHD Taking VYVANSE and at least Twice the Incidence in Patients Taking Placebo in a 4-Week Clinical Trial (Study 1) 
                                                     VYVANSE(n=218)                  Placebo(n=72)          
  
 Decreased Appetite                                   39%                             4%                    
 Insomnia                                             23%                             3%                    
 Abdominal Pain Upper                                 12%                             6%                    
 Irritability                                         10%                             0%                    
 Vomiting                                             9%                              4%                    
 Weight Decreased                                     9%                              1%                    
 Nausea                                               6%                              3%                    
 Dry Mouth                                            5%                              0%                    
 Dizziness                                            5%                              0%                    
 Affect lability                                      3%                              0%                    
 Rash                                                 3%                              0%                    
 Pyrexia                                              2%                              1%                    
 Somnolence                                           2%                              1%                    
 Tic                                                  2%                              0%                    
        Table 2 Adverse Reactions Reported by 2% or More of Adolescent (Ages 13 to 17 Years) Patients with ADHD Taking VYVANSE and at least Twice the Incidence in Patients Taking Placebo in a 4-Week Clinical Trial (Study 4) 
                                                     VYVANSE(n=233)                  Placebo(n=77)          
  
 Decreased Appetite                                   34%                             3%                    
 Insomnia                                             13%                             4%                    
 Weight Decreased                                     9%                              0%                    
 Dry Mouth                                            4%                              1%                    
        Table 3 Adverse Reactions Reported by 2% or More of Adult Patients with ADHD Taking VYVANSE and at least Twice the Incidence in Patients Taking Placebo in a 4-Week Clinical Trial (Study 7) 
                                                     VYVANSE(n=358)                  Placebo(n=62)          
  
 Decreased Appetite                                   27%                             2%                    
 Insomnia                                             27%                             8%                    
 Dry Mouth                                            26%                             3%                    
 Diarrhea                                             7%                              0%                    
 Nausea                                               7%                              0%                    
 Anxiety                                              6%                              0%                    
 Anorexia                                             5%                              0%                    
 Feeling Jittery                                      4%                              0%                    
 Agitation                                            3%                              0%                    
 Increased Blood Pressure                             3%                              0%                    
 Hyperhidrosis                                        3%                              0%                    
 Restlessness                                         3%                              0%                    
 Decreased Weight                                     3%                              0%                    
 Dyspnea                                              2%                              0%                    
 Increased Heart Rate                                 2%                              0%                    
 Tremor                                               2%                              0%                    
         In addition, in the adult population erectile dysfunction was observed in 2.6% of males on VYVANSE and 0% on placebo; decreased libido was observed in 1.4% of subjects on VYVANSE and 0% on placebo.
 

     Weight Loss and Slowing Growth Rate in Pediatric Patients with ADHD  



 In a controlled trial of VYVANSE in children ages 6 to 12 years (Study 1), mean weight loss from baseline after 4 weeks of therapy was -0.9, -1.9, and -2.5 pounds, respectively, for patients receiving 30 mg, 50 mg, and 70 mg of VYVANSE, compared to a 1 pound weight gain for patients receiving placebo. Higher doses were associated with greater weight loss with 4 weeks of treatment. Careful follow-up for weight in children ages 6 to 12 years who received VYVANSE over 12 months suggests that consistently medicated children (i.e. treatment for 7 days per week throughout the year) have a slowing in growth rate, measured by body weight as demonstrated by an age- and sex-normalized mean change from baseline in percentile, of -13.4 over 1 year (average percentiles at baseline and 12 months were 60.9 and 47.2, respectively). In a 4-week controlled trial of VYVANSE in adolescents ages 13 to 17 years, mean weight loss from baseline to endpoint was -2.7, -4.3, and -4.8 lbs., respectively, for patients receiving 30 mg, 50 mg, and 70 mg of VYVANSE, compared to a 2.0 pound weight gain for patients receiving placebo.



 Careful follow-up of weight and height in children ages 7 to 10 years who were randomized to either methylphenidate or non-medication treatment groups over 14 months, as well as in naturalistic subgroups of newly methylphenidate-treated and non-medication treated children over 36 months (to the ages of 10 to 13 years), suggests that consistently medicated children (i.e. treatment for 7 days per week throughout the year) have a temporary slowing in growth rate (on average, a total of about 2 cm less growth in height and 2.7 kg less growth in weight over 3 years), without evidence of growth rebound during this period of development. In a controlled trial of amphetamine (d- to l-enantiomer ratio of 3:1) in adolescents, mean weight change from baseline within the initial 4 weeks of therapy was -1.1 pounds and -2.8 pounds, respectively, for patients receiving 10 mg and 20 mg of amphetamine. Higher doses were associated with greater weight loss within the initial 4 weeks of treatment  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  .



     Weight Loss in Adults with ADHD  



 In the controlled adult trial (Study 7), mean weight loss after 4 weeks of therapy was 2.8 pounds, 3.1 pounds, and 4.3 pounds, for patients receiving final doses of 30 mg, 50 mg, and 70 mg of VYVANSE, respectively, compared to a mean weight gain of 0.5 pounds for patients receiving placebo.



     Binge Eating Disorder  



 The safety data in this section is based on data from two 12 week parallel group, flexible-dose, placebo-controlled studies in adults with BED  [see  Clinical Studies 14.2  ]  . Patients with cardiovascular risk factors other than obesity and smoking were excluded.



     Adverse Reactions Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment in BED Clinical Trials  



 In controlled trials of patients ages 18 to 55 years, 5.1% (19/373) of VYVANSE-treated patients discontinued due to adverse reactions compared to 2.4% (9/372) of placebo-treated patients. No single adverse reaction led to discontinuation in 1% or more of VYVANSE-treated patients.



 The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=5% and at a rate at least twice placebo) reported in adults were dry mouth, insomnia, decreased appetite, increased heart rate, constipation, feeling jittery, and anxiety.



 Adverse reactions reported in the pooled controlled trials in adult patients (Study 10 and 11) treated with VYVANSE or placebo are presented in Table 4 below.



 Table 4 Adverse Reactions Reported by 2% or More of Adult Patients with BED Taking VYVANSE and at least Twice the Incidence in Patients Taking Placebo in 12-Week Clinical Trials (Study 10 and 11) 
                                                          VYVANSE(N=373)             Placebo(N=372)         
  
 Dry Mouth                                                      36%                        7%               
 Insomnia                                                       20%                        8%               
 Decreased Appetite                                             8%                         2%               
 Increased Heart Rate                                           7%                         1%               
 Feeling Jittery                                                6%                         1%               
 Constipation                                                   6%                         1%               
 Anxiety                                                        5%                         1%               
 Diarrhea                                                       4%                         2%               
 Decreased Weight                                               4%                         0%               
 Hyperhidrosis                                                  4%                         0%               
 Vomiting                                                       2%                         1%               
 Gastroenteritis                                                2%                         1%               
 Paresthesia                                                    2%                         1%               
 Pruritis                                                       2%                         1%               
 Upper Abdominal Pain                                           2%                         0%               
 Energy Increased                                               2%                         0%               
 Urinary Tract Infection                                        2%                         0%               
 Nightmare                                                      2%                         0%               
 Restlessness                                                   2%                         0%               
 Oropharyngeal Pain                                             2%                         0%               
           6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of VYVANSE. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. These events are as follows: palpitations, cardiomyopathy, mydriasis, diplopia, difficulties with visual accommodation, blurred vision, eosinophilic hepatitis, anaphylactic reaction, hypersensitivity, dyskinesia, tics, bruxism, depression, dermatillomania, aggression, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome, angioedema, urticaria, seizures, libido changes, frequent or prolonged erections, constipation, and rhabdomyolysis.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING:  ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE

    WARNING:  ABUSE AND DEPENDENCE  

    CNS stimulants (amphetamines and methylphenidate-containing products), including VYVANSE, have a high potential for abuse and dependence.  Assess the risk of abuse prior to prescribing and monitor for signs of abuse and dependence while on therapy   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1  ,   5.2  ), and   Drug Abuse and Dependence (9.2  ,   9.3  )].    



   EXCERPT:   WARNING:  ABUSE  AND DEPENDENCE 



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  CNS stimulants (amphetamines and methylphenidate-containing products), including VYVANSE, have a high potential for abuse and dependence (5.1, 9.2, 9.3) 
 *  Assess the risk of abuse prior to prescribing and monitor for signs of abuse and dependence while on therapy (5.1, 9.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Serious Cardiovascular Reactions: Sudden death in children and adolescents with serious heart problems, as well as sudden death, stroke, and myocardial infarction in adults reported. Avoid use in patients with known structural cardiac abnormalities, cardiomyopathy, serious heart arrhythmia, or coronary artery disease (  5.2  ) 
 *   Blood Pressure and Heart Rate Increases: Monitor blood pressure and pulse. Consider benefits and risks before use in patients for whom blood pressure increases may be problematic (  5.3  ) 
 *   Psychiatric Adverse Reactions: May cause psychotic or manic symptoms in patients with no prior history, or exacerbation of symptoms in patients with pre-existing psychosis. Evaluate for bipolar disorder prior to stimulant use (  5.4  ) 
 *   Suppression of Growth: Monitor height and weight in pediatric patients during treatment (  5.5  ) 
 *   Peripheral Vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon: Stimulants are associated with peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon. Careful observation for digital changes is necessary during treatment with stimulants (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Potential for Abuse and Dependence



  CNS stimulants (amphetamines and methylphenidate-containing products), including VYVANSE, have a high potential for abuse and dependence. Assess the risk of abuse prior to prescribing, and monitor for signs of abuse and dependence while on therapy [see  Drug Abuse and Dependence (9.2  ,  9.3)  ]  .



    5.2 Serious Cardiovascular Reactions



  Sudden death, stroke and myocardial infarction have been reported in adults with CNS stimulant treatment at recommended doses. Sudden death has been reported in children and adolescents with structural cardiac abnormalities and other serious heart problems taking CNS stimulants at recommended doses for ADHD. Avoid use in patients with known structural cardiac abnormalities, cardiomyopathy, serious heart arrhythmia, coronary artery disease, and other serious heart problems. Further evaluate patients who develop exertional chest pain, unexplained syncope, or arrhythmias during VYVANSE treatment.



    5.3 Blood Pressure and Heart Rate Increases



  CNS stimulants cause an increase in blood pressure (mean increase about 2-4 mm Hg) and heart rate (mean increase about 3-6 bpm). Monitor all patients for potential tachycardia and hypertension.



    5.4 Psychiatric Adverse Reactions



   Exacerbation of Pre-existing Psychosis  



 CNS stimulants may exacerbate symptoms of behavior disturbance and thought disorder in patients with a pre-existing psychotic disorder.



    Induction of a Manic Episode in Patients with Bipolar Disorder  



 CNS stimulants may induce a mixed/manic episode in patients with bipolar disorder. Prior to initiating treatment, screen patients for risk factors for developing a manic episode.



    New Psychotic or Manic Symptoms  



 CNS stimulants, at recommended doses, may cause psychotic or manic symptoms, e.g. hallucinations, delusional thinking, or mania in children and adolescents without a prior history of psychotic illness or mania. If such symptoms occur, consider discontinuing VYVANSE. In a pooled analysis of multiple short-term, placebo-controlled studies of CNS stimulants, psychotic or manic symptoms occurred in 0.1% of CNS stimulant-treated patients compared to 0% in placebo-treated patients.



    5.5 Suppression of Growth



  CNS stimulants have been associated with weight loss and slowing of growth rate in pediatric patients. Closely monitor growth (weight and height) in pediatric patients treated with CNS stimulants, including VYVANSE. In a 4-week, placebo-controlled trial of VYVANSE in patients ages 6 to 12 years old with ADHD, there was a dose-related decrease in weight in the VYVANSE groups compared to weight gain in the placebo group. Additionally, in studies of another stimulant, there was slowing of the increase in height [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



    5.6 Peripheral Vasculopathy, including Raynaud's Phenomenon



  Stimulants, including VYVANSE, are associated with peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon. Signs and symptoms are usually intermittent and mild; however, very rare sequelae include digital ulceration and/or soft tissue breakdown. Effects of peripheral vasculopathy, including Raynaud's phenomenon, were observed in post-marketing reports at different times and at therapeutic doses in all age groups throughout the course of treatment. Signs and symptoms generally improve after reduction in dose or discontinuation of drug. Careful observation for digital changes is necessary during treatment with stimulants. Further clinical evaluation (e.g., rheumatology referral) may be appropriate for certain patients.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
