<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="wellbutrin" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *    Suicidal thoughts and behaviors in adolescents and young adults [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  
 *    Neuropsychiatric symptoms and suicide risk in smoking cessation treatment [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  
 *    Seizure [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]  
 *    Hypertension [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)]  
 *    Activation of mania or hypomania [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)]  
 *    Psychosis and other neuropsychiatric reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (5.6)]  
 *    Angle-closure glaucoma [see Warnings and Precautions (5.7)]  
 *    Hypersensitivity reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (5.8)]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=5% and &gt;=2% more than placebo rate) are: headache, dry mouth, nausea, insomnia, dizziness, pharyngitis, constipation, agitation, anxiety, abdominal pain, tinnitus, tremor, palpitation, myalgia, sweating, rash, and anorexia. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact GlaxoSmithKline at 1-888-825-5249 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



   Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation of Treatment:  In placebo-controlled clinical trials, 4%, 9%, and 11% of the placebo, 300-mg-per-day, and 400-mg-per-day groups, respectively, discontinued treatment due to adverse reactions. The specific adverse reactions leading to discontinuation in at least 1% of the 300-mg-per-day or 400-mg-per-day groups and at a rate at least twice the placebo rate are listed in Table 2.



 Table 2. Treatment Discontinuations Due to Adverse Reactions in Placebo-Controlled Trials 
  Adverse Reaction      Placebo  (n = 385)    WELLBUTRIN SR 300 mg/day  (n = 376)    WELLBUTRIN SR 400 mg/day  (n = 114)    
  Rash                  0.0%         2.4%                                0.9%                                
  Nausea                0.3%         0.8%                                1.8%                                
  Agitation             0.3%         0.3%                                1.8%                                
  Migraine              0.3%         0.0%                                1.8%                                
            Commonly Observed Adverse Reactions  : Adverse reactions from Table 3 occurring in at least 5% of subjects treated with WELLBUTRIN SR and at a rate at least twice the placebo rate are listed below for the 300- and 400-mg-per-day dose groups.
 

 WELLBUTRIN SR 300 mg per day: Anorexia, dry mouth, rash, sweating, tinnitus, and tremor.



 WELLBUTRIN SR 400 mg per day: Abdominal pain, agitation, anxiety, dizziness, dry mouth, insomnia, myalgia, nausea, palpitation, pharyngitis, sweating, tinnitus, and urinary frequency.



 Adverse reactions reported in placebo-controlled trials are presented in Table 3. Reported adverse reactions were classified using a COSTART-based Dictionary.



 Table 3. Adverse Reactions Reported by at Least 1% of Subjects and at a Greater Frequency than Placebo in Controlled Clinical Trials 
  Body System/  Adverse Reaction       WELLBUTRIN SR 300 mg/day  (n = 376)    WELLBUTRIN SR 400 mg/day  (n = 114)    Placebo  (n = 385)    
  Body (General)                                                                                              
                                      Headache                            
                                                                            26%                           25%                           23%        
                                      Infection                           
                                                                            8%                            9%                            6%         
                                      Abdominal pain                      
                                                                            3%                            9%                            2%         
                                      Asthenia                            
                                                                            2%                            4%                            2%         
                                      Chest pain                          
                                                                            3%                            4%                            1%         
                                      Pain                                
                                                                            2%                            3%                            2%         
                                      Fever                               
                                                                            1%                            2%                            -          
  Cardiovascular                                                                                              
                                      Palpitation                         
                                                                            2%                            6%                            2%         
                                      Flushing                            
                                                                            1%                            4%                            -          
                                      Migraine                            
                                                                            1%                            4%                            1%         
                                      Hot flashes                         
                                                                            1%                            3%                            1%         
  Digestive                                                                                                   
                                      Dry mouth                           
                                                                            17%                           24%                           7%         
                                      Nausea                              
                                                                            13%                           18%                           8%         
                                      Constipation                        
                                                                            10%                           5%                            7%         
                                      Diarrhea                            
                                                                            5%                            7%                            6%         
                                      Anorexia                            
                                                                            5%                            3%                            2%         
                                      Vomiting                            
                                                                            4%                            2%                            2%         
                                      Dysphagia                           
                                                                            0%                            2%                            0%         
  Musculoskeletal                                                                                             
                                      Myalgia                             
                                                                            2%                            6%                            3%         
                                      Arthralgia                          
                                                                            1%                            4%                            1%         
                                      Arthritis                           
                                                                            0%                            2%                            0%         
                                      Twitch                              
                                                                            1%                            2%                            -          
  Nervous system                                                                                              
                                      Insomnia                            
                                                                            11%                           16%                           6%         
                                      Dizziness                           
                                                                            7%                            11%                           5%         
                                      Agitation                           
                                                                            3%                            9%                            2%         
                                      Anxiety                             
                                                                            5%                            6%                            3%         
                                      Tremor                              
                                                                            6%                            3%                            1%         
                                      Nervousness                         
                                                                            5%                            3%                            3%         
                                      Somnolence                          
                                                                            2%                            3%                            2%         
                                      Irritability                        
                                                                            3%                            2%                            2%         
                                      Memory decreased                    
                                                                            -                             3%                            1%         
                                      Paresthesia                         
                                                                            1%                            2%                            1%         
                                      Central nervous system stimulation  
                                                                            2%                            1%                            1%         
  Respiratory                                                                                                 
                                      Pharyngitis                         
                                                                            3%                            11%                           2%         
                                      Sinusitis                           
                                                                            3%                            1%                            2%         
                                      Increased cough                     
                                                                            1%                            2%                            1%         
  Skin                                                                                                        
                                      Sweating                            
                                                                            6%                            5%                            2%         
                                      Rash                                
                                                                            5%                            4%                            1%         
                                      Pruritus                            
                                                                            2%                            4%                            2%         
                                      Urticaria                           
                                                                            2%                            1%                            0%         
  Special senses                                                                                              
                                      Tinnitus                            
                                                                            6%                            6%                            2%         
                                      Taste perversion                    
                                                                            2%                            4%                            -          
                                      Blurred vision or diplopia          
                                                                            3%                            2%                            2%         
  Urogenital                                                                                                  
                                      Urinary frequency                   
                                                                            2%                            5%                            2%         
                                      Urinary urgency                     
                                                                            -                             2%                            0%         
                                      Vaginal hemorrhage  a               
                                                                            0%                            2%                            -          
                                      Urinary tract infection             
                                                                            1%                            0%                            -          
            a  Incidence based on the number of female subjects.
 

 - Hyphen denotes adverse events occurring in greater than 0 but less than 0.5% of subjects.



   Other Adverse Reactions Observed During the Clinical Development of Bupropion  : In addition to the adverse reactions noted above, the following adverse reactions have been reported in clinical trials with the sustained-release formulation of bupropion in depressed subjects and in nondepressed smokers, as well as in clinical trials with the immediate-release formulation of bupropion.



 Adverse reaction frequencies represent the proportion of subjects who experienced a treatment-emergent adverse reaction on at least one occasion in placebo-controlled trials for depression (n = 987) or smoking cessation (n = 1,013), or subjects who experienced an adverse reaction requiring discontinuation of treatment in an open-label surveillance trial with WELLBUTRIN SR (n = 3,100). All treatment-emergent adverse reactions are included except those listed in Table 3, those listed in other safety-related sections of the prescribing information, those subsumed under COSTART terms that are either overly general or excessively specific so as to be uninformative, those not reasonably associated with the use of the drug, and those that were not serious and occurred in fewer than 2 subjects.



 Adverse reactions are further categorized by body system and listed in order of decreasing frequency according to the following definitions of frequency: Frequent adverse reactions are defined as those occurring in at least 1/100 subjects. Infrequent adverse reactions are those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1,000 subjects, while rare events are those occurring in less than 1/1,000 subjects.



   Body (General):  Infrequent were chills, facial edema, and photosensitivity. Rare was malaise.



   Cardiovascular  : Infrequent were postural hypotension, stroke, tachycardia, and vasodilation. Rare were syncope and myocardial infarction.



   Digestive:  Infrequent were abnormal liver function, bruxism, gastric reflux, gingivitis, increased salivation, jaundice, mouth ulcers, stomatitis, and thirst. Rare was edema of tongue.



   Hemic and Lymphatic:  Infrequent was ecchymosis.



   Metabolic and Nutritional:  Infrequent were edema and peripheral edema.



   Musculoskeletal:  Infrequent were leg cramps.



   Nervous System:  Infrequent were abnormal coordination, decreased libido, depersonalization, dysphoria, emotional lability, hostility, hyperkinesia, hypertonia, hypesthesia, suicidal ideation, and vertigo. Rare were amnesia, ataxia, derealization, and hypomania.



   Respiratory:  Rare was bronchospasm.



   Special Senses:  Infrequent were accommodation abnormality and dry eye.



   Urogenital:  Infrequent were impotence, polyuria, and prostate disorder.



   Changes in Body Weight:  In placebo-controlled trials, subjects experienced weight gain or weight loss as shown in Table 4.



 Table 4. Incidence of Weight Gain and Weight Loss (&gt;=5 lbs) in Placebo-Controlled Trials 
  Weight Change       WELLBUTRIN SR 300 mg/day  (n = 339)    WELLBUTRIN SR 400 mg/day  (n = 112)    Placebo  (n = 347)    
  Gained &gt;5 lbs       3%                                   2%                                   4%            
  Lost &gt;5 lbs         14%                                  19%                                  6%            
          In clinical trials conducted with the immediate-release formulation of bupropion, 35% of subjects receiving tricyclic antidepressants gained weight, compared with 9% of subjects treated with the immediate-release formulation of bupropion. If weight loss is a major presenting sign of a patient's depressive illness, the anorectic and/or weight-reducing potential of WELLBUTRIN SR should be considered.
 

   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of WELLBUTRIN SR and are not described elsewhere in the label. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Body (General):  Arthralgia, myalgia, and fever with rash and other symptoms suggestive of delayed hypersensitivity. These symptoms may resemble serum sickness  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.8)].  



   Cardiovascular:  Complete atrioventricular block, extrasystoles, hypotension, hypertension (in some cases severe), phlebitis, and pulmonary embolism.



   Digestive:  Colitis, esophagitis, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, gum hemorrhage, hepatitis, intestinal perforation, pancreatitis, and stomach ulcer.



   Endocrine:  Hyperglycemia, hypoglycemia, and syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone.



   Hemic and Lymphatic:  Anemia, leukocytosis, leukopenia, lymphadenopathy, pancytopenia, and thrombocytopenia. Altered PT and/or INR, infrequently associated with hemorrhagic or thrombotic complications, were observed when bupropion was coadministered with warfarin.



   Metabolic and Nutritional  : Glycosuria.



   Musculoskeletal:  Muscle rigidity/fever/rhabdomyolysis and muscle weakness.



   Nervous System:  Abnormal electroencephalogram (EEG), aggression, akinesia, aphasia, coma, completed suicide, delirium, delusions, dysarthria, dyskinesia, dystonia, euphoria, extrapyramidal syndrome, hallucinations, hypokinesia, increased libido, manic reaction, neuralgia, neuropathy, paranoid ideation, restlessness, suicide attempt, and unmasking tardive dyskinesia.



   Respiratory:  Pneumonia.



   Skin:  Alopecia, angioedema, exfoliative dermatitis, hirsutism, and Stevens-Johnson syndrome.



   Special Senses:  Deafness, increased intraocular pressure, and mydriasis.



   Urogenital:  Abnormal ejaculation, cystitis, dyspareunia, dysuria, gynecomastia, menopause, painful erection, salpingitis, urinary incontinence, urinary retention, and vaginitis.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: SUICIDAL THOUGHTS AND BEHAVIORS; AND NEUROPSYCHIATRIC REACTIONS

  WARNING: SUICIDAL THOUGHTS AND BEHAVIORS; AND NEUROPSYCHIATRIC REACTIONS

      SUICIDALITY AND ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS    



 *   Antidepressants increased the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term trials. These trials did not show an increase in the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior with antidepressant use in subjects over age 24; there was a reduction in risk with antidepressant use in subjects aged 65 and older [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
 *   In patients of all ages who are started on antidepressant therapy, monitor closely for worsening, and for emergence of suicidal thoughts and behaviors. Advise families and caregivers of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
        NEUROPSYCHIATRIC REACTIONS IN PATIENTS TAKING BUPROPION FOR SMOKING CESSATION    
 

 *   Serious neuropsychiatric reactions have occurred in patientstaking bupropion for smoking cessation [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]. The majority of these reactions occurred during bupropion treatment, but some occurred in the context of discontinuing treatment. In many cases, a causal relationship to bupropion treatment is not certain, because depressed mood may be a symptom of nicotine withdrawal. However, some of the cases occurred in patients taking bupropion who continued to smoke. Although WELLBUTRIN(r) SR is not approved for smoking cessation, observe all patients for neuropsychiatric reactions. Instruct the patient to contact a healthcare provider if such reactions occur [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]. 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING: SUICIDAL THOUGHTS AND BEHAVIORS; AND NEUROPSYCHIATRIC REACTIONS
 

   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Increased the risk of suicidal thinking and behavior in children, adolescents, and young adults taking antidepressants. (5.1) 
 *  Monitor worsening and emergence of suicidal thoughts and behavior (5.1) 
 *  Serious neuropsychiatric events have been reported in patients taking bupropion for smoking cessation. (5.2) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Seizure risk: The risk is dose-related. Can minimize risk by gradually increasing the dose and limiting daily dose to 400 mg. Discontinue if seizure occurs. (  4  ,  5.3  ,  7.3  ) 
 *    Hypertension: WELLBUTRIN SR can increase blood pressure. Monitor blood pressure before initiating treatment and periodically during treatment. (  5.4  ) 
 *    Activation of mania/hypomania: Screen patients for bipolar disorder and monitor for these symptoms. (  5.5  ) 
 *    Psychosis and other neuropsychiatric reactions: Instruct patients to contact a healthcare professional if such reactions occur. (  5.6  ) 
 *    Angle-closure glaucoma: Angle-closure glaucoma has occurred in patients with untreated anatomically narrow angles treated with antidepressants. (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Suicidal Thoughts and Behaviors in Children, Adolescents, and Young Adults



  Patients with MDD, both adult and pediatric, may experience worsening of their depression and/or the emergence of suicidal ideation and behavior (suicidality) or unusual changes in behavior, whether or not they are taking antidepressant medications, and this risk may persist until significant remission occurs. Suicide is a known risk of depression and certain other psychiatric disorders, and these disorders themselves are the strongest predictors of suicide. There has been a long-standing concern that antidepressants may have a role in inducing worsening of depression and the emergence of suicidality in certain patients during the early phases of treatment.



 Pooled analyses of short-term placebo-controlled trials of antidepressant drugs (selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors [SSRIs] and others) show that these drugs increase the risk of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults (ages 18 to 24) with MDD and other psychiatric disorders. Short-term clinical trials did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared with placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction with antidepressants compared with placebo in adults aged 65 and older.



 The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in children and adolescents with MDD, obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD), or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 24 short-term trials of 9 antidepressant drugs in over 4,400 subjects. The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in adults with MDD or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 295 short-term trials (median duration of 2 months) of 11 antidepressant drugs in over 77,000 subjects. There was considerable variation in risk of suicidality among drugs, but a tendency toward an increase in the younger subjects for almost all drugs studied. There were differences in absolute risk of suicidality across the different indications, with the highest incidence in MDD. The risk differences (drug vs. placebo), however, were relatively stable within age strata and across indications. These risk differences (drug-placebo difference in the number of cases of suicidality per 1,000 subjects treated) are provided in Table 1.



 Table 1. Risk Differences in the Number of Suicidality Cases by Age Group in the Pooled Placebo-Controlled Trials of Antidepressants in Pediatric and Adult Subjects 
  Age Range      Drug-Placebo Difference in Number of Cases of Suicidality per 1,000 Subjects Treated     
  Increases Compared With Placebo    
  &lt;18            14 additional cases                                                                      
  18-24          5 additional cases                                                                       
  Decreases Compared With Placebo    
  25-64          1 fewer case                                                                             
  &gt;=65           6 fewer cases                                                                            
        No suicides occurred in any of the pediatric trials. There were suicides in the adult trials, but the number was not sufficient to reach any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.
 

 It is unknown whether the suicidality risk extends to longer-term use, i.e., beyond several months. However, there is substantial evidence from placebo-controlled maintenance trials in adults with depression that the use of antidepressants can delay the recurrence of depression.



  All patients being treated with antidepressants for any indication should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, and unusual changes in behavior, especially during the initial few months of a course of drug therapy, or at times of dose changes, either increases or decreases [see Boxed Warning]  .  



 The following symptoms, anxiety, agitation, panic attacks, insomnia, irritability, hostility, aggressiveness, impulsivity, akathisia (psychomotor restlessness), hypomania, and mania, have been reported in adult and pediatric patients being treated with antidepressants for major depressive disorder as well as for other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric. Although a causal link between the emergence of such symptoms and either the worsening of depression and/or the emergence of suicidal impulses has not been established, there is concern that such symptoms may represent precursors to emerging suicidality.



 Consideration should be given to changing the therapeutic regimen, including possibly discontinuing the medication, in patients whose depression is persistently worse, or who are experiencing emergent suicidality or symptoms that might be precursors to worsening depression or suicidality, especially if these symptoms are severe, abrupt in onset, or were not part of the patient's presenting symptoms.



  Families and caregivers of patients being treated with antidepressants for MDD or other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric, should be alerted about the need to monitor patients for the emergence of agitation, irritability, unusual changes in behavior, and the other symptoms described above, as well as the emergence of suicidality, and to report such symptoms immediately to healthcare providers. Such monitoring should include daily observation by families and caregivers. Prescriptions for WELLBUTRIN SR should be written for the smallest quantity of tablets consistent with good patient management, in order to reduce the risk of overdose.  



    5.2 Neuropsychiatric Symptoms and Suicide Risk in Smoking Cessation Treatment



  WELLBUTRIN SR is not approved for smoking cessation treatment; however, ZYBAN  (r)  is approved for this use. Serious neuropsychiatric symptoms have been reported in patients taking bupropion for smoking cessation. These have included changes in mood (including depression and mania), psychosis, hallucinations, paranoia, delusions, homicidal ideation, hostility, agitation, aggression, anxiety, and panic, as well as suicidal ideation, suicide attempt, and completed suicide [see Boxed Warning, Adverse Reactions (6.2)]  . Observe patients for the occurrence of neuropsychiatric reactions. Instruct patients to contact a healthcare professional if such reactions occur.



 In many of these cases, a causal relationship to bupropion treatment is not certain, because depressed mood can be a symptom of nicotine withdrawal. However, some of the cases occurred in patients taking bupropion who continued to smoke.



    5.3 Seizure



  WELLBUTRIN SR can cause seizure. The risk of seizure is dose-related. The dose should not exceed 400 mg per day. Increase the dose gradually. Discontinue WELLBUTRIN SR and do not restart treatment if the patient experiences a seizure.



 The risk of seizures is also related to patient factors, clinical situations, and concomitant medications that lower the seizure threshold. Consider these risks before initiating treatment with WELLBUTRIN SR. WELLBUTRIN SR is contraindicated in patients with a seizure disorder, current or prior diagnosis of anorexia nervosa or bulimia, or undergoing abrupt discontinuation of alcohol, benzodiazepines, barbiturates, and antiepileptic drugs [see Contraindications (4), Drug Interactions (7.3)]  . The following conditions can also increase the risk of seizure: severe head injury; arteriovenous malformation; CNS tumor or CNS infection; severe stroke; concomitant use of other medications that lower the seizure threshold (e.g., other bupropion products, antipsychotics, tricyclic antidepressants, theophylline, and systemic corticosteroids); metabolic disorders (e.g., hypoglycemia, hyponatremia, severe hepatic impairment, and hypoxia); use of illicit drugs (e.g., cocaine); or abuse or misuse of prescription drugs such as CNS stimulants. Additional predisposing conditions include diabetes mellitus treated with oral hypoglycemic drugs or insulin; use of anorectic drugs; and excessive use of alcohol, benzodiazepines, sedative/hypnotics, or opiates.



  Incidence of Seizure with Bupropion Use  : When WELLBUTRIN SR is dosed up to 300 mg per day, the incidence of seizure is approximately 0.1% (1/1,000) and increases to approximately 0.4% (4/1,000) at the maximum recommended dose of 400 mg per day.



 The risk of seizure can be reduced if the dose of WELLBUTRIN SR does not exceed 400 mg per day, given as 200 mg twice daily, and the titration rate is gradual.



    5.4 Hypertension



  Treatment with WELLBUTRIN SR can result in elevated blood pressure and hypertension. Assess blood pressure before initiating treatment with WELLBUTRIN SR, and monitor periodically during treatment. The risk of hypertension is increased if WELLBUTRIN SR is used concomitantly with MAOIs or other drugs that increase dopaminergic or noradrenergic activity [see Contraindications (4)].  



 Data from a comparative trial of the sustained-release formulation of bupropion HCl, nicotine transdermal system (NTS), the combination of sustained-release bupropion plus NTS, and placebo as an aid to smoking cessation suggest a higher incidence of treatment-emergent hypertension in patients treated with the combination of sustained-release bupropion and NTS. In this trial, 6.1% of subjects treated with the combination of sustained-release bupropion and NTS had treatment-emergent hypertension compared with 2.5%, 1.6%, and 3.1% of subjects treated with sustained-release bupropion, NTS, and placebo, respectively. The majority of these subjects had evidence of pre-existing hypertension. Three subjects (1.2%) treated with the combination of sustained-release bupropion and NTS and 1 subject (0.4%) treated with NTS had study medication discontinued due to hypertension compared with none of the subjects treated with sustained-release bupropion or placebo. Monitoring of blood pressure is recommended in patients who receive the combination of bupropion and nicotine replacement.



 In a clinical trial of bupropion immediate-release in MDD subjects with stable congestive heart failure (N = 36), bupropion was associated with an exacerbation of pre-existing hypertension in 2 subjects, leading to discontinuation of bupropion treatment. There are no controlled trials assessing the safety of bupropion in patients with a recent history of myocardial infarction or unstable cardiac disease.



    5.5 Activation of Mania/Hypomania



  Antidepressant treatment can precipitate a manic, mixed, or hypomanic manic episode. The risk appears to be increased in patients with bipolar disorder or who have risk factors for bipolar disorder. Prior to initiating WELLBUTRIN SR, screen patients for a history of bipolar disorder and the presence of risk factors for bipolar disorder (e.g., family history of bipolar disorder, suicide, or depression). WELLBUTRIN SR is not approved for use in treating bipolar depression.



    5.6 Psychosis and Other Neuropsychiatric Reactions



  Depressed patients treated with WELLBUTRIN SR have had a variety of neuropsychiatric signs and symptoms, including delusions, hallucinations, psychosis, concentration disturbance, paranoia, and confusion. Some of these patients had a diagnosis of bipolar disorder. In some cases, these symptoms abated upon dose reduction and/or withdrawal of treatment. Instruct patients to contact a healthcare professional if such reactions occur.



     5.7 Angle-Closure Glaucoma  



   The pupillary dilation that occurs following use of many antidepressant drugs including WELLBUTRIN SR may trigger an angle-closure attack in a patient with anatomically narrow angles who does not have a patent iridectomy.  



    5.8 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reactions have occurred during clinical trials with bupropion. Reactions have been characterized by pruritus, urticaria, angioedema, and dyspnea requiring medical treatment. In addition, there have been rare, spontaneous postmarketing reports of erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and anaphylactic shock associated with bupropion. Instruct patients to discontinue WELLBUTRIN SR and consult a healthcare provider if they develop an allergic or anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reaction (e.g., skin rash, pruritus, hives, chest pain, edema, and shortness of breath) during treatment.



 There are reports of arthralgia, myalgia, fever with rash and other serum sickness-like symptoms suggestive of delayed hypersensitivity.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
