<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="wellbutrinxl" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  



 The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 Suicidal thoughts and behaviors in children, adolescents, and young adults [see



     Warnings and Precautions (5.1)    



 ]Neuropsychiatric symptoms and suicide risk in smoking cessation treatment [see



     Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    



 ]Seizure [see



     Warnings and Precautions (5.3)    



 ]Hypertension [see



     Warnings and Precautions (5.4)    



 ]Activation of mania or hypomania [see



     Warnings and Precautions (5.5)    



 ]Psychosis and other neuropsychiatric events [see



     Warnings and Precautions (5.6)    



 ]Angle Closure Glaucoma [see



     Warnings and Precautions (5.7)    



 ]Hypersensitivity reactions [see



     Warnings and Precautions (5.8)    



 ]



  



 



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



  



 



 Adverse reactions that occurred in at least 5% of patients treated with bupropion HCl sustained-release (300 mg and 400 mg per day) and at a rate at least twice the placebo rate are listed below.



   300 mg/day of bupropion HCl sustained-release:  anorexia, dry mouth, rash, sweating, tinnitus, and tremor.



   400 mg/day of bupropion HCl sustained-release:  abdominal pain, agitation, anxiety, dizziness, dry mouth, insomnia, myalgia, nausea, palpitation, pharyngitis, sweating, tinnitus, and urinary frequency.



 WELLBUTRIN XL has been demonstrated to have similar bioavailability both to the immediate-release and sustained-release formulations of bupropion. The information included under this subsection and under the subsections 6.2 is based primarily on data from controlled clinical trials with the sustained-release and extended release formulations of bupropion hydrochloride.



       Major Depressive Disorder      



   Adverse Reactions Leading to Discontinuation of Treatment with Bupropion HCl Immediate-Release, Bupropion HCl Sustained-Release, and Bupropion HCl Extended-Release in Major Depressive Disorder Trials  



 In placebo-controlled clinical trials with bupropion HCl sustained-release, 4%, 9%, and 11% of the placebo, 300 mg/day and 400 mg/day groups, respectively, discontinued treatment because of adverse reactions. The specific adverse reactions leading to discontinuation in at least 1% of the 300 mg/day or 400 mg/day groups and at a rate at least twice the placebo rate are listed in Table 2.



 Table 2: Treatment Discontinuation Due to Adverse Reactions in Placebo-Controlled Trials in MDD 
   Adverse Reaction Term      Placebo    (n=385)         Bupropion HCl Sustained-Release 300 mg/day    (n=376)      Bupropion HCl Sustained-Release 400 mg/day    (n=114)     
  Rash                       0.0%                       2.4%                       0.9%                       
  Nausea                     0.3%                       0.8%                       1.8%                       
  Agitation                  0.3%                       0.3%                       1.8%                       
  Migraine                   0.3%                       0.0%                       1.8%                       
          In clinical trials with bupropion HCl immediate-release, 10% of patients and volunteers discontinued due to an adverse reaction. Reactions resulting in discontinuation, (in addition to those listed above for the sustained-release formulation), included vomiting, seizures, and sleep disturbances.
 

   Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of &gt;1% in Patients Treated with Bupropion HCl Immediate-Release or Bupropion HCl Sustained-Release in MDD  



 Table 3 summarizes the adverse reactions that occurred in placebo-controlled trials in patients treated with bupropion HCl sustained-release 300 mg/day and 400 mg/day. These include reactions that occurred in either the 300 mg or 400 mg group at an incidence of 1% or more and were more frequent than in the placebo group are included.



 Table 3: Adverse Reactions in Placebo-Controlled Trials in Patients with MDD 
   Body System/Adverse Reaction      Placebo    (n=385)         Bupropion HCl Sustained-Release 300 mg/day    (n=376)      Bupropion HCl Sustained-Release 400 mg/day    (n=114)     
  Body (General)                                                                                              
      Headache               23%                        26%                        25%                        
      Infection              6%                         8%                         9%                         
      Abdominal pain         2%                         3%                         9%                         
      Asthenia               2%                         2%                         4%                         
      Chest Pain             1%                         3%                         4%                         
      Pain                   2%                         2%                         3%                         
      Fever                  -                          1%                         2%                         
  Cardiovascular                                                                                              
      Palpitation            2%                         2%                         6%                         
      Flushing               -                          1%                         4%                         
      Migraine               1%                         1%                         4%                         
      Hot flashes            1%                         1%                         3%                         
  Digestive                                                                                                   
      Dry mouth              7%                         17%                        24%                        
      Nausea                 8%                         13%                        18%                        
      Constipation           7%                         10%                        5%                         
      Diarrhea               6%                         5%                         7%                         
      Anorexia               2%                         5%                         3%                         
      Vomiting               2%                         4%                         2%                         
      Dysphagia              0%                         0%                         2%                         
  Musculoskeletal                                                                                             
      Myalgia                3%                         2%                         6%                         
      Arthralgia             1%                         1%                         4%                         
      Arthritis              0%                         0%                         2%                         
      Twitch                 -                          1%                         2%                         
  Nervous System                                                                                              
      Insomnia               6%                         11%                        16%                        
      Dizziness              5%                         7%                         11%                        
      Agitation              2%                         3%                         9%                         
      Anxiety                3%                         5%                         6%                         
      Tremor                 1%                         6%                         3%                         
      Nervousness            3%                         5%                         3%                         
      Somnolence             2%                         2%                         3%                         
      Irritability           2%                         3%                         2%                         
      Memory decreased       1%                         -                          3%                         
      Paresthesia            1%                         1%                         2%                         
      Central nervous system stimulation    1%                         2%                         1%                         
  Respiratory                                                                                                 
      Pharyngitis            2%                         3%                         11%                        
      Sinusitis              2%                         3%                         1%                         
      Increased cough        1%                         1%                         2%                         
  Skin                                                                                                        
      Sweating               2%                         6%                         5%                         
      Rash                   1%                         5%                         4%                         
      Pruritus               2%                         2%                         4%                         
      Urticaria              0%                         2%                         1%                         
  Special Senses                                                                                              
      Tinnitus               2%                         6%                         6%                         
      Taste perversion       -                          2%                         4%                         
      Blurred vision or diplopia    2%                         3%                         2%                         
  Urogenital                                                                                                  
      Urinary frequency      2%                         2%                         5%                         
      Urinary urgency        0%                         -                          2%                         
      Vaginal hemorrhage*    -                          0%                         2%                         
      Urinary tract infection    -                          1%                         0%                         
        (Incidence based on the number of female patients.)  
 

   (Hyphen denotes adverse reactions occurring in greater than 0 but less than 0.5% of patients) 
 

 The following additional adverse reactions occurred in controlled trials of bupropion HCl immediate-release (300 to 600 mg per day) at an incidence of at least 1% more frequently than in the placebo group were: cardiac arrhythmia (5% vs. 4%), hypertension (4% vs. 2%), hypotension (3% vs. 2%), menstrual complaints (5% vs. 1%), akathisia (2% vs. 1%), impaired sleep quality (4% vs. 2%), sensory disturbance (4% vs. 3%), confusion (8% vs. 5%), decreased libido (3% vs. 2%), hostility (6% vs. 4%), auditory disturbance (5% vs. 3%), and gustatory disturbance (3% vs. 1%).



       Seasonal Affective Disorder      



 In placebo-controlled clinical trials in SAD, 9% of patients treated with WELLBUTRIN XL and 5% of patients treated with placebo discontinued treatment because of adverse reactions. The adverse reactions leading to discontinuation in at least 1% of patients treated with bupropion and at a rate numerically greater than the placebo rate were insomnia (2% vs. &lt;1%) and headache (1% vs. &lt;1%).



 Table 4 summarizes the adverse reactions that occurred in patients treated with WELLBUTRIN XL for up to approximately 6 months in 3 placebo-controlled trials. These include reactions that occurred at an incidence of 2% or more and were more frequent than in the placebo group.



 Table 4: Adverse Reactions in Placebo-Controlled Trials in Patients with SAD 
   System Organ Class/Preferred Term         Placebo    (n=511)              Bupropion HCl    Extended-Release    (n=537)     
  Gastrointestinal Disorder                                                                                 
      Dry mouth                             15%                             26%                             
      Nausea                                8%                              13%                             
      Constipation                          2%                              9%                              
      Flatulence                            3%                              6%                              
      Abdominal pain                        &lt;1%                             2%                              
  Nervous System Disorders                                                                                  
      Headache                              26%                             34%                             
      Dizziness                             5%                              6%                              
      Tremor                                &lt;1%                             3%                              
  Infections and Infestations                                                                               
      Nasopharyngitis                       12%                             13%                             
      Upper respiratory tract infection     8%                              9%                              
      Sinusitis                             4%                              5%                              
  Psychiatric Disorders                                                                                     
      Insomnia                              13%                             20%                             
      Anxiety                               5%                              7%                              
      Abnormal dreams                       2%                              3%                              
      Agitation                             &lt;1%                             2%                              
  Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders                                                                    
      Myalgia                               2%                              3%                              
      Pain in extremity                     2%                              3%                              
  Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal Disorders                                                                    
      Cough                                 3%                              4%                              
  General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions                                                                    
      Feeling jittery                       2%                              3%                              
  Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders                                                                    
      Rash                                  2%                              3%                              
  Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders                                                                        
      Decreased appetite                    1%                              4%                              
  Reproductive System and Breast Disorders                                                                    
      Dysmenorrhea                          &lt;1%                             2%                              
  Ear and Labyrinth Disorders                                                                               
      Tinnitus                              &lt;1%                             3%                              
  Vascular Disorders                                                                                        
      Hypertension                          0%                              2%                              
               Changes in Body Weight      
 

 Table 5 presents the incidence of body weight changes (&gt;=5 lbs) in the short-term MDD trials using bupropion HCl sustained-release. There was a dose-related decrease in body weight.



 Table 5: Incidence of Weight Gain or Weight Loss (&gt;=5 lbs.) in MDD Trials Using Bupropion HCl Sustained-Release 
   Weight Change              Bupropion HCl    Sustained-Release    300 mg/day    (n=339)      Bupropion HCl    Sustained-Release    400 mg/day    (n=112)      Placebo    (n=347)        
  Gained &gt;5 lbs              3%                         2%                         4%                         
  Lost &gt;5 lbs                14%                        19%                        6%                         
          Table 6 presents the incidence of body weight changes (&gt;=5 lbs) in the 3 SAD trials using bupropion HCl extended-release. A higher proportion of subjects in the bupropion group (23%) had a weight loss &gt;=5 lbs., compared to the placebo group (11%). These were relatively long-term trials (up to 6 months).
 

 Table 6: Incidence of Weight Gain or Weight Loss (&gt;=5 lbs) in SAD Trials Using Bupropion HCl Extended-Release 
   Weight Change                       Bupropion HCl    Extended-Release    150 to 300 mg/day    (n=537)      Placebo    (n=511)                
  Gained &gt;5 lbs                       11%                                21%                                
  Lost &gt;5 lbs                         23%                                11%                                
          
 

 



 The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of WELLBUTRIN XL. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Body (General)  



 Chills, facial edema, edema, peripheral edema, musculoskeletal chest pain, photosensitivity, and malaise.



   Cardiovascular  



 Postural hypotension, hypertension, stroke, vasodilation, syncope, complete atrioventricular block, extrasystoles, myocardial infarction, phlebitis, and pulmonary embolism.



   Digestive  



 Abnormal liver function, bruxism, gastric reflux, gingivitis, glossitis, increased salivation, jaundice, mouth ulcers, stomatitis, thirst, edema of tongue, colitis, esophagitis, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, gum hemorrhage, hepatitis, intestinal perforation, liver damage, pancreatitis, and stomach ulcer.



   Endocrine  



 Hyperglycemia, hypoglycemia, and syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion.



   Hemic and Lymphatic  



 Ecchymosis, anemia, leukocytosis, leukopenia, lymphadenopathy, pancytopenia, and thrombocytopenia. Altered PT and/or INR, associated with hemorrhagic or thrombotic complications, were observed when bupropion was coadministered with warfarin.



   Metabolic and Nutritional  



 Glycosuria.



   Musculoskeletal  



 Leg cramps, fever/rhabdomyolysis, and muscle weakness.



   Nervous System  



 Abnormal coordination, depersonalization, emotional lability, hyperkinesia, hypertonia, hypesthesia, vertigo, amnesia, ataxia, derealization, abnormal electroencephalogram (EEG), aggression, akinesia, aphasia, coma, dysarthria, dyskinesia, dystonia, euphoria, extrapyramidal syndrome, hypokinesia, increased libido, neuralgia, neuropathy, paranoid ideation, restlessness, suicide attempt, and unmasking tardive dyskinesia.



   Respiratory  



 Bronchospasm and pneumonia.



   Skin  



 Maculopapular rash, alopecia, angioedema, exfoliative dermatitis, and hirsutism.



   Special Senses  



 Accommodation abnormality, dry eye, deafness, increased intraocular pressure, angle-closure glaucoma, and mydriasis.



   Urogenital  



 Impotence, polyuria, prostate disorder, abnormal ejaculation, cystitis, dyspareunia, dysuria, gynecomastia, menopause, painful erection, salpingitis, urinary incontinence, urinary retention, and vaginitis.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: Boxed Warning section

  Boxed Warning section

  



   SUICIDALITY AND ANTIDEPRESSANT DRUGS  



   Antidepressants increased the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior in children, adolescents, and young adults in short-term trials.  These trials did not show an increase in the risk of suicidal thoughts and behavior with antidepressants use in subjects aged 65 and older [see   Warnings and Precautions (        5.1    )      ].  



   In patients of all ages who are started on antidepressant therapy, monitor closely for worsening, and for emergence of suicidal thoughts and behaviors.  Advise families and caregivers of the need for close observation and communication with the prescriber [see   Warnings and Precautions (        5.1    )      ].    



   NEUROPSYCHIATRIC REACTIONS IN PATIENTS TAKING BUPROPION FOR SMOKING CESSATION  



   Serious neuropsychiatric reactions have occurred in patients taking bupropion for smoking cessation [see   Warnings and Precautions (        5.2    )      ].  The majority of these reactions occurred during bupropion treatment, but some occurred in the context of discontinuing treatment.  In many cases, a causal relationship to bupropion treatment is not certain, because depressed mood may be a symptom of nicotine withdrawal.  However, some of the cases occurred in patients taking bupropion who continued to smoke.  Although WELLBUTRIN XL is not approved for smoking cessation, observe all patients for neuropsychiatric reactions.  Instruct the patient to contact a healthcare provider if such reactions occur [see   Warnings and Precautions (        5.2    )      ].  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  



 Seizure risk: The risk is dose-related. Can minimize risk by limiting daily dose to 450 mg and gradually increasing the dose. Discontinue if seizure occurs. (



   4  



 ,



   5.3  



 ,



   7.3  



 )Hypertension: WELLBUTRIN XL can increase blood pressure. Monitor blood pressure before initiating treatment and periodically during treatment. (



   5.4  



 )Activation of mania/hypomania: Screen patients for bipolar disorder and monitor for these symptoms. (



   5.5  



 )Psychosis and other neuropsychiatric reactions: Instruct patients to contact a healthcare professional if such reactions occur. (



   5.6  



 )Angle Closure Glaucoma: Angle closure glaucoma has occurred in patients with untreated anatomically narrow angles treated with antidepressants. (



   5.7  



 )



  



 



 Patients with major depressive disorder (MDD), both adult and pediatric, may experience worsening of their depression and/or the emergence of suicidal ideation and behavior (suicidality) or unusual changes in behavior, whether or not they are taking antidepressant medications, and this risk may persist until significant remission occurs. Suicide is a known risk of depression and certain other psychiatric disorders, and these disorders themselves are the strongest predictors of suicide. There has been a long-standing concern that antidepressants may have a role in inducing worsening of depression and the emergence of suicidality in certain patients during the early phases of treatment.



 Pooled analyses of short-term placebo-controlled trials of antidepressant drugs (SSRIs and others) show that these drugs increase the risk of suicidal thinking and behavior (suicidality) in children, adolescents, and young adults (ages 18 to 24) with major depressive disorder (MDD) and other psychiatric disorders. Short-term studies did not show an increase in the risk of suicidality with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults beyond age 24; there was a reduction with antidepressants compared to placebo in adults aged 65 and older.



 The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in children and adolescents with MDD, obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD), or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 24 short-term trials of 9 antidepressant drugs in over 4400 patients. The pooled analyses of placebo-controlled trials in adults with MDD or other psychiatric disorders included a total of 295 short-term trials (median duration of 2 months) of 11 antidepressant drugs in over 77,000 patients. There was considerable variation in risk of suicidality among drugs, but a tendency toward an increase in the younger patients for almost all drugs studied. There were differences in absolute risk of suicidality across the different indications, with the highest incidence in MDD. The risk differences (drug vs. placebo), however, were relatively stable within age strata and across indications. These risk differences (drug-placebo difference in the number of cases of suicidality per 1000 patients treated) are provided in Table 1.



 Table 1: Risk Differences in the Number of Suicidality Cases by Age Group in the Pooled Placebo-Controlled Trials of Antidepressants in Pediatric and Adult Patients 
  Age Range                                           Drug-Placebo Difference in Number of Cases   of Suicidality per 1000 Patients Treated     
  Increases Compared to Placebo                       
  &lt;18 years                                           14 additional cases                                 
  18-24 years                                         5 additional cases                                  
  Decreases Compared to Placebo                       
  25-64 years                                         1 fewer case                                        
  &gt;=65 years                                          6 fewer cases                                       
        No suicides occurred in any of the pediatric trials. There were suicides in the adult trials, but the number was not sufficient to reach any conclusion about drug effect on suicide.
 

 It is unknown whether the suicidality risk extends to longer-term use, i.e., beyond several months. However, there is substantial evidence from placebo-controlled maintenance trials in adults with depression that the use of antidepressants can delay the recurrence of depression.



  All patients being treated with antidepressants for any indication should be monitored appropriately and observed closely for clinical worsening, suicidality, and unusual changes in behavior, especially during the initial few months of a course of drug therapy, or at times of dose changes, either increases or decreases [see   Boxed Warning    and   Use in Specific Populations (8.4)    ].  



 The following symptoms, anxiety, agitation, panic attacks, insomnia, irritability, hostility, aggressiveness, impulsivity, akathisia (psychomotor restlessness), hypomania, and mania have been reported in adult and pediatric patients being treated with antidepressants for major depressive disorder as well as for other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric. Although a causal link between the emergence of such symptoms and either the worsening of depression and/or the emergence of suicidal impulses has not been established, there is concern that such symptoms may represent precursors to emerging suicidality.



 Consideration should be given to changing the therapeutic regimen, including possibly discontinuing the medication, in patients whose depression is persistently worse, or who are experiencing emergent suicidality or symptoms that might be precursors to worsening depression or suicidality, especially if these symptoms are severe, abrupt in onset, or were not part of the patient's presenting symptoms.



  Families and caregivers of patients being treated with antidepressants for major depressive disorder or other indications, both psychiatric and nonpsychiatric, should be alerted about the need to monitor patients for the emergence of agitation, irritability, unusual changes in behavior, and the other symptoms described above, as well as the emergence of suicidality, and to report such symptoms immediately to health care providers. Such monitoring should include daily observation by families and caregivers. Prescriptions for WELLBUTRIN XL should be written for the smallest quantity of tablets consistent with good patient management, in order to reduce the risk of overdose.  



  



 



 WELLBUTRIN XL is not approved for smoking cessation treatment; however, bupropion HCl sustained-release is approved for this use. Serious neuropsychiatric symptoms have been reported in patients taking bupropion for smoking cessation. These have included changes in mood (including depression and mania), psychosis, hallucinations, paranoia, delusions, homicidal ideation, hostility, agitation, aggression, anxiety, and panic, as well as suicidal ideation, suicide attempt, and completed suicide [see   Boxed Warning    and   Adverse Reactions (6.2)    ]. Observe patients for the occurrence of neuropsychiatric reactions. Instruct patients to contact a healthcare professional if such reactions occur.



 In many of these cases, a causal relationship to bupropion treatment is not certain, because depressed mood can be a symptom of nicotine withdrawal. However, some of the cases occurred in patients taking bupropion who continued to smoke.



  



 



 WELLBUTRIN XL can cause seizure. The risk of seizure is dose-related. The dose should not exceed 300 mg once daily. Increase the dose gradually. Discontinue WELLBUTRIN XL and do not restart treatment if the patient experiences a seizure.



 The risk of seizures is also related to patient factors, clinical situations, and concomitant medications that lower the seizure threshold. Consider these risks before initiating treatment with WELLBUTRIN XL. WELLBUTRIN XL is contraindicated in patients with a seizure disorder or conditions that increase the risk of seizure (e.g., severe head injury, arteriovenous malformation, CNS tumor or CNS infection, severe stroke, anorexia nervosa or bulimia, or abrupt discontinuation of alcohol, benzodiazepines, barbiturates, and antiepileptic drugs [see   Contraindications (4)    ]. The following conditions can also increase the risk of seizure: concomitant use of other medications that lower the seizure threshold (e.g., other bupropion products, antipsychotics, tricyclic antidepressants, theophylline, and systemic corticosteroids), metabolic disorders (e.g., hypoglycemia, hyponatremia, severe hepatic impairment, and hypoxia), or use of illicit drugs (e.g., cocaine) or abuse or misuse of prescription drugs such as CNS stimulants. Additional predisposing conditions include diabetes mellitus treated with oral hypoglycemic drugs or insulin, use of anorectic drugs, excessive use of alcohol, benzodiazepines, sedative/hypnotics, or opiates.



  Incidence of Seizure with Bupropion Use  



 The incidence of seizure with WELLBUTRIN XL has not been formally evaluated in clinical trials. In studies using bupropion HCl sustained-release up to 300 mg per day the incidence of seizure was approximately 0.1% (1/1000 patients). In a large prospective, follow-up study, the seizure incidence was approximately 0.4% (13/3200) with bupropion HCl immediate-release in the range of 300 mg to 450 mg per day.



 Additional data accumulated for bupropion immediate-release suggests that the estimated seizure incidence increases almost tenfold between 450 and 600 mg/day. The risk of seizure can be reduced if the WELLBUTRIN XL dose does not exceed 450 mg once daily and the titration rate is gradual.



  



 



 Treatment with WELLBUTRIN XL can result in elevated blood pressure and hypertension. Assess blood pressure before initiating treatment with WELLBUTRIN XL, and monitor periodically during treatment. The risk of hypertension is increased if WELLBUTRIN XL is used concomitantly with MAOIs or other drugs that increase dopaminergic or noradrenergic activity [see Contraindications (       4   )     ].  



  Data from a comparative trial of the sustained-release formulation of bupropion HCl, nicotine transdermal system (NTS), the combination of sustained-release bupropion plus NTS, and placebo as an aid to smoking cessation suggest a higher incidence of treatment-emergent hypertension in patients treated with the combination of sustained-release bupropion and NTS. In this trial, 6.1% of subjects treated with the combination of sustained-release bupropion and NTS had treatment-emergent hypertension compared to 2.5%, 1.6%, and 3.1% of subjects treated with sustained-release bupropion, NTS, and placebo, respectively. The majority of these subjects had evidence of pre-existing hypertension. Three subjects (1.2%) treated with the combination of sustained-release bupropion and NTS and 1 subject (0.4%) treated with NTS had study medication discontinued due to hypertension compared with none of the subjects treated with sustained-release bupropion or placebo. Monitoring of blood pressure is recommended in patients who receive the combination of bupropion and nicotine replacement.  



 In the 3 trials of bupropion HCl extended-release in seasonal affective disorder, there were significant elevations in blood pressure. Hypertension was reported as an adverse reaction for 2% of the bupropion group (11/537) and none in the placebo group (0/511). In the SAD trials, 2 patients treated with bupropion discontinued from the study because they developed hypertension. None of the placebo group discontinued because of hypertension. The mean increase in systolic blood pressure was 1.3 mmHg in the bupropion group and 0.1 mmHg in the placebo group. The difference was statistically significant (p=0.013). The mean increase in diastolic blood pressure was 0.8 mmHg in the bupropion group and 0.1 mmHg in the placebo group. The difference was not statistically significant (p=0.075). In the SAD trials, 82% of patients were treated with 300 mg per day, and 18% were treated with 150 mg per day. The mean daily dose was 270 mg per day. The mean duration of bupropion exposure was 126 days.



 In a clinical trial of bupropion immediate-release in MDD subjects with stable congestive heart failure (N=36), bupropion was associated with an exacerbation of pre-existing hypertension in 2 patients, leading to discontinuation of bupropion treatment. There are no controlled studies assessing the safety of bupropion in patients with a recent history of myocardial infarction or unstable cardiac disease.



  



 



 Antidepressant treatment can precipitate a manic, mixed, or hypomanic manic episode. The risk appears to be increased in patients with bipolar disorder or who have risk factors for bipolar disorder. Prior to initiating WELLBUTRIN XL, screen patients for a history of bipolar disorder and the presence of risk factors for bipolar disorder (e.g., family history of bipolar disorder, suicide, or depression). WELLBUTRIN XL is not approved for the treatment of bipolar depression.



  



 



 Depressed patients treated with bupropion have had a variety of neuropsychiatric signs and symptoms, including delusions, hallucinations, psychosis, concentration disturbance, paranoia, and confusion. Some of these patients had a diagnosis of bipolar disorder. In some cases, these symptoms abated upon dose reduction and/or withdrawal of treatment. Discontinue WELLBUTRIN XL if these reactions occur.



  



 



  Angle-Closure Glaucoma: The pupillary dilation that occurs following use of many antidepressant drugs including WELLBUTRIN XL may trigger an angle closure attack in a patient with anatomically narrow angles who does not have a patent iridectomy.  



  



 



 Anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reactions have occurred during clinical trials with bupropion. Reactions have been characterized by pruritus, urticaria, angioedema, and dyspnea, requiring medical treatment. In addition, there have been rare, spontaneous postmarketing reports of erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, and anaphylactic shock associated with bupropion. Instruct patients to discontinue WELLBUTRIN XL and consult a health care provider if they develop an allergic or anaphylactoid/anaphylactic reaction (e.g., skin rash, pruritus, hives, chest pain, edema, and shortness of breath) during treatment.



 There are reports of arthralgia, myalgia, fever with rash and other symptoms of serum sickness suggestive of delayed hypersensitivity.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
