<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="xartemis" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following treatment-emergent adverse reactions are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Respiratory Depression [see Contraindications (  4  ), Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  ), and Overdosage (  10  )]  
 *  Hepatotoxicity [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
 *  Use With Other Acetaminophen-containing Products [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.11  )]  
 *  Interactions with Other CNS Depressants [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse events with XARTEMIS XR are nausea, dizziness, headache, vomiting, constipation and somnolence. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Mallinckrodt at 1-800-778-7898 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1       Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 In safety data from two Phase 3 (one placebo-controlled, one open-label) trials where multiple doses of XARTEMIS XR were administered for up to 42 days, the most common adverse reactions (reported by &gt;=10% in any XARTEMIS XR dose group) were: nausea, dizziness and vomiting. The most common reasons for discontinuation due to AEs in these 2 studies (reported by &gt;=1% in any XARTEMIS XR dose group) were vomiting (4.8%) and nausea (4.1%); there were no reports of these adverse reactions in the placebo-treated patients.



 A total of 1028 subjects in 14 clinical studies were treated with XARTEMIS XR during the clinical development program, including 892 subjects treated with 15 mg oxycodone and 650 mg acetaminophen. This dosage regimen of XARTEMIS XR was administered to 607 patients in two Phase 3 studies (one placebo-controlled and one open-label).



 In a placebo-controlled post-bunionectomy acute pain trial, 329 patients were dosed with 15 mg oxycodone and 650 mg acetaminophen XARTEMIS XR or placebo orally every 12 hours, for approximately 48 hours (blinded period)  [see Clinical Studies (  14  )]  .  Table 1  lists the adverse reactions reported by &gt;=1% of XARTEMIS XR-treated patients and more frequently in XARTEMIS XR-treated patients compared with placebo.



   Table 1. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions* Reported by &gt;=1% of XARTEMIS XR-Treated Patients and More Frequently than Placebo in XARTEMIS XR-Treated Patients with Postoperative Bunionectomy Pain (blinded period)  




  Preferred Term    XARTEMIS XR(N = 166)%    Placebo(N = 163)%    
  Nausea           31               6                
  Dizziness        13               1                
  Headache         10               5                
  Vomiting         9                0                
  Constipation     4                3                
  Somnolence       4                &lt;1               
  Rash             2                1                
  Blister          1                &lt;1               
  Dysuria          1                0                
  Edema peripheral    1                0                
  Erythema         1                0                
  Excoriation      1                0                
  Hot flush        1                &lt;1               
  Pruritus generalized    1                0                
             *A treatment-emergent adverse reaction refers to any untoward medical event associated with the use of the drug in             humans, whether or not considered drug-related.
 

   6.2       Other Adverse Reactions Observed During the Premarketing Evaluation of XARTEMIS XR

  The following adverse drug reactions not listed above occurred in &gt;=1% of XARTEMIS XR-treated patients in the pooled safety data from two Phase 3 studies (including a placebo-controlled and an open-label non-controlled safety study) where multiple-doses of XARTEMIS XR were administered every 12 hours for up to 42 days:



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  dry mouth, dyspepsia, diarrhea



   General disorders and administration site conditions:  fatigue



   Investigations:  hepatic enzyme increased



   Psychiatric disorders:  insomnia



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  cough



 The following adverse drug reactions occurred in &lt;1% of XARTEMIS XR-treated patients in the pooled safety data from the two Phase 3 studies described above:



   Cardiac disorders:  palpitations



   Eye and    ea    r disorders:  tinnitus, vision blurred



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  abdominal discomfort, abdominal pain, esophageal spasm



   General disorders and administration site conditions:  asthenia, chest discomfort, chills, contusion, fall, feeling jittery, malaise, non-cardiac chest pain, thirst



   Immune    s    ystem    d    isorders    :  hypersensitivity



   Investigations:  alanine aminotransferase increased, aspartate aminotransferase increased, blood lactate dehydrogenase increased, blood pressure increased, gamma-glutamyltransferase increased, liver functional test abnormal



   Metabolic and    nutritional    :  decreased appetite



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  arthralgia, musculoskeletal stiffness



   Nervous system disorders:  cognitive disorder, memory impairment, migraine, myoclonus, paraesthesia, sedation, tremor



   Psychiatric disorders:  anxiety, confusional state, disorientation, euphoric mood, mood altered, sleep disorder, withdrawal syndrome



   Renal and urinary disorders:  urine flow decreased



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  dyspnea, hiccups, hypopnea, oropharyngeal pain, throat irritation



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  dermatitis, ecchymosis, hyperhidrosis, urticaria



   Vascular disorders:  flushing, hypertension
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: 

  

      WARNING: ADDICTION, ABUSE, AND MISUSE; LIFE-THREATENING     RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL EXPOSURE; NEONATAL OPIOID     WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME; and HEPATOTOXICITY    



     Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse      XARTEMIS XR exposes patients and other users to the risks of opioid addiction, abuse, and misuse, which can lead to overdose and death. Assess each patient's risk prior to prescribing XARTEMIS XR, and monitor all patients regularly for the development of these behaviors or conditions   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  .  



     Life-threatening Respiratory Depression      Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression may occur with use of XARTEMIS XR. Monitor for respiratory depression, especially during initiation of XARTEMIS XR or following a dose increase  .   Instruct patients to swallow XARTEMIS XR tablets whole; crushing, chewing, or dissolving XARTEMIS XR can cause rapid release and absorption of a potentially fatal dose of oxycodone   [see Warnings and     Precautions (  5.2  )]  .  



     Accidental Exposure      Accidental ingestion of XARTEMIS XR, especially in children, can result in a fatal overdose of oxycodone   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  .  



     Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome      Prolonged use of XARTEMIS XR during pregnancy can result in neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, which may be life-threatening if not recognized and requires management according to protocols developed by neonatology experts. If opioid use is required for a prolonged period in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )]  .  



     Hepatotoxicity      XARTEMIS XR contains acetaminophen. Acetaminophen has been associated with cases of acute liver failure, at times resulting in liver transplant and death. Most of the cases of liver injury are associated with the use of acetaminophen at doses that exceed the maximum daily limit, and often involve more than one acetaminophen-containing product   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  ,   5.11  )].    



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: ADDICTION, ABUSE, AND MISUSE; LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL EXPOSURE; NEONATAL OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME; and HEPATOTOXICITY  



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 *  XARTEMIS XR exposes users to risks of addiction, abuse, and misuse, which can lead to overdose and death. Assess each patient's risk before prescribing, and monitor regularly for development of these behaviors or conditions. (5.1) 
 *  Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression may occur. Monitor closely, especially upon initiation or following a dose increase. Instruct patients to swallow tablets whole to avoid exposure to a potentially fatal dose of oxycodone. (5.2) 
 *  Accidental consumption of XARTEMIS XR, especially in children, can result in fatal overdose of oxycodone. (5.2) 
 *  Prolonged use of XARTEMIS XR during pregnancy can result in neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, which may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated. If opioid use is required for a prolonged period in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available. (5.3) 
 *  XARTEMIS XR contains acetaminophen. Acetaminophen has been associated with cases of acute liver failure, at times resulting in liver transplant and death. Most of the cases of liver injury are associated with the use of acetaminophen at doses that exceed the maximum daily limit, and often involve more than one acetaminophen-containing product. (5.7, 5.11) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  XARTEMIS XR is not interchangeable with other oxycodone/acetaminophen products because of differing pharmacokinetic profiles that affect the frequency of administration.



    EXCERPT:    *  XARTEMIS XR is not interchangeable with other oxycodone/ acetaminophen products because of differing pharmacokinetic profiles that affect the frequency of administration. (  5  ) 
 *  Controlled substance: XARTEMIS XR is a Schedule II controlled substance with an abuse liability similar to other opioids. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Accidental exposure, especially in children, can result in fatal overdose of oxycodone. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Interactions with CNS depressants: Concomitant use may cause profound sedation, respiratory depression, and death. If coadministration is required, consider dose reduction of one or both drugs. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Use with caution in patients who are receiving other CNS depressants. (  5.4  ,  7.1  ) 
 *  Elderly, cachectic, debilitated patients, and those with chronic pulmonary disease: Monitor closely because of increased risk for life-threatening respiratory depression. (  5.5  ,  5.6  ) 
 *  Use caution when administering in patients with hepatic impairment. (  5.7  ) 
 *  May cause serious skin reactions. Discontinue use if reaction occurs. (  5.8  ) 
 *  May worsen increased intracranial pressure and obscure its signs, such as level of consciousness or pupillary signs. (  5.9  ) 
 *  May cause hypotension. Use with caution in patients at increased risk of hypotension and in patients in circulatory shock. (  5.10  ) 
 *  Due to the potential for acetaminophen hepatotoxicity at doses higher than 4000 mg/day, XARTEMIS XR should not be used with other acetaminophen-containing products. (  5.11  ) 
 *  Discontinue XARTEMIS XR immediately if symptoms associated with allergy or hypersensitivity occur. Do not use in patients with acetaminophen allergy. (  5.12  ) 
 *  Use with caution in patients with biliary tract disease, including acute pancreatitis. (  5.14  ) 
 *  Concomitant use of CYP3A4 inhibitors may increase opioid effects. (  5.15  ) 
 *  May impair the mental and physical abilities needed to perform potentially hazardous activities such as driving a car or operating machinery. (  5.16  ) 
    
 

   5.1       Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse



  XARTEMIS XR contains oxycodone, a Schedule II controlled substance. As an opioid, XARTEMIS XR exposes users to the risks of addiction, abuse, and misuse [see Drug Abuse and Dependence (  9  )]  . Although the risk of addiction in any individual is unknown, it can occur in patients appropriately prescribed XARTEMIS XR and in those who obtain the drug illicitly. Addiction can occur at recommended doses and if the drug is misused or abused.



 Assess each patient's risk for opioid addiction, abuse, or misuse prior to prescribing XARTEMIS XR, and monitor all patients receiving XARTEMIS XR for the development of these behaviors or conditions. Risks are increased in patients with a personal or family history of substance abuse (including drug or alcohol addiction or abuse) or mental illness (e.g., major depression). The potential for these risks should not, however, prevent the prescribing of XARTEMIS XR for the proper management of pain in any given patient. Patients at increased risk may be prescribed modified-release opioid formulations such as XARTEMIS XR, but use in such patients necessitates intensive counseling about the risks and proper use of XARTEMIS XR along with intensive monitoring for signs of addiction, abuse, and misuse.



 Abuse or misuse of XARTEMIS XR by crushing, chewing, snorting, or injecting the dissolved product will result in the uncontrolled delivery of the oxycodone and can result in overdose and death [see Overdosage (  10  )]  .



    5.2       Life-threatening Respiratory Depression



  Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression has been reported with the use of opioids, even when used as recommended. Respiratory depression from opioid use, if not immediately recognized and treated, may lead to respiratory arrest and death. Management of respiratory depression may include close observation, supportive measures, and use of opioid antagonists, depending on the patient's clinical status [see Overdosage (  10  )]  . Carbon dioxide (CO2) retention from opioid-induced respiratory depression can exacerbate the sedating effects of opioids.



 While serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression can occur at any time during the use of XARTEMIS XR, the risk is greatest during the initiation of therapy or following a dose increase. Closely monitor patients for respiratory depression when initiating therapy with XARTEMIS XR and following dose increases.



 To reduce the risk of respiratory depression, proper dosing and titration of XARTEMIS XR are essential [see Dosage and Administration (  2  )]  . Overestimating the XARTEMIS XR dose when converting patients from another opioid product can result in fatal overdose with the first dose.



 Accidental consumption of XARTEMIS XR, especially by children, can result in respiratory depression and death due to an overdose of oxycodone.



    5.3       Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome



  Prolonged use of XARTEMIS XR during pregnancy can result in withdrawal signs in the neonate. Neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, unlike opioid withdrawal syndrome in adults, may be life-threatening if not recognized and requires management according to protocols developed by neonatology experts. If opioid use is required for a prolonged period in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available.



 Neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome presents as irritability, hyperactivity and abnormal sleep pattern, high pitched cry, tremor, vomiting, diarrhea and failure to gain weight. The onset, duration, and severity of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome vary based on the specific opioid used, duration of use, timing and amount of last maternal use, and rate of elimination of the drug by the newborn.



    5.4       Interactions with Central Nervous System Depressants



  Hypotension, profound sedation, coma, respiratory depression, and death may result if XARTEMIS XR is used concomitantly with alcohol or other central nervous system (CNS) depressants (e.g., sedatives, anxiolytics, hypnotics, neuroleptics, other opioids).



 When considering the use of XARTEMIS XR in a patient taking a CNS depressant, assess the duration use of the CNS depressant and the patient's response, including the degree of tolerance that has developed to CNS depression. Additionally, evaluate the patient's use of alcohol or illicit drugs that cause CNS depression. If the decision to begin XARTEMIS XR is made, start with XARTEMIS XR 1 tablet every 12 hours, monitor patients for signs of sedation and respiratory depression, and consider using a lower dose of the concomitant CNS depressant [see Drug Interactions (  7.1  )]  .



    5.5       Elderly, Cachectic, and Debilitated Patients



  Life-threatening respiratory depression is more likely to occur in elderly, cachectic, or debilitated patients as they may have altered pharmacokinetics or altered clearance compared to younger, healthier patients. Monitor such patients closely, particularly when initiating and titrating XARTEMIS XR and when XARTEMIS XR is given concomitantly with other drugs that depress respiration [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  .



    5.6       Use in Patients with Chronic Pulmonary Disease



  Monitor patients with significant chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or cor pulmonale, and patients having a substantially decreased respiratory reserve, hypoxia, hypercapnia, or preexisting respiratory depression for respiratory depression, particularly when initiating therapy and titrating with XARTEMIS XR, as in these patients, even usual therapeutic doses of XARTEMIS XR may decrease respiratory drive to the point of apnea [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )].  Consider the use of alternative non-opioid analgesics in these patients if possible.



    5.7       Hepatotoxicity



  XARTEMIS XR contains oxycodone and acetaminophen. Acetaminophen has been associated with cases of acute liver failure, at times resulting in liver transplant and death. Most of the cases of liver injury are associated with the use of acetaminophen at doses that exceed 4000 milligrams per day, and often involve more than one acetaminophen-containing product. The excessive intake of acetaminophen may be intentional to cause self-harm or unintentional as patients attempt to obtain more pain relief or unknowingly take other acetaminophen-containing products. The typical daily acetaminophen contribution from XARTEMIS XR is 1300 mg.



 The risk of acute liver failure is higher in individuals with underlying liver disease and in individuals who ingest alcohol while taking acetaminophen.



 Instruct patients to look for acetaminophen or APAP on package labels and not to use more than one product that contains acetaminophen. Instruct patients to seek medical attention immediately upon ingestion of more than 4000 milligrams of acetaminophen per day, even if they feel well.



    5.8       Serious Skin Reactions



  Rarely, acetaminophen may cause serious skin reactions such as acute generalized exanthematous pustulosis (AGEP), Stevens-Johnson Syndrome (SJS), and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), which can be fatal. Inform patients about the signs of serious skin reactions, and use of the drug should be discontinued at the first appearance of skin rash or any other sign of hypersensitivity.



    5.9       Head Injury and Increased Intracranial Pressure



  The respiratory depressant effects of narcotics and their capacity to elevate cerebrospinal fluid pressure may be markedly exaggerated in the presence of head injury, other intracranial lesions, or a pre-existing increase in intracranial pressure. Furthermore, narcotics produce adverse reactions which may obscure the clinical course of patients with head injuries.



    5.10    Hypotensive Effect



  Oxycodone may cause severe hypotension particularly in individuals whose ability to maintain blood pressure has been compromised by a depleted blood volume, or after concurrent administration with drugs which compromise vasomotor tone such as phenothiazines. Administer XARTEMIS XR with caution to patients in circulatory shock, since vasodilation produced by the drug may further reduce cardiac output and blood pressure. XARTEMIS XR may produce orthostatic hypotension in ambulatory patients [see Drug Interactions (  7.1  )]  .



    5.11     Use With Other Acetaminophen-containing Products



  The typical daily acetaminophen-contribution from XARTEMIS XR is 1300 mg. Due to the potential for acetaminophen hepatotoxicity at doses higher than 4000 milligrams/day, XARTEMIS XR should not be used concomitantly with other acetaminophen-containing products.



    5.12    Hypersensitivity/Anaphylaxis



  There have been post-marketing reports of hypersensitivity and anaphylaxis associated with use of acetaminophen. Clinical signs included swelling of the face, mouth, and throat, respiratory distress, urticaria, rash, pruritus, and vomiting. There were infrequent reports of life-threatening anaphylaxis requiring emergency medical attention. Instruct patients to discontinue XARTEMIS XR immediately and seek medical care if they experience these symptoms. Do not prescribe XARTEMIS XR for patients with acetaminophen allergy.



    5.13    Difficulty Swallowing



  Due to characteristics of the formulation that cause the tablets to swell and become sticky when wet, consider use of an alternative analgesic in patients who have difficulty swallowing and patients at risk for underlying GI disorders resulting in a small gastrointestinal lumen. Instruct patients not to pre-soak, lick or otherwise wet XARTEMIS XR tablets prior to placing in the mouth, and to take one tablet at a time with enough water to ensure complete swallowing immediately after placing in mouth.



    5.14    Gastrointestinal Effects



  XARTEMIS XR is contraindicated in patients with known or suspected paralytic ileus. Opioids diminish propulsive peristaltic waves in the gastrointestinal tract and decrease bowel motility. Monitor for decreased bowel motility in post-operative patients receiving opioids. The administration of XARTEMIS XR may obscure the diagnosis or clinical course in patients with acute abdominal conditions. Oxycodone may cause spasm of the Sphincter of Oddi. Monitor patients with biliary tract disease, including acute pancreatitis.



    5.15    Cytochrome P450 3A4 Inhibitors and Inducers



  Since the CYP3A4 isoenzyme plays a major role in the metabolism of XARTEMIS XR, drugs that alter CYP3A4 activity may cause changes in clearance of oxycodone which could lead to changes in oxycodone plasma concentrations.



 Inhibition of CYP3A4 activity by its inhibitors, such as macrolide antibiotics (e.g., erythromycin), azole-antifungal agents (e.g., ketoconazole), and protease inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir), may increase plasma concentrations of oxycodone and prolong opioid effects. These effects could be more pronounced with concomitant use of CYP 2D6 and 3A4 inhibitors.



 Cytochrome P450 inducers, such as rifampin, carbamazepine, and phenytoin, may induce the metabolism of oxycodone and, therefore, may cause increased clearance of the drug which could lead to a decrease in oxycodone plasma concentrations, resulting in a potential lack of efficacy.



 If co-administration is necessary, caution is advised when initiating XARTEMIS XR treatment in patients currently taking, or discontinuing CYP3A4 inhibitors or inducers. Evaluate these patients at frequent intervals and consider dose adjustments until stable drug effects are achieved [see Drug Interactions (     7.4     )]  .



    5.16    Driving and Operating Machinery



  XARTEMIS XR may impair the mental and/or physical abilities required for the performance of potentially hazardous tasks such as driving a car or operating machinery. The patient using this drug should be cautioned accordingly.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
