<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="xtampza" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are described elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Interactions with CNS Depressants [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
 *  Adrenal Insufficiency [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
 *  Severe Hypotension [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)  ]  
 *  Gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  
 *  Seizures [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.11)  ]  
 *  Withdrawal [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.12)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;5%) were nausea, headache, constipation, somnolence, pruritus, vomiting, and dizziness. (  6.1  ).
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Collegium Pharmaceutical, Inc. at 1-855-331-5615 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of XTAMPZA ER was evaluated in a Phase 3, randomized-withdrawal, double-blind clinical trial involving 740 patients with moderate-to-severe chronic lower back pain. In the double-blind maintenance phase, 389 patients were randomized and 193 patients were assigned to the XTAMPZA ER treatment group.



 The most common AEs (&gt;5%) reported by patients in the Phase 3 clinical trial during the titration phase were: nausea (16.6%), headache (13.9%), constipation (13.0%), somnolence (8.8%), pruritus (7.4%), vomiting (6.4%), and dizziness (5.7%).



 The most common adverse reactions (&gt;5%) reported by patients in the Phase 3 clinical trial comparing XTAMPZA ER with placebo are shown in Table 1 below:



 Table 1: Common Adverse Reactions (&gt;5%) 
                                    Titration                 Maintenance          
 Adverse Reaction              XTAMPZA ER(n = 740)        XTAMPZA ER(n = 193)         Placebo(n = 196)        
 (%)                                   (%)                        (%)              
  
 Nausea                               16.6                       10.9                        4.6              
 Headache                             13.9                        6.2                       11.7              
 Constipation                         13.0                        5.2                        0.5              
 Somnolence                            8.8                        &lt;1                         &lt;1               
 Pruritus                              7.4                        2.6                        1.5              
 Vomiting                              6.4                        4.1                        1.5              
 Dizziness                             5.7                        1.6                         0               
          In the Phase 3 clinical trial, the following adverse reactions were reported in patients treated with XTAMPZA ER with incidences of 1% to 5%:
 

   Eye disorders:  vision blurred



   Gastrointestinal disorders:  abdominal pain, upper abdominal pain, diarrhea, gastroesophageal reflux disease



   General disorders and administration site conditions:  chills, drug withdrawal syndrome, fatigue, irritability, edema, pyrexia



   Injury, poisoning and procedural complications:  excoriation



   Metabolism and nutrition disorders:  decreased appetite, hyperglycemia



   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders:  arthralgia, back pain, musculoskeletal pain, myalgia



   Nervous system disorders:  migraine, tremor



   Psychiatric disorders:  anxiety, insomnia, withdrawal syndrome



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  cough, oropharyngeal pain



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  hyperhidrosis, rash



   Vascular disorders:  hot flush, hypertension



 In the Phase 3 clinical trial, the following treatment-related adverse reactions were reported in patients treated with XTAMPZA ER with incidences of  less than 1% of patients.  



   Investigations:  increased gamma-glutamyl transferase, increased heart rate



   Nervous system disorders:  lethargy, memory impairment, poor-quality sleep



   Psychiatric disorders:  abnormal dreams, euphoric mood, restlessness



   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders:  dyspnea



   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders:  night sweats



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of oxycodone. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Serotonin syndrome  : Cases of serotonin syndrome, a potentially life-threatening condition, have been reported during concomitant use of opioids with serotonergic drugs.



   Adrenal insufficiency  : Cases of adrenal insufficiency have been reported with opioid use, more often following greater than one month of use.



   Anaphylaxis  : Anaphylaxis has been reported with ingredients contained in XTAMPZA ER.



   Androgen deficiency  : Cases of androgen deficiency have occurred with chronic use of opioids  [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)  ]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING:  ADDICTION, ABUSE, AND MISUSE; LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL INGESTION; NEONATAL OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME; and CYTOCHROME P450 3A4 INTERACTION 

    WARNING:  ADDICTION, ABUSE, AND MISUSE; LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL INGESTION; NEONATAL OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME; and CYTOCHROME P450 3A4 INTERACTION   

  EXCERPT:   WARNING:  ADDICTION, ABUSE, AND MISUSE; LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL INGESTION; NEONATAL OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME; and CYTOCHROME P450 3A4 INTERACTION



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning  .  



 *  XTAMPZA ER exposes users to risks of addiction, abuse, and misuse, which can lead to overdose and death. Assess each patient's risk before prescribing and monitor regularly for development of these behaviors and conditions. (5.1) 
 *  Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression may occur. Monitor closely, especially upon initiation or following a dose increase. (5.2) 
 *  Accidental ingestion of XTAMPZA ER, especially by children, can result in fatal overdose of oxycodone. (5.2) 
 *  Prolonged maternal use of XTAMPZA ER during pregnancy can result in neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, which may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated. If prolonged opioid use is required in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available. (5.3) 
 *  Concomitant use with CYP3A4 inhibitors (or discontinuation of CYP3A4 inducers) can result in a fatal overdose of oxycodone from XTAMPZA ER. (5.4, 12.3) 
    
 

    Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse   



   XTAMPZA ER exposes patients and other users to the risks of opioid addiction, abuse, and misuse, which can lead to overdose and death.  Assess each patient's risk prior to prescribing XTAMPZA ER and monitor all patients regularly for the development of these behaviors or conditions   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ].    



     Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression   



   Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression may occur with use of XTAMPZA ER.  Monitor for respiratory depression, especially during initiation of XTAMPZA ER or following a dose increase   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ].    



     Accidental Ingestion  



   Accidental ingestion of even one dose of XTAMPZA ER, especially by children, can result in a fatal overdose of oxycodone   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  .   



     Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome   



   Prolonged use of XTAMPZA ER during pregnancy can result in neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, which may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated, and requires management according to protocols developed by neonatology experts. If opioid use is required for an prolonged period in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  .  



     Cytochrome P450 3A4 Interaction   



   The concomitant use of XTAMPZA ER with all cytochrome P450 3A4 inhibitors may result in an increase in oxycodone plasma concentrations, which could increase or prolong adverse drug effects and may cause potentially fatal respiratory depression. In addition, discontinuation of a concomitantly used cytochrome P450 3A4 inducer may result in an increase in oxycodone plasma concentration. Monitor patients receiving XTAMPZA ER and any CYP3A4 inhibitor or inducer   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   and   Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .  
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Risk of life-threatening respiratory depression in patients with chronic pulmonary disease or in elderly, cachectic, or debilitated patients : Monitor closely, particularly during initiation and titration. (  5.6  ) 
 *   Adrenal Insufficiency : If diagnosed, treat with physiologic replacement of corticosteroids, and wean patient off of the opioid. (   5.7   ) 
 *   Severe hypotension : Monitor during dosage initiation and titration. Avoid use of XTAMPZA ER in patients with circulatory shock (   5.8   ) 
 *   Risks of use in patients with increased intracranial pressure, brain tumors, head injury, or impaired consciousness : Monitor for sedation and respiratory depression. Avoid use of XTAMPZA ER in patients with impaired consciousness or coma. (   5.9   ) 
    
 

   5.1 Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse



  XTAMPZA ER contains oxycodone, a Schedule II controlled substance. As an opioid, XTAMPZA ER exposes users to the risks of addiction, abuse, and misuse [see  Drug Abuse and Dependence (9)  ]  . As extended-release products such as XTAMPZA ER deliver the opioid over an extended period of time, there is a greater risk for overdose and death due to the larger amount of oxycodone present [see  Drug Abuse and Dependence (9)  ]  .



 Although the risk of addiction in any individual is unknown, it can occur in patients appropriately prescribed XTAMPZA ER. Addiction can occur at recommended dosages and if the drug is misused or abused.



 Assess each patient's risk for opioid addiction, abuse, or misuse prior to prescribing XTAMPZA ER, and monitor all patients receiving XTAMPZA ER for the development of these behaviors or conditions. Risks are increased in patients with a personal or family history of substance abuse (including drug or alcohol abuse or addiction) or mental illness (e.g., major depression). The potential for these risks should not, however, prevent the proper management of pain in any given patient. Patients at increased risk may be prescribed opioids such as XTAMPZA ER, but use in such patients necessitates intensive counseling about the risks and proper use of XTAMPZA ER along with intensive monitoring for signs of addiction, abuse, and misuse.



 Abuse or misuse of XTAMPZA ER by snorting or by injecting the dissolved product can result in overdose and death [see  Overdosage (10)  ].  



 Opioids are sought by drug abusers and people with addiction disorders and are subject to criminal diversion. Consider these risks when prescribing or dispensing XTAMPZA ER. Strategies to reduce these risks include prescribing the drug in the smallest appropriate quantity and advising the patient on the proper disposal of unused drug [see  Patient Counseling Information (17)  ]  . Contact local state professional licensing board or state controlled substances authority for information on how to prevent and detect abuse or diversion of this product.



    5.2 Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression



  Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression has been reported with the use of opioids, even when used as recommended. Respiratory depression, if not immediately recognized and treated, may lead to respiratory arrest and death. Management of respiratory depression may include close observation, supportive measures, and use of opioid antagonists, depending on the patient's clinical status [see  Overdosage (10)  ]  . Carbon dioxide (CO2) retention from opioid-induced respiratory depression can exacerbate the sedating effects of opioids.



 While serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression can occur at any time during the use of XTAMPZA ER, the risk is greatest during the initiation of therapy or following a dosage increase. Closely monitor patients for respiratory depression, especially within the first 24-72 hours of initiating therapy with and following dosage increases of XTAMPZA ER.



 To reduce the risk of respiratory depression, proper dosing and titration of XTAMPZA ER are essential [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  ]  . Overestimating the XTAMPZA ER dose when converting patients from another opioid product can result in a fatal overdose with the first dose.



 Accidental ingestion of even one dose of XTAMPZA ER, especially by children, can result in respiratory depression and death due to an overdose of oxycodone.



    5.3 Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome



  Prolonged use of XTAMPZA ER during pregnancy can result in withdrawal in the neonate. Neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, unlike opioid withdrawal syndrome in adults, may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated, and requires management according to protocols developed by neonatology experts. Observe newborns for signs of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and manage accordingly. Advise pregnant women using opioids for a prolonged period of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ,  Patient Counseling Information (17)  ]  .



    5.4 Risks of Concomitant Use or Discontinuation of Cytochrome P450 3A4 Inhibitors and Inducers



  Concomitant use of XTAMPZA ER with a CYP3A4 inhibitor, such as macrolide antibiotics (e.g., erythromycin), azole-antifungal agents (e.g., ketoconazole), and protease inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir), may increase plasma concentrations of oxycodone and prolong opioid adverse reactions, which may cause potentially fatal respiratory depression [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  , particularly when an inhibitor is added after a stable dose of XTAMPZA ER is achieved. Similarly, discontinuation of a CYP3A4 inducer, such as rifampin, carbamazepine, and phenytoin, in XTAMPZA ER-treated patients may increase oxycodone plasma concentrations and prolong opioid adverse reactions. When using XTAMPZA ER with CYP3A4 inhibitors or discontinuing CYP3A4 inducers in XTAMPZA ER-treated patients, monitor patients closely at frequent intervals and consider dosage reduction of XTAMPZA ER until stable drug effects are achieved [see  Drug Interactions (7)  ].  



 Concomitant use of XTAMPZA ER with CYP3A4 inducers or discontinuation of an CYP3A4 inhibitor could decrease oxycodone plasma concentrations, decrease opioid efficacy or, possibly, lead to a withdrawal syndrome in a patient who had developed physical dependence to oxycodone. When using XTAMPZA ER with CYP3A4 inducers or discontinuing CYP3A4 inhibitors, monitor patients closely at frequent intervals and consider increasing the opioid dosage if needed to maintain adequate analgesia or if symptoms of opioid withdrawal occur [see  Drug Interactions (7)  ]  .



    5.5 Risks Due to Interactions with Central Nervous System Depressants



  Hypotension, profound sedation, respiratory depression, coma, and death may result if XTAMPZA ER is used concomitantly with other central nervous system (CNS) depressants (e.g., benzodiazepines and other sedative-hypnotics, anxiolytics, tranquilizers, muscle relaxants, general anesthetics, antipsychotics, and other opioids).



 When considering the use of XTAMPZA ER in a patient taking a CNS depressant, assess the duration of use of the CNS depressant and the patient's response, including the degree of tolerance that has developed to CNS depression. Additionally, evaluate the patient's use of alcohol or illicit drugs that can cause CNS depression. If the decision to begin XTAMPZA ER therapy is made, start with 1/3 to 1/2 the usual dose XTAMPZA ER, monitor patients for signs of respiratory depression, sedation, and hypotension, and consider using a lower dose of the concomitant CNS depressant. Use an alternative analgesic for patients who require a dose of XTAMPZA ER less than 9 mg [see  Drug Interactions (7)  ]  .



    5.6 Risk of Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression in Patients with Chronic Pulmonary Disease or in Elderly, Cachectic, or Debilitated Patients



  The use of XTAMPZA ER in patients with acute or severe bronchial asthma in an unmonitored setting or in the absence of resuscitative equipment is contraindicated.



    Patients with Chronic Pulmonary Disease:  XTAMPZA ER-treated patients with significant chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or cor pulmonale, and those with a substantially decreased respiratory reserve, hypoxia, hypercapnia, or pre-existing respiratory depression are at increased risk of decreased respiratory drive including apnea, even at recommended dosages of XTAMPZA ER [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ].



    Elderly, Cachetic, or Debilitated Patients:  Life-threatening respiratory depression is more likely to occur in elderly, cachectic, or debilitated patients as they may have altered pharmacokinetics or altered clearance compared to younger, healthier patients.



 Monitor such patients closely, particularly when initiating and titrating XTAMPZA ER and when XTAMPZA ER is given concomitantly with other drugs that depress respiration [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  . Alternatively, consider the use of non-opioid analgesics in these patients. Use an alternative analgesic for patients who require a dose of XTAMPZA ER less than 9 mg.



    5.7 Adrenal Insufficiency



  Cases of adrenal insufficiency have been reported with opioid use, more often following greater than one month of use. Presentation of adrenal insufficiency may include non-specific symptoms and signs including nausea, vomiting, anorexia, fatigue, weakness, dizziness, and low blood pressure. If adrenal insufficiency is suspected, confirm the diagnosis with diagnostic testing as soon as possible. If adrenal insufficiency is diagnosed, treat with physiologic replacement doses of corticosteroids. Wean the patient off of the opioid to allow adrenal function to recover and continue corticosteroid treatment until adrenal function recovers. Other opioids may be tried as some cases reported use of a different opioid without recurrence of adrenal insufficiency. The information available does not identify any particular opioids as being more likely to be associated with adrenal insufficiency.



    5.8 Severe Hypotension



  XTAMPZA ER may cause severe hypotension including orthostatic hypotension and syncope in ambulatory patients. There is an increased risk in patients whose ability to maintain blood pressure has already been compromised by a reduced blood volume or concurrent administration of certain CNS depressant drugs (e.g., phenothiazines or general anesthetics) [see  Drug Interactions (7)  ]  . Monitor these patients for signs of hypotension after initiating or titrating the dosage of XTAMPZA ER. In patients with circulatory shock, XTAMPZA ER may cause vasodilation that can further reduce cardiac output and blood pressure. Avoid the use of XTAMPZA ER in patients with circulatory shock.



    5.9 Risks of Use in Patients with Increased Intracranial Pressure, Brain Tumors, Head Injury, or Impaired Consciousness



  In patients who may be susceptible to the intracranial effects of CO2retention (e.g., those with evidence of increased intracranial pressure or brain tumors), XTAMPZA ER may reduce respiratory drive, and the resultant CO2retention can further increase intracranial pressure. Monitor such patients for signs of sedation and respiratory depression, particularly when initiating therapy with XTAMPZA ER.



 Opioids may also obscure the clinical course in a patient with a head injury. Avoid the use of XTAMPZA ER in patients with impaired consciousness or coma.



    5.10 Risks of Use in Patients with Gastrointestinal Conditions



  XTAMPZA ER is contraindicated in patients with gastrointestinal obstruction, including paralytic ileus.



 The oxycodone in XTAMPZA ER may cause spasm of the sphincter of Oddi. Opioids may cause increases in the serum amylase. Monitor patients with biliary tract disease, including acute pancreatitis, for worsening symptoms.



    5.11 Risk of Use in Patients with Seizure Disorders



  The oxycodone in XTAMPZA ER may increase the frequency of seizures in patients with seizure disorders, and may increase the risk of seizures in other clinical settings associated with seizures. Monitor patients with a history of seizure disorders for worsened seizure control during XTAMPZA ER therapy.



    5.12 Withdrawal



  Avoid the use of mixed agonist/antagonist (e.g., pentazocine, nalbuphine, and butorphanol) or partial agonist (e.g., buprenorphine) analgesics in patients who have received or are receiving a course of therapy with a full opioid agonist analgesic, including XTAMPZA ER. In these patients, mixed agonist/antagonist and partial agonist analgesics may reduce the analgesic effect and/or may precipitate withdrawal symptoms.



 When discontinuing XTAMPZA ER, gradually taper the dosage [see  Dosage and Administration (2.5)  ]  . Do not abruptly discontinue XTAMPZA ER.



    5.13 Risks of Driving and Operating Machinery



  XTAMPZA ER may impair the mental or physical abilities needed to perform potentially hazardous activities such as driving a car or operating machinery. Warn patients not to drive or operate dangerous machinery unless they are tolerant to the effects of XTAMPZA ER and know how they will react to the medication.



    5.14 Laboratory Monitoring



  Not every urine drug test for "opioids" or "opiates" detects oxycodone reliably, especially those designed for in-office use. Further, many laboratories will report urine drug concentrations below a specified "cut-off" value as "negative". Therefore, if urine testing for oxycodone is considered in the clinical management of an individual patient, ensure that the sensitivity and specificity of the assay is appropriate, and consider the limitations of the testing used when interpreting results.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
