<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="xultophy" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are described below or elsewhere in the prescribing information:



 *    Risk of Thyroid C-cell Tumors [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.1    )]  
 *    Pancreatitis [see Warnings and Precautions (    5.2    )]  
 *    Hypoglycemia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *    Acute Kidney Injury [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7)  ]  
 *    Hypersensitivity and Allergic Reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  
 *    Hypokalemia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.9  )]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions, reported in &gt;=5% of patients treated with XULTOPHY 100/3.6: nasopharyngitis, headache, nausea, diarrhea, increased lipase and upper respiratory tract infection (  6  ).
 

 To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novo Nordisk Inc. at 1-800-727-6500 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The data in Table 3 reflect the exposure of 1881 patients to XULTOPHY 100/3.6 and a mean duration of exposure of 33 weeks. The mean age was 57 years and 2.8% were older than 75 years; 52.6% were male, 75.0% were White, 6.2% were Black or African American and 15.9% were Hispanic or Latino. The mean body mass index (BMI) was 31.8 kg/m  2  . The mean duration of diabetes was 8.7 years and the mean HbA1cat baseline was 8.2%. A history of neuropathy, ophthalmopathy, nephropathy and cardiovascular disease at baseline was reported in 25.4%, 12.0%, 6.5% and 6.3% respectively. The mean eGFR at baseline was 88.3 mL/min/1.73 m  2  and 6.24% of the patients had an eGFR less than 60 mL/min/1.73 m  2  .



 Table 3: Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=5% of XULTOPHY 100/3.6-Treated Patients with Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus 
                             XULTOPHY 100/3.6  N = 1881  %                         
  Nasopharyngitis            9.6                                                   
  Headache                   9.1                                                   
  Nausea                     7.8                                                   
  Diarrhea                   7.5                                                   
  Increased Lipase           6.7                                                   
  Upper respiratory tract infection     5.7                                                   
          Hypoglycemia  
 

 Hypoglycemia is the most commonly observed adverse reaction in patients using insulin and insulin containing products, including XULTOPHY 100/3.6  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )].  The number of reported hypoglycemia episodes depends on the definition of hypoglycemia used, insulin dose, intensity of glucose control, background therapies, and other intrinsic and extrinsic patient factors. For these reasons, comparing rates of hypoglycemia in clinical trials for XULTOPHY 100/3.6 with the incidence of hypoglycemia for other products may be misleading and also, may not be representative of hypoglycemia rates that will occur in clinical practice.



 In the phase 3 clinical program  [see Clinical Studies (  14  )]  , events of severe hypoglycemia were defined as an episode requiring assistance of another person to actively administer carbohydrate, glucagon, or other resuscitative actions (Table 4).



 No clinically important differences in risk of severe hypoglycemia between XULTOPHY 100/3.6 and comparators were observed in clinical trials.



   Table 4: Severe Hypoglycemia Episodes Reported in XULTOPHY 100/3.6-Treated Patients with T2DM  




                                    
  
                                    Study A               Study B                  Study C                  
                                    XULTOPHY 100/3.6      XULTOPHY 100/3.6         XULTOPHY 100/3.6         
  Total Subjects (N)                291                   199                      278                      
  Severe Hypoglycemia                                     
  Percent of patients  (n/total N)    0.3                   0.5                      0.0                      
            Gastrointestinal Adverse Reactions  
 

 Gastrointestinal adverse reactions including nausea, diarrhea, vomiting, constipation, dyspepsia, gastritis, abdominal pain, flatulence, eructation, gastroesophageal reflux disease, abdominal distension and decreased appetite have been reported in patients treated with XULTOPHY 100/3.6. Gastrointestinal adverse reactions may occur more frequently at the beginning of XULTOPHY 100/3.6 therapy and diminish within a few days or weeks on continued treatment.



   Malignancy  



   VICTOZA (liraglutide)  



 In a pooled analysis of liraglutide clinical trials, the incidence rate (per 1,000 patient-years) for malignant neoplasms (based on investigator-reported events, medical history, pathology reports, and surgical reports from both blinded and open-label study periods) was 10.9 for liraglutide, 6.3 for placebo, and 7.2 for active comparator. After excluding papillary thyroid carcinoma events, no particular cancer cell type predominated. Seven malignant neoplasm events were reported beyond 1 year of exposure to study medication, six events among liraglutide-treated patients (4 colon, 1 prostate and 1 nasopharyngeal), no events with placebo and one event with active comparator (colon). Causality has not been established.



   Papillary thyroid carcinoma  



   VICTOZA (liraglutide)  



 In clinical trials of liraglutide, there were 7 reported cases of papillary thyroid carcinoma in patients treated with liraglutide and 1 case in a comparator-treated patient (1.5 vs. 0.5 cases per 1000 patient years). Most of these papillary thyroid carcinomas were &lt;1 cm in greatest diameter and were diagnosed in surgical pathology specimens after thyroidectomy prompted by findings on protocol-specified screening with serum calcitonin or thyroid ultrasound.



   Cholelithiasis and cholecystitis  



   VICTOZA and SAXENDA (liraglutide)  



 In clinical trials of liraglutide the incidence of cholelithiasis was 0.3% in both liraglutide-treated and placebo-treated patients. The incidence of cholecystitis was 0.2% in both liraglutide treated and placebo-treated patients.



 In clinical trials of liraglutide at doses up to 3 mg, 1.5% and 0.6% of liraglutide-treated patients reported adverse reactions of cholelithiasis and cholecystitis versus 0.5% and 0.2% of placebo-treated patients. The majority of liraglutide-treated patients with adverse reactions of cholelithiasis and cholecystitis required cholecystectomy.



   Initiation of insulin containing products and intensification of glucose control  



 Intensification or rapid improvement in glucose control has been associated with a transitory, reversible ophthalmologic refraction disorder, worsening of diabetic retinopathy, and acute painful peripheral neuropathy. However, long-term glycemic control decreases the risk of diabetic retinopathy and neuropathy.            



   Lipodystrophy  



 Long-term use of insulin containing products, including XULTOPHY 100/3.6, can cause lipodystrophy at the site of repeated injections. Lipodystrophy includes lipohypertrophy (thickening of adipose tissue) and lipoatrophy (thinning of adipose tissue), and may affect absorption  [see Dosage and Administration (  2.4  )]  .            



   Peripheral Edema  



 Insulin containing products, including XULTOPHY 100/3.6, may cause sodium retention and edema, particularly if previously poor metabolic control is improved rapidly by intensified therapy.



   Weight Gain  



 Weight gain can occur with insulin containing products, including XULTOPHY 100/3.6, and has been attributed to the anabolic effects of insulin. In study A, after 26 weeks of treatment, patients converting to XULTOPHY 100/3.6 from liraglutide had a mean increase in body weight of 2 kg.



   Injection Site reactions  



 As with any insulin and GLP-1 receptor agonist-containing products, patients taking XULTOPHY 100/3.6 may experience injection site reactions, including injection site hematoma, pain, hemorrhage, erythema, nodules, swelling, discoloration, pruritus, warmth, and injection site mass. In the clinical program, the proportion of injection site reactions occurring in patients treated with XULTOPHY 100/3.6 was 2.6%. These reactions were usually mild and transitory and they normally disappear during continued treatment.



   Systemic Allergy  



 Severe, life-threatening, generalized allergy, including anaphylaxis, generalized skin reactions, angioedema, bronchospasm, hypotension, and shock may occur with any insulin-containing products including XULTOPHY 100/3.6 and may be life threatening  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  . Hypersensitivity (manifested with swelling of tongue and lips, diarrhea, nausea, tiredness, and itching) and urticaria were reported.



   Laboratory tests  



   Bilirubin  



   VICTOZA (liraglutide)  



 In the five clinical trials of at least 26 weeks duration, mildly elevated serum bilirubin concentrations (elevations to no more than twice the upper limit of the reference range) occurred in 4.0% of liraglutide-treated patients, 2.1% of placebo-treated patients and 3.5% of active-comparator-treated patients. This finding was not accompanied by abnormalities in other liver tests. The significance of this isolated finding is unknown.



   Calcitonin  



   XULTOPHY 100/3.6  



 Calcitonin, a biological marker of MTC, was measured throughout the XULTOPHY 100/3.6 clinical development program. Among patients with pretreatment calcitonin &lt;20 ng/L, calcitonin elevations to &gt;20 ng/L occurred in 0.7% of XULTOPHY 100/3.6-treated patients, 0.7% of placebo-treated patients, and 1.1% and 0.7% of active-comparator-treated patients (basal insulins and GLP-1s respectively). The clinical significance of these findings is unknown.



   VICTOZA (liraglutide)  



 Calcitonin, a biological marker of MTC, was measured throughout the liraglutide clinical development program. At the end of the clinical trials, adjusted mean serum calcitonin concentrations were higher in liraglutide-treated patients compared to placebo-treated patients but not compared to patients receiving active comparator. Between group differences in adjusted mean serum calcitonin values were approximately 0.1 ng/L or less. Among patients with pretreatment calcitonin &lt;20 ng/L, calcitonin elevations to &gt;20 ng/L occurred in 0.7% of liraglutide-treated patients, 0.3% of placebo-treated patients, and 0.5% of active-comparator-treated patients. The clinical significance of these findings is unknown.



   Lipase and Amylase  



   VICTOZA (liraglutide)  



 In one placebo-controlled trial in renal impairment patients, a mean increase of 33% for lipase and 15% for amylase from baseline was observed for liraglutide-treated patients while placebo-treated patients had a mean decrease in lipase of 3% and a mean increase in amylase of 1%.The clinical significance of these changes is unknown.



   Vital signs  



 Mean increases from baseline in heart rate of 2 to 3 beats per minute have been observed with XULTOPHY 100/3.6 which is attributable to the liraglutide component. The long-term clinical effects of the increase in pulse rate have not been established  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.11  )]  .



   6.2 Immunogenicity

    XULTOPHY 100/3.6  



 As with all therapeutic proteins, there is potential for immunogenicity. The detection of antibody formation is highly dependent on the sensitivity and specificity of the assay. Additionally, the observed incidence of antibody (including neutralizing antibody) positivity in an assay may be influenced by several factors including assay methodology, sample handling, timing of sample collection, concomitant medications, and underlying disease. For these reasons, comparison of the incidence of antibodies to XULTOPHY 100/3.6 in the studies described below with the incidence of antibodies in other studies or to other products may be misleading.



 Administration of XULTOPHY 100/3.6 may cause formation of antibodies against insulin degludec and/or liraglutide. In rare cases, the presence of such antibodies may necessitate adjustment of the XULTOPHY 100/3.6 dose in order to correct a tendency to hyper- or hypoglycemia. In the clinical trials where antibodies were measured in patients receiving XULTOPHY 100/3.6, 11.1% of patients were positive for insulin degludec specific antibodies at end of treatment vs. 2.4% at baseline, 30.8% of patients were positive for antibodies cross-reacting with human insulin at end of treatment vs. 14.6% at baseline. 2.1% of patients were positive for anti-liraglutide antibodies at end of treatment (no patients were positive at baseline). Antibody formation has not been associated with reduced efficacy of XULTOPHY 100/3.6.



   VICTOZA (liraglutide)  



 Consistent with the potentially immunogenic properties of protein and peptide pharmaceuticals, patients treated with liraglutide may develop anti-liraglutide antibodies. Approximately 50-70% of liraglutide-treated patients in five double-blind clinical trials of 26 weeks duration or longer were tested for the presence of anti-liraglutide antibodies at the end of treatment. Low titers (concentrations not requiring dilution of serum) of anti-liraglutide antibodies were detected in 8.6% of these liraglutide-treated patients. Sampling was not performed uniformly across all patients in the clinical trials, and this may have resulted in an underestimate of the actual percentage of patients who developed antibodies. Crossreacting anti-liraglutide antibodies to native glucagon-like peptide-1 (GLP-1) occurred in 6.9% of the liraglutide-treated patients in the double-blind 52-week monotherapy trial and in 4.8% of the liraglutide-treated patients in the double-blind 26-week add-on combination therapy trials. These cross-reacting antibodies were not tested for neutralizing effect against native GLP-1, and thus the potential for clinically significant neutralization of native GLP-1 was not assessed. Antibodies that had a neutralizing effect on liraglutide in an in vitro assay occurred in 2.3% of the liraglutide-treated patients in the double-blind 52-week monotherapy trial and in 1.0% of the liraglutide-treated patients in the double-blind 26-week add-on combination therapy trials.



 Among liraglutide-treated patients who developed anti-liraglutide antibodies, the most common category of adverse reactions was that of infections, which occurred among 40% of these patients compared to 36%, 34% and 35% of antibody-negative liraglutide-treated, placebo-treated and active-control-treated patients, respectively. The specific infections which occurred with greater frequency among liraglutide-treated antibody-positive patients were primarily non-serious upper respiratory tract infections, which occurred among 11% of liraglutide-treated antibody-positive patients; and among 7%, 7% and 5% of antibody-negative liraglutide-treated, placebo-treated and active-control-treated patients, respectively. Among liraglutide-treated antibody-negative patients, the most common category of adverse reactions was that of gastrointestinal events, which occurred in 43%, 18% and 19% of antibody-negative liraglutide-treated, placebo-treated and active-control-treated patients, respectively. Antibody formation was not associated with reduced efficacy of liraglutide when comparing mean HbA1cof all antibody-positive and all antibody-negative patients. However, the 3 patients with the highest titers of anti-liraglutide antibodies had no reduction in HbA1cwith liraglutide treatment.



 In five double-blind clinical trials of liraglutide, events from a composite of adverse events potentially related to immunogenicity (e.g. urticaria, angioedema) occurred among 0.8% of liraglutide-treated patients and among 0.4% of comparator-treated patients. Urticaria accounted for approximately one-half of the events in this composite for liraglutide-treated patients. Patients who developed anti-liraglutide antibodies were not more likely to develop events from the immunogenicity events composite than were patients who did not develop anti-liraglutide antibodies.



   TRESIBA (insulin degludec)  



 In studies of type 2 diabetes patients, 31.5% of patients who received insulin degludec once daily were positive for anti-insulin antibodies (AIA) at least once during the studies, including 14.5% that were positive at baseline. The antibody incidence rates for type 2 diabetes may be underreported due to potential assay interference by endogenous insulin in samples in these patients. The presence of antibodies that affect clinical efficacy may necessitate dose adjustments to correct for tendencies toward hyper or hypoglycemia.



 The incidence of anti-insulin degludec antibodies has not been established.



   6.3 Post-Marketing Experience

  The following additional adverse reactions have been reported during post-approval use. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is generally not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Liraglutide  



 *    Medullary thyroid carcinoma 
 *    Dehydration resulting from nausea, vomiting and diarrhea. 
 *    Increased serum creatinine, acute renal failure or worsening of chronic renal failure, sometimes requiring hemodialysis. 
 *    Angioedema and anaphylactic reactions. 
 *    Allergic reactions: rash and pruritus 
 *    Acute pancreatitis, hemorrhagic and necrotizing pancreatitis sometimes resulting in death 
 *    Hepatobiliary disorders: elevations of liver enzymes, hyperbilirubinemia, cholestasis, hepatitis 
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: RISK OF THYROID C-CELL TUMORS 

  WARNING: RISK OF THYROID C-CELL TUMORS 

    *  Liraglutide, one of the components of XULTOPHY 100/3.6, causes dose-dependent and treatment-duration-dependent thyroid C-cell tumors at clinically relevant exposures in both genders of rats and mice. It is unknown whether XULTOPHY 100/3.6 causes thyroid C-cell tumors, including medullary thyroid carcinoma (MTC), in humans, as the human relevance of liraglutide-induced rodent thyroid C-cell tumors has not been determined [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1) and Nonclinical Toxicology (13)]. 
 *  XULTOPHY 100/3.6 is contraindicated in patients with a personal or family history of MTC and in patients with Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia syndrome type 2 (MEN 2). Counsel patients regarding the potential risk for MTC with the use of XULTOPHY 100/3.6 and inform them of symptoms of thyroid tumors (e.g. a mass in the neck, dysphagia, dyspnea, persistent hoarseness). Routine monitoring of serum calcitonin or using thyroid ultrasound is of uncertain value for early detection of MTC in patients treated with XULTOPHY 100/3.6 [see Contraindications (4), Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]. 
      EXCERPT:   WARNING: RISK OF THYROID C-CELL TUMORS 
 

     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 *  Liraglutide, one of the components of XULTOPHY 100/3.6, causes thyroid C-cell tumors at clinically relevant exposures in both genders of rats and mice. It is unknown whether XULTOPHY 100/3.6 causes thyroid C-cell tumors, including medullary thyroid carcinoma (MTC), in humans, as the human relevance of liraglutide-induced rodent thyroid C-cell tumors has not been determined (5.1, 13.1). 
 *  XULTOPHY 100/3.6 is contraindicated in patients with a personal or family history of MTC or in patients with Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia syndrome type 2 (MEN 2). Counsel patients regarding the potential risk of MTC and the symptoms of thyroid tumors (4, 5.1). 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *     Thyroid C-cell Tumors : See Boxed Warning (  5.1  ). 
 *     Pancreatitis : Postmarketing reports, including fatal and non-fatal hemorrhagic or necrotizing pancreatitis have been reported for liraglutide. Discontinue promptly if pancreatitis is suspected (  5.2  ). 
 *     Never share a XULTOPHY 100/3.6 pen between patients, even if the needle is changed (  5.3  ). 
 *     Hyper- or hypoglycemia with changes in XULTOPHY 100/3.6 regimen : Carry out under close medical supervision and increase frequency of blood glucose monitoring (  5.4  ). 
 *     Overdose due to medication errors : XULTOPHY 100/3.6 contains two drugs. Instruct patients to check label before injection since accidental mix-ups with insulin containing products can occur. Do not exceed the maximum dose or administer with other GLP-1 receptor agonists (  5.5  ). 
 *     Hypoglycemia: May be life-threatening. Increase monitoring with changes to: dosage, co-administered glucose lowering medications, meal pattern, physical activity; and in patients with renal impairment or hepatic impairment or hypoglycemia unawareness (  5.6  ,  6.1  ). 
 *     Acute Kidney Injury: Has been reported postmarketing for liraglutide, usually in association with nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, or dehydration, which may sometimes require hemodialysis. Advise patients of the potential risk of dehydration due to gastrointestinal adverse reactions and take precautions to avoid fluid depletion (  5.7  ). 
 *     Hypersensitivity and Allergic Reactions: Severe, life-threatening, generalized allergy, including anaphylaxis, angioedema, bronchospasm, hypotension, and shock can occur.  If a hypersensitivity reaction occurs, discontinue and treat per standard of care (  5.8  ). 
 *     Hypokalemia: May be life-threatening. Monitor potassium levels in patients at risk for hypokalemia and treat if indicated (  5.9  ). 
 *     Fluid retention and congestive heart failure with use of thiazolidinediones (TZDs): Observe for signs and symptoms of heart failure; consider dosage reduction or discontinuation if heart failure occurs (  5.10  ). 
 *     Macrovascular Outcomes : There have been no studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with XULTOPHY 100/3.6 (  5.11  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Risk of Thyroid C-cell Tumors



  Liraglutide, one of the components of XULTOPHY 100/3.6, causes dose-dependent and treatment-duration-dependent thyroid C-cell tumors (adenomas and/or carcinomas) at clinically relevant exposures in both genders of rats and mice [see Nonclinical Toxicology (  13.1  )]  . Malignant thyroid C-cell carcinomas were detected in rats and mice. It is unknown whether XULTOPHY 100/3.6 will cause thyroid C-cell tumors, including medullary thyroid carcinoma (MTC), in humans, as the human relevance of liraglutide-induced rodent thyroid C-cell tumors has not been determined.



 Cases of MTC in patients treated with liraglutide have been reported in the postmarketing period; the data in these reports are insufficient to establish or exclude a causal relationship between MTC and liraglutide use in humans.



 XULTOPHY 100/3.6 is contraindicated in patients with a personal or family history of MTC or in patients with MEN 2. Counsel patients regarding the potential risk for MTC with the use of XULTOPHY 100/3.6 and inform them of symptoms of thyroid tumors (e.g. a mass in the neck, dysphagia, dyspnea, persistent hoarseness).



 Routine monitoring of serum calcitonin or using thyroid ultrasound is of uncertain value for early detection of MTC in patients treated with XULTOPHY 100/3.6. Such monitoring may increase the risk of unnecessary procedures, due to low test specificity for serum calcitonin and a high background incidence of thyroid disease. Significantly elevated serum calcitonin may indicate MTC and patients with MTC usually have calcitonin values &gt;50 ng/L. If serum calcitonin is measured and found to be elevated, the patient should be further evaluated. Patients with thyroid nodules noted on physical examination or neck imaging should also be further evaluated.



    5.2 Pancreatitis



  Based on spontaneous postmarketing reports, acute pancreatitis, including fatal and non-fatal hemorrhagic or necrotizing pancreatitis, has been observed in patients treated with liraglutide, one of the components of XULTOPHY 100/3.6. In clinical trials of liraglutide, there have been 13 cases of pancreatitis among liraglutide-treated patients and 1 case in a comparator (glimepiride) treated patient (2.7 vs. 0.5 cases per 1000 patient-years). Nine of the 13 cases with liraglutide were reported as acute pancreatitis and four were reported as chronic pancreatitis. In one case in a liraglutide-treated patient, pancreatitis, with necrosis, was observed and led to death; however clinical causality could not be established. Some patients had other risk factors for pancreatitis, such as a history of cholelithiasis or alcohol abuse.



 After initiation of XULTOPHY 100/3.6, observe patients carefully for signs and symptoms of pancreatitis (including persistent severe abdominal pain, sometimes radiating to the back and which may or may not be accompanied by vomiting). If pancreatitis is suspected, XULTOPHY 100/3.6 should promptly be discontinued and appropriate management should be initiated. If pancreatitis is confirmed, restarting XULTOPHY 100/3.6 is not recommended. Consider antidiabetic therapies other than XULTOPHY 100/3.6 in patients with a history of pancreatitis.



    5.3 Never Share a XULTOPHY 100/3.6 Pen Between Patients



  XULTOPHY 100/3.6 pen must never be shared between patients, even if the needle is changed. Sharing of the pen poses a risk for transmission of blood-borne pathogens.



    5.4 Hyperglycemia or Hypoglycemia with Changes in XULTOPHY 100/3.6 Regimen



  Changes in XULTOPHY 100/3.6 regimen may affect glycemic control and predispose to hypoglycemia or hyperglycemia [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  . These changes should be made cautiously and only under medical supervision and the frequency of blood glucose monitoring should be increased. Adjustments in concomitant oral anti-diabetic treatment may be needed. When converting from basal insulin therapies or liraglutide to XULTOPHY 100/3.6 follow dosing recommendations [see Dosage and Administration (  2.1,    2.2  )].  



    5.5 Overdose due to Medication Errors



  XULTOPHY 100/3.6 contains two drugs: insulin degludec and liraglutide. Administration of more than 50 units of XULTOPHY 100/3.6 daily can result in overdose of the liraglutide component. Do not exceed the 1.8 mg maximum recommended dose of liraglutide or use with other glucagon-like peptide-1 receptor agonists.



 Accidental mix-ups between insulin products have been reported. To avoid medication errors between XULTOPHY 100/3.6 (an insulin containing product) and other insulin products, instruct patients to always check the label before each injection.



    5.6 Hypoglycemia



  Hypoglycemia is the most common adverse reaction of insulin containing products, including XULTOPHY 100/3.6 [see Adverse Reactions (  6.1  )]  . Severe hypoglycemia can cause seizures, may be life-threatening or cause death. Hypoglycemia can impair concentration ability and reaction time; this may place an individual and others at risk in situations where these abilities are important (e.g., driving or operating other machinery). XULTOPHY 100/3.6 (an insulin-containing product) or any insulin, should not be used during episodes of hypoglycemia [see   Contraindications (  4    ) ]  .



 Hypoglycemia can happen suddenly and symptoms may differ in each individual and change over time in the same individual. Symptomatic awareness of hypoglycemia may be less pronounced in patients with longstanding diabetes, in patients with diabetic nerve disease, in patients using medications that block the sympathetic nervous system (e.g., beta-blockers) [see   Drug Interactions (  7.1    ) ]  , or in patients who experience recurrent hypoglycemia.



  Risk Factors for Hypoglycemia  



 The risk of hypoglycemia generally increases with intensity of glycemic control. The risk of hypoglycemia after an injection is related to the duration of action of the insulin [ see   Clinical Pharmacology (  12.2  )]  and, in general, is highest when the glucose lowering effect of the insulin is maximal. As with all insulin containing products, the glucose lowering effect time course of XULTOPHY 100/3.6 may vary among different individuals or at different times in the same individual and depends on many conditions, including the area of injection as well as the injection site blood supply and temperature.



 Other factors which may increase the risk of hypoglycemia include changes in meal pattern (e.g., macronutrient content or timing of meals), changes in level of physical activity, or changes to co-administered medication [ see Drug Interactions (  7.1  )]  . Patients with renal or hepatic impairment may be at higher risk of hypoglycemia [see Use in Specific Populations   (  8.6  ,  8.7  )]  .



  Risk Mitigation Strategies for Hypoglycemia  



 Patients and caregivers must be educated to recognize and manage hypoglycemia. Self-monitoring of blood glucose plays an essential role in the prevention and management of hypoglycemia. In patients at higher risk for hypoglycemia and patients who have reduced symptomatic awareness of hypoglycemia, increased frequency of blood glucose monitoring is recommended.



    5.7 Acute Kidney Injury



  There have been postmarketing reports of acute renal failure and worsening of chronic renal failure, which may sometimes require hemodialysis in patients treated with liraglutide, one of the components of XULTOPHY 100/3.6 [see Adverse Reactions (  6.3  )]  . Some of these events were reported in patients without known underlying renal disease. A majority of the reported events occurred in patients who had experienced nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, or dehydration. Some of the reported events occurred in patients receiving one or more medications known to affect renal function or hydration status. Altered renal function has been reversed in many of the reported cases with supportive treatment and discontinuation of potentially causative agents, including liraglutide. Advise patients of the potential risk of dehydration due to gastrointestinal adverse reactions and take precautions to avoid fluid depletion.



    5.8 Hypersensitivity and Allergic Reactions



  Severe, life-threatening, generalized allergy, including anaphylaxis, angioedema, bronchospasm, hypotension, and shock can occur with XULTOPHY 100/3.6.   Allergic reactions (manifested with signs and symptoms such as urticaria, rash, pruritus) have been reported with XULTOPHY 100/3.6. There have been postmarketing reports of serious hypersensitivity reactions (e.g., anaphylactic reactions and angioedema) in patients treated with liraglutide, one of the components of XULTOPHY 100/3.6 [see Adverse Reactions (  6.3  )]  . If a hypersensitivity reaction occurs, discontinue XULTOPHY 100/3.6; treat per standard of care and monitor until symptoms and signs resolve.



 Angioedema has also been reported with other GLP-1 receptor agonists. Use caution in a patient with a history of angioedema with another GLP-1 receptor agonist because it is unknown whether such patients will be predisposed to angioedema with XULTOPHY 100/3.6. XULTOPHY 100/3.6 is contraindicated in patients who have had hypersensitivity reactions to insulin degludec, liraglutide or one of the excipients of these products [see Contraindications (  4  )]  .



    5.9 Hypokalemia



  All insulin-containing products, including XULTOPHY 100/3.6, cause a shift in potassium from the extracellular to intracellular space, possibly leading to hypokalemia. Untreated hypokalemia may cause respiratory paralysis, ventricular arrhythmia, and death. Monitor potassium levels in patients at risk for hypokalemia if indicated (e.g., patients using potassium-lowering medications, patients taking medications sensitive to serum potassium concentrations).



    5.10 Fluid Retention and Congestive Heart Failure with Concomitant Use of a PPAR Gamma Agonist



  Peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor (PPAR)-gamma agonists can cause dose related fluid retention, particularly when used in combination with insulin containing products, including XULTOPHY 100/3.6. Fluid retention may lead to or exacerbate congestive heart failure. Patients treated with insulin containing products, including XULTOPHY 100/3.6 and a PPAR-gamma agonist should be observed for signs and symptoms of congestive heart failure. If congestive heart failure develops, it should be managed according to current standards of care and discontinuation or dose reduction of the PPAR-gamma agonist must be considered.



    5.11 Macrovascular Outcomes



  There have been no clinical studies establishing conclusive evidence of macrovascular risk reduction with XULTOPHY 100/3.6 or any other antidiabetic drug.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
