<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="xylocaine1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Systemic

  Adverse experiences following the administration of lidocaine HCl are similar in nature to those observed with other amide local anesthetic agents.  These adverse experiences are, in general, dose-related and may result from high plasma levels caused by excessive dosage, rapid absorption or inadvertent intravascular injection, or may result from a hypersensitivity, idiosyncrasy or diminished tolerance on the part of the patient.  Serious adverse experiences are generally systemic in nature.  The following types are those most commonly reported:



   Central Nervous System

  CNS manifestations are excitatory and/or depressant and may be characterized by lightheadedness, nervousness, apprehension, euphoria, confusion, dizziness, drowsiness, tinnitus, blurred or double vision, vomiting, sensations of heat, cold or numbness, twitching, tremors, convulsions, unconsciousness, respiratory depression and arrest.  The excitatory manifestations may be very brief or may not occur at all, in which case the first manifestation of toxicity may be drowsiness merging into unconsciousness and respiratory arrest.



 Drowsiness following the administration of lidocaine HCl is usually an early sign of a high blood level of the drug and may occur as a consequence of rapid absorption.



   Cardiovascular System

  Cardiovascular manifestations are usually depressant and are characterized by bradycardia, hypotension, and cardiovascular collapse, which may lead to cardiac arrest.



   Allergic

  Allergic reactions are characterized by cutaneous lesions, urticaria, edema or anaphylactoid reactions.  Allergic reactions may occur as a result of sensitivity either to local anesthetic agents or to the methylparaben used as a preservative in the multiple dose vials.  Allergic reactions, including anaphylactic reactions, may occur as a result of sensitivity to lidocaine, but are infrequent.  If allergic reactions do occur, they should be managed by conventional means.  The detection of sensitivity by skin testing is of doubtful value.There have been no reports of cross sensitivity between lidocaine hydrochloride and procainamide or between lidocaine hydrochloride and quinidine.



   Neurologic

  The incidences of adverse reactions associated with the use of local anesthetics may be related to the total dose of local anesthetic administered and are also dependent upon the particular drug used, the route of administration and the physical status of the patient.  In a prospective review of 10,440 patients who received lidocaine HCl for spinal anesthesia, the incidences of adverse reactions were reported to be about 3 percent each for positional headaches, hypotension and backache; 2 percent for shivering; and less than 1 percent each for peripheral nerve symptoms, nausea, respiratory inadequacy and double vision.  Many of these observations may be related to local anesthetic techniques, with or without a contribution from the local anesthetic.



 In the practice of caudal or lumbar epidural block, occasional unintentional penetration of the subarachnoid space by the catheter may occur.  Subsequent adverse effects may depend partially on the amount of drug administered subdurally.  These may include spinal block of varying magnitude (including total spinal block), hypotension secondary to spinal block, loss of bladder and bowel control, and loss of perineal sensation and sexual function.  Persistent motor, sensory and/or autonomic (sphincter control) deficit of some lower spinal segments with slow recovery (several months) or incomplete recovery have been reported in rare instances when caudal or lumbar epidural block has been attempted.  Backache and headache have also been noted following use of these anesthetic procedures.



 There have been reported cases of permanent injury to extraocular muscles requiring surgical repair following retrobulbar administration.    Hematologic    Methemoglobinemia.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
