<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="xyrem" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions appear in other sections of the labeling:



 *    CNS depression [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *    Abuse and Misuse [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )]  
 *    Respiratory Depression and Sleep-disordered Breathing [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
 *    Depression and Suicidality [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.5  )]  
 *    Other Behavioral or Psychiatric Adverse Reactions [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.6  )]  
 *    Parasomnias [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.7  )]  
 *    Use in Patients Sensitive to High Sodium Intake [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 5% and at least twice the incidence with placebo) were nausea, dizziness, vomiting, somnolence, enuresis, and tremor (  6.1  ).  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Jazz Pharmaceuticals at 1-800-520-5568, or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/Medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 Xyrem was studied in three placebo-controlled clinical trials (Trials N1, N3, and N4, described in  Sections 14.1  and  14.2  ) in 611 patients with narcolepsy (398 subjects treated with Xyrem, and 213 with placebo). A total of 781 patients with narcolepsy were treated with Xyrem in controlled and uncontrolled clinical trials.



 Section 6.1 and Table 3 presents adverse reactions from three pooled, controlled trials (N1, N3, N4) in patients with narcolepsy.



   Adverse Reactions Leading to Treatment Discontinuation:  



 Of the 398 Xyrem-treated patients with narcolepsy, 10.3% of patients discontinued because of adverse reactions compared with 2.8% of patients receiving placebo. The most common adverse reaction leading to discontinuation was nausea (2.8%). The majority of adverse reactions leading to discontinuation began during the first few weeks of treatment.



   Commonly Observed Adverse Reactions in Controlled Clinical Trials:  



 The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;= 5% and twice the rate seen with placebo) in Xyrem-treated patients were nausea, dizziness, vomiting, somnolence, enuresis, and tremor.



   Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of 2% or greater:  



 Table 3 lists adverse reactions that occurred at a frequency of 2% or more in any treatment group for three controlled trials and were more frequent in any Xyrem treatment group than with placebo. Adverse reactions are summarized by dose at onset. Nearly all patients in these studies initiated treatment at 4.5 g per night. In patients who remained on treatment, adverse reactions tended to occur early and to diminish over time.  Table 3    Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=2% of Patients and More Frequently with Xyrem than Placebo in Three Controlled Trials (N1, N3, N4) by Body System and Dose at Onset  




   System Organ Class/MedDRA Preferred Term      Placebo    (n=213) %      Xyrem 4.5g    (n=185) %      Xyrem 6g    (n=258) %      Xyrem 9g    (n=178) %     
  
  ANY ADVERSE REACTION             62              45               55              70               
  GASTROINTESTINAL DISORDERS       
  Nausea                           3               8                13              20               
  Vomiting                         1               2                4               11               
  Diarrhea                         2               4                3               4                
  Abdominal pain upper             2               3                1               2                
  Dry mouth                        2               1                2               1                
  GENERAL DISORDERS AND ADMINISTRATIVE SITE CONDITIONS    
  Pain                             1               1                &lt; 1             3                
  Feeling drunk                    1               0                &lt; 1             3                
  Edema peripheral                 1               3                0               0                
  MUSCULOSKELETAL AND CONNECTIVE TISSUE DISORDERS    
  Pain in extremity                1               3                1               1                
  Cataplexy                        1               1                1               2                
  Muscle spasms                    2               2                &lt; 1             2                
  NERVOUS SYSTEM DISORDERS         
  Dizziness                        4               9                11              15               
  Somnolence                       4               1                3               8                
  Tremor                           0               0                2               5                
  Paresthesia                      1               2                1               3                
  Disturbance in attention         0               1                0               4                
  Sleep paralysis                  1               0                1               3                
  PSYCHIATRIC DISORDERS            
  Disorientation                   1               1                2               3                
  Anxiety                          1               1                1               2                
  Irritability                     1               0                &lt; 1             3                
  Sleep walking                    0               0                0               3                
  RENAL AND URINARY DISORDERS      
  Enuresis                         1               3                3               7                
  SKIN AND SUBCUTANEOUS TISSUE DISORDERS    
  Hyperhidrosis                    0               1                1               3                
             Dose-Response Information  
 

 In clinical trials in narcolepsy, a dose-response relationship was observed for nausea, vomiting, paresthesia, disorientation, irritability, disturbance in attention, feeling drunk, sleepwalking, and enuresis. The incidence of all these reactions was notably higher at 9 g per night.



 In controlled trials in narcolepsy, discontinuations of treatment due to adverse reactions were greater at higher doses of Xyrem.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following additional adverse reactions that have a likely causal relationship to Xyrem exposure have been identified during postmarketing use of Xyrem. These adverse reactions include: arthralgia, decreased appetite, fall, fluid retention, hangover, headache, hypersensitivity, hypertension, memory impairment, panic attack, vision blurred, and weight decreased. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING:  CENTRAL NERVOUS SYSTEM DEPRESSION and MISUSE AND ABUSE. 

  WARNING:  CENTRAL NERVOUS SYSTEM DEPRESSION and MISUSE AND ABUSE. 

    Xyrem (sodium oxybate) is a CNS depressant. In clinical trials at recommended doses obtundation and clinically significant respiratory depression occurred in Xyrem-treated patients. Almost all of the patients who received Xyrem during clinical trials in narcolepsy were receiving central nervous system stimulants   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]      .  



   Xyrem  (r)   (sodium oxybate) is the sodium salt of gamma hydroxybutyrate (GHB). Abuse of GHB, either alone or in combination with other CNS depressants, is associated with CNS adverse reactions, including seizure, respiratory depression, decreases in the level of consciousness, coma, and death   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.2  )].    



   Because of the risks of CNS depression, abuse, and misuse, Xyrem is available only through a restricted distribution program called the Xyrem REMS Program, using the central pharmacy that is specially certified.  Prescribers and patients must enroll in the program. For further information go to   www.XYREMREMS.com   or call 1-866-XYREM88  (r)   (1-866-997-3688).   [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )].    



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: CENTRAL NERVOUS SYSTEM (CNS) DEPRESSION and MISUSE AND ABUSE.



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 *  Respiratory depression can occur with Xyrem use (5.4) 
 *  Xyrem is a Schedule III controlled substance and is the sodium salt of gamma hydroxybutyrate (GHB), a Schedule I controlled substance. Abuse or misuse of illicit GHB is associated with CNS adverse reactions, including seizure, respiratory depression, decreased consciousness, coma and death (5.2, 9.2) 
 *  Because of the risks of CNS depression, abuse, and misuse, Xyrem is available only through a restricted distribution program called the Xyrem REMS Program using the central pharmacy that is specially certified. Prescribers and patients must enroll in the program. (5.3) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    CNS depression: Use caution when considering the concurrent use of Xyrem with other CNS depressants (  5.1  ). 
 *    Caution patients against hazardous activities requiring complete mental alertness or motor coordination within the first 6 hours of dosing or after first initiating treatment until certain that Xyrem does not affect them adversely (  5.1  ). 
 *    Depression and suicidality: Monitor patients for emergent or increased depression and suicidality (  5.5  ). 
 *    Confusion/Anxiety: Monitor for impaired motor/cognitive function (  5.6  ). 
 *    Parasomnias: Evaluate episodes of sleepwalking (  5.7  ). 
 *    High sodium content in Xyrem: Monitor patients with heart failure, hypertension, or impaired renal function (  5.8  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Central Nervous System Depression



  Xyrem is a central nervous system (CNS) depressant. Alcohol and sedative hypnotics are contraindicated in patients who are using Xyrem. The concurrent use of Xyrem with other CNS depressants, including but not limited to opioid analgesics, benzodiazepines, sedating antidepressants or antipsychotics, sedating anti-epileptic drugs, general anesthetics, muscle relaxants, and/or illicit CNS depressants, may increase the risk of respiratory depression, hypotension, profound sedation, syncope, and death. If use of these CNS depressants in combination with Xyrem is required, dose reduction or discontinuation of one or more CNS depressants (including Xyrem) should be considered. In addition, if short-term use of an opioid (e.g. post- or perioperative) is required, interruption of treatment with Xyrem should be considered.



 Healthcare providers should caution patients about operating hazardous machinery, including automobiles or airplanes, until they are reasonably certain that Xyrem does not affect them adversely (e.g., impair judgment, thinking, or motor skills). Patients should not engage in hazardous occupations or activities requiring complete mental alertness or motor coordination, such as operating machinery or a motor vehicle or flying an airplane, for at least 6 hours after taking the second nightly dose of Xyrem. Patients should be queried about CNS depression -  related events upon initiation of Xyrem therapy and periodically thereafter [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )].  



    5.2 Abuse and Misuse



  Xyrem is a Schedule III controlled substance. The active ingredient of Xyrem, sodium oxybate or gamma-hydroxybutyrate (GHB), is a Schedule I controlled substance. Abuse of illicit GHB, either alone or in combination with other CNS depressants, is associated with CNS adverse reactions, including seizure, respiratory depression, decreases in the level of consciousness, coma, and death. The rapid onset of sedation, coupled with the amnestic features of Xyrem, particularly when combined with alcohol, has proven to be dangerous for the voluntary and involuntary user (e.g., assault victim). Because illicit use and abuse of GHB have been reported, physicians should carefully evaluate patients for a history of drug abuse and follow such patients closely, observing them for signs of misuse or abuse of GHB (e.g. increase in size or frequency of dosing, drug-seeking behavior, feigned cataplexy) [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.3  )  and Drug Abuse and Dependence (  9.2  )].  



     5.3 Xyrem REMS Program  



   Because of the risks of central nervous system depression and abuse/misuse, Xyrem is available only through a restricted distribution program called the Xyrem REMS Program.  



  Required components of the Xyrem REMS Program include:  



 *     Healthcare Providers who prescribe Xyrem are specially certified  
 *     Xyrem will be dispensed only by the central pharmacy that is specially certified  
 *     Xyrem will be dispensed and shipped only to patients who are enrolled in the XYREM REMS Program with documentation of safe use  
     Further information is available at     www.XYREMREMS.com     or 1-866-XYREM88  (r)  (1-866-997-3688)  .  
 

    5.4 Respiratory Depression and Sleep-Disordered Breathing



  Xyrem may impair respiratory drive, especially in patients with compromised respiratory function. In overdoses, life-threatening respiratory depression has been reported [see Overdosage (  10  )].  



 In a study assessing the respiratory-depressant effects of Xyrem at doses up to 9 g per night in 21 patients with narcolepsy, no dose-related changes in oxygen saturation were demonstrated in the group as a whole. One of the four patients with preexisting, moderate-to-severe sleep apnea had significant worsening of the apnea/hypopnea index during treatment.



 In a study assessing the effects of Xyrem 9 g per night in 50 patients with obstructive sleep apnea, Xyrem did not increase the severity of sleep-disordered breathing and did not adversely affect the average duration and severity of oxygen desaturation overall. However, there was a significant increase in the number of central apneas in patients taking Xyrem, and clinically significant oxygen desaturation (&lt;= 55%) was measured in three patients (6%) after Xyrem administration, with one patient withdrawing from the study and two continuing after single brief instances of desaturation. Prescribers should be aware that increased central apneas and clinically relevant desaturation events have been observed with Xyrem administration.



 In clinical trials in 128 patients with narcolepsy, two subjects had profound CNS depression, which resolved after supportive respiratory intervention. Two other patients discontinued sodium oxybate because of severe difficulty breathing and an increase in obstructive sleep apnea. In two controlled trials assessing polysomnographic (PSG) measures in patients with narcolepsy, 40 of 477 patients were included with a baseline apnea/hypopnea index of 16 to 67 events per hour, indicative of mild to severe sleep-disordered breathing. None of the 40 patients had a clinically significant worsening of respiratory function as measured by apnea/hypopnea index and pulse oximetry at doses of 4.5 g to 9 g per night.



 Prescribers should be aware that sleep-related breathing disorders tend to be more prevalent in obese patients and in postmenopausal women not on hormone replacement therapy as well as among patients with narcolepsy.



    5.5 Depression and Suicidality



  In clinical trials in patients with narcolepsy (n=781), there were two suicides and two attempted suicides in Xyrem-treated patients, including three patients with a previous history of depressive psychiatric disorder. Of the two suicides, one patient used Xyrem in conjunction with other drugs. Xyrem was not involved in the second suicide. Adverse reactions of depression were reported by 7% of 781 Xyrem-treated patients, with four patients (&lt; 1%) discontinuing because of depression. In most cases, no change in Xyrem treatment was required.



 In a controlled trial, with patients randomized to fixed doses of 3 g, 6 g, or 9 g per night Xyrem or placebo, there was a single event of depression at the 3 g per night dose. In another controlled trial, with patients titrated from an initial 4.5 g per night starting dose, the incidences of depression were 1 (1.7%), 1 (1.5%), 2 (3.2%), and 2 (3.6%) for the placebo, 4.5 g, 6 g, and 9 g per night doses, respectively.



 The emergence of depression in patients treated with Xyrem requires careful and immediate evaluation. Patients with a previous history of a depressive illness and/or suicide attempt should be monitored carefully for the emergence of depressive symptoms while taking Xyrem.



    5.6 Other Behavioral or Psychiatic Adverse Reactions



  During clinical trials in narcolepsy, 3% of 781 patients treated with Xyrem experienced confusion, with incidence generally increasing with dose.



 Less than 1% of patients discontinued the drug because of confusion. Confusion was reported at all recommended doses from 6 g to 9 g per night. In a controlled trial where patients were randomized to fixed total daily doses of 3 g, 6 g, or 9 g per night or placebo, a dose-response relationship for confusion was demonstrated, with 17% of patients at 9 g per night experiencing confusion. In all cases in that controlled trial, the confusion resolved soon after termination of treatment. In Trial 3 where sodium oxybate was titrated from an initial 4.5 g per night dose, there was a single event of confusion in one patient at the 9 g per night dose. In the majority of cases in all clinical trials in narcolepsy, confusion resolved either soon after termination of dosing or with continued treatment. However, patients treated with Xyrem who become confused should be evaluated fully, and appropriate intervention considered on an individual basis.



 Anxiety occurred in 5.8% of the 874 patients receiving Xyrem in clinical trials in another population. The emergence of or increase in anxiety in patients taking Xyrem should be carefully monitored.



 Other neuropsychiatric reactions reported in Xyrem clinical trials included hallucinations, paranoia, psychosis, and agitation. The emergence of thought disorders and/or behavior abnormalities requires careful and immediate evaluation.



    5.7 Parasomnias



  Sleepwalking, defined as confused behavior occurring at night and at times associated with wandering, was reported in 6% of 781 patients with narcolepsy treated with Xyrem in controlled and long-term open-label studies, with &lt; 1% of patients discontinuing due to sleepwalking. Rates of sleepwalking were similar for patients taking placebo and patients taking Xyrem in controlled trials. It is unclear if some or all of the reported sleepwalking episodes correspond to true somnambulism, which is a parasomnia occurring during non-REM sleep, or to any other specific medical disorder. Five instances of significant injury or potential injury were associated with sleepwalking during a clinical trial of Xyrem in patients with narcolepsy.



 Parasomnias including sleepwalking have been reported in postmarketing experience with Xyrem. Therefore, episodes of sleepwalking should be fully evaluated and appropriate interventions considered.



    5.8 Use in Patients Sensitive to High Sodium Intake



   Xyrem has a high salt content. In patients sensitive to salt intake (e.g., those with heart failure, hypertension, or renal impairment) consider the amount of daily sodium intake in each dose of Xyrem. Table 2 provides the approximate sodium content per Xyrem dose.   Table 2  
 

   Approximate Sodium Content per Total Nightly Dose of Xyrem (g = grams)    
 


  Xyrem Dose                 Sodium Content/Total Nightly Exposure    
  3 g per night              550 mg                               
  4.5 g per night            820 mg                               
  6 g per night              1100 mg                              
  7.5 g per night            1400 mg                              
  9 g per night              1640 mg                              
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
