<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="xyzal1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Use of XYZAL has been associated with somnolence, fatigue, and asthenia [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.1)    ].



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (rate &gt;=2% and &gt; placebo) were somnolence, nasopharyngitis, fatigue, dry mouth, and pharyngitis in subjects 12 years of age and older, and pyrexia, somnolence, cough, and epistaxis in children 6 to 12 years of age. In subjects 1 to 5 years of age, the most common adverse reactions (rate &gt;=2% and &gt; placebo) were pyrexia, diarrhea, vomiting, and otitis media. In subjects 6 to 11 months of age, the most common adverse reactions (rate &gt;=3% and &gt; placebo) were diarrhea and constipation. (  6.1  ).



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact UCB, Inc. at 866-822-0068 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

     



 The safety data described below reflect exposure to XYZAL in 2708 patients with seasonal or perennial allergic rhinitis or chronic idiopathic urticaria in 14 controlled clinical trials of 1 week to 6 months duration.



 The short-term (exposure up to 6 weeks) safety data for adults and adolescents are based upon eight clinical trials in which 1896 patients (825 males and 1071 females aged 12 years and older) were treated with XYZAL 2.5, 5, or 10 mg once daily in the evening.



 The short-term safety data from pediatric patients are based upon two clinical trials in which 243 children with seasonal or perennial allergic rhinitis (162 males and 81 females 6 to 12 years of age) were treated with XYZAL 5 mg once daily for 4 to 6 weeks, one clinical trial in which 114 children (65 males and 49 females 1 to 5 years of age) with allergic rhinitis or chronic idiopathic urticaria were treated with XYZAL 1.25 mg twice daily for 2 weeks, and one clinical trial in which 45 children (28 males and 17 females 6 to 11 months of age) with symptoms of allergic rhinitis or chronic urticaria were treated with XYZAL 1.25 mg once daily for 2 weeks.



 The long-term (exposure of 4 or 6 months) safety data in adults and adolescents are based upon two clinical trials in which 428 patients (190 males and 238 females) with allergic rhinitis were exposed to treatment with XYZAL 5 mg once daily. Long term safety data are also available from an 18-month trial in 255 XYZAL-treated subjects 12-24 months of age.



 Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trial of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



           Adults and Adolescents 12 years of Age and Older  



 In studies up to 6 weeks in duration, the mean age of the adult and adolescent patients was 32 years, 44% of the patients were men and 56% were women, and the large majority (more than 90%) was Caucasian.



 In these trials 43% and 42% of the subjects in the XYZAL 2.5 mg and 5 mg groups, respectively, had at least one adverse event compared to 43% in the placebo group.



 In placebo-controlled trials of 1-6 weeks in duration, the most common adverse reactions were somnolence, nasopharyngitis, fatigue, dry mouth, and pharyngitis, and most were mild to moderate in intensity. Somnolence with XYZAL showed dose ordering between tested doses of 2.5, 5 and 10 mg and was the most common adverse reaction leading to discontinuation (0.5%).



 Table 1 lists adverse reactions that were reported in greater than or equal to 2% of subjects aged 12 years and older exposed to XYZAL 2.5 mg or 5 mg in eight placebo-controlled clinical trials and that were more common with XYZAL than placebo.



 Table 1 Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;= 2%* of Subjects Aged 12 Years and Older Exposed to XYZAL 2.5 mg or 5 mg Once Daily in Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials 1-6 Weeks in Duration 
   Adverse Reactions          XYZAL 2.5 mg(n = 421)      XYZAL 5 mg(n = 1070)       Placebo(n = 912)          
 Somnolence                 22 (5%)                    61 (6%)                    16 (2%)                     
 Nasopharyngitis            25 (6%)                    40 (4%)                    28 (3%)                     
 Fatigue                    5 (1%)                     46 (4%)                    20 (2%)                     
 Dry Mouth                  12 (3%)                    26 (2%)                    11 (1%)                     
 Pharyngitis                10 (2%)                    12 (1%)                    9 (1%)                      
     *   Rounded to the closest unit percentage Additional adverse reactions of medical significance observed at a higher incidence than in placebo in adults and adolescents aged 12 years and older exposed to XYZAL are syncope (0.2%) and weight increased (0.5%).
 

           Pediatric Patients 6 to 12 Years of Age  



 A total of 243 pediatric patients 6 to 12 years of age received XYZAL 5 mg once daily in two short-term placebo controlled double-blind trials. The mean age of the patients was 9.8 years, 79 (32%) were 6 to 8 years of age, and 50% were Caucasian. Table 2 lists adverse reactions that were reported in greater than or equal to 2% of subjects aged 6 to 12 years exposed to XYZAL 5 mg in placebo-controlled clinical trials and that were more common with XYZAL than placebo.



 Table 2 Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=2%* of Subjects Aged 6-12 Years Exposed to XYZAL 5 mg Once Daily in Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials 4 and 6 Weeks in Duration 
   Adverse Reactions          XYZAL 5 mg(n = 243)        Placebo(n = 240)          
 Pyrexia                    10 (4%)                    5 (2%)                      
 Cough                       8 (3%)                    2 (less than 1%)            
 Somnolence                 7 (3%)                     1 (less than 1%)            
 Epistaxis                  6 (2%)                     1 (less than 1%)            
     *  Rounded to the closest unit percentage   Pediatric Patients 1 to 5 Years of Age  
 

 A total of 114 pediatric patients 1 to 5 years of age received XYZAL 1.25 mg twice daily in a two week placebo-controlled double-blind safety trial. The mean age of the patients was 3.8 years, 32% were 1 to 2 years of age, 71% were Caucasian and 18% were Black. Table 3 lists adverse reactions that were reported in greater than or equal to 2% of subjects aged 1 to 5 years exposed to XYZAL 1.25 mg twice daily in the placebo-controlled safety trial and that were more common with XYZAL than placebo.



 Table 3 Adverse Reactions Reported in &gt;=2%* of Subjects Aged 1-5 Years Exposed to XYZAL 1.25 mg Twice Daily in a 2-Week Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trial 
   Adverse Reactions          XYZAL 1.25 mg Twice Daily(n = 114)      Placebo(n = 59)           
 Pyrexia                    5 (4%)                     1 (2%)                      
 Diarrhea                   4 (4%)                     2 (3%)                      
 Vomiting                   4 (4%)                     2 (3%)                      
 Otitis Media               3 (3%)                     0 (0%)                      
     *   Rounded to the closest unit percentage   Pediatric Patients 6 to 11 Months of Age  
 

 A total of 45 pediatric patients 6 to 11 months of age received XYZAL 1.25 mg once daily in a two week placebo-controlled double-blind safety trial. The mean age of the patients was 9 months, 51% were Caucasian and 31% were Black. Adverse reactions that were reported in more than 1 subject (i.e. greater than or equal to 3% of subjects) aged 6 to 11 months exposed to XYZAL 1.25 mg once daily in the placebo-controlled safety trial and that were more common with XYZAL than placebo included diarrhea and constipation which were reported in 6 (13%) and 1 (4%) and 3 (7%) and 1 (4%) children in the XYZAL and placebo-treated groups, respectively.



           Long-Term Clinical Trials Experience  



 In two controlled clinical trials, 428 patients (190 males and 238 females) aged 12 years and older were treated with XYZAL 5 mg once daily for 4 or 6 months. The patient characteristics and the safety profile were similar to that seen in the short-term studies. Ten (2.3%) patients treated with XYZAL discontinued because of somnolence, fatigue or asthenia compared to 2 (less than 1%) in the placebo group.



 There are no long term clinical trials in children below 12 years of age with allergic rhinitis or chronic idiopathic urticaria.



           Laboratory Test Abnormalities  



 Elevations of blood bilirubin and transaminases were reported in less than 1% of patients in the clinical trials. The elevations were transient and did not lead to discontinuation in any patient.



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  In addition to the adverse reactions reported during clinical trials and listed above, adverse events have also been identified during post-approval use of XYZAL in other countries. Because these events are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. Adverse events of hypersensitivity and anaphylaxis, angioneurotic edema, fixed drug eruption, pruritus, rash, and urticaria, convulsion, aggression and agitation, visual disturbances, palpitations, dyspnea, nausea, hepatitis, and myalgia have been reported.



 Besides these events reported under treatment with XYZAL, other potentially severe adverse events have been reported from the post-marketing experience with cetirizine. Since levocetirizine is the principal pharmacologically active component of cetirizine, one should take into account the fact that the following adverse events could also potentially occur under treatment with XYZAL: hallucinations, suicidal ideation, orofacial dyskinesia, severe hypotension, cholestasis, glomerulonephritis, and still birth.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  Enter section text here



    EXCERPT:    *  Avoid engaging in hazardous occupations requiring complete mental alertness such as driving or operating machinery when taking XYZAL (  5.1  ). 
 *  Avoid concurrent use of alcohol or other central nervous system depressants with XYZAL (  5.1  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Activities Requiring Mental Alertness



  In clinical trials the occurrence of somnolence, fatigue, and asthenia has been reported in some patients under therapy with XYZAL. Patients should be cautioned against engaging in hazardous occupations requiring complete mental alertness, and motor coordination such as operating machinery or driving a motor vehicle after ingestion of XYZAL. Concurrent use of XYZAL with alcohol or other central nervous system depressants should be avoided because additional reductions in alertness and additional impairment of central nervous system performance may occur.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
