<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="yaz" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions with the use of COCs are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *    Serious cardiovascular events and stroke [see Boxed Warning and Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *    Vascular events [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  )]  
 *    Liver disease [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  )]  
    Adverse reactions commonly reported by COC users are:
 

 *    Irregular uterine bleeding 
 *    Nausea 
 *    Breast tenderness 
 *    Headache 
   *    The most frequent adverse reactions (&gt;= 2%) in contraception and acne clinical trials were: headache/migraine (6.7%), menstrual irregularities (4.7%), nausea/vomiting (4.2%), breast pain/tenderness (4.0%) and mood changes (2.2%). (  6.1  ) 
 *    The most frequent adverse reactions (&gt;= 2%) in PMDD clinical trials were: menstrual irregularities (24.9%), nausea (15.8%), headache (13.0%), breast tenderness (10.5%), fatigue (4.2%), irritability (2.8%), decreased libido (2.8%), increased weight (2.5%), and affect lability (2.1%). (  6.1  ) 
      EXCERPT:     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Bayer HealthCare Pharmaceuticals Inc. at 1-888-842-2937 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Contraception and Acne Clinical Trials  

  The data provided reflect the experience with the use of Yaz in the adequate and well-controlled studies for contraception (N=1,056) and for moderate acne vulgaris (N=536).



 For contraception, a Phase 3, multicenter, multinational, open-label study was conducted to evaluate safety and efficacy up to one year in 1,027 women aged 17 - 36 who took at least one dose of Yaz. A second Phase 3 study was a single center, open-label, active-controlled study to evaluate the effect of 7 28-day cycles of Yaz on carbohydrate metabolism, lipids and hemostasis in 29 women aged 18-35. For acne, two multicenter, double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled studies, in 536 women aged 14-45 with moderate acne vulgaris who took at least one dose of Yaz, evaluated the safety and efficacy during up to 6 cycles.



 The adverse reactions seen across the 2 indications overlapped, and are reported using the frequencies from the pooled dataset. The most common adverse reactions (&gt;= 2% of users) were: headache/migraine (6.7%), menstrual irregularities (including vaginal hemorrhage [primarily spotting] and metrorrhagia (4.7%), nausea/vomiting (4.2%), breast pain/tenderness (4%) and mood changes (mood swings, depression, depressed mood and affect lability) (2.2%).



     PMDD Clinical Trials  

  Safety data from trials for the indication of PMDD are reported separately due to differences in study design and setting in the Contraception and Acne studies as compared to the PMDD clinical program.



 Two (one parallel and one crossover designed) multicenter, double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled trials for the secondary indication of treating the symptoms of PMDD evaluated safety and efficacy of Yaz during up to 3 cycles among 285 women aged 18-42, diagnosed with PMDD and who took at least one dose of Yaz.



 Common adverse reactions (&gt;= 2% of users) were: menstrual irregularities (including vaginal hemorrhage [primarily spotting] and metrorrhagia) (24.9%), nausea (15.8%), headache (13.0%), breast tenderness (10.5%), fatigue (4.2%), irritability (2.8%), decreased libido (2.8%), increased weight (2.5%), and affect lability (2.1%).



     Adverse Reactions (&gt;=1%) Leading to Study Discontinuation:  

    Contraception Clinical Trials  

  Of 1,056 women, 6.6% discontinued from the clinical trials due to an adverse reaction; the most frequent adverse reactions leading to discontinuation were headache/migraine (1.6%) and nausea/vomiting (1.0%).



     Acne Clinical Trials  

  Of 536 women, 5.4% discontinued from the clinical trials due to an adverse reaction; the most frequent adverse reaction leading to discontinuation was menstrual irregularities (including menometrorrhagia, menorrhagia, metrorrhagia and vaginal hemorrhage) (2.2%).



     PMDD Clinical Trials  

  Of 285 women, 11.6% discontinued from the clinical trials due to an adverse reaction; the most frequent adverse reactions leading to discontinuation were: nausea/vomiting (4.6%), menstrual irregularity (including vaginal hemorrhage, menorrhagia, menstrual disorder, menstruation irregular and metrorrhagia) (4.2%), fatigue (1.8%), breast tenderness (1.4%), depression (1.4%), headache (1.1%), and irritability (1.1%).



     Serious Adverse Reactions  

    Contraception Clinical Trials  : migraine and cervical dysplasia



   Acne Clinical Trials:  none reported in the clinical trials



   PMDD Clinical Trials:  cervical dysplasia



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of Yaz. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Adverse reactions are grouped into System Organ Classes, and ordered by frequency.



 Vascular disorders: Venous and arterial thromboembolic events (including pulmonary emboli, deep vein thrombosis, cerebral thrombosis, retinal thrombosis, myocardial infarction and stroke), hypertension (including hypertensive crisis)



 Hepatobiliary disorders: Gallbladder disease, liver function disturbances, liver tumors



 Immune system disorders: Hypersensitivity (including anaphylactic reaction)



 Metabolism and nutrition disorders: Hyperkalemia, hypertriglyceridemia, changes in glucose tolerance or effect on peripheral insulin resistance (including diabetes mellitus)



 Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders: Chloasma, angioedema, erythema nodosum, erythema multiforme



 Gastrointestinal disorders: Inflammatory bowel disease



 Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders: Systemic lupus erythematosus
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: CIGARETTE SMOKING AND SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR EVENTS

  WARNING: CIGARETTE SMOKING AND SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR EVENTS

    Cigarette smoking increases the risk of serious cardiovascular events from combination oral contraceptives (COC) use. This risk increases with age, particularly in women over 35 years of age, and with the number of cigarettes smoked. For this reason, COCs should not be used by women who are over 35 years of age and smoke   [see Contraindications (  4  )]  .  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: CIGARETTE SMOKING AND SERIOUS CARDIOVASCULAR EVENTS



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Women over 35 years old who smoke should not use Yaz (4). 
 *  Cigarette smoking increases the risk of serious cardiovascular events from combination oral contraceptive (COC) use. (4) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *     Vascular risks : Stop Yaz if a thrombotic event occurs. Stop at least 4 weeks before and through 2 weeks after major surgery. Start no earlier than 4 weeks after delivery, in women who are not breastfeeding. (5.1) COCs containing DRSP may be associated with a higher risk of venous thromboembolism (VTE) than COCs containing levonorgestrel or some other progestins. Before initiating Yaz in a new COC user or a woman who is switching from a contraceptive that does not contain DRSP, consider the risks and benefits of a DRSP-containing COC in light of her risk of a VTE. (  5.1  ) 
 *     Hyperkalemia : DRSP has anti-mineralocorticoid activity. Do not use in patients predisposed to hyperkalemia. Check serum potassium concentration during the first treatment cycle in women on long-term treatment with medications that may increase serum potassium concentration. (  5.2  ,  7.1  ,  7.2  ) 
 *     Liver disease : Discontinue Yaz if jaundice occurs. (  5.4  ) 
 *     High blood pressure : Do not prescribe Yaz for women with uncontrolled hypertension or hypertension with vascular disease. (  5.5  ) 
 *     Carbohydrate and lipid metabolic effects : Monitor prediabetic and diabetic women taking Yaz. Consider an alternate contraceptive method for women with uncontrolled dyslipidemia. (  5.7  ) 
 *     Headache : Evaluate significant change in headaches and discontinue Yaz if indicated. (  5.8  ) 
 *     Uterine bleeding : Evaluate irregular bleeding or amenorrhea. (  5.9  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Thromboembolic Disorders and Other Vascular Problems



  Stop Yaz if an arterial or venous thrombotic (VTE) event occurs.



 Based on presently available information on DRSP-containing COCs with 0.03 mg ethinyl estradiol (that is, Yasmin), DRSP-containing COCs may be associated with a higher risk of venous thromboembolism (VTE) than COCs containing the progestin levonorgestrel or some other progestins. Epidemiologic studies that compared the risk of VTE reported that the risk ranged from no increase to a three-fold increase. Before initiating use of Yaz in a new COC user or a woman who is switching from a contraceptive that does not contain DRSP, consider the risks and benefits of a DRSP-containing COC in light of her risk of a VTE. Known risk factors for VTE include smoking, obesity, and family history of VTE, in addition to other factors that contraindicate use of COCs [see Contraindications (  4  )]  .



 A number of studies have compared the risk of VTE for users of Yasmin (which contains 0.03 mg of EE and 3 mg of DRSP) to the risk for users of other COCs, including COCs containing levonorgestrel. Those that were required or sponsored by regulatory agencies are summarized in Table 1.



 Table 1: Estimates (Hazard Ratios) of Venous Thromboembolism Risk in Current Users of Yasmin Compared to Users of Oral Contraceptives that Contain Other Progestins 
  Epidemiologic Study(Author, Year of Publication) Population Studied    Comparator Product (all are low-dose COCs; with &lt;= 0.04 mg of EE)    Hazard Ratio (HR)(95% CI)       
  i3 Ingenix (Seeger 2007) Initiators, including new users"New users" - no use of combination hormonal contraception for at least the prior 6 months    All COCs available in the USduring the conduct of the studyIncludes low-dose COCs containing the following progestins: norgestimate, norethindrone, levonorgestrel, desogestrel, norgestrel, medroxyprogesterone, or ethynodiol diacetate    HR: 0.9(0.5-1.6)                
  EURAS(Dinger 2007)Initiators, including new users    All COCs available in Europeduring the conduct of the studyIncludes low-dose COCs containing the following progestins: levonorgestrel, desogestrel, dienogest, chlormadinone acetate, gestodene, cyproterone acetate, norgestimate, or norethindrone    HR: 0.9 (0.6-1.4)               
                                  Levonorgestrel/EE                HR: 1.0(0.6-1.8)                
  FDA-funded study" (2011)                                                                         
  New users                       Other COCs available during the course of the studyIncludes low-dose COCs containing the following progestins: norgestimate, norethindrone, or levonorgestrel    HR: 1.8(1.3-2.4)                
                                  Levonorgestrel/0.03 mg EE        HR: 1.6(1.1-2.2)                
  All users(i.e., initiation and continuing use of study combination hormonal contraception)    Other COCs available during the course of the study    HR: 1.7(1.4-2.1)                
                                  Levonorgestrel/0.03 mg EE        HR: 1.5(1.2-1.8)                
         In addition to these "regulatory studies," other studies of various designs have been conducted. Overall, there are two prospective cohort studies (see Table 1): the US post-approval safety study Ingenix [Seeger 2007], the European post-approval safety study EURAS (European Active Surveillance Study) [Dinger 2007]. An extension of the EURAS study, the Long-Term Active Surveillance Study (LASS), did not enroll additional subjects, but continued to assess VTE risk. There are three retrospective cohort studies: one study in the US funded by the FDA (see Table 1), and two from Denmark [Lidegaard 2009, Lidegaard 2011]. There are two case-control studies: the Dutch MEGA study analysis [van Hylckama Vlieg 2009] and the German case-control study [Dinger 2010]. There are two nested case-control studies that evaluated the risk of non-fatal idiopathic VTE: the PharMetrics study [Jick 2011] and the GPRD study [Parkin 2011]. The results of all of these studies are presented in Figure 1.
 

 Figure 1: VTE Risk with Yasmin Relative to LNG-Containing COCs (adjusted risk#)



 Risk ratios displayed on logarithmic scale; risk ratio &lt; 1 indicates a lower risk of VTE for DRSP, &gt; 1 indicates an increased risk of VTE for DRSP.



 *Comparator "Other COCs", including LNG- containing COCs



  LASS is an extension of the EURAS study



 #Some adjustment factors are indicated by superscript letters: a) Current heavy smoking, b) hypertension, c) obesity, d) family history, e) age, f) BMI, g) duration of use, h) VTE history, i) period of inclusion, j) calendar year, k) education, l) length of use, m) parity, n) chronic disease, o) concomitant medication, p) smoking, q) duration of exposure, r) site



 (References: Ingenix [Seeger 2007]  1  , EURAS (European Active Surveillance Study) [Dinger 2007]  2  , LASS (Long-Term Active Surveillance Study) [Dinger, unpublished document on file], FDA-funded study [Sidney 2011]  3  , Danish [Lidegaard 2009]  4  , Danish re-analysis [ Lidegaard 2011]  5  , MEGA study [van Hylckama Vlieg 2009]  6  , German Case-Control study [Dinger 2010]  7  , PharMetrics [Jick 2011]  8  , GPRD study [Parkin 2011]  9  )



 Although the absolute VTE rates are increased for users of hormonal contraceptives compared to non-users, the rates during pregnancy are even greater, especially during the post-partum period (see Figure 2). The risk of VTE in women using COCs has been estimated to be 3 to 9 per 10,000 woman-years. The risk of VTE is highest during the first year of use. Data from a large, prospective cohort safety study of various COCs suggest that this increased risk, as compared to that in non-COC users, is greatest during the first 6 months of COC use. Data from this safety study indicate that the greatest risk of VTE is present after initially starting a COC or restarting (following a 4 week or greater pill-free interval) the same or a different COC.



 The risk of thromboembolic disease due to oral contraceptives gradually disappears after COC use is discontinued.



 Figure 2 shows the risk of developing a VTE for women who are not pregnant and do not use oral contraceptives, for women who use oral contraceptives, for pregnant women, and for women in the postpartum period. To put the risk of developing a VTE into perspective: If 10,000 women who are not pregnant and do not use oral contraceptives are followed for one year, between 1 and 5 of these women will develop a VTE.



 Figure 2: Likelihood of Developing a VTE



 If feasible, stop Yaz at least 4 weeks before and through 2 weeks after major surgery or other surgeries known to have an elevated risk of thromboembolism.



 Start Yaz no earlier than 4 weeks after delivery, in women who are not breastfeeding. The risk of postpartum thromboembolism decreases after the third postpartum week, whereas the risk of ovulation increases after the third postpartum week.



 Use of COCs also increases the risk of arterial thromboses such as strokes and myocardial infarctions, especially in women with other risk factors for these events.



 COCs have been shown to increase both the relative and attributable risks of cerebrovascular events (thrombotic and hemorrhagic strokes), although, in general, the risk is greatest among older (&gt;35 years of age), hypertensive women who also smoke. COCs also increase the risk for stroke in women with other underlying risk factors.



 Oral contraceptives must be used with caution in women with cardiovascular disease risk factors.



 Stop Yaz if there is unexplained loss of vision, proptosis, diplopia, papilledema, or retinal vascular lesions. Evaluate for retinal vein thrombosis immediately. [See Adverse Reactions (  6  ).]  



  fig 1  Figure 2 Likelihood of Developing a VTE    5.2 Hyperkalemia



  Yaz contains 3 mg of the progestin DRSP which has anti-mineralocorticoid activity, including the potential for hyperkalemia in high-risk patients, comparable to a 25 mg dose of spironolactone. Yaz is contraindicated in patients with conditions that predispose to hyperkalemia (that is, renal impairment, hepatic impairment, and adrenal insufficiency). Women receiving daily, long-term treatment for chronic conditions or diseases with medications that may increase serum potassium concentration should have their serum potassium concentration checked during the first treatment cycle. Medications that may increase serum potassium concentration include ACE inhibitors, angiotensin-II receptor antagonists, potassium-sparing diuretics, potassium supplementation, heparin, aldosterone antagonists, and NSAIDS. Consider monitoring serum potassium concentration in high-risk patients who take a strong CYP3A4 inhibitor long-term and concomitantly. Strong CYP3A4 inhibitors include azole antifungals (e.g. ketoconazole, itraconazole, voriconazole), HIV/HCV protease inhibitors (e.g., indinavir, boceprevir), and clarithromycin [see Clinical Pharmacology (       12.3   )]     .  



    5.3 Carcinoma of the Breasts and Reproductive Organs



  Women who currently have or have had breast cancer should not use Yaz because breast cancer is a hormonally-sensitive tumor.



 There is substantial evidence that COCs do not increase the incidence of breast cancer. Although some past studies have suggested that COCs might increase the incidence of breast cancer, more recent studies have not confirmed such findings.



 Some studies suggest that COCs are associated with an increase in the risk of cervical cancer or intraepithelial neoplasia. However, there is controversy about the extent to which these findings may be due to differences in sexual behavior and other factors.



    5.4 Liver Disease



  Discontinue Yaz if jaundice develops. Steroid hormones may be poorly metabolized in patients with impaired liver function. Acute or chronic disturbances of liver function may necessitate the discontinuation of COC use until markers of liver function return to normal and COC causation has been excluded.



 Hepatic adenomas are associated with COC use. An estimate of the attributable risk is 3.3 cases/100,000 COC users. Rupture of hepatic adenomas may cause death through intra-abdominal hemorrhage.



 Studies have shown an increased risk of developing hepatocellular carcinoma in long-term (&gt;8 years) COC users. However, the attributable risk of liver cancers in COC users is less than one case per million users.



 Oral contraceptive-related cholestasis may occur in women with a history of pregnancy-related cholestasis. Women with a history of COC-related cholestasis may have the condition recur with subsequent COC use.



    5.5 High Blood Pressure



  For women with well-controlled hypertension, monitor blood pressure and stop Yaz if blood pressure rises significantly. Women with uncontrolled hypertension or hypertension with vascular disease should not use COCs.



 An increase in blood pressure has been reported in women taking COCs, and this increase is more likely in older women and with extended duration of use. The incidence of hypertension increases with increasing concentration of progestin.



    5.6 Gallbladder Disease



  Studies suggest a small increased relative risk of developing gallbladder disease among COC users.



    5.7 Carbohydrate and Lipid Metabolic Effects



  Carefully monitor prediabetic and diabetic women who are taking Yaz. COCs may decrease glucose intolerance in a dose-related fashion.



 Consider alternative contraception for women with uncontrolled dyslipidemias. A small proportion of women will have adverse lipid changes while on COC's.



 Women with hypertriglyceridemia, or a family history thereof, may be at an increased risk of pancreatitis when using COCs.



    5.8 Headache



  If a woman taking Yaz develops new headaches that are recurrent, persistent, or severe, evaluate the cause and discontinue Yaz if indicated.



 An increase in frequency or severity of migraine during COC use (which may be prodromal of a cerebrovascular event) may be a reason for immediate discontinuation of the COC.



    5.9 Bleeding Irregularities



  Unscheduled (breakthrough or intracyclic) bleeding and spotting sometimes occur in patients on COCs, especially during the first three months of use. If bleeding persists or occurs after previously regular cycles, check for causes such as pregnancy or malignancy. If pathology and pregnancy are excluded, bleeding irregularities may resolve over time or with a change to a different COC.



 Based on patient diaries from two contraceptive clinical trials of Yaz, 8 to 25% of women experienced unscheduled bleeding per 28-day cycle. A total of 12 subjects out of 1,056 (1.1%) discontinued due to menstrual disorders including intermenstrual bleeding, menorrhagia, and metrorrhagia.



 Women who use Yaz may experience absence of withdrawal bleeding, even if they are not pregnant. Based on subject diaries from contraception trials for up to 13 cycles, 6 to 10% of women experienced cycles with no withdrawal bleeding. Some women may encounter post-pill amenorrhea or oligomenorrhea, especially when such a condition was pre-existent.



 If withdrawal bleeding does not occur, consider the possibility of pregnancy. If the patient has not adhered to the prescribed dosing schedule (missed one or more active tablets or started taking them on a day later than she should have), consider the possibility of pregnancy at the time of the first missed period and take appropriate diagnostic measures. If the patient has adhered to the prescribed regimen and misses two consecutive periods, rule out pregnancy.



    5.10 COC Use Before or During Early Pregnancy



  Extensive epidemiological studies have revealed no increased risk of birth defects in women who have used oral contraceptives prior to pregnancy. Studies also do not suggest a teratogenic effect, particularly in so far as cardiac anomalies and limb-reduction defects are concerned, when taken inadvertently during early pregnancy.



 The administration of oral contraceptives to induce withdrawal bleeding should not be used as a test for pregnancy [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.1  )]  .



    5.11 Depression



  Women with a history of depression should be carefully observed and Yaz discontinued if depression recurs to a serious degree.



    5.12 Interference with Laboratory Tests



  The use of COCs may change the results of some laboratory tests, such as coagulation factors, lipids, glucose tolerance, and binding proteins. Women on thyroid hormone replacement therapy may need increased doses of thyroid hormone because serum concentrations of thyroid-binding globulin increase with use of COCs [see Drug Interactions (  7.2  )]  .



 DRSP causes an increase in plasma renin activity and plasma aldosterone induced by its mild anti-mineralocorticoid activity.



    5.13 Monitoring



  A woman who is taking COCs should have a yearly visit with her healthcare provider for a blood pressure check and for other indicated healthcare.



    5.14 Other Conditions



  In women with hereditary angioedema, exogenous estrogens may induce or exacerbate symptoms of angioedema. Chloasma may occasionally occur, especially in women with a history of chloasma gravidarum. Women with a tendency to chloasma should avoid exposure to the sun or ultraviolet radiation while taking COCs.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
