<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="yondelis" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in more detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *  Anaphylaxis [see  Contraindications (4)  ]  
 *  Neutropenic Sepsis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Rhabdomyolysis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Hepatotoxicity [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Cardiomyopathy [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Extravasation Resulting in Tissue Necrosis [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   The most common (&gt;=20%) adverse reactions are nausea, fatigue, vomiting, constipation, decreased appetite, diarrhea, peripheral edema, dyspnea, headache. The most common (&gt;=5%) grades 3-4 laboratory abnormalities are: neutropenia, increased ALT, thrombocytopenia, anemia, increased AST, and increased creatine phosphokinase. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Janssen Biotech, Inc. at 1-800-526-7736 (1-800-JANSSEN) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Adverse Reactions in Clinical Trials

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The data described below reflect exposure to YONDELIS in 755 patients with soft tissue sarcoma including 197 (26%) patients exposed to YONDELIS for greater than or equal to 6 months and 57 (8%) patients exposed to YONDELIS for greater than or equal to 1 year. The safety of YONDELIS was evaluated in six open-label, single-arm trials, in which 377 patients received YONDELIS and one open-label, randomized, active-controlled clinical trial in which 378 patients received YONDELIS (Trial 1). All patients received YONDELIS at the recommended dosing regimen of 1.5 mg/m  2  administered as an intravenous infusion over 24 hours once every 3 weeks (q3wk, 24-h). The median age was 54 years (range: 18 to 81 years), 63% were female, and all patients had metastatic soft tissue sarcoma.



 Tables 2 and 3 present selected adverse reactions and laboratory abnormalities, respectively, observed in Trial 1, an open-label, randomized (2:1), active-controlled trial in which 550 patients with previously treated leiomyosarcoma or liposarcoma (dedifferentiated, myxoid round cell, or pleomorphic) received YONDELIS 1.5 mg/m  2  intravenous infusion over 24 hours once every 3 weeks (n=378) or dacarbazine 1000 mg/m  2  intravenous infusion over 20 to 120 minutes once every 3 weeks (n=172)  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  . All patients treated with YONDELIS were required to receive dexamethasone 20 mg intravenous injection 30 minutes prior to start of the YONDELIS infusion.



 In Trial 1, patients had been previously treated with an anthracycline- and ifosfamide-containing regimen or with an anthracycline-containing regimen and one additional cytotoxic chemotherapy regimen. The trial excluded patients with known central nervous system metastasis, elevated serum bilirubin or significant chronic liver disease, such as cirrhosis or active hepatitis, and history of myocardial infarction within 6 months, history of New York Heart Association Class II to IV heart failure, or abnormal left ventricular ejection fraction at baseline. The median age of patients in Trial 1 was 57 years (range: 17 to 81 years), with 69% female, 77% White, 12% Black or African American, 4% Asian, and &lt;1% American Indian or Alaska Native. The median duration of exposure to trabectedin was 13 weeks (range: 1 to 127 weeks) with 30% of patients exposed to YONDELIS for greater than 6 months and 7% of patients exposed to YONDELIS for greater than 1 year.



 In Trial 1, adverse reactions resulting in permanent discontinuation of YONDELIS occurred in 26% (98/378) of patients; the most common were increased liver tests (defined as ALT, AST, alkaline phosphatase, bilirubin) (5.6%), thrombocytopenia (3.4%), fatigue (1.6%), increased creatine phosphokinase (1.1%), and decreased ejection fraction (1.1%). Adverse reactions that led to dose reductions occurred in 42% (158/378) of patients treated with YONDELIS; the most common were increased liver tests (24%), neutropenia (including febrile neutropenia) (8%), thrombocytopenia (4.2%), fatigue (3.7%), increased creatine phosphokinase (2.4%), nausea (1.1%), and vomiting (1.1%). Adverse reactions led to dose interruptions in 52% (198/378) of patients treated with YONDELIS; the most common were neutropenia (31%), thrombocytopenia (15%), increased liver tests (6%), fatigue (2.9%), anemia (2.6%), increased creatinine (1.1%), and nausea (1.1%).



 The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=20%) were nausea, fatigue, vomiting, constipation, decreased appetite, diarrhea, peripheral edema, dyspnea, and headache. The most common laboratory abnormalities (&gt;=20%) were increases in AST or ALT, increased alkaline phosphatase, hypoalbuminemia, increased creatinine, increased creatine phosphokinase, anemia, neutropenia, and thrombocytopenia.



 Table 2: Selected Adverse ReactionsLimited to adverse reactions at a rate of &gt;=10% in the trabectedin arm and at a rate higher in the trabectedin arm compared with dacarbazine arm by &gt;=5% in overall incidence or by &gt;=2% for Grade 3-4 adverse reactions. occurring in &gt;=10% of Patients receiving YONDELIS and at a higher incidence than in the Control Arm - Trial 1 
                             YONDELIS(N=378)    Dacarbazine(N=172)    
 System Organ Class  Adverse Reaction     All Grades(%)        Grades 3-4(%)        All Grades(%)        Grades 3-4(%)      
  
   Gastrointestinal disorders     
     Nausea                        75                    7                   50                   1.7           
     Vomiting                      46                    6                   22                   1.2           
     Constipation                  37                   0.8                  31                   0.6           
     Diarrhea                      35                   1.6                  23                    0            
   General disorders and administration site conditions     
     Fatigue                       69                    8                   52                   1.7           
     Peripheral edema              28                   0.8                  13                   0.6           
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders     
     Decreased appetite            37                   1.9                  21                   0.6           
   Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders     
     Dyspnea                       25                   4.2                  20                   1.2           
   Nervous system disorders     
     Headache                      25                   0.3                  19                    0            
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders     
     Arthralgia                    15                    0                    8                   1.2           
     Myalgia                       12                    0                    6                    0            
   Psychiatric disorders     
     Insomnia                      15                   0.3                   9                    0            
           Other clinically important adverse reactions observed in &lt;10% of patients (N=755) with soft tissue sarcoma receiving YONDELIS were:
 

   Nervous system disorders  : peripheral neuropathy, paresthesia, hypoesthesia.



   Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders  : pulmonary embolism.



 Table 3: Incidence of Selected Treatment-Emergent Laboratory AbnormalitiesTreatment-emergent laboratory abnormalities including those higher in the trabectedin arm compared with the dacarbazine arm by &gt;=5% (all Grades) or by &gt;=2% (Grade 3-4). Incidence based on number of patients who had both baseline and at least one on-study laboratory measurement - Trial 1 
 Laboratory Abnormalities           YONDELIS          Dacarbazine       
 All Grades(%)                   Grades 3-4(%)       All Grades(%)       Grades 3-4(%)      
  
 YONDELIS group (range: 373 to 377 patients) and dacarbazine group (range: 166 to 168 patients).   
  
   Chemistry                                                                                                    
     Increased ALT                     90                  31                  33                 0.6           
     Increased AST                     84                  17                  32                 1.2           
     Increased alkaline phosphatase          70                 1.6                  60                 0.6           
     Hypoalbuminemia                   63                 3.7                  51                 3.0           
     Increased creatinine              46                 4.2                  29                 1.2           
     Increased creatine phosphokinase          33                 6.4                  9                  0.6           
     Hyperbilirubinemia                13                 1.9                  5                  0.6           
   Hematology                                                                                                   
     Anemia                            96                  19                  79                  12           
     Neutropenia                       66                  43                  47                  26           
     Thrombocytopenia                  59                  21                  57                  20           
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Neutropenic sepsis: Severe, and fatal, neutropenic sepsis may occur. Monitor neutrophil count during treatment. Withhold YONDELIS for Grade 2 or greater neutropenia (  5.1  ) 
 *  Rhabdomyolysis: Rhabdomyolysis may occur; withhold YONDELIS for severe or life-threatening increases in creatine phosphokinase level (  5.2  ) 
 *  Hepatotoxicity: Hepatotoxicity may occur. Monitor and delay and/or reduce dose if needed (  5.3  ) 
 *  Cardiomyopathy: Severe and fatal cardiomyopathy can occur. Withhold YONDELIS in patients with left ventricular dysfunction (  5.4  ) 
 *  Embryofetal toxicity: Can cause fetal harm. Advise of potential risk to a fetus and use effective contraception (  5.6  ,  8.1  ,  8.3  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Neutropenic Sepsis



  Neutropenic sepsis, including fatal cases, can occur with YONDELIS. In Trial 1, the incidence of Grade 3 or 4 neutropenia, based on laboratory values, in patients receiving YONDELIS was 43% (161/378). The median time to the first occurrence of Grade 3 or 4 neutropenia was 16 days (range: 8 days to 9.7 months); the median time to complete resolution of neutropenia was 13 days (range: 3 days to 2.3 months). Febrile neutropenia (fever &gt;=38.5 degrees C with Grade 3 or 4 neutropenia) occurred in 18 patients (5%) treated with YONDELIS. Ten patients (2.6%) experienced neutropenic sepsis, 5 of whom had febrile neutropenia, which was fatal in 4 patients (1.1%).



 Assess neutrophil count prior to administration of each dose of YONDELIS and periodically throughout the treatment cycle. Withhold YONDELIS for neutrophil counts of less than 1500 cells/microliter on the day of dosing. Permanently reduce the dose of YONDELIS for life-threatening or prolonged, severe neutropenia in the preceding cycle [see  Dosage and Administration (2.3)  ]  .



    5.2 Rhabdomyolysis



  YONDELIS can cause rhabdomyolysis and musculoskeletal toxicity. In Trial 1, rhabdomyolysis leading to death occurred in 3 (0.8%) of the 378 patients receiving YONDELIS. Elevations in creatine phosphokinase (CPK) occurred in 122 (32%) of the 378 patients receiving YONDELIS, including Grade 3 or 4 CPK elevation in 24 patients (6%), compared to 15 (9%) of the 172 patients receiving dacarbazine with any CPK elevation, including 1 patient (0.6%) with Grade 3 CPK elevation. Among the 24 patients receiving YONDELIS with Grade 3 or 4 CPK elevation, renal failure occurred in 11 patients (2.9%); rhabdomyolysis with the complication of renal failure occurred in 4 of these 11 patients (1.1%). The median time to first occurrence of Grade 3 or 4 CPK elevations was 2 months (range: 1 to 11.5 months). The median time to complete resolution was 14 days (range: 5 days to 1 month).



 Assess CPK levels prior to each administration of YONDELIS. Withhold YONDELIS for serum CPK levels more than 2.5 times the upper limit of normal. Permanently discontinue YONDELIS for rhabdomyolysis [see  Dosage and Administration (2.3)  ]  .



    5.3 Hepatotoxicity



  Hepatotoxicity, including hepatic failure, can occur with YONDELIS. Patients with serum bilirubin levels above the upper limit of normal or AST or ALT levels &gt;2.5 * ULN were not enrolled in Trial 1. In Trial 1, the incidence of Grade 3-4 elevated liver function tests (defined as elevations in ALT, AST, total bilirubin, or alkaline phosphatase) was 35% (134/378) in patients receiving YONDELIS. The median time to development of Grade 3-4 elevation in ALT or AST was 29 days (range: 3 days to 11.5 months). Of the 134 patients with Grade 3-4 elevations in LFTs, 114 (85%) experienced complete resolution with the median time to complete resolution of 13 days (range: 4 days to 4.4 months).



 In Trial 1, the incidence of drug-induced liver injury (defined as concurrent elevation in ALT or AST of more than three times the upper limit of normal, alkaline phosphatase less than two times the upper limit of normal, and total bilirubin at least two times the upper limit of normal) was 1.3% (5/378) in patients receiving YONDELIS. ALT or AST elevation greater than eight times the ULN occurred in 18% (67/378) of patients receiving YONDELIS.



 Assess LFTs prior to each administration of YONDELIS. Manage elevated LFTs with treatment interruption, dose reduction, or permanent discontinuation based on severity and duration of LFT abnormality [see  Dosage and Administration (2.3)  ]  .



    5.4 Cardiomyopathy



  Cardiomyopathy including cardiac failure, congestive heart failure, ejection fraction decreased, diastolic dysfunction, or right ventricular dysfunction can occur with YONDELIS. In Trial 1, patients with a history of New York Heart Association Class II to IV heart failure or abnormal left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) at baseline were ineligible. In Trial 1, cardiomyopathy occurred in 23 patients (6%) receiving YONDELIS and in four patients (2.3%) receiving dacarbazine. Grade 3 or 4 cardiomyopathy occurred in 15 patients (4%) receiving YONDELIS and 2 patients (1.2%) receiving dacarbazine; cardiomyopathy leading to death occurred in 1 patient (0.3%) receiving YONDELIS and in none of the patients receiving dacarbazine. The median time to development of Grade 3 or 4 cardiomyopathy in patients receiving YONDELIS was 5.3 months (range: 26 days to 15.3 months).



 Assess left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) by echocardiogram or multigated acquisition (MUGA) scan before initiation of YONDELIS and at 2- to 3-month intervals thereafter until YONDELIS is discontinued. Withhold YONDELIS for LVEF below lower limit of normal. Permanently discontinue YONDELIS for symptomatic cardiomyopathy or persistent left ventricular dysfunction that does not recover to lower limit of normal within 3 weeks [see  Dosage and Administration (2.3)  ]  .



    5.5 Extravasation Resulting in Tissue Necrosis



  Extravasation of YONDELIS, resulting in tissue necrosis requiring debridement, can occur. Evidence of tissue necrosis can occur more than 1 week after the extravasation. There is no specific antidote for extravasation of YONDELIS. Administer YONDELIS through a central venous line [see  Dosage and Administration (2.5)  ]  .



    5.6 Embryofetal Toxicity



  Based on its mechanism of action, YONDELIS can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. Advise females of reproductive potential to use effective contraception during therapy and for at least 2 months after the last dose of YONDELIS. Advise males with female partners of reproductive potential to use effective contraception during therapy and for at least 5 months after the last dose of YONDELIS [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1  ,  8.3)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
