<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="yosprala" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6          ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions in adults (&gt;= 2%) are: gastritis, nausea, diarrhea, gastric polyps, and non-cardiac chest pain. (  6.1  ) 



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Aralez Pharmaceuticals at 1-866-207-6592 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

    6.1          Clinical Studies Experience  

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 YOSPRALA 325 mg/40 mg was studied primarily in two randomized, double-blind controlled clinical trials (n=524) of 6 months duration. Table 1 lists adverse reactions that occurred in  &gt;  2% of patients in the YOSPRALA arm and were more common than in the control arm, consisting of 325 mg of enteric coated (EC)-aspirin.



 Table 1: Most Common Adverse Reactions in Study 1 and Study 2* 
   Preferred Term      YOSPRALA        325 mg/40 mg    once daily    (n=521)    %      EC-Aspirin    325 mg once    daily    (n=524)    %     
 Gastritis        18               16                
 Nausea           3                2                 
 Diarrhea         3                2                 
 Gastric polyps   2                1                 
 Non-cardiac chest pain  2                1                 
         *Adverse reactions occurring in &gt;=2% of YOSPRALA-treated patients and more common than in the control arm
 

 In Study 1 and Study 2 combined, 7% of patients taking YOSPRALA discontinued due to adverse reactions compared to 11% of patients taking EC-aspirin alone. The most common reasons for discontinuations due to adverse reactions in the YOSPRALA treatment group were upper abdominal pain (&lt;1%, n=2), diarrhea (&lt;1%, n=2) and dyspepsia (&lt;1%, n=2).



   Less Common Adverse Reactions  



 In YOSPRALA-treated patients in the clinical trials there were 2 patients with upper GI bleeding (gastric or duodenal) and 2 patients with lower GI bleeding (hematochezia and large intestinal hemorrhage) and one additional patient experienced obstruction in the small bowel.



 See also the full prescribing information of aspirin and omeprazole products for additional adverse reactions.



     6.2          Post-    M    arketing    E    xperience  

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of aspirin and omeprazole separately. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Aspirin    Body as a Whole    :      Fever, hypothermia, thirst  Cardiovascular  : Dysrhythmias, hypotension, tachycardia  Central Nervous System:  Agitation, cerebral edema, coma, confusion, dizziness, headache, subdural or intracranial hemorrhage, lethargy, seizures  Fluid and Electrolyte  : Dehydration, hyperkalemia, metabolic acidosis, respiratory alkalosisG  astrointestinal  : Dyspepsia, GI bleeding, ulceration and perforation, nausea, vomiting, transient elevations of hepatic enzymes, hepatitis, Reye's Syndrome   [see          Contraindications (4)      ]  , pancreatitis  Hematologic  : Prolongation of the prothrombin time, disseminated intravascular coagulation, coagulopathy, thrombocytopenia  Hypersensitivity  : Acute anaphylaxis, angioedema, asthma, bronchospasm, laryngeal edema, urticaria  Musculoskeletal  : Rhabdomyolysis  Metabolism  : Hypoglycemia (in pediatrics), hyperglycemia  Reproductive  : Prolonged pregnancy and labor, stillbirths, lower birth weight infants, antepartum and postpartum bleeding  Respiratory  : Hyperpnea, pulmonary edema, tachypnea  Special Senses  : Hearing loss, tinnitus. Patients with high frequency hearing loss may have difficulty perceiving tinnitus.  In these patients, tinnitus cannot be used as a clinical indicator of salicylism.  Urogenital  : Interstitial nephritis, papillary necrosis, proteinuria, renal impairment and failure



   Omeprazole    Body As a Whole:  Hypersensitivity reactions including anaphylaxis, anaphylactic shock, angioedema, bronchospasm   [see      Contraindications (4)      ]  , interstitial nephritis, urticaria (see also  Skin  below), systemic lupus erythematosus, fever, pain, fatigue, malaise  Cardiovascular:  Chest pain or angina, tachycardia, bradycardia, palpitations, elevated blood pressure, peripheral edema  Endocrine:  Gynecomastia  Gastrointestinal:  Pancreatitis (some fatal), anorexia, irritable colon, fecal discoloration, esophageal candidiasis, mucosal atrophy of the tongue, stomatitis, abdominal swelling, dry mouth, microscopic colitisBenign gastric fundic gland polyps have been noted rarely and appear to be reversible when treatment is discontinued.Gastroduodenal carcinoids have been reported in patients with Zollinger-Ellison syndrome on long-term treatment with omeprazole. This finding is believed to be a manifestation of the underlying condition, which is known to be associated with such tumors.  Hematologic:  Agranulocytosis (some fatal), hemolytic anemia, pancytopenia, neutropenia, anemia, thrombocytopenia, leukopenia, leukocytosis  Hepatic:  Liver disease including hepatic failure (some fatal), liver necrosis (some fatal), hepatic encephalopathy hepatocellular disease, cholestatic disease, mixed hepatitis, jaundice, and elevations of liver function tests [ALT, AST, GGT, alkaline phosphatase, and bilirubin]  Infections and Infestations: Clostridium difficile    -  associated diarrhea   [see      Warnings and Precautions (5.9)      ]    Metabolism and Nutritional disorders  : Hypoglycemia, hypomagnesemia, with or without hypocalcemia and/or hypokalemia, hyponatremia, weight gain  Musculoskeletal  : Muscle weakness, myalgia, muscle cramps, joint pain, leg pain, bone fracture  Nervous System/Psychiatric  : Psychiatric and sleep disturbances including depression, agitation, aggression, hallucinations, confusion, insomnia, nervousness, apathy, somnolence, anxiety, and dream abnormalities; tremors, paresthesia; vertigo  Respiratory:  Epistaxis, pharyngeal pain  Skin:  Severe generalized skin reactions including toxic epidermal necrolysis (some fatal), Stevens-Johnson syndrome, cutaneous lupus erythematosus and erythema multiforme; photosensitivity; urticaria; rash; skin inflammation; pruritus; petechiae; purpura; alopecia; dry skin; hyperhidrosis  Special Senses:  Tinnitus, taste perversion  Ocular:  Optic atrophy, anterior ischemic optic neuropathy, optic neuritis, dry eye syndrome, ocular irritation, blurred vision, double vision  Urogenital:  Interstitial nephritis, hematuria, proteinuria, elevated serum creatinine, microscopic pyuria, urinary tract infection, glycosuria, urinary frequency, testicular pain
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">     5   WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *   Coagulation Abnormalities: Risk of increased bleeding time with aspirin, especially in patients with inherited (hemophilia) or acquired (liver disease or vitamin K deficiency) bleeding disorders. Monitor patients for signs of increased bleeding. (  5.1  ) 
 *   GI Adverse Reactions (including ulceration and bleeding): Monitor for signs and symptoms and discontinue treatment if bleeding occurs. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Bleeding Risk with Use of Alcohol: Avoid heavy alcohol use (three or more drinks every day). (  5.3  ) 
 *   Reduction in Antiplatelet Activity with Clopidogrel due to Interference with CYP2C19 Metabolism: Consider other antiplatelet therapy. (  5.4  ,  7  ) 
 *   Reduction in Efficacy of Ticagrelor:  Avoid use with the 325/40 strength of YOSPRALA. (  5.5  ,  7  ) 
 *   Renal Failure: Avoid YOSPRALA in patients with severe renal failure. (  5.6  ,  8.6  ) 
 *   Gastric Malignancy:  In adults, response to gastric symptoms does not preclude the presence of gastric malignancy; Consider additional follow-up and diagnostic testing. (  5.7  ) 
 *   Acute Interstitial Nephritis:  Observed in patients taking PPIs. (  5.8  ) 
 *   Clostridium difficile  -  Associated Diarrhea:  PPI therapy may be associated with increased risk; use lowest dose and shortest duration of treatment. (  5.9  ) 
 *   Bone Fracture: Long-term and multiple daily dose PPI therapy may be associated with an increased risk for osteoporosis-related fractures of the hip, wrist or spine; use lowest dose and shortest duration of treatment. (  5.10  ) 
 *   Cutaneous and Systemic Lupus Erythematosus:  Mostly cutaneous; new onset or exacerbation of existing disease; discontinue YOSPRALA and refer to specialist for evaluation. (  5.11  ) 
 *   Hepatic Impairment: Avoid YOSPRALA in patients with all degrees of hepatic impairment. (  5.12  ,  8.7  ) 
 *   Cyanocobalamin (Vitamin B-12) Deficiency:  Daily long-term use (e.g., longer than 3 years) of PPI may lead to malabsorption or deficiency. (  5.13  ) 
 *   Hypomagnesemia: Reported rarely with prolonged treatment with PPIs; consider monitoring magnesium levels. (  5.14  ) 
 *   Reduced Effect of Omeprazole with  St. John's Wort or  Rifampin : Avoid concomitant use. (  5.15  ,  7  ) 
 *   Interactions with Diagnostic Investigations for Neuroendocrine Tumors : Increased Chromogranin A (CgA) levels may interfere with diagnostic investigations for neuroendocrine tumors; temporarily stop YOSPRALA at least 14 days before assessing CgA levels (  5.16  ,  7  ) 
 *   Bone Marrow Toxicity with Methotrexate, especially in the elderly or renally impaired: Use with PPIs may elevate and/or prolong serum levels of methotrexate and/or its metabolite, possibly leading to toxicity. With high dose methotrexate, consider a temporary withdrawal of YOSPRALA. (  5.17  ,  7  ) 
 *   P  remature closure of the ductus arteriosus : Avoid use in pregnant women starting at 30 weeks gestation. (  5.18  ,  8.1  ) 
    
 

    5.   1         Coagulation Abnormalities  



  Even low doses of aspirin can inhibit platelet function leading to an increase in bleeding time. This can adversely affect patients with inherited (hemophilia) or acquired (liver disease or vitamin K deficiency) bleeding disorders. Monitor patients for signs of increased bleeding.



     5.   2   Gastrointestinal   Adverse Reactions  



  Aspirin is associated with serious gastrointestinal (GI) adverse reactions, including inflammation, bleeding ulceration and perforation of the upper and lower GI tract. Other adverse reactions with aspirin include stomach pain, heartburn, nausea, and vomiting.



 Serious GI adverse reactions reported in the clinical trials of YOSPRALA were: gastric ulcer hemorrhage in one of the 521 patients treated with YOSPRALA and duodenal ulcer hemorrhage in one of the 524 patients treated with enteric-coated aspirin.  In addition, there were two cases of intestinal hemorrhage, one in each treatment group, and one patient treated with YOSPRALA experienced obstruction of the small bowel.



 Although minor upper GI symptoms, such as dyspepsia, are common and can occur anytime during therapy, monitor patients for signs of ulceration and bleeding, even in the absence of previous GI symptoms. Inform patients about the signs and symptoms of GI adverse reactions. 



 If active and clinically significant bleeding from any source occurs in patients receiving YOSPRALA, discontinue treatment.



     5.3         Bleeding Risk with Use of Alcohol  



  Counsel patients who consume three or more alcoholic drinks every day about the bleeding risks involved with chronic, heavy alcohol use while taking YOSPRALA.



     5.4         Interaction with Clopidogrel  



  Avoid concomitant use of YOSPRALA with clopidogrel. Clopidogrel is a prodrug. Inhibition of platelet aggregation by clopidogrel is entirely due to an active metabolite. The metabolism of clopidogrel to its active metabolite can be impaired by use with concomitant medications, such as omeprazole, that interfere with CYP2C19 activity. Co-administration of clopidogrel with 80 mg omeprazole reduces the pharmacological activity of clopidogrel, even when administered 12 hours apart. When using YOSPRALA, consider alternative anti-platelet therapy  [see     Drug Interactions (7)     ,     Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)     ]  .



     5.5         Interaction with Ticagrelor  



  Maintenance doses of aspirin above 100 mg reduce the effectiveness of ticagrelor in preventing thrombotic cardiovascular events. Avoid concomitant use of ticagrelor with the 325 mg/40 mg tablet strength of YOSPRALA [see        Drug Interactions (7)     ]  .



     5.   6   Renal Failure  



  Avoid YOSPRALA in patients with severe renal failure (glomerular filtration rate less than 10 mL/minute). Regular use of aspirin is associated in a dose-dependent manner with an increased risk of chronic renal failure. Aspirin use decreases glomerular filtration rate and renal blood flow especially with patients with pre-existing renal disease. [   see        Use in Specific Populations (8.6)     ,        Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)     ]  .



     5.7         Presence of Gastric Malignancy  



  In adults, response to gastric symptoms with YOSPRALA does not preclude the presence of gastric malignancy. Consider additional gastrointestinal follow-up and diagnostic testing in adult patients who experience gastric symptoms during treatment with YOSPRALA or have a symptomatic relapse after completing treatment. In older patients, also consider an endoscopy.



     5.   8   Acute Interstitial Nephritis  



  Acute interstitial nephritis has been observed in patients taking PPIs including omeprazole. Acute interstitial nephritis may occur at any point during PPI therapy and is generally attributed to an idiopathic hypersensitivity reaction. Discontinue YOSPRALA if acute interstitial nephritis develops [see     Contraindications (4)     ].  



     5.   9   Clostridium   difficile   -   Associated Diarrhea  



  Published observational studies suggest that PPI-containing therapy like YOSPRALA may be associated with an increased risk of Clostridium difficile  -associated diarrhea (CDAD), especially in hospitalized patients. This diagnosis should be considered for diarrhea that does not improve [  see   Adverse Reactions (6.2)     ]  .



 Use the lowest dose and shortest duration of YOSPRALA appropriate to the condition being treated.



     5.   10   Bone Fracture  



  Several published observational studies suggest that PPI therapy may be associated with an increased risk for osteoporosis-related fractures of the hip, wrist, or spine. The risk of fracture was increased in patients who received high-dose, defined as multiple daily doses, and long-term PPI therapy (a year or longer). Use the lowest dose and shortest duration of YOSPRALA therapy appropriate to the condition being treated. Manage patients at risk for osteoporosis-related fractures according to established treatment guidelines  [see     Adverse Reactions (6.2)     ]  .



     5.   11   Cutaneous and Systemic Lupus Erythematosus  



  Cutaneous lupus erythematosus (CLE) and systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) have been reported in patients taking PPIs, including omeprazole. These events have occurred as both new onset and an exacerbation of existing autoimmune disease. The majority of PPI-induced lupus erythematous cases were CLE.



 The most common form of CLE reported in patients treated with PPIs was subacute CLE (SCLE). Onset of CLE occurred up to 2 years after continuous drug therapy (range from 1 to 104 weeks). CLE occurred primarily in older patients, although cases were reported in patients as young as 7 months of age. Generally, positive antinuclear antibodies (ANA) and histological findings were observed, consistent with a diagnosis of CLE. Organ involvement was not typically seen. Complete recovery generally has occurred within 12 weeks after discontinuation of the drug.



 Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) is less commonly reported than CLE in patients receiving PPIs. PPI associated SLE is usually milder than non-drug induced SLE. Onset of SLE typically occurred within 30 days after initiating PPI treatment, but some cases occurred days or years after initiating treatment. SLE occurred primarily in older patients, although cases also occurred in young adults. The majority of patients presented with rash; however, arthralgia and cytopenia were also reported. Antibody testing for lupus, including ANA and antihistone antibodies, may be positive. Clinical signs and symptoms of SLE associated with PPI use were usually reversible once the PPI was discontinued. Clinical symptoms generally resolved within 8 weeks. Elevated serological test results may take longer to resolve than clinical manifestations.



 Avoid administration of PPIs for longer than medically indicated. If signs or symptoms consistent with CLE or SLE are noted in patients receiving YOSPRALA, discontinue the drug and refer the patient to the appropriate specialist for evaluation. Most patients improve with discontinuation of the PPI alone in 4 to 12 weeks.



     5.12         Hepatic Impairment  



  Long-term moderate to high doses of aspirin may result in elevations in serum ALT levels. These abnormalities resolve rapidly with discontinuation of aspirin. The hepatotoxicity of aspirin is usually mild and asymptomatic. Bilirubin elevations are usually mild or absent. Systemic exposure to omeprazole is increased in patients with hepatic impairment    [see     Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)     ]  . Avoid YOSPRALA in patients with any degree of hepatic impairment  [see     Use in Specific Populations (8.7)     ]  .



     5.1   3         Cyanocobalamin (Vitamin B-12) Deficiency  



  Daily treatment with any acid-suppressing medications over a long period of time (e.g., longer than 3 years) may lead to malabsorption of cyanocobalamin (vitamin B-12) caused by hypo- or achlorhydria. Rare reports of cyanocobalamin deficiency occurring with acid-suppressing therapy have been reported in the literature. This diagnosis should be considered if clinical symptoms consistent with cyanocobalamin deficiency are observed in patients treated with



 YOSPRALA.



     5.1   4   Hypomagnesemia  



  Hypomagnesemia, symptomatic and asymptomatic, has been reported rarely in patients treated with PPIs for at least three months, in most cases after a year of therapy. Serious adverse events include tetany, arrhythmias, and seizures. In most patients, treatment of hypomagnesemia required magnesium replacement and discontinuation of the PPI. For patients expected to be on prolonged treatment or who take YOSPRALA with medications such as digoxin or drugs that may cause hypomagnesemia (e.g., diuretics), consider monitoring magnesium levels prior to initiation of YOSPRALA and periodically during treatment [see     Adverse Reactions (6.2)     ]  . 



     5.   15         Reduced Effect of Omeprazole with St. John's Wort or   R   ifampin  



  Drugs which induce the CYP2C19 or CYP3A4 (such as St. John's Wort or rifampin) can substantially decrease concentrations of omeprazole. Avoid concomitant use of YOSPRALA with St. John's Wort or rifampin  [see     Drug Interactions (7)     ]  .



     5.   16         Interactions with Diagnostic Investigations for Neuroendocrine Tumors  



  Serum chromogranin A (CgA) levels increase secondary to omeprazole-induced decreases in gastric acidity. The increased CgA level may cause false positive results in diagnostic interventions for neuroendocrine tumors. Temporarily discontinue treatment with YOSPRALA at least 14 days before assessing CgA levels and consider repeating the test if initial CgA levels are high. If serial tests are performed (e.g., for monitoring), the same commercial laboratory should be used for testing, as reference ranges between tests may vary [see        Drug Interactions (7)       and      Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)     ]  .



     5.   17         Interaction with Methotrexate  



  Literature suggests that concomitant use of PPIs with methotrexate (primarily at high dose) may elevate and prolong serum levels of methotrexate and/or its metabolite, possibly leading to methotrexate toxicities. In high-dose methotrexate administration, a temporary withdrawal of YOSPRALA may be considered in some patients [see     Drug Interactions (7)     ]  .



     5.   18   Premature Closure of Fetal Ductus Arteriosus  



  NSAIDs including aspirin, may cause premature closure of the fetal ductus arteriosus. Avoid use of NSAIDs, including YOSPRALA, in pregnant women starting at 30 weeks of gestation (third trimester).  [see     Use in Specific Populations (8.1)     ].  



     5.   19         Abnormal Laboratory Tests  



  Aspirin has been associated with elevated hepatic enzymes, blood urea nitrogen and serum creatinine, hyperkalemia, proteinuria, and prolonged bleeding time.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
