<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="yuvafem" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6 ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Cardiovascular Disorders [see   Boxed Warning,     Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Malignant Neoplasms [see   Boxed Warning,     Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   In prospective, randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind studies the most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=5 percent) were upper respiratory tract infection, headache, abdominal pain, back pain, genital pruritus, moniliasis, vulvovaginal mycotic infection and diarrhea. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Amneal Pharmaceuticals at 1-877-835-5472 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or    www.fda.gov/medwatch  .    



 

    6.1       Clinical Trials Experience  

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In a 12-month randomized, double-blind, parallel group, placebo-controlled study, a total of 309 postmenopausal women were randomized to receive either placebo or Yuvafem 10 mcg tablets. Adverse reactions with an incidence of &gt;=5 percent in the Yuvafem 10 mcg group and greater than those reported in the placebo group are listed in Table 1.




  Table 1: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions Reported at a Frequency of &gt;= 5 Percent in Women Receiving Yuvafem 10 mcg    
  Body SystemAdverse Reaction                         TreatmentNumber (%) of Women    
                                                      PlaceboN = 103n (%)    YuvafemN = 205n (%)        
  Body As A Whole                                                                                 
  Back Pain                                           2 (2)            14 (7)                     
  Digestive System                                                                                
  Diarrhea                                            0                11 (5)                     
  Urogenital System                                                                               
  Vulvovaginal Mycotic Infection                      3 (3)            17 (8)                     
  Vulvovaginal Pruritus                               2 (2)            16 (8)                     
         N = Total number of women in study.n = Number of women who experienced adverse reactions.
 

 In a 12-week, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study, 138 postmenopausal women were randomized to receive either placebo or Yuvafem 25 mcg tablets. Adverse reactions with an incidence of &gt;=5 percent in the Yuvafem 25 mcg group and greater than those reported in the placebo group are listed in Table 2.




  Table 2: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions Reported at a Frequency of &gt;= 5 Percent in Women Receiving Yuvafem 25 mcg    
  Body SystemAdverse Reaction                         TreatmentNumber (%) of Women    
                                                      PlaceboN = 47n (%)    YuvafemN = 91n (%)         
  Body As A Whole                                                                                 
  Headache                                            3 (6)            8 (9)                      
  Abdominal Pain                                      2 (4)            6 (7)                      
  Back Pain                                           3 (6)            6 (7)                      
  Respiratory System                                                                              
  Upper Respiratory Tract Infection                   2 (4)            5 (5)                      
  Urogenital System                                                                               
  Moniliasis Genital                                  1 (2)            5 (5)                      
         N = Total number of women in study.n = Number of women who experienced adverse reactions.
 

     6.2       Postmarketing Experience  

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of Yuvafem 25 mcg. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Genitourinary System  Endometrial cancer, endometrial hyperplasia, vaginal irritation, vaginal pain, vaginismus, vaginal ulceration



   Breast  Breast cancer



   Cardiovascular  Deep vein thrombosis



   Gastrointestinal  Diarrhea



   Skin  Urticaria, erythematous or pruritic rash, genital pruritus



   Central Nervous System  Aggravated migraine, depression, insomnia



   Miscellaneous  Fluid retention, weight increase, drug ineffectiveness, hypersensitivity, blood estrogen increase



 Additional postmarketing adverse reactions have been reported in patients receiving other forms of hormone therapy.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: ENDOMETRIAL CANCER, CARDIOVASCULAR DISORDERS, BREAST CANCER and PROBABLE DEMENTIA

    WARNING: ENDOMETRIAL CANCER, CARDIOVASCULAR DISORDERS, BREAST CANCER and PROBABLE DEMENTIA  

      Estrogen-Alone Therapy                                                                            Endometrial Cancer  



   There is an increased risk of endometrial cancer in a woman with a uterus who uses unopposed estrogens. Adding a progestin to estrogen therapy has been shown to reduce the risk of endometrial hyperplasia, which may be a precursor to endometrial cancer. Adequate diagnostic measures, including directed or random endometrial sampling when indicated, should be undertaken to rule out malignancy in postmenopausal women with undiagnosed persistent or recurring abnormal genital bleeding   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  .  



                                                     Cardiovascular Disorders and Probable Dementia  



   Estrogen-alone therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2,     5.4)  , and   Clinical Studies (14.2,     14.3)  ]  .  



   The Women's Health Initiative (WHI) estrogen-alone substudy reported increased risks of stroke and deep vein thrombosis (DVT) in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age) during 7.1 years of treatment with daily oral conjugated estrogens (CE) [0.625 mg]-alone, relative to placebo   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2),   and   Clinical Studies (14.2)  ].    



   The WHI Memory Study (WHIMS) estrogen-alone ancillary study of WHI reported an increased risk of developing probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age or older during 5.2 years of treatment with daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone, relative to placebo. It is unknown whether this finding applies to younger postmenopausal women   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.4),     Use in Specific Populations (8.5),   and   Clinical Studies (14.3)  ]  .  



   In the absence of comparable data, these risks should be assumed to be similar for other doses of CE and other dosage forms of estrogens.  



   Estrogens with or without progestins should be prescribed at the lowest effective doses and for the shortest duration consistent with treatment goals and risks for the individual woman.  



     Estrogen Plus Progestin Therapy    



                                                Cardiovascular Disorders and Probable Dementia  



   Estrogen plus progestin therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2,     5.4),   and   Clinical Studies (14.2,     14.3)  ]  .  



   The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported increased risks of DVT, pulmonary embolism (PE), stroke and myocardial infarction (MI) in postmenopausal women (50 to 79 years of age) during 5.6 years of treatment with daily oral CE (0.625 mg) combined with medroxyprogesterone acetate (MPA) [2.5 mg], relative to placebo   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2),   and   Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]  .  



   The WHIMS estrogen plus progestin ancillary study of the WHI reported an increased risk of developing probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age or older during 4 years of treatment with daily CE (0.625 mg) combined with MPA (2.5 mg), relative to placebo. It is unknown whether this finding applies to younger postmenopausal women   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.4),     Use in Specific Populations (8.5),   and   Clinical Studies (14.3)  ].    



                                                                              Breast Cancer  



   The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy also demonstrated an increased risk of invasive breast cancer   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3),   and   Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]  .  



   In the absence of comparable data, these risks should be assumed to be similar for other doses of CE and MPA, and other combinations and dosage forms of estrogens and progestins.  



   Estrogens with or without progestins should be prescribed at the lowest effective doses and for the shortest duration consistent with treatment goals and risks for the individual woman.  



   EXCERPT:              WARNING: ENDOMETRIAL CANCER, CARDIOVASCULAR DISORDERS, BREAST CANCER and PROBABLE DEMENTIA    



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning    



       Estrogen-Alone Therapy      



 *  There is an increased risk of endometrial cancer in a woman with a uterus who uses unopposed estrogens (5.3) 
 *  Estrogen-alone therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia (5.2, 5.4) 
 *  The Women's Health Initiative (WHI) estrogen-alone substudy reported increased risks of stroke and deep vein thrombosis (DVT) (5.2) 
 *  The WHI Memory Study (WHIMS) estrogen-alone ancillary study of WHI reported an increased risk of probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age and older (5.4) 
          Estrogen Plus Progestin Therapy      
 

 *  Estrogen plus progestin therapy should not be used for the prevention of cardiovascular disease or dementia (5.2, 5.4) 
 *  The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported increased risks of stroke, DVT, pulmonary embolism (PE), and myocardial infarction (MI) (5.2) 
 *  The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported increased risks of invasive breast cancer (5.3) 
 *  The WHIMS estrogen plus progestin ancillary study of WHI reported an increased risk of probable dementia in postmenopausal women 65 years of age and older (5.4) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">     5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *  Estrogens increase the risk of gallbladder disease (  5.5  ) 
 *  Discontinue estrogen if severe hypercalcemia, loss of vision, severe hypertriglyceridemia or cholestatic jaundice occurs (  5.6,     5.7,     5.10,     5.11  ) 
 *  The Yuvafem applicator may cause vaginal abrasion (  5.17  ) 
 *  Monitor thyroid function in women on thyroid replacement therapy (  5.12,     5.19  ) 
    
 

    5.1       Risks from Systemic Absorption  



  Yuvafem is intended only for vaginal administration. Systemic absorption occurs with the use of Yuvafem. The warnings, precautions, and adverse reactions associated with the use of systemic estrogen-alone therapy should be taken into account.



     5.2       Cardiovascular Disorders  



  An increased risk of stroke and DVT has been reported with estrogen-alone therapy. An increased risk of PE, DVT, stroke, and MI has been reported with estrogen plus progestin therapy. Should any of these occur or be suspected, estrogen with or without progestin therapy should be discontinued immediately.



 Risk factors for arterial vascular disease (for example, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, tobacco use, hypercholesterolemia, and obesity) and/or venous thromboembolism (VTE) (for example, personal history or family history of VTE, obesity, and systemic lupus erythematosus) should be managed appropriately.



  Stroke  



 In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, a statistically significant increased risk of stroke was reported in women 50 to 79 years of age receiving daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone compared to women in the same age group receiving placebo (45 versus 33 per 10,000 women-years). The increase in risk was demonstrated in year 1 and persisted [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ].  Should a stroke occur or be suspected, estrogen-alone therapy should be discontinued immediately.



 Subgroup analyses of women 50 to 59 years of age suggest no increased risk of stroke for those women receiving CE (0.625 mg)-alone versus those receiving placebo (18 versus 21 per 10,000 women-years).  1  



 In the WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy, a statistically significant increased risk of stroke was reported in women 50 to 79 years of age receiving daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) compared to women in the same age group receiving placebo (33 versus 25 per 10,000 women-years) [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ].  The increase in risk was demonstrated after the first year and persisted.  1  Should a stroke occur or be suspected, estrogen plus progestin therapy should be discontinued immediately.



  Coronary Heart Disease  



 In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, no overall effect on coronary heart disease (CHD) events (defined as nonfatal MI, silent MI, or CHD death) was reported in women receiving estrogen-alone compared to placebo  2   [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ].  



 Subgroup analysis of women 50 to 59 years of age suggests a statistically non-significant reduction in CHD events (CE [0.625 mg]-alone compared to placebo) in women with less than 10 years since menopause (8 versus 16 per 10,000 women-years).  1  



 In the WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy, there was a statistically non-significant increased risk of CHD events reported in women receiving daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) compared to women receiving placebo (41 versus 34 per 10,000 women-years).  1  An increase in relative risk was demonstrated in year 1, and a trend toward decreasing relative risk was reported in years 2 through 5 [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]  .



 In postmenopausal women with documented heart disease (n=2,763), average 66.7 years of age, in a controlled clinical trial of secondary prevention of cardiovascular disease (Heart and Estrogen/Progestin Replacement Study [HERS]), treatment with daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) demonstrated no cardiovascular benefit. During an average follow-up of 4.1 years, treatment with CE plus MPA did not reduce the overall rate of CHD events in postmenopausal women with established coronary heart disease. There were more CHD events in the CE plus MPA-treated group than in the placebo group in year 1, but not during the subsequent years. Two thousand, three hundred and twenty-one (2,321) women from the original HERS trial agreed to participate in an open label extension of the original HERS, HERS II. Average follow-up in HERS II was an additional 2.7 years, for a total of 6.8 years overall. Rates of CHD events were comparable among women in the CE plus MPA group and the placebo group in HERS, HERS II, and overall.



  Venous Thromboembolism  



 In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, the risk of VTE (DVT and PE) was increased for women receiving daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone compared to placebo (30 versus 22 per 10,000 women-years), although only the increased risk of DVT reached statistical significance (23 versus 15 per 10,000 women-years). The increase in VTE risk was demonstrated during the first 2 years  3   [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ].  Should a VTE occur or be suspected, estrogen-alone therapy should be discontinued immediately.



 In the WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy, a statistically significant 2-fold greater rate of VTE was reported in women receiving daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) compared to women receiving placebo (35 versus 17 per 10,000 women-years). Statistically significant increases in risk for both DVT (26 versus 13 per 10,000 women-years) and PE (18 versus 8 per 10,000 women-years) were also demonstrated. The increase in VTE risk was demonstrated during the first year and persisted  4   [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ].  Should a VTE occur or be suspected, estrogen plus progestin therapy should be discontinued immediately.



 If feasible, estrogens should be discontinued at least 4 to 6 weeks before surgery of the type associated with an increased risk of thromboembolism, or during periods of prolonged immobilization.



     5.3       Malignant Neoplasms  



   Endometrial Cancer  



 An increased risk of endometrial cancer has been reported with the use of unopposed estrogen therapy in a woman with a uterus. The reported endometrial cancer risk among unopposed estrogen users is about 2 to 12 times greater than in non-users, and appears dependent on duration of treatment and on estrogen dose. Most studies show no significant increased risk associated with use of estrogens for less than 1 year. The greatest risk appears associated with prolonged use, with an increased risk of 15- to 24-fold for 5 to 10 years or more and this risk has been shown to persist for at least 8 to 15 years after estrogen therapy is discontinued.



 Clinical surveillance of all women using estrogen-alone or estrogen plus progestin therapy is important. Adequate diagnostic measures, including directed or random endometrial sampling when indicated, should be undertaken to rule out malignancy in postmenopausal women with undiagnosed persistent or recurring abnormal genital bleeding.



 There is no evidence that the use of natural estrogens results in a different endometrial risk profile than synthetic estrogens of equivalent estrogen dose. Adding a progestin to estrogen therapy in postmenopausal women has been shown to reduce the risk of endometrial hyperplasia, which may be a precursor to endometrial cancer.



  Breast Cancer  



 The most important randomized clinical trial providing information about breast cancer in estrogen-alone users is the WHI substudy of daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone. In the WHI estrogen-alone substudy, after an average follow-up of 7.1 years, daily CE-alone was not associated with an increased risk of invasive breast cancer [relative risk (RR) 0.80]    5   [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]  .



 The most important randomized clinical trial providing information about breast cancer in estrogen plus progestin users is the WHI substudy of daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg). After a mean follow-up of 5.6 years, the estrogen plus progestin substudy reported an increased risk of invasive breast cancer in women who took daily CE plus MPA. In this substudy, prior use of estrogen-alone or estrogen plus progestin therapy was reported by 26 percent of the women. The relative risk of invasive breast cancer was 1.24, and the absolute risk was 41 versus 33 cases per 10,000 women-years, for CE plus MPA compared with placebo. Among women who reported prior use of hormone therapy, the relative risk of invasive breast cancer was 1.86, and the absolute risk was 46 versus 25 cases per 10,000 women-years, for CE plus MPA compared with placebo. Among women who reported no prior use of hormone therapy, the relative risk of invasive breast cancer was 1.09, and the absolute risk was 40 versus 36 cases per 10,000 women-years for CE plus MPA compared with placebo. In the same substudy, invasive breast cancers were larger, were more likely to be node positive, and were diagnosed at a more advanced stage in the CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) group compared with the placebo group. Metastatic disease was rare, with no apparent difference between the two groups. Other prognostic factors, such as histologic subtype, grade and hormone receptor status did not differ between the groups  6   [see  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]  .



 Consistent with the WHI clinical trial, observational studies have also reported an increased risk of breast cancer for estrogen plus progestin therapy, and a smaller increased risk for estrogen-alone therapy, after several years of use. The risk increased with duration of use, and appeared to return to baseline over about 5 years after stopping treatment (only the observational studies have substantial data on risk after stopping). Observational studies also suggest that the risk of breast cancer was greater, and became apparent earlier, with estrogen plus progestin therapy as compared to estrogen-alone therapy. However, these studies have not generally found significant variation in the risk of breast cancer among different estrogen plus progestin combinations, doses, or routes of administration.



 The use of estrogen-alone and estrogen plus progestin therapy has been reported to result in an increase in abnormal mammograms requiring further evaluation.



 All women should receive yearly breast examinations by a healthcare provider and perform monthly breast self-examinations. In addition, mammography examinations should be scheduled based on patient age, risk factors, and prior mammogram results.



  Ovarian Cancer  



 The WHI estrogen plus progestin substudy reported a statistically non-significant increased risk of ovarian cancer. After an average follow-up of 5.6 years, the relative risk for ovarian cancer for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 1.58 (95 percent CI, 0.77-3.24). The absolute risk for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 4 versus 3 cases per 10,000 women-years.  7  In some epidemiologic studies, the use of estrogen plus progestin and estrogen-only products, in particular for 5 or more years, has been associated with an increased risk of ovarian cancer. However, the duration of exposure associated with increased risk is not consistent across all epidemiologic studies, and some report no association.



     5.4       Probable Dementia  



  In the WHIMS estrogen-alone ancillary study of WHI, a population of 2,947 hysterectomized women 65 to 79 years of age was randomized to daily CE (0.625 mg)-alone or placebo.



 After an average follow-up of 5.2 years, 28 women in the estrogen-alone group and 19 women in the placebo group were diagnosed with probable dementia. The relative risk of probable dementia for CE-alone versus placebo was 1.49 (95 percent CI, 0.83-2.66). The absolute risk of probable dementia for CE-alone versus placebo was 37 versus 25 cases per 10,000 women-years  8   [see   Use in Specific Populations (8.5),  and  Clinical Studies (14.3)  ]  .



 In the WHIMS estrogen plus progestin ancillary study of WHI, a population of 4,532 postmenopausal women 65 to 79 years of age was randomized to daily CE (0.625 mg) plus MPA (2.5 mg) or placebo. After an average follow-up of 4 years, 40 women in the CE plus MPA group and 21 women in the placebo group were diagnosed with probable dementia. The relative risk of probable dementia for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 2.05 (95 percent CI, 1.21-3.48). The absolute risk of probable dementia for CE plus MPA versus placebo was 45 versus 22 cases per 10,000 women-years  8   [see   Use in Specific Populations (8.5),        and   Clinical Studies (14.3)       ]  .



 When data from the two populations in the WHIMS estrogen-alone and estrogen plus progestin ancillary studies were pooled as planned in the WHIMS protocol, the reported overall relative risk for probable dementia was 1.76 (95 percent CI, 1.19-2.60). Since both ancillary studies were conducted in women 65 to 79 years of age, it is unknown whether these findings apply to younger postmenopausal women  8   [see      Use in Specific Populations (8.5),     and   Clinical Studies (14.3)       ]   .  



     5.5       Gallbladder Disease  



  A 2- to 4-fold increase in the risk of gallbladder disease requiring surgery in postmenopausal women receiving estrogens has been reported.



     5.6       Hypercalcemia  



  Estrogen administration may lead to severe hypercalcemia in women with breast cancer and bone metastases. If hypercalcemia occurs, use of the drug should be stopped and appropriate measures taken to reduce the serum calcium level.



     5.7       Visual Abnormalities  



  Retinal vascular thrombosis has been reported in women receiving estrogens.  Discontinue medication pending examination if there is a sudden partial or complete loss of vision, or a sudden onset of proptosis, diplopia, or migraine.  If examination reveals papilledema or retinal vascular lesions, estrogens should be permanently discontinued.



     5.8       Addition of a Progestin When a Woman Has Not Had a Hysterectomy  



  Studies of the addition of a progestin for 10 or more days of a cycle of estrogen administration, or daily with estrogen in a continuous regimen, have reported a lowered incidence of endometrial hyperplasia than would be induced by estrogen treatment alone. Endometrial hyperplasia may be a precursor to endometrial cancer.



 There are, however, possible risks that may be associated with the use of progestins with estrogens compared to estrogen-alone regimens. These include an increased risk of breast cancer.



     5.9       Elevated Blood Pressure  



  In a small number of case reports, substantial increases in blood pressure have been attributed to idiosyncratic reactions to estrogens. In a large, randomized, placebo-controlled clinical trial, a generalized effect of estrogens on blood pressure was not seen.



     5.10     Hypertriglyceridemia  



  In women with pre-existing hypertriglyceridemia, estrogen therapy may be associated with elevations of plasma triglycerides leading to pancreatitis. Consider discontinuation of treatment if pancreatitis occurs.



     5.11     Hepatic Impairment and/or Past History of Cholestatic Jaundice  



  Estrogens may be poorly metabolized in women with impaired liver function. For women with a history of cholestatic jaundice associated with past estrogen use or with pregnancy, caution should be exercised, and in the case of recurrence, medication should be discontinued.



     5.12     Hypothyroidism  



  Estrogen administration leads to increased thyroid-binding globulin (TBG) levels. Women with normal thyroid function can compensate for the increased TBG by making more thyroid hormone, thus maintaining free T4and T3serum concentrations in the normal range. Women dependent on thyroid hormone replacement therapy who are also receiving estrogens may require increased doses of their thyroid replacement therapy. These women should have their thyroid function monitored in order to maintain their free thyroid hormone levels in an acceptable range.



     5.13     Fluid Retention  



  Estrogens may cause some degree of fluid retention. Women with conditions that might be influenced by this factor, such as a cardiac or renal dysfunction, warrant careful observation when estrogen-alone is prescribed.



     



     5.14     Hypocalcemia  



  Estrogen therapy should be used with caution in women with hypoparathyroidism as estrogen-induced hypocalcemia may occur.



     5.15     Exacerbation of Endometriosis  



  A few cases of malignant transformation of residual endometrial implants have been reported in women treated post-hysterectomy with estrogen-alone therapy. For women known to have residual endometriosis post-hysterectomy, the addition of progestin should be considered.



     5.16     Hereditary Angioedema  



  Exogenous estrogens may exacerbate symptoms of angioedema in women with hereditary angioedema.



     5.17     Exacerbation of Other Conditions  



  Estrogen therapy may cause an exacerbation of asthma, diabetes mellitus, epilepsy, migraine, porphyria, systemic lupus erythematosus, and hepatic hemangiomas and should be used with caution in women with these conditions.



     5.18     Local Abrasion  



  A few cases of local abrasion induced by the Yuvafem applicator have been reported, especially in women with severely atrophic vaginal mucosa.



     5.19     Laboratory Tests  



   Serum follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) and estradiol levels have not been shown to be useful in the management of moderate to severe symptoms of vulvar and vaginal atrophy.  
 

     5.20     Drug-Laboratory Test Interactions  



  Accelerated prothrombin time, partial thromboplastin time, and platelet aggregation time; increased platelet count; increased factors II, VII antigen, VIII antigen, VIII coagulant activity, IX, X, XII, VII-X complex, II-VII-X complex, and beta-thromboglobulin; decreased levels of antifactor Xa and antithrombin III, decreased antithrombin III activity; increased levels of fibrinogen and fibrinogen activity; increased plasminogen antigen and activity.



 Increased thyroid-binding globulin (TBG) levels leading to increased circulating total thyroid hormone  as measured by protein-bound iodine (PBI), T4levels (by column or by radioimmunoassay) or T3levels by radioimmunoassay. T3resin uptake is decreased, reflecting the elevated TBG. Free T4and free T3concentrations are unaltered. Women on thyroid replacement therapy may require higher doses of thyroid hormone.



 Other binding proteins may be elevated in serum, for example, corticosteroid binding globulin (CBG), sex hormone-binding globulin (SHBG), leading to increased total circulating corticosteroids and sex steroids, respectively. Free hormone concentrations, such as testosterone and estradiol, may be decreased. Other plasma proteins may be increased (angiotensinogen/renin substrate, alpha-1-antitrypsin, ceruloplasmin).



 Increased plasma high-density lipoprotein (HDL) and HDL2cholesterol subfraction concentrations, reduced low-density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol concentrations, increased triglyceride levels.



 Impaired glucose tolerance.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
