<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="zanaflex1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are described elsewhere in other sections of the prescribing information:



 *  Hypotension [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *  Liver Injury [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
 *  Sedation [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ] 
 *  Hallucinosis/Psychotic-Like Symptoms [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   ] 
 *  Hypersensitivity Reactions [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)   ] 
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (greater than 2% of 264 patients taking tizanidine and greater than in placebo-treated patients in three multiple dose, placebo-controlled studies) were dry mouth, somnolence, asthenia, dizziness, urinary tract infection, constipation, liver function tests abnormal, vomiting, speech disorder, amblyopia, urinary frequency, flu syndrome, SGPT/ALT increased, dyskinesia, nervousness, pharyngitis, and rhinitis (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Acorda Therapeutics at 1-800-367-5109 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 Three double-blind, randomized, placebo controlled -clinical studies were conducted to evaluate the effect of tizanidine on spasticity control. Two studies were conducted in patients with multiple sclerosis and one in patients with spinal cord injury. Each study had a 13-week active treatment period which included a 3-week titration phase to the maximum tolerated dose up to 36 mg/day in three divided doses, a 9-week plateau phase where the dose of tizanidine was held constant and a 1-week dose tapering. In all, 264 patients received tizanidine and 261 patients received placebo. Across the three studies patient ages ranged from 15-69 years and 51.4 percent were women. The median dose during the plateau phase ranged from 20-28 mg/day.



 The most frequent adverse reactions reported in multiple dose, placebo-controlled clinical studies involving 264 patients with spasticity were dry mouth, somnolence/sedation, asthenia (weakness, fatigue and/or tiredness) and dizziness. Three-quarters of the patients rated the events as mild to moderate and one-quarter of the patients rated the events as being severe. These events appeared to be dose related.



 Table 1 lists signs and symptoms that were reported in greater than 2% of patients in three multiple dose, placebo-controlled studies who received Zanaflex where the frequency in the Zanaflex group was greater than the placebo group. For comparison purposes, the corresponding frequency of the event (per 100 patients) among placebo treated patients is also provided.



 Table 1: Multiple Dose, Placebo-Controlled Studies-Frequent (&gt;2%) Adverse Reactions Reported for Which Zanaflex Tablets Incidence is Greater than Placebo 
 Event                                                 PlaceboN = 261%        Zanaflex TabletN = 264%       
  
 Dry mouth                                                    10                         49                 
 Somnolence                                                   10                         48                 
 Asthenia                                                     16                         41                 
 Dizziness                                                    4                          16                 
 UTI                                                          7                          10                 
 Infection                                                    5                          6                  
 Constipation                                                 1                          4                  
 Liver test abnormality                                       2                          6                  
 Vomiting                                                     0                          3                  
 Speech disorder                                              0                          3                  
 Amblyopia (blurred vision)                                   &lt;1                         3                  
 Urinary frequency                                            2                          3                  
 Flu syndrome                                                 2                          3                  
 Dyskinesia                                                   0                          3                  
 Nervousness                                                  &lt;1                         3                  
 Pharyngitis                                                  1                          3                  
 Rhinitis                                                     2                          3                  
         In the single dose, placebo-controlled study involving 142 patients with spasticity due to multiple sclerosis (Study 1)  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  , the patients were specifically asked if they had experienced any of the four most common adverse reactions: dry mouth, somnolence (drowsiness), asthenia (weakness, fatigue and/or tiredness) and dizziness. In addition, hypotension and bradycardia were observed. The occurrence of these reactions is summarized in Table 2. Other events were, in general, reported at a rate of 2% or less.
 

 Table 2: Single Dose, Placebo-Controlled Study-Common Adverse Reactions Reported 
 Event                              PlaceboN = 48%     Zanaflex Tablet, 8mg, N = 45%  Zanaflex Tablet, 16 mg, N = 49%   
  
 Somnolence                               31                      78                         92               
 Dry mouth                                35                      76                         88               
 Asthenia                                 40                      67                         78               
 Dizziness                                4                       22                         45               
 Hypotension                              0                       16                         33               
 Bradycardia                              0                        2                         10               
            6.2 Post-Marketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during post approval use of Zanaflex. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Certain events, such as somnolence, dry mouth, hypotension, decreased blood pressure, bradycardia, dizziness, weakness or asthenia, muscle spasms, hallucinations, fatigue, liver function test abnormality and hepatotoxicity, have been observed in post marketing and clinical trials and are discussed in previous sections of this document.



 The following adverse reactions have been identified as occurring in the post marketing experience of Zanaflex. Based on the information provided regarding these reactions, a causal relationship with Zanaflex cannot be entirely excluded. The events are listed in order of decreasing clinical significance; severity in the post marketing setting is not reported.



 *  Stevens Johnson Syndrome 
 *  Anaphylactic Reaction 
 *  Exfoliative Dermatitis 
 *  Ventricular Tachycardia 
 *  Hepatitis 
 *  Convulsion 
 *  Depression 
 *  Arthralgia 
 *  Paresthesia 
 *  Rash 
 *  Tremor 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Hypotension: monitor for signs and symptoms of hypotension, in particular in patients receiving concurrent antihypertensives; Zanaflex should not be used with other alpha2-adrenergic agonists (  5.1  ,  7.7  ) 
 *  Risk of liver injury: monitor ALTs; discontinue Zanaflex if liver injury occurs (  5.2  ) 
 *  Sedation: Zanaflex may interfere with everyday activities; sedative effects of Zanaflex, alcohol, and other CNS depressants are additive (  5.3  ,  7.5  ,  7.6  ) 
 *  Hallucinations: consider discontinuation of Zanaflex (  5.4  ) 
 *  Less potent inhibitors of CYP1A2: may cause hypotension, bradycardia, or excessive drowsiness, use caution if Zanaflex is used with less potent inhibitors of CYP1A2, e.g., zileuton, other fluoroquinolones, antiarrythmics , cimetidine, famotidine, oral contraceptives, acyclovir, and ticlopidine (  5.5  ,  7.3  ,  12.3  ) 
 *  Renal impairment (creatinine clearance &lt; 25 mL/min): use Zanaflex with caution, and monitor closely for dry mouth, somnolence, asthenia and dizziness as indicators of potential overdose (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypotension



  Tizanidine is an alpha2-adrenergic agonist that can produce hypotension. Syncope has been reported in the post marketing setting. The chance of significant hypotension may possibly be minimized by titration of the dose and by focusing attention on signs and symptoms of hypotension prior to dose advancement. In addition, patients moving from a supine to fixed upright position may be at increased risk for hypotension and orthostatic effects.



 Monitor for hypotension when Zanaflex is used in patients receiving concurrent antihypertensive therapy. It is not recommended that Zanaflex be used with other alpha2-adrenergic agonists. Clinically significant hypotension (decreases in both systolic and diastolic pressure) has been reported with concomitant administration of either fluvoxamine or ciprofloxacin and single doses of 4 mg of Zanaflex. Therefore, concomitant use of Zanaflex with fluvoxamine or with ciprofloxacin, potent inhibitors of CYP1A2, is contraindicated [ see  Contraindications (4)    and   Drug Interactions (7.1  ,  7.2  )  ].



    5.2 Risk of Liver Injury



  Zanaflex may cause hepatocellular liver injury. Zanaflex should be used with caution in patients with any hepatic impairment.. Monitoring of aminotransferase levels is recommended for baseline and 1 month after maximum dose is achieved, or if hepatic injury is suspected. [ see     Dosage and Administration (2.3)  and  Use in Specific Populations (8.7)    ]



    5.3 Sedation



  Zanaflex can cause sedation, which may interfere with everyday activity. In the multiple dose studies, the prevalence of patients with sedation peaked following the first week of titration and then remained stable for the duration of the maintenance phase of the study. The CNS depressant effects of Zanaflex with alcohol and other CNS depressants (e.g., benzodiazepines, opioids, tricyclic antidepressants) may be additive. Monitor patients who take Zanaflex with another CNS depressant for symptoms of excess sedation. [ see  Drug Interactions (7.5  ,  7.6  )  ]



    5.4 Hallucinosis/Psychotic-Like Symptoms



  Zanaflex use has been associated with hallucinations. Formed, visual hallucinations or delusions have been reported in 5 of 170 patients (3%) in two North American controlled clinical studies. Most of the patients were aware that the events were unreal. One patient developed psychosis in association with the hallucinations. One patient among these 5 continued to have problems for at least 2 weeks following discontinuation of tizanidine. Consider discontinuing Zanaflex in patients who develop hallucinations.



    5.5 Interaction with CYP1A2 Inhibitors



  Because of potential drug interactions, Zanaflex is contraindicated in patients taking potent CYP1A2 inhibitors, such as fluvoxamine or ciprofloxacin. Adverse reactions such as hypotension, bradycardia, or excessive drowsiness can occur when Zanaflex is taken with other CYP1A2 inhibitors, such as zileuton, fluoroquinolones other than ciprofloxacin (which is contraindicated), antiarrythmics (amiodarone, mexiletine, propafenone), cimetidine, famotidine, oral contraceptives, acyclovir, and ticlopidine ). Concomitant use should be avoided unless the necessity for Zanaflex therapy is clinically evident. In such a case, use with caution. [ see  Drug Interactions (7.3)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)    ]



    5.6 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Zanaflex can cause anaphylaxis. Signs and symptoms including respiratory compromise, urticaria, and angioedema of the throat and tongue have been reported. Patients should be informed of the signs and symptoms of severe allergic reactions and instructed to discontinue Zanaflex and seek immediate medical care should these signs and symptoms occur. [ see  Contraindications (4)    ]



    5.7 Increased Risk of Adverse Reactions in Patients with Renal Impairment



  Zanaflex should be used with caution in patients with renal insufficiency (creatinine clearance &lt; 25 mL/min), as clearance is reduced by more than 50%. In these patients, during titration, the individual doses should be reduced. If higher doses are required, individual doses rather than dosing frequency should be increased. These patients should be monitored closely for the onset or increase in severity of the common adverse events (dry mouth, somnolence, asthenia and dizziness) as indicators of potential overdose. [ see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  and  Use in Specific Populations (8.6)    ]



    5.8 Withdrawal Adverse Reactions



  Withdrawal adverse reactions include rebound hypertension, tachycardia, and hypertonia. To minimize the risk of these reactions, particularly in patients who have been receiving high doses (20 to 28 mg daily) for long periods of time (9 weeks or more) or who may be on concomitant treatment with narcotics, the dose should be decreased slowly (2 to 4 mg per day). [see  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ]  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
