<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="zanaflex0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  In multiple dose, placebo-controlled clinical studies, 264 patients were treated with tizanidine and 261 with placebo. Adverse events, including severe adverse events, were more frequently reported with tizanidine than with placebo.



   COMMON ADVERSE EVENTS LEADING TO DISCONTINUATION

  Forty-five of 264 (17%) patients receiving tizanidine and 13 of 261 (5%) of patients receiving placebo in three multiple dose, placebo-controlled clinical studies, discontinued treatment for adverse events. When patients withdrew from the study, they frequently had more than one reason for discontinuing. The adverse events most frequently leading to withdrawal of tizanidine treated patients in the controlled clinical studies were asthenia (weakness, fatigue and/or tiredness) (3%), somnolence (3%), dry mouth (3%), increased spasm or tone (2%), and dizziness (2%).



   MOST FREQUENT ADVERSE CLINICAL EVENTS SEEN IN ASSOCIATION WITH THE USE OF TIZANIDINE

  In multiple dose, placebo-controlled clinical studies involving 264 patients with spasticity, the most frequent adverse effects were dry mouth, somnolence/sedation, asthenia (weakness, fatigue and/or tiredness) and dizziness. Three-quarters of the patients rated the events as mild to moderate and one-quarter of the patients rated the events as being severe. These events appeared to be dose related.



   ADVERSE EVENTS REPORTED IN CONTROLLED STUDIES

  The events cited reflect experience gained under closely monitored conditions of clinical studies in a highly selected patient population. In actual clinical practice or in other clinical studies, these frequency estimates may not apply, as the conditions of use, reporting behavior, and the kinds of patients treated may differ. Table 1 lists treatment emergent signs and symptoms that were reported in greater than 2% of patients in three multiple dose, placebo-controlled studies who received tizanidine where the frequency in the tizanidine group was at least as common as in the placebo group. These events are not necessarily related to tizanidine treatment. For comparison purposes, the corresponding frequency of the event (per 100 patients) among placebo treated patients is also provided.



 Table 1: Multiple Dose, Placebo-Controlled Studies-Frequent (&gt; 2%) Adverse Events Reported for Which Tizanidine Tablets Incidence is Greater than Placebo 
 Event                                                    PlaceboN = 261%        Zanaflex TabletN = 264%    
  
 Dry mouth                                                      10                         49               
 Somnolence                                                     10                         48               
 Asthenia                                                       16                         41               
 Dizziness                                                       4                         16               
 UTI                                                             7                         10               
 Infection                                                       5                          6               
 Constipation                                                    1                          4               
 Liver function tests abnormal                                  &lt;1                          3               
 Vomiting                                                        0                          3               
 Speech disorder                                                 0                          3               
 Amblyopia (blurred vision)                                     &lt;1                          3               
 Urinary frequency                                               2                          3               
 Flu syndrome                                                    2                          3               
 SGPT/ALT increased                                             &lt;1                          3               
 Dyskinesia                                                      0                          3               
 Nervousness                                                    &lt;1                          3               
 Pharyngitis                                                     1                          3               
 Rhinitis                                                        2                          3               
         In the single dose, placebo-controlled study involving 142 patients with spasticity, the patients were specifically asked if they had experienced any of the four most common adverse events: dry mouth, somnolence (drowsiness), asthenia (weakness, fatigue and/or tiredness) and dizziness. In addition, hypotension and bradycardia were observed. The occurrence of these adverse effects is summarized in Table 2. Other events were, in general, reported at a rate of 2% or less.
 

 Table 2: Single Dose, Placebo-Controlled Study-Common Adverse Events Reported 
 Event                                PlaceboN = 48%   Tizanidine Tablet,8mg, N = 45%  Tizanidine Tablet,16 mg, N = 49%   
  
 Somnolence                                 31                    78                         92               
 Dry mouth                                  35                    76                         88               
 Asthenia                                   40                    67                         78               
 Dizziness                                   4                    22                         45               
 Hypotension                                 0                    16                         33               
 Bradycardia                                 0                     2                         10               
            OTHER ADVERSE EVENTS OBSERVED DURING THE EVALUATION OF TIZANIDINE
   Tizanidine was administered to 1385 patients in additional clinical studies where adverse event information was available. The conditions and duration of exposure varied greatly, and included (in overlapping categories) double-blind and open-label studies, uncontrolled and controlled studies, inpatient and outpatient studies, and titration studies. Untoward events associated with this exposure were recorded by clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. Consequently, it is not possible to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse events without first grouping similar types of untoward events into a smaller number of standardized event categories.



 In the tabulations that follow, reported adverse events were classified using a standard COSTART-based dictionary terminology. The frequencies presented, therefore, represent the proportion of the 1385 patients exposed to tizanidine who experienced an event of the type cited on at least one occasion while receiving tizanidine. All reported events are included except those already listed in Table 1. If the COSTART term for an event was so general as to be uninformative, it was replaced by a more informative term. It is important to emphasize that, although the events reported occurred during treatment with tizanidine, they were not necessarily caused by it.



 Events are further categorized by body system and listed in order of decreasing frequency according to the following definitions: frequent adverse events are those occurring on one or more occasions in at least 1/100 patients (only those not already listed in the tabulated results from placebo-controlled studies appear in this listing); infrequent adverse events are those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1000 patients; rare adverse events are those occurring in fewer than 1/1000 patients.




 BODY AS A WHOLE   
  
 Frequent:    Fever                                                                                       
 Infrequent:  Allergic reaction, moniliasis, malaise, abscess, neck pain, sepsis, cellulites, death, overdose   
 Rare:        Carcinoma, congenital anomaly, suicide attempt                                              
      
 CARDIOVASCULAR SYSTEM   
  
 Infrequent:  Vasodilatation, postural hypotension, syncope, migraine, arrhythmia                         
 Rare:        Angina pectoris, coronary artery disorder, heart failure, myocardial infarct, phlebitis, pulmonary embolus, ventricular extrasystoles, ventricular tachycardia   
      
 DIGESTIVE SYSTEM   
  
 Frequent:    Abdomen pain, diarrhea, dyspepsia                                                           
 Infrequent:  Dysphagia, cholelithiasis, fecal impaction, flatulence, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, hepatitis, melena   
 Rare:        Gastroenteritis, hematemesis, hepatoma, intestinal obstruction, liver damage                
      
 HEMIC AND LYMPHATIC SYSTEM   
  
 Infrequent:  Ecchymosis, hypercholesteremia, anemia, hyperlipemia, leukopenia, leukocytosis, sepsis      
 Rare:        Petechia, purpura, thrombocythemia, thrombocytopenia                                        
      
 METABOLIC AND NUTRITIONAL SYSTEM   
  
 Infrequent:  Edema, hypothyroidism, weight loss                                                          
 Rare:        Adrenal cortex insufficiency, hyperglycemia, hypokalemia, hyponatremia, hypoproteinemia, respiratory acidosis   
      
 MUSCULOSKELETAL SYSTEM   
  
 Frequent:    Myasthenia, back pain                                                                       
 Infrequent:  Pathological fracture, arthralgia, arthritis, bursitis                                      
      
 NERVOUS SYSTEM   
  
 Frequent:    Depression, anxiety, paresthesia                                                            
 Infrequent:  Tremor, emotional lability, convulsion, paralysis, thinking abnormal, vertigo, abnormal dreams, agitation, depersonalization, euphoria, migraine, stupor, dysautonomia, neuralgia   
 Rare:        Dementia, hemiplegia, neuropathy                                                            
      
 RESPIRATORY SYSTEM   
  
 Infrequent:  Sinusitis, pneumonia, bronchitis                                                            
 Rare:        Asthma                                                                                      
      
 SKIN AND APPENDAGES   
  
 Frequent:    Rash, sweating, skin ulcer                                                                  
 Infrequent:  Pruritus, dry skin, acne, alopecia, urticaria                                               
 Rare:        Exfoliative dermatitis, herpes simplex, herpes zoster, skin carcinoma                       
      
 SPECIAL SENSES   
  
 Infrequent:  Ear pain, tinnitus, deafness, glaucoma, conjunctivitis, eye pain, optic neuritis, otitis media, retinal hemorrhage, visual field defect   
 Rare:        Iritis, keratitis, optic atrophy                                                            
      
 UROGENITAL SYSTEM   
  
 Infrequent:  Urinary urgency, cystitis, menorrhagia, pyelonephritis, urinary retention, kidney calculus, uterine fibroids enlarged, vaginal moniliasis, vaginitis   
 Rare:        Albuminuria, glycosuria, hematuria, metrorrhagia                                            
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
