<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="zelapar" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in more detail in the Warnings and Precautions section of labeling.



 *    Risk for Hypertension [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *    Risk of Serotonin Syndrome [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
 *    Falling Asleep During Activities of Daily Living and Somnolence [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ] 
 *    Hypotension/Orthostatic Hypotension [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   ] 
 *    Dyskinesia [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.5)   ] 
 *    Hallucinations/Psychotic-Like Behavior [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.6)   ] 
 *    Impulse Control / Compulsive Behaviors [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.7)   ] 
 *    Withdrawal Emergent Hyperpyrexia and Confusion [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.8)   ] 
 *    Melanoma [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.9)   ] 
 *    Irritation of the Buccal Mucosa [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.10)   ] 
 *    Risk for Phenylketonuric Patients [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.11)   ] 
 *    Effect on Renal Function [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.12)   ] 
      EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence at least 3% greater than on placebo) are constipation, skin disorders, vomiting, dizziness, dyskinesia, insomnia, dyspnea, myalgia, and rash  (6.1)  
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Valeant Pharmaceuticals North America LLC at 1-800-321-4576 or contact FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, the incidence of adverse reactions (number of unique patients experiencing an adverse reaction per total number of patients treated) observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the incidence of adverse reactions observed in clinical practice.



 Because the controlled trials performed during premarketing development both used a titration design (1.25 mg per day for 6 weeks, followed by 2.5 mg per day for 6 weeks), with a resultant confounding of time and dose, it was impossible to adequately evaluate the effects of dose on the incidence of adverse events.



 The most common adverse reactions (treatment difference incidence at least 3% greater than placebo incidence) reported in the double-blind, placebo-controlled trials during ZELAPAR treatment were constipation, skin disorders, vomiting, dizziness, dyskinesia, insomnia, dyspnea, myalgia, and rash (See  Table 1  ).



 Of the 194 patients treated with ZELAPAR in the double-blind, placebo-controlled trials, 5% discontinued due to adverse reactions compared to 1% of the 98 patients who received placebo. Most common adverse reactions causing discontinuation of treatment included dizziness, chest pain, accidental injury, and myasthenia.



     Incidence in controlled clinical trials  



   Table 1  lists the adverse events reported in the placebo-controlled trials after at least one dose of ZELAPAR (incidence 2% or greater).



 Table 1: Treatment-Emergent Adverse EventsPatients may have reported multiple adverse experiences during the study or at discontinuation; thus patients may be included in more than one category. Incidence in Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trials (Events &gt;=2% of Patients Treated with ZELAPAR and Numerically More Frequent than the Placebo Group) 
     Body System/        Adverse Event          ZELAPAR        1.25/2.5 mg        N=194        %          Placebo        N=98        %         
  
  Body as a Whole                      
  Back Pain                            5                            3                                       
  Chest Pain                           2                            0                                       
  Pain                                 8                            7                                       
  Cardiovascular System                
  Hypertension                         3                            2                                       
  Digestive System                     
  Constipation                         4                            0                                       
  Diarrhea                             2                            1                                       
  Dysphagia                            2                            1                                       
  Dyspepsia                            5                            3                                       
  Flatulence                           2                            1                                       
  Nausea                               11                           9                                       
  Stomatitis                           5                            4                                       
  Tooth Disorder                       2                            1                                       
  Vomiting                             3                            0                                       
  Hemic and Lymphatic System           
  Ecchymosis                           2                            0                                       
  Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders    
  Hypokalemia                          2                            0                                       
  Musculoskeletal System               
  Leg Cramps                           3                            1                                       
  Myalgia                              3                            0                                       
  Nervous System                       
  Ataxia                               3                            1                                       
  Depression                           2                            1                                       
  Dizziness                            11                           8                                       
  Dry Mouth                            4                            2                                       
  Dyskinesia                           6                            3                                       
  Hallucinations                       4                            2                                       
  Headache                             7                            6                                       
  Insomnia                             7                            4                                       
  Somnolence                           3                            2                                       
  Tremor                               3                            1                                       
  Respiratory System                   
  Dyspnea                              3                            0                                       
  Pharyngitis                          4                            2                                       
  Rhinitis                             7                            6                                       
  Skin and Appendages                  
  Rash                                 4                            1                                       
  Skin DisordersSkin disorders represent any new skin abnormality that would not be characterized as rash or neoplastic lesion. These include events such as skin ulcer, fungal dermatitis, skin hypertrophy, contact dermatitis, herpes simplex, dry skin, sweating, urticaria, and pruritus.    6                            2                                       
         Treatment-emergent adverse reactions for certain events were reported at a higher frequency by patients &gt;=65 years of age compared to patients &lt;65 years [see    Use in Specific Populations (8.5)    ].
 

 No consistent differences in the incidences of adverse reactions were observed between male and female patients.



 There were insufficient data to assess the impact of race on the incidence of adverse reactions.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    May cause hypertension above 2.5 mg/day  (5.1)   
 *    May cause serotonin syndrome when used with antidepressants  (5.2)   
 *    May cause falling asleep during activities of daily living  (5.3)   
 *    May cause hypotension/orthostatic hypotension  (5.4)   
 *    May cause or exacerbate dyskinesia  (5.5)   
 *    May cause hallucinations and psychotic-like behavior  (5.6)   
 *    May cause problems with impulse control and compulsive behaviors  (5.7)   
 *    Abrupt discontinuation may cause hyperpyrexia and confusion  (5.8)   
 *    Increased risk of melanoma  (5.9)   
 *    May cause irritation of the buccal mucosa  (5.10)   
 *    Increased risk for phenylketonuric patients (  5.11  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypertension



  ZELAPAR should not be used at daily doses exceeding those recommended (2.5 mg/day) because of the risks associated with non-selective inhibition of MAO [see   Drug Interactions (7.3)    and   Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)    ].



 The selectivity of ZELAPAR for MAO-B may not be absolute even at the recommended daily dose of 2.5 mg a day. The selectivity of MAO-B inhibitors, typically decreases and it is ultimately lost as the dose is increased beyond recommended doses. Hypertensive reactions associated with ingestion of tyramine containing foods have been reported even in patients taking the recommended daily dose of swallowed selegiline, a dose which is generally believed to be selective for MAO-B. Selectivity for MAO-B inhibition is gradually lost with increasing daily doses. An increase in tyramine sensitivity for blood pressure responses appears to begin at a dose of 5 mg ZELAPAR daily [see   Drug Interactions (7.5)    ]. However, the precise dose at which ZELAPAR becomes a non-selective inhibitor of all MAO enzymes in individual patients is unknown.



 Reports of hypertensive reactions have occurred in patients who ingested tyramine-containing consumables (i.e., food or drink) while receiving swallowed selegiline at the recommended dose (a dose believed to be relatively selective for MAO-B).



 The safe use of ZELAPAR at doses above 2.5 mg daily without dietary tyramine restrictions has not been established.



 A pharmacodynamic study showed increased tyramine sensitivity for increasing blood pressure and decreased selectivity for MAO-B with dosing above the recommended level (2.5 mg daily)[see   Clinical Pharmacology (12.2)    ].



 Uncontrolled hypertension has been reported when taking the recommended dose of swallowed selegiline and a sympathomimetic medication (ephedrine).



 After starting ZELAPAR, monitor patients for new onset hypertension or exacerbation of hypertension that is not adequately controlled.



    5.2 Serotonin Syndrome



  Serotonin syndrome and hyperpyrexia have been reported with the combined treatment of an antidepressant (e.g., selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors-SSRIs, serotonin-norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors-SNRIs, tricyclic antidepressants, tetracyclic antidepressants, triazolopyridine antidepressants) and a non-selective MAOI (e.g., phenelzine, tranylcypromine) or selective MAO-B inhibitors, such as selegiline (Eldepryl), rasagiline (AZILECT), and Zydis selegiline (ZELAPAR).



 Serotonin syndrome is a potentially serious condition, which can result in death. Typical clinical signs and symptoms include behavioral and cognitive/mental status changes (e.g., confusion, hypomania, hallucinations, agitation, delirium, headache, and coma), autonomic effects (e.g., syncope, shivering, sweating, high fever/hyperthermia, hypertension, hypotension, tachycardia, nausea, diarrhea), and somatic effects (e.g., muscular rigidity, myoclonus, muscle twitching, hyperreflexia manifested by clonus, and tremor).



 In the post-marketing period, fatal and non-fatal cases of serotonin syndrome have been reported in patients treated with antidepressants concomitantly with ZELAPAR [see   Contraindications (4)    and Drug Interactions (  7.1  ,  7.2  ,  7.3  )  ].



 Clinical studies of ZELAPAR did not allow concomitant use of any selective serotonin re-uptake inhibitor (e.g., fluoxetine-Prozac, fluvoxamine-Luvox, paroxetine-Paxil, sertraline, venlafaxine-Effexor, or nefazadone-Serzone) or any non-selective serotonin reuptake inhibiting antidepressant drug (except when taken at a low dose and only at night for the purpose of effective sleep) with ZELAPAR.



 Because the mechanisms responsible for these reactions are not fully understood, avoid the combination of ZELAPAR with any antidepressant. At least 14 days should elapse between discontinuation of ZELAPAR and initiation of treatment with a SSRI, SNRI, tricyclic, tetracyclic, or triazolopyridine antidepressant. In patients taking antidepressants with a long half-life (e.g., fluoxetine and its active metabolite), allow at least five weeks (perhaps longer, especially if fluoxetine has been prescribed chronically and/or at higher doses) to elapse between discontinuation of fluoxetine and initiation of ZELAPAR [see   Drug Interactions (7.6)    ].



    5.3 Falling Asleep During Activities of Daily Living and Somnolence



   Patients with Parkinson's disease treated with ZELAPAR or other drugs increasing dopaminergic tone have reported falling asleep while engaged in activities of daily living, including the operation of motor vehicles, which sometimes resulted in accidents. Although many of these patients reported somnolence, some did not perceive warning signs, such as excessive drowsiness, and believed that they were alert immediately prior to the event. Some of these events have been reported as late as one year after initiation of treatment.  



  It has been reported that falling asleep while engaged in activities of daily living always occurs in a setting of pre-existing somnolence, although patients may not give such a history. For this reason, prescribers should reassess patients for drowsiness or sleepiness especially since some of the events occur well after the start of treatment.  



  Somnolence may occur in patients receiving ZELAPAR. There was an increased risk for somnolence in geriatric patients (&gt;65 years) vs non-geriatric patients treated with ZELAPAR. Prescribers should also be aware that patients may not acknowledge drowsiness or sleepiness until directly questioned about drowsiness or sleepiness during specific activities. Patients should be advised to exercise caution while driving, operating machines, or working at heights during treatment with ZELAPAR. Patients who have already experienced somnolence and/or an episode of sudden sleep onset should not participate in these activities during treatment with ZELAPAR.  



  Before initiating treatment with ZELAPAR, advise patients about the potential to develop drowsiness and specifically ask about factors that may increase this risk, such as concomitant sedating medications and the presence of sleep disorders. If a patient develops daytime sleepiness or episodes of falling asleep during activities that require active participation (e.g., conversations, eating, etc.), ZELAPAR should ordinarily be discontinued. If a decision is made to continue ZELAPAR, patients should be advised not to drive and to avoid other potentially dangerous activities. There is insufficient information to establish whether dose reduction will eliminate episodes of falling asleep while engaged in activities of daily living  .



    5.4 Hypotension/Orthostatic Hypotension



  Assessments of orthostatic (supine and standing) blood pressures at different times throughout the 12 week study period in two controlled trials showed that the frequency of orthostatic hypotension (&gt;20 mm Hg decrease in systolic blood pressure and/or &gt;10 mm Hg decrease in diastolic blood pressure) was greater with ZELAPAR treatment than with placebo treatment. Patients taking ZELAPAR were most likely to experience a decline in systolic and diastolic blood pressure at 8 weeks (2 weeks after initiating 2.5 mg ZELAPAR). At that time, the incidence of systolic orthostatic hypotension was about 21% in ZELAPAR-treated patients and 9% in placebo-treated patients. The incidence of diastolic orthostatic hypotension was about 12% in ZELAPAR-treated patients and about 4% in placebo-treated patients. Thus, it appears that there may be an increased risk for orthostatic hypotension in the period after increasing the daily dose of ZELAPAR  (r)  from 1.25 to 2.5 mg.



 The incidence of orthostatic hypotension was higher in geriatric patients (&gt;=65 years) than in non-geriatric patients. In the geriatric patients, orthostatic hypotension occurred in about 3% of ZELAPAR-treated patients compared to 0% of placebo-treated patients.



    5.5 Dyskinesia



  ZELAPAR may potentiate dopaminergic side effects of levodopa and may cause dyskinesia or exacerbate preexisting dyskinesia. In controlled trials, the incidence of dyskinesia was 6% in ZELAPAR-treated patients and 3% in placebo-treated patients. Decreasing the dose of levodopa may lessen dyskinesia. The incidence of dyskinesia causing study discontinuation was greater on ZELAPAR than on placebo.



    5.6 Hallucinations/Psychotic-Like Behavior



  In controlled trials, hallucination was reported by 4% of ZELAPAR-treated patients and 2% in placebo-treated patients. Hallucinations led to drug discontinuation and premature withdrawal from clinical trials in about 1% of ZELAPAR-treated patients, compared to no patient on placebo.



 Postmarketing reports indicate that patients may experience new or worsening mental status and behavioral changes, which may be severe, including psychotic-like behavior during ZELAPAR treatment or after starting or increasing the dose of ZELAPAR. Other drugs prescribed to improve the symptoms of Parkinson's disease can have similar effects on thinking and behavior. This abnormal thinking and behavior can consist of one or more of a variety of manifestations including paranoid ideation, delusions, hallucinations, confusion, psychotic-like behavior, disorientation, aggressive behavior, agitation, and delirium.



 Patients with a major psychotic disorder should ordinarily not be treated with ZELAPAR because of the risk of exacerbating psychosis. In addition, certain medications used to treat psychosis may exacerbate the symptoms of Parkinson's disease and may decrease the effectiveness of ZELAPAR [see   Drug Interactions (7.8)    ].



    5.7 Impulse Control/Compulsive Behaviors



   Case reports suggest that patients can experience intense urges to gamble, increased sexual urges, intense urges to spend money, binge eating, and/or other intense urges, and the inability to control these urges while taking one or more of the medications, including ZELAPAR, that increase central dopaminergic tone and that are generally used for the treatment of Parkinson's disease. In some cases, although not all, these urges were reported to have stopped when the dose was reduced or the medication was discontinued. Because patients may not recognize these behaviors as abnormal, it is important for prescribers to specifically ask patients or their caregivers about the development of new or increased gambling urges, sexual urges, uncontrolled spending, binge eating, or other urges while being treated with ZELAPAR. Physicians should consider dose reduction or stopping the medication if a patient develops such urges while taking ZELAPAR  .



    5.8 Withdrawal Emergent Hyperpyrexia and Confusion



  Although not reported with ZELAPAR in the clinical development program, a symptom complex resembling the neuroleptic malignant syndrome (characterized by elevated temperature, muscular rigidity, altered consciousness, and autonomic instability), with no other obvious etiology, has been reported in association with rapid dose reduction, withdrawal of, or changes in antiparkinsonian therapy.



    5.9 Melanoma



  Epidemiological studies have shown that patients with Parkinson's disease have a higher risk (2- to approximately 6-fold higher) of developing melanoma than the general population. Whether the increased risk observed was due to Parkinson's disease or other factors, such as drugs used to treat Parkinson's disease, is unclear.



 For the reasons stated above, patients and providers are advised to monitor for melanomas frequently and on a regular basis when using ZELAPAR for any indication. Ideally, periodic skin examinations should be performed by appropriately qualified individuals (e.g., dermatologists).



    5.10 Irritation of the Buccal Mucosa



  In the controlled clinical trials, periodic examinations of the tongue and oral mucosa were performed. At the end of the study, the frequency of mild oropharyngeal abnormality (e.g., swallowing pain, mouth pain, discrete areas of focal reddening, multiple foci of reddening, edema, and/or ulceration) in patients without similar abnormality at baseline was 10% in ZELAPAR-treated patients compared to 3% in placebo-treated patients.



    5.11 Risk for Phenylketonuric Patients



  It is important to note that each ZELAPAR tablet contains 1.25 mg phenylalanine (a component of aspartame). Patients taking the 2.5 mg dose of ZELAPAR will receive 2.5 mg phenylalanine.



    5.12 Effect on Renal Function



  Small increments in serum BUN and creatinine have been observed in patients treated with high dose ZELAPAR (10 mg daily; 4 times the recommended dose).
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
