<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="zemaira" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Serious adverse reactions identified during postmarketing use were hypersensitivity reactions  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1  ,  5.2)  ]  .



 The serious adverse reactions reported following administration of Zemaira in clinical trials included one event each in separate subjects of bronchitis and dyspnea, and one event each in a single subject of chest pain, cerebral ischemia and convulsion. The most common adverse reactions (ARs) occurring in at least 5% of subjects receiving Zemaira in all clinical trials were headache, sinusitis, upper respiratory infection, bronchitis, asthenia, cough increased, fever, injection site hemorrhage, rhinitis, sore throat, and vasodilation.



   EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions occurring in at least 5% of subjects receiving Zemaira in all clinical trials were headache, sinusitis, upper respiratory infection, bronchitis, asthenia, cough increased, fever, injection site hemorrhage, rhinitis, sore throat, and vasodilation (  6  ).  To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact CSL Behring Pharmacovigilance at 1-866-915-6958 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

    Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug product cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.  



 Four clinical trials were conducted with Zemaira: 1) a controlled, double-blind trial in 44 subjects, who received a 60 mg/kg dose of either Zemaira (30 subjects) or Prolastin  (r)  (a commercially available Alpha1-Proteinase Inhibitor [Human] product) (14 subjects) weekly for 10 weeks, followed by an open-label phase in which 43 subjects received Zemaira weekly for 14 weeks; 2) an open-label trial in 9 subjects who received a 60 mg/kg dose of Zemaira weekly for 26 weeks, followed by a 7-week to 22-week extension; 3) a crossover, double-blind trial in 18 subjects who received a single 60 mg/kg dose of Zemaira and a single 60 mg/kg dose of Prolastin; and 4) an open-label trial of 19 subjects who received a single 15 mg/kg (2 subjects), 30 mg/kg (5 subjects), 60 mg/kg (6 subjects), or 120 mg/kg (6 subjects) dose of Zemaira. A total of 89 subjects were administered Zemaira in clinical trials, 23 of whom participated in more than 1 trial  [see  Clinical Studies (14)  ]  .



 Table 1 summarizes the ARs, expressed as events per subject-year, and the corresponding number of ARs per infusion, expressed as % of all infusions, for each treatment in all clinical trials of Zemaira.



 Table 1: Overall Adverse Reactions (ARs) and Serious ARs 
                                 Number of Subjects(Events per Subject-Year)  Number of Infusions(% of all Infusions)   
 Zemaira(n=66, SY=28.72)         Prolastin(n=32), SY=3.83)   Zemaira(n=1296)     Prolastin(n=160)    
  
 ARs (AEs assessed by investigator as at least possibly related or occurring during or within 72 hours after the end of the infusion or for which causality assessment was missing or indeterminate).      54 (5.6)            16 (3.8)           160 (12.3)          31 (19.4)       
 Serious ARs (Serious AEs assessed by investigator as at least possibly related or occurring during or within 72 hours after the end of the infusion or for which causality assessment was missing or indeterminate).       4 (0.2)            1 (1.0)             6 (0.5)             1 (0.6)        
           Table 2 summarizes the ARs occurring in 5% or more (&gt;3) subjects, expressed as events per subject-year, and the corresponding number of ARs per infusion, expressed as % of all infusions, for each treatment in all clinical trials of Zemaira.
 

 Table 2: Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=5% of Subjects 
 ARs (AEs assessed by investigator as at least possibly related or occurring during or within 72 hours after the end of the infusion or for which causality assessment was missing or indeterminate).  Number of Subjects(Events per Subject-Year)  Number of Infusions(% of all Infusions)   
 Zemaira(n=66, SY=28.72)         Prolastin(n=32, SY=3.83)  Zemaira(n=1296)    Prolastin(n=160)     
  
 Headache                            13 (0.7)          5 (1.3)            19 (1.5)              5 (3.1)         
 Sinusitis                           10 (0.5)          1 (0.3)            13 (1.0)              1 (0.6)         
 Upper Respiratory Infection         10 (0.4)          1 (0.3)            10 (0.8)              1 (0.6)         
 Bronchitis                          5 (0.2)           0 (0.0)             6 (0.5)              0 (0.0)         
 Asthenia                            5 (0.2)           2 (0.5)             5 (0.4)              2 (1.3)         
 Cough Increased                     5 (0.2)           1 (0.5)             5 (0.4)              2 (1.3)         
 Fever                               4 (0.1)           0 (0.0)             4 (0.3)              0 (0.0)         
 Injection Site Hemorrhage           4 (0.1)           0 (0.0)             4 (0.3)              0 (0.0)         
 Rhinitis                            4 (0.1)           0 (0.0)             4 (0.3)              0 (0.0)         
 Sore Throat                         4 (0.1)           0 (0.0)             4 (0.3)              0 (0.0)         
 Vasodilation                        4 (0.1)           1 (0.3)             4 (0.3)              1 (0.6)         
           Diffuse interstitial lung disease was noted on a routine chest x-ray of one subject at Week 24. Causality could not be determined.
 

 In a retrospective analysis, during the 10-week blinded portion of the 24-week clinical trial, 6 subjects (20%) of the 30 treated with Zemaira had a total of 7 exacerbations of their chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD). Nine subjects (64%) of the 14 treated with Prolastin had a total of 11 exacerbations of their COPD. The observed difference between groups was 44% (95% confidence interval [CI] from 8% to 70%). Over the entire 24-week treatment period, of the 30 subjects in the Zemaira treatment group, 7 subjects (23%) had a total of 11 exacerbations of their COPD.



 In the 24-week double-blind trial, Zemaira-treated subjects were tested for HAV, HBV, HCV, HIV, and parvovirus B19 (B19V), and no evidence of virus transmission was observed.



   6.2 Immunogenicity

  As with all therapeutic proteins, there is potential for immunogenicity. No anti-A1PI antibodies have been detected in clinical trials of Zemaira. The detection of antibody formation is highly dependent on the sensitivity and specificity of the assay. Additionally, the observed incidence of antibody (including neutralizing antibody) positivity in an assay may be influenced by several factors including assay methodology, sample handling, timing of sample collection, concomitant medications, and underlying disease. For these reasons, comparison of the incidence of antibodies to Zemaira with the incidence of antibodies to other products may be misleading.



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

    Because postmarketing reporting of adverse reactions is voluntary and from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate the frequency of these reactions or establish a causal relationship to product exposure.  



 Table 3 lists the ARs that have been identified during postmarketing use of Zemaira. This list does not include reactions already reported in clinical trials with Zemaira  [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  .



 Table 3: ARs Reported During the Postmarketing Use of Zemaira 
 System Organ Class                        Preferred Term/Symptoms                                        
  
 Blood and lymphatic system disorders      Lymph node pain                                                
 Gastrointestinal disorders                Nausea                                                         
 General disorders and administration site conditions  Chills, infusion site reactions, facial, periorbital, lip and extremity swelling   
 Immune system disorders                   Hypersensitivity, anaphylactic reactions, tachycardia, hypotension, confusion, syncope, oxygen consumption decreased, pharyngeal edema   
 Nervous system disorders                  Hypoesthesia, paresthesia                                      
 Skin disorders                            Hyperhidrosis, pruritus, rash including exfoliative and generalized, urticaria   
 Vascular disorders                        Flushing                                                       
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Use caution when administering Zemaira to individuals who have experienced anaphylaxis or severe systemic reactions to another A1-PI product (  5.1  ). 
 *  Patients with selective or severe IgA deficiency can develop antibodies to IgA and, therefore, have a greater risk of developing potentially severe hypersensitivity and anaphylactic reactions. If anaphylactic or severe anaphylactoid reactions occur, discontinue the infusion immediately (  5.2  ). 
 *  Because Zemaira is made from human plasma, it may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents (e.g., viruses, and theoretically, the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease [CJD] agent) (  5.3  ). 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity to Other A1-PI Products



  Caution should be used when administering Zemaira to individuals who have experienced anaphylaxis or severe systemic reaction to another A1-PI product. IF ANAPHYLACTIC OR SEVERE ANAPHYLACTOID REACTIONS OCCUR, DISCONTINUE THE INFUSION IMMEDIATELY  . Have epinephrine and other appropriate supportive therapy available for the treatment of any acute anaphylactic or anaphylactoid reaction. Zemaira is contraindicated in patients with a history of anaphylaxis or severe systemic reactions to Zemaira or A1-PI protein.



    5.2 Hypersensitivity to IgA



  Zemaira may contain trace amounts of IgA. Patients with selective or severe IgA deficiency can develop antibodies to IgA and, therefore, have a greater risk of developing potentially severe hypersensitivity and anaphylactic reactions. IF ANAPHYLACTIC OR SEVERE ANAPHYLACTOID REACTIONS OCCUR, DISCONTINUE THE INFUSION IMMEDIATELY  . Have epinephrine and other appropriate supportive therapy available for the treatment of any acute anaphylactic or anaphylactoid reaction. Zemaira is contraindicated in IgA-deficient patients with antibodies against IgA, due to the risk of severe hypersensitivity.



    5.3 Transmissible Infectious Agents



  Because Zemaira is made from human plasma, it may carry a risk of transmitting infectious agents (e.g., viruses, and theoretically the Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease [CJD] agent). The risk of infectious agent transmission has been reduced by screening plasma donors for prior exposure to certain viruses, testing for the presence of certain current virus infections, and including virus inactivation/removal steps in the manufacturing process for Zemaira [see  Description (11)  ]  . Despite these measures, Zemaira, like other products made from human plasma, may still potentially contain human pathogenic agents, including those not yet known or identified. Thus, the risk of transmission of infectious agents cannot be totally eliminated.



 All infections thought by a physician to have been possibly transmitted by this product should be reported by the physician or other healthcare provider to the CSL Behring Pharmacovigilance Department at 1-866-915-6958 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
