<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="zemplar" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Zemplar has been evaluated for safety in clinical studies in 609 CKD Stage 5 patients. In four, placebo-controlled, double-blind, multicenter studies, discontinuation of therapy due to any adverse event occurred in 6.5% of 62 patients treated with Zemplar (dosage titrated as tolerated, see  CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY -  Clinical Studies    ) and 2.0% of 51 patients treated with placebo for 1 to 3 months. Adverse events occurring in the Zemplar group at a frequency of 2% or greater and with an incidence greater than that in the placebo group, regardless of causality, are presented in the following table:



 Adverse Event Incidence Rates for All Treated Patients In All Placebo-Controlled Studies 
   Adverse Event              Zemplar (n = 62)    %      Placebo (n = 51)    %     
   Overall                    71                         78                        
   Cardiac Disorders                                                               
     Palpitations           3.2                        0.0                         
   Gastrointestinal Disorders                                                           
     Dry Mouth              3.2                        2.0                         
     Gastrointestinal Hemorrhage  4.8                        2.0                         
     Nausea                 12.9                       7.8                         
     Vomiting               8.1                        5.9                         
   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions                                                           
     Chills                 4.8                        2.0                         
     Edema                  6.5                        0.0                         
     Malaise                3.2                        0.0                         
     Pyrexia                4.8                        2.0                         
   Infections and Infestations                                                           
     Influenza              4.8                        3.9                         
     Pneumonia              4.8                        0.0                         
     Sepsis                 4.8                        2.0                         
   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders                                                           
     Arthralgia             4.8                        3.9                         
      A patient who reported the same medical term more than once was counted only once for that medical term.
 

 Safety parameters (changes in mean Ca, P, Ca * P) in an open-label safety study up to 13 months in duration support the long-term safety of Zemplar in this patient population (see    CLINICAL STUDIES    ).



   Other Adverse Reactions Observed During Clinical Evaluation of Zemplar Injection

  The following adverse reactions, with a causal relationship to Zemplar, occurred in &lt;2% of the Zemplar treated patients in the above double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trial data set. In addition, the following also includes adverse reactions reported in Zemplar-treated patients who participated in other studies (non placebo-controlled), including double-blind, active-controlled and open-label studies:



   Blood and Lymphatic System Disorders:  



 Anemia, lymphadenopathy



   Cardiac Disorders:  



 Arrhythmia, atrial flutter, cardiac arrest



   Ear and Labyrinth Disorders  :



 Ear discomfort



   Endocrine Disorders:  



 Hyperparathyroidism, hypoparathyroidism



   Eye Disorders  :



 Conjunctivitis, glaucoma, ocular hyperemia



   Gastrointestinal Disorders  :



 Abdominal discomfort, constipation, diarrhea, dysphagia, gastritis, intestinal ischemia, rectal hemorrhage



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  



 Asthenia, chest discomfort, chest pain, condition aggravated, edema peripheral, fatigue, feeling abnormal, gait disturbance, injection site extravasation, injection site pain, pain, swelling, thirst



   Infections and Infestations:  



 Nasopharyngitis, upper respiratory tract infection, vaginal infection



   Investigations:  



 Aspartate aminotransferase increased, bleeding time prolonged, heart rate irregular, laboratory test abnormal, weight decreased



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  



 Decreased appetite, hypercalcemia, hyperkalemia, hyperphosphatemia, hypocalcemia



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  



 Joint stiffness, muscle twitching, myalgia



   Neoplasms Benign, Malignant and Unspecified:  



 Breast cancer



   Nervous System Disorders:  



 Cerebrovascular accident, dizziness, dysgeusia, headache, hypoesthesia, myoclonus, paresthesia, syncope, unresponsive to stimuli



   Psychiatric Disorders  :



 Agitation, confusional state, delirium, insomnia, nervousness, restlessness



   Reproductive System and Breast Disorders  :



 Breast pain, erectile dysfunction



   Respiratory, Thoracic and Mediastinal Disorders:  



 Cough, dyspnea, orthopnea, pulmonary edema, wheezing



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  



 Alopecia, blister, hirsutism, night sweats, rash pruritic, pruritus, skin burning sensation



   Vascular Disorders:  



 Hypertension, hypotension



   Additional Adverse Events Reported During Post-marketing Experience

  Allergic reactions, such as rash, urticaria, and angioedema (including laryngeal edema) have been reported.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
