<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="zerit" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6    ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the labeling:



 *    lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis [see   Boxed Warning   and   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ] 
 *    hepatic toxicity [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ] 
 *    neurologic symptoms and motor weakness [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ] 
 *    pancreatitis [see   Boxed Warning   and   Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   ] 
 *    lipoatrophy/lipodystrophy [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.5)   ] 
    When ZERIT is used in combination with other agents with similar toxicities, the incidence of adverse reactions may be higher than when stavudine is used alone.
 

    EXCERPT:    *    In adults, the most common adverse reactions are headache, diarrhea, neuropathy, rash, nausea, and vomiting.  (6.1)   
 *    Adverse reactions in pediatric patients were consistent with those seen in adults.  (6.2)   
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Bristol-Myers Squibb at 1-800-721-5072 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1    Clinical Trial Experience in Adults

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



 Selected adverse reactions that occurred in adult patients receiving ZERIT in a controlled monotherapy study (Study AI455-019) are provided in  Table 2  .



 Table 2: Selected Adverse Reactions in Study AI455-019a (Monotherapy) 
                                          Percent (%)                   
   Adverse Reaction                       ZERIT  b      (40 mg twice daily)    (n=412)      zidovudine    (200 mg 3 times daily)    (n=402)     
  
   a    The incidences reported included all severity grades and all reactions regardless of causality.  b    Median duration of stavudine therapy = 79 weeks; median duration of zidovudine therapy = 53 weeks.   
  
  Headache                               54                             49                                  
  Diarrhea                               50                             44                                  
  Peripheral Neurologic     Symptoms/Neuropathy    52                             39                                  
  Rash                                   40                             35                                  
  Nausea and Vomiting                    39                             44                                  
         Pancreatitis was observed in 3 of the 412 adult patients who received ZERIT in study AI455-019.
 

 Selected adverse reactions that occurred in antiretroviral-naive adult patients receiving ZERIT from two controlled combination studies are provided in  Table 3  .



 Table 3: Selected Adverse Reactionsa in START 1 and START 2b Studies (Combination Therapy) 
                                    Percent (%)       
                                    START 1            START 2  b        
   Adverse Reaction                 ZERIT +    lamivudine +    indinavir    (n=100  c  )      zidovudine +    lamivudine +    indinavir    (n=102)      ZERIT +    didanosine +    indinavir    (n=102  c  )      zidovudine +    lamivudine +    indinavir    (n=103)     
  
   a    The incidences reported included all severity grades and all reactions regardless of causality.  b    START 2 compared two triple-combination regimens in 205 treatment-naive patients. Patients received either ZERIT (40 mg twice daily) plus didanosine plus indinavir or zidovudine plus lamivudine plus indinavir.  c    Duration of stavudine therapy = 48 weeks.   
  
  Nausea                           43                 63                 53                 67                 
  Diarrhea                         34                 16                 45                 39                 
  Headache                         25                 26                 46                 37                 
  Rash                             18                 13                 30                 18                 
  Vomiting                         18                 33                 30                 35                 
  Peripheral Neurologic     Symptoms/Neuropathy    8                  7                  21                 10                 
           Selected laboratory abnormalities reported in a controlled monotherapy study (Study AI455-019) are provided in  Table 4  .
 

 Table 4: Selected Laboratory Abnormalities in Study AI455-019a,b 
                                  Percent (%)                       
   Parameter                      ZERIT    (40 mg twice daily)    (n=412)      zidovudine    (200 mg 3 times daily)    (n=402)     
  
   a    Data presented for patients for whom laboratory evaluations were performed.  b    Median duration of stavudine therapy = 79 weeks; median duration of zidovudine therapy = 53 weeks.ULN = upper limit of normal.   
  
  AST (SGOT)     (&gt;5.0 * ULN)    11                                 10                                      
  ALT (SGPT)     (&gt;5.0 * ULN)    13                                 11                                      
  Amylase     (&gt;=1.4 * ULN)      14                                 13                                      
         Selected laboratory abnormalities reported in two controlled combination studies are provided in  Tables 5  and  6  .
 

 Table 5: Selected Laboratory Abnormalities in START 1 and START 2 Studies (Grades 3-4) 
                            Percent (%)         
                            START 1              START 2             
   Parameter                ZERIT +    lamivudine +    indinavir    (n=100)      zidovudine +    lamivudine +    indinavir    (n=102)      ZERIT +    didanosine +    indinavir    (n=102)      zidovudine +    lamivudine +    indinavir    (n=103)     
  
 ULN = upper limit of normal.   
  
  Bilirubin     (&gt;2.6 * ULN)    7                    6                    16                   8                    
  AST (SGOT)     (&gt;5 * ULN)    5                    2                    7                    7                    
  ALT (SGPT)     (&gt;5 * ULN)    6                    2                    8                    5                    
  GGT     (&gt;5 * ULN)       2                    2                    5                    2                    
  Lipase     (&gt;2 * ULN)    6                    3                    5                    5                    
  Amylase     (&gt;2 * ULN)    4                    &lt;1                   8                    2                    
          Table 6: Selected Laboratory Abnormalities in START 1 and START 2 Studies (All Grades) 
                          Percent (%)          
                          START 1               START 2              
   Parameter              ZERIT +    lamivudine +    indinavir    (n=100)      zidovudine +    lamivudine +    indinavir    (n=102)      ZERIT +    didanosine +    indinavir    (n=102)      zidovudine +    lamivudine +    indinavir    (n=103)     
  
  Total Bilirubin        65                    60                    68                   55                    
  AST (SGOT)             42                    20                    53                   20                    
  ALT (SGPT)             40                    20                    50                   18                    
  GGT                    15                    8                     28                   12                    
  Lipase                 27                    12                    26                   19                    
  Amylase                21                    19                    31                   17                    
             6.2    Clinical Trial Experience in Pediatric Patients
   Adverse reactions and serious laboratory abnormalities reported in pediatric patients from birth through adolescence during clinical trials were similar in type and frequency to those seen in adult patients. [See    Use in Specific Populations (8.4)    .]



   6.3    Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postmarketing use of ZERIT. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. These reactions have been chosen for inclusion due to their seriousness, frequency of reporting, causal connection to ZERIT, or a combination of these factors.



 *      Body as a Whole: abdominal pain, allergic reaction, chills/fever, and redistribution/accumulation of body fat [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.5)    ]. 
 *      Digestive Disorders: anorexia. 
 *      Exocrine Gland Disorders: pancreatitis, including fatal cases [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.4)    ]. 
 *      Hematologic Disorders: anemia, leukopenia, thrombocytopenia, neutropenia, and macrocytosis. 
 *      Liver: symptomatic hyperlactatemia/lactic acidosis and hepatic steatosis [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.1)    ], hepatitis and liver failure. 
 *      Metabolic Disorders: lipoatrophy, lipodystrophy [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.5)    ], diabetes mellitus and hyperglycemia. 
 *      Musculoskeletal: myalgia. 
 *      Nervous System: insomnia, severe motor weakness (most often reported in the setting of lactic acidosis) [see    Warnings and Precautions (5.1   ,   5.3)    ]. 
      Use with Didanosine- and Hydroxyurea-Based Regimens  
 

 When stavudine is used in combination with other agents with similar toxicities, the incidence of these toxicities may be higher than when stavudine is used alone. Thus, patients treated with ZERIT in combination with didanosine, with or without hydroxyurea, may be at increased risk for pancreatitis and hepatotoxicity, which may be fatal, and severe peripheral neuropathy [see    Warnings and Precautions (5)    ]. The combination of ZERIT and hydroxyurea, with or without didanosine, should be avoided.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS and HEPATOMEGALY with STEATOSIS; PANCREATITIS 

  WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS and HEPATOMEGALY with STEATOSIS; PANCREATITIS 

    Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogues alone or in combination, including stavudine and other antiretrovirals. Fatal lactic acidosis has been reported in pregnant women who received the combination of stavudine and didanosine with other antiretroviral agents. The combination of stavudine and didanosine should be used with caution during pregnancy and is recommended only if the potential benefit clearly outweighs the potential risk [see     Warnings and Precautions (5.1)    ].  



   Fatal and nonfatal pancreatitis have occurred during therapy when ZERIT was part of a combination regimen that included didanosine in both treatment-naive and treatment-experienced patients, regardless of degree of immunosuppression [see     Warnings and Precautions (5.4)    ].  



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: LACTIC ACIDOSIS and HEPATOMEGALY withSTEATOSIS; PANCREATITIS



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases. Fatal lactic acidosis has been reported in pregnant women who received the combination of stavudine and didanosine. (5.1) 
 *  Fatal and nonfatal pancreatitis have occurred when ZERIT was part of a combination regimen that included didanosine. (5.4) 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5    WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *     Lactic acidosis/severe hepatomegaly with steatosis: Suspend treatment with ZERIT in patients who develop clinical symptoms or signs with or without laboratory findings.  (5.1)   
 *     Hepatic toxicity: May be severe, fatal. Consider interruption or discontinuation. Avoid use in combination with didanosine and hydroxyurea. Risk of hepatic decompensation exists when used in combination with interferon and ribavirin; closely monitor and consider discontinuation of stavudine.  (5.2)   
 *     Neurologic symptoms: Motor weakness, most often seen in the setting of lactic acidosis, may mimic Guillain-Barre syndrome; discontinue treatment. Monitor for peripheral neuropathy, which can be severe; treatment discontinuation should be considered.  (5.3)   
 *     Pancreatitis: Suspend treatment, resume with particular caution and close monitoring and avoid use in combination with didanosine.  (5.4)   
 *    Patients may develop redistribution/accumulation of body fat, monitor for signs and symptoms of lipoatrophy/lipodystrophy. Alternative antiretrovirals should be considered.  (5.5)   
 *    Patients may develop immune reconstitution syndrome.  (5.6)   
    
 

   5.1    Lactic Acidosis/Severe Hepatomegaly with Steatosis



   Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogues alone or in combination, including stavudine and other antiretrovirals.  Although relative rates of lactic acidosis have not been assessed in prospective well-controlled trials, longitudinal cohort and retrospective studies suggest that this infrequent event may be more often associated with antiretroviral combinations containing stavudine. Female gender, obesity, and prolonged nucleoside exposure may be risk factors. Fatal lactic acidosis has been reported in pregnant women who received the combination of stavudine and didanosine with other antiretroviral agents. The combination of stavudine and didanosine should be used with caution during pregnancy and is recommended only if the potential benefit clearly outweighs the potential risk [see   Use in Specific Populations (8.1)    ].



 Particular caution should be exercised when administering ZERIT to any patient with known risk factors for liver disease; however, cases of lactic acidosis have also been reported in patients with no known risk factors. Generalized fatigue, digestive symptoms (nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, and unexplained weight loss); respiratory symptoms (tachypnea and dyspnea); or neurologic symptoms, including motor weakness [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)    ] might be indicative of the development of symptomatic hyperlactatemia or lactic acidosis syndrome.



 Treatment with ZERIT (stavudine) should be suspended in any patient who develops clinical or laboratory findings suggestive of symptomatic hyperlactatemia, lactic acidosis, or pronounced hepatotoxicity (which may include hepatomegaly and steatosis even in the absence of marked transaminase elevations). Permanent discontinuation of ZERIT should be considered for patients with confirmed lactic acidosis.



    5.2    Hepatic Toxicity



  The safety and efficacy of ZERIT have not been established in HIV-infected patients with significant underlying liver disease. During combination antiretroviral therapy, patients with preexisting liver dysfunction, including chronic active hepatitis, have an increased frequency of liver function abnormalities, including severe and potentially fatal hepatic adverse events, and should be monitored according to standard practice. If there is evidence of worsening liver disease in such patients, interruption or discontinuation of treatment must be considered.



 Hepatotoxicity and hepatic failure resulting in death were reported during postmarketing surveillance in HIV-infected patients treated with hydroxyurea and other antiretroviral agents. Fatal hepatic events were reported most often in patients treated with the combination of hydroxyurea, didanosine, and stavudine. This combination should be avoided. [See   Adverse Reactions (6)    .]



      Use with Interferon and Ribavirin-Based Regimens    



   In vitro  studies have shown ribavirin can reduce the phosphorylation of pyrimidine nucleoside analogues such as stavudine. Although no evidence of a pharmacokinetic or pharmacodynamic (eg, loss of HIV-1/HCV virologic suppression) interaction was seen when ribavirin was coadministered with stavudine in HIV-1/HCV co-infected patients [see   Drug Interactions (7)    ], hepatic decompensation (some fatal) has occurred in HIV-1/HCV co-infected patients receiving combination antiretroviral therapy for HIV-1 and interferon and ribavirin  . Patients receiving interferon with or without ribavirin and stavudine should be closely monitored for treatment-associated toxicities, especially hepatic decompensation. Discontinuation of stavudine should be considered as medically appropriate. Dose reduction or discontinuation of interferon, ribavirin, or both should also be considered if worsening clinical toxicities are observed, including hepatic decompensation (eg, Child-Pugh &gt;6) (see the full prescribing information for interferon and ribavirin  ).



    5.3    Neurologic Symptoms



  Motor weakness has been reported rarely in patients receiving combination antiretroviral therapy including ZERIT. Most of these cases occurred in the setting of lactic acidosis. The evolution of motor weakness may mimic the clinical presentation of Guillain-Barre syndrome (including respiratory failure). If motor weakness develops, ZERIT should be discontinued. Symptoms may continue or worsen following discontinuation of therapy.



 Peripheral sensory neuropathy, manifested by numbness, tingling, or pain in the hands or feet, has been reported in patients receiving ZERIT therapy. Peripheral neuropathy, which can be severe, is dose related and occurs more frequently in patients with advanced HIV-1 disease, a history of peripheral neuropathy, or in patients receiving other drugs that have been associated with neuropathy, including didanosine [see   Adverse Reactions (6)    ].



 Patients should be monitored for the development of peripheral neuropathy. Stavudine-related peripheral neuropathy may resolve if therapy is withdrawn promptly. If peripheral neuropathy develops permanent discontinuation of ZERIT should be considered. In some cases, symptoms may worsen temporarily following discontinuation of therapy.



    5.4    Pancreatitis



  Fatal and nonfatal pancreatitis have occurred during therapy when ZERIT was part of a combination regimen that included didanosine in both treatment-naive and treatment-experienced patients, regardless of degree of immunosuppression. The combination of ZERIT and didanosine and any other agents that are toxic to the pancreas should be suspended in patients with suspected pancreatitis. Reinstitution of ZERIT after a confirmed diagnosis of pancreatitis should be undertaken with particular caution and close patient monitoring; avoid use in combination with didanosine.



    5.5    Fat Redistribution



  Redistribution/accumulation of body fat including central obesity, dorsocervical fat enlargement (buffalo hump), peripheral wasting, facial wasting, breast enlargement, and "cushingoid appearance" have been observed in patients receiving antiretroviral therapy.



 In randomized controlled trials of treatment-naive patients, clinical lipoatrophy or lipodystrophy developed in a higher proportion of patients treated with stavudine compared to other nucleosides (tenofovir or abacavir). Dual energy x-ray absorptiometry (DEXA) scans demonstrated overall limb fat loss in stavudine-treated patients compared to limb fat gain or no gain in patients treated with other nucleosides (abacavir, tenofovir, or zidovudine). The incidence and severity of lipoatrophy or lipodystrophy are cumulative over time with stavudine-containing regimens. In clinical trials, switching from stavudine to other nucleosides (tenofovir or abacavir) resulted in increases in limb fat with modest to no improvements in clinical lipoatrophy. Patients receiving ZERIT should be monitored for symptoms or signs of lipoatrophy or lipodystrophy and questioned about body changes related to lipoatrophy or lipodystrophy. Given the potential risks of using ZERIT including lipoatrophy or lipodystrophy, a benefit-risk assessment for each patient should be made and an alternative antiretroviral should be considered.



    5.6    Immune Reconstitution Syndrome



  Immune reconstitution syndrome has been reported in patients treated with combination antiretroviral therapy, including ZERIT. During the initial phase of combination antiretroviral treatment, patients whose immune system responds may develop an inflammatory response to indolent or residual opportunistic infections (such as Mycobacterium avium  infection, cytomegalovirus, Pneumocystis jiroveci  pneumonia (PCP), or tuberculosis), which may necessitate further evaluation and treatment.



 Autoimmune disorders (such as Graves' disease, polymyositis, and Guillain-Barre syndrome) have also been reported to occur in the setting of immune reconstitution; however, the time to onset is more variable, and can occur many months after initiation of treatment.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
