<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="zestoretic" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  ZESTORETIC has been evaluated for safety in 930 patients including 100 patients treated for 50 weeks or more.



 In clinical trials with ZESTORETIC no adverse experiences peculiar to this combination drug have been observed.  Adverse experiences that have occurred have been limited to those that have been previously reported with lisinopril or hydrochlorothiazide.



 The most frequent clinical adverse experiences in controlled trials (including open label extensions) with any combination of lisinopril and hydrochlorothiazide were:  dizziness (7.5%), headache (5.2%), cough (3.9%), fatigue (3.7%) and orthostatic effects (3.2%) all of which were more common than in placebo-treated patients.  Generally, adverse experiences were mild and transient in nature, but see  WARNINGS  regarding angioedema and excessive hypotension or syncope.  Discontinuation of therapy due to adverse effects was required in 4.4% of patients principally because of dizziness, cough, fatigue and muscle cramps.



 Adverse experiences occurring in greater than one percent of patients treated with lisinopril plus hydrochlorothiazide in controlled clinical trials are shown below.



   Percent of Patients in Controlled Studies  




                              Lisinopril and Hydrochlorothiazide (n=930)    Incidence (discontinuation)      Placebo (n=207)    Incidence     
  
 Dizziness                  7.5                        (0.8)                      1.9                         
 Headache                   5.2                        (0.3)                      1.9                         
 Cough                      3.9                        (0.6)                      1.0                         
 Fatigue                    3.7                        (0.4)                      1.0                         
 Orthostatic Effects        3.2                        (0.1)                      1.0                         
 Diarrhea                   2.5                        (0.2)                      2.4                         
 Nausea                     2.2                        (0.1)                      2.4                         
 Upper RespiratoryInfection  2.2                        (0.0)                      0.0                         
 Muscle Cramps              2.0                        (0.4)                      0.5                         
 Asthenia                   1.8                        (0.2)                      1.0                         
 Paresthesia                1.5                        (0.1)                      0.0                         
 Hypotension                1.4                        (0.3)                      0.5                         
 Vomiting                   1.4                        (0.1)                      0.5                         
 Dyspepsia                  1.3                        (0.0)                      0.0                         
 Rash                       1.2                        (0.1)                      0.5                         
 Impotence                  1.2                        (0.3)                      0.0                         
      Clinical adverse experiences occurring in 0.3% to 1.0% of patients in controlled trials and rarer, serious, possibly drug-related events reported in marketing experience are listed below:
 

   Body as a Whole:   Chest pain, abdominal pain, syncope, chest discomfort, fever, trauma, virus infection.   Cardiovascular:    Palpitation, orthostatic hypotension.   Digestive:  Gastrointestinal cramps, dry mouth, constipation, heartburn.   Musculoskeletal:    Back pain, shoulder pain, knee pain, back strain, myalgia, foot pain.   Nervous/Psychiatric:   Decreased libido, vertigo, depression, somnolence.   Respiratory:    Common cold, nasal congestion, influenza, bronchitis, pharyngeal pain, dyspnea, pulmonary congestion, chronic sinusitis, allergic rhinitis, pharyngeal discomfort.   Skin:    Flushing, pruritus, skin inflammation, diaphoresis, cutaneous pseudolymphoma.   Special Senses:    Blurred vision, tinnitus, otalgia.   Urogenital:    Urinary tract infection.



   Angioedema:    Angioedema of the face, extremities, lips, tongue, glottis and/or larynx has been reported (See  WARNINGS  ).



 In rare cases, intestinal angioedema has been reported in post marketing experience.



   Hypotension:    In clinical trials, adverse effects relating to hypotension occurred as follows:  hypotension (1.4%), orthostatic hypotension (0.5%), other orthostatic effects (3.2%). In addition syncope occurred in 0.8% of patients (See  WARNINGS  ).



   Cough:   See  PRECAUTIONS - Cough  .



 



 



     



     Clinical Laboratory Test Findings  

    Serum Electrolytes:   (See  PRECAUTIONS  ).



   Creatinine, Blood Urea Nitrogen:               Minor reversible increases in blood urea nitrogen and serum creatinine were observed in patients with essential hypertension treated with ZESTORETIC.  More marked increases have also been reported and were more likely to occur in patients with renal artery stenosis (See  PRECAUTIONS  ).



   Serum Uric Acid, Glucose, Magnesium, Cholesterol, Triglycerides and Calcium:  (See  PRECAUTIONS  ).



   Hemoglobin and Hematocrit:    Small decreases in hemoglobin and hematocrit (mean decreases of approximately 0.5 g% and 1.5 vol%, respectively) occurred frequently in hypertensive patients treated with ZESTORETIC but were rarely of clinical importance unless another cause of anemia coexisted.  In clinical trials, 0.4% of patients discontinued therapy due to anemia.



   Liver Function Tests:    Rarely, elevations of liver enzymes and/or serum bilirubin have occurred.  (See  WARNINGS, Hepatic Failure  ).



 Other adverse reactions that have been reported with the individual components are listed below:



   Lisinopril -  In clinical trials adverse reactions which occurred with lisinopril were also seen with ZESTORETIC.  In addition, and since lisinopril has been marketed, the following adverse reactions have been reported with lisinopril and should be considered potential adverse reactions for ZESTORETIC:   Body as a Whole:    Anaphylactoid reactions (see  WARNINGS, Anaphylactoid Reactions During Membrane Exposure  ), malaise, edema, facial edema, pain, pelvic pain, flank pain, chills;  Cardiovascular:    Cardiac arrest, myocardial infarction or cerebrovascular accident, possibly secondary to excessive hypotension in high risk patients (see  WARNINGS, Hypotension  ), pulmonary embolism and infarction, worsening of heart failure, arrhythmias (including tachycardia, ventricular tachycardia, atrial tachycardia, atrial fibrillation, bradycardia, and premature ventricular contractions), angina pectoris, transient ischemic attacks, paroxysmal nocturnal dyspnea, decreased blood pressure, peripheral edema, vasculitis;  Digestive:    Pancreatitis, hepatitis (hepatocellular or cholestatic jaundice) (see  WARNINGS, Hepatic Failure  ), gastritis, anorexia, flatulence, increased salivation;  Endocrine:    Diabetes mellitus, inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion;  Hematologic:    Rare cases of bone marrow depression, hemolytic anemia, leukopenia/neutropenia, and thrombocytopenia have been reported in which a causal relationship to lisinopril can not be excluded;  Metabolic:   Gout, weight loss, dehydration, fluid overload, weight gain;  Musculoskeletal:    Arthritis, arthralgia, neck pain, hip pain, joint pain, leg pain, arm pain, lumbago;  Nervous System/Psychiatric:    Ataxia, memory impairment, tremor, insomnia, stroke, nervousness, confusion, peripheral neuropathy (eg, paresthesia, dysesthesia), spasm, hypersomnia, irritability; mood alterations (including depressive symptoms);    hallucinations;  Respiratory:    Malignant lung neoplasms, hemoptysis, pulmonary edema, pulmonary infiltrates, bronchospasm, asthma, pleural effusion, pneumonia, eosinophilic pneumonitis, wheezing, orthopnea, painful respiration, epistaxis, laryngitis, sinusitis, pharyngitis, rhinitis, rhinorrhea, chest sound abnormalities;  Skin:  Urticaria, alopecia, herpes zoster, photosensitivity, skin lesions, skin infections, pemphigus, erythema, psoriasis, rare cases of other severe skin reactions, including toxic epidermal necrolysis and Stevens-Johnson Syndrome (causal relationship has not been established);  Special Senses:   Visual loss, diplopia, photophobia, taste alteration, olfactory disturbance;  Urogenital:    Acute renal failure, oliguria, anuria, uremia, progressive azotemia, renal dysfunction (see  PRECAUTIONS  and  DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION  ), pyelonephritis, dysuria, breast pain.



   Miscellaneous:    A symptom complex has been reported which may include a positive ANA, an elevated erythrocyte sedimentation rate, arthralgia/arthritis, myalgia, fever, vasculitis, eosinophilia and leukocytosis.  Rash, photosensitivity or other dermatological manifestations may occur alone or in combination with these symptoms.



   Hydrochlorothiazide - Body as a Whole:    Weakness;  Digestive:   Anorexia, gastric irritation, cramping, jaundice (intrahepatic cholestatic jaundice) (See  WARNINGS, Hepatic Failure  ), pancreatitis, sialoadenitis, constipation;  Hematologic:    Leukopenia, agranulocytosis, thrombocytopenia, aplastic anemia, hemolytic anemia;  Musculoskeletal:    Muscle spasm;  Nervous System/Psychiatric:  Restlessness;  Renal:   Renal failure, renal dysfunction, interstitial nephritis (see  WARNINGS  );  Skin:    Erythema multiforme including Stevens-Johnson Syndrome, exfoliative dermatitis including toxic epidermal necrolysis, alopecia;  Special Senses:    Xanthopsia;  Hypersensitivity:    Purpura, photosensitivity, urticaria, necrotizing angiitis (vasculitis and cutaneous vasculitis), respiratory distress including pneumonitis and pulmonary edema, anaphylactic reactions.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY

    WARNING: FETAL TOXICITY  

    See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  When pregnancy is detected, discontinue ZESTORETIC as soon as possible. 
 *  Drugs that act directly on the renin-angiotensin system can cause injury and death to the developing fetus.  See Warnings: Fetal Toxicity. 
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
