<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="zetia" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the label:



 *    Liver enzyme abnormalities [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *    Rhabdomyolysis and myopathy [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
        Monotherapy Studies:  In the ZETIA controlled clinical trials database (placebo-controlled) of 2396 patients with a median treatment duration of 12 weeks (range 0 to 39 weeks), 3.3% of patients on ZETIA and 2.9% of patients on placebo discontinued due to adverse reactions. The most common adverse reactions in the group of patients treated with ZETIA that led to treatment discontinuation and occurred at a rate greater than placebo were:
 

 *    Arthralgia (0.3%) 
 *    Dizziness (0.2%) 
 *    Gamma-glutamyltransferase increased (0.2%) 
    The most commonly reported adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=2% and greater than placebo) in the ZETIA monotherapy controlled clinical trial database of 2396 patients were: upper respiratory tract infection (4.3%), diarrhea (4.1%), arthralgia (3.0%), sinusitis (2.8%), and pain in extremity (2.7%).
 

     Statin Coadministration Studies:  In the ZETIA + statin controlled clinical trials database of 11,308 patients with a median treatment duration of 8 weeks (range 0 to 112 weeks), 4.0% of patients on ZETIA + statin and 3.3% of patients on statin alone discontinued due to adverse reactions. The most common adverse reactions in the group of patients treated with ZETIA + statin that led to treatment discontinuation and occurred at a rate greater than statin alone were:



 *  1.  Alanine aminotransferase increased (0.6%) 
 *  2.  Myalgia (0.5%) 
 *  3.  Fatigue, aspartate aminotransferase increased, headache, and pain in extremity (each at 0.2%) 
    The most commonly reported adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=2% and greater than statin alone) in the ZETIA + statin controlled clinical trial database of 11,308 patients were: nasopharyngitis (3.7%), myalgia (3.2%), upper respiratory tract infection (2.9%), arthralgia (2.6%) and diarrhea (2.5%).
 

     To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or 1-800-822-7967 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



   6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



     Monotherapy  



 In 10 double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trials, 2396 patients with primary hyperlipidemia (age range 9-86 years, 50% women, 90% Caucasians, 5% Blacks, 3% Hispanics, 2% Asians) and elevated LDL-C were treated with ZETIA 10 mg/day for a median treatment duration of 12 weeks (range 0 to 39 weeks).



 Adverse reactions reported in &gt;=2% of patients treated with ZETIA and at an incidence greater than placebo in placebo-controlled studies of ZETIA, regardless of causality assessment, are shown in  Table 1  .



 TABLE 1: Clinical Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=2% of Patients Treated with ZETIA and at an Incidence Greater than Placebo, Regardless of Causality 
  Body System/Organ Class  Adverse Reaction           ZETIA 10 mg (%)n = 2396    Placebo(%)n = 1159         
  Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                                
    Diarrhea                                          4.1                        3.7                        
  General disorders and administration site conditions                                                          
    Fatigue                                           2.4                        1.5                        
  Infections and infestations                                                                               
    Influenza                                         2.0                        1.5                        
    Sinusitis                                         2.8                        2.2                        
    Upper respiratory tract infection                 4.3                        2.5                        
  Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders                                                           
    Arthralgia                                        3.0                        2.2                        
    Pain in extremity                                 2.7                        2.5                        
         The frequency of less common adverse reactions was comparable between ZETIA and placebo.
 

     Combination with a Statin  



 In 28 double-blind, controlled (placebo or active-controlled) clinical trials, 11,308 patients with primary hyperlipidemia (age range 10-93 years, 48% women, 85% Caucasians, 7% Blacks, 4% Hispanics, 3% Asians) and elevated LDL-C were treated with ZETIA 10 mg/day concurrently with or added to on-going statin therapy for a median treatment duration of 8 weeks (range 0 to 112 weeks).



 The incidence of consecutive increased transaminases (&gt;=3 * ULN) was higher in patients receiving ZETIA administered with statins (1.3%) than in patients treated with statins alone (0.4%).  [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  .]  



 Clinical adverse reactions reported in &gt;=2% of patients treated with ZETIA + statin and at an incidence greater than statin, regardless of causality assessment, are shown in  Table 2  .



 TABLE 2: Clinical Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;=2% of Patients Treated with ZETIA Coadministered with a Statin and at an Incidence Greater than Statin, Regardless of Causality 
  Body System/Organ Class  Adverse Reaction           All StatinsAll Statins = all doses of all statins(%)n = 9361    ZETIA + All Statins(%)n = 11,308    
  Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                                
    Diarrhea                                          2.2                        2.5                        
  General disorders and administration site conditions                                                          
    Fatigue                                           1.6                        2.0                        
  Infections and infestations                                                                               
    Influenza                                         2.1                        2.2                        
    Nasopharyngitis                                   3.3                        3.7                        
    Upper respiratory tract infection                 2.8                        2.9                        
  Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders                                                           
    Arthralgia                                        2.4                        2.6                        
    Back pain                                         2.3                        2.4                        
    Myalgia                                           2.7                        3.2                        
    Pain in extremity                                 1.9                        2.1                        
             Combination with Fenofibrate  
 

 This clinical study involving 625 patients with mixed dyslipidemia (age range 20-76 years, 44% women, 79% Caucasians, 0.1% Blacks, 11% Hispanics, 5% Asians) treated for up to 12 weeks and 576 patients treated for up to an additional 48 weeks evaluated coadministration of ZETIA and fenofibrate. This study was not designed to compare treatment groups for infrequent events. Incidence rates (95% CI) for clinically important elevations (&gt;=3 * ULN, consecutive) in hepatic transaminase levels were 4.5% (1.9, 8.8) and 2.7% (1.2, 5.4) for fenofibrate monotherapy (n=188) and ZETIA coadministered with fenofibrate (n=183), respectively, adjusted for treatment exposure. Corresponding incidence rates for cholecystectomy were 0.6% (95% CI: 0.0%, 3.1%) and 1.7% (95% CI: 0.6%, 4.0%) for fenofibrate monotherapy and ZETIA coadministered with fenofibrate, respectively  [see  Drug Interactions (7.3)  ]  . The numbers of patients exposed to coadministration therapy as well as fenofibrate and ezetimibe monotherapy were inadequate to assess gallbladder disease risk. There were no CPK elevations &gt;10 * ULN in any of the treatment groups.



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  Because the reactions below are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is generally not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 The following additional adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of ZETIA:



 Hypersensitivity reactions, including anaphylaxis, angioedema, rash, and urticaria; erythema multiforme; arthralgia; myalgia; elevated creatine phosphokinase; myopathy/rhabdomyolysis  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  ; elevations in liver transaminases; hepatitis; abdominal pain; thrombocytopenia; pancreatitis; nausea; dizziness; paresthesia; depression; headache; cholelithiasis; cholecystitis.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    ZETIA is not recommended in patients with moderate or severe hepatic impairment. (  5.4  ,  8.7  ,  12.3  ) 
 *    Liver enzyme abnormalities and monitoring: Persistent elevations in hepatic transaminase can occur when ZETIA is added to a statin. Therefore, when ZETIA is added to statin therapy, monitor hepatic transaminase levels before and during treatment according to the recommendations for the individual statin used. (  5.2  ) 
 *    *    Cases of myopathy and rhabdomyolysis have been reported in patients treated with ZETIA coadministered with a statin and with ZETIA administered alone. Risk for skeletal muscle toxicity increases with higher doses of statin, advanced age (&gt;65), hypothyroidism, renal impairment, and depending on the statin used, concomitant use of other drugs. (  5.3  ,  6.2  ) 
   Skeletal muscle effects (e.g., myopathy and rhabdomyolysis): 
    
 

   5.1 Use with Statins or Fenofibrate



  Concurrent administration of ZETIA with a specific statin or fenofibrate should be in accordance with the product labeling for that medication.



    5.2 Liver Enzymes



  In controlled clinical monotherapy studies, the incidence of consecutive elevations (&gt;=3 * the upper limit of normal [ULN]) in hepatic transaminase levels was similar between ZETIA (0.5%) and placebo (0.3%).



 In controlled clinical combination studies of ZETIA initiated concurrently with a statin, the incidence of consecutive elevations (&gt;=3 * ULN) in hepatic transaminase levels was 1.3% for patients treated with ZETIA administered with statins and 0.4% for patients treated with statins alone. These elevations in transaminases were generally asymptomatic, not associated with cholestasis, and returned to baseline after discontinuation of therapy or with continued treatment. When ZETIA is coadministered with a statin, liver tests should be performed at initiation of therapy and according to the recommendations of the statin. Should an increase in ALT or AST &gt;=3 * ULN persist, consider withdrawal of ZETIA and/or the statin.



    5.3 Myopathy/Rhabdomyolysis



  In clinical trials, there was no excess of myopathy or rhabdomyolysis associated with ZETIA compared with the relevant control arm (placebo or statin alone). However, myopathy and rhabdomyolysis are known adverse reactions to statins and other lipid-lowering drugs. In clinical trials, the incidence of creatine phosphokinase (CPK) &gt;10 * ULN was 0.2% for ZETIA vs. 0.1% for placebo, and 0.1% for ZETIA coadministered with a statin vs. 0.4% for statins alone. Risk for skeletal muscle toxicity increases with higher doses of statin, advanced age (&gt;65), hypothyroidism, renal impairment, and depending on the statin used, concomitant use of other drugs.



 In post-marketing experience with ZETIA, cases of myopathy and rhabdomyolysis have been reported. Most patients who developed rhabdomyolysis were taking a statin prior to initiating ZETIA. However, rhabdomyolysis has been reported with ZETIA monotherapy and with the addition of ZETIA to agents known to be associated with increased risk of rhabdomyolysis, such as fibrates. ZETIA and any statin or fibrate that the patient is taking concomitantly should be immediately discontinued if myopathy is diagnosed or suspected. The presence of muscle symptoms and a CPK level &gt;10 * the ULN indicates myopathy.



    5.4 Hepatic Impairment



  Due to the unknown effects of the increased exposure to ezetimibe in patients with moderate to severe hepatic impairment, ZETIA is not recommended in these patients. [See  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  .]  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
