<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="ziagen1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are discussed in other sections of the labeling:



 *    Serious and sometimes fatal hypersensitivity reactions . [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]  
 *    Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis . [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  
 *    Immune reconstitution syndrome . [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3)]  
 *    Fat redistribution . [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)]  
 *    Myocardial infarction . [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)]  
   *    The most commonly reported adverse reactions of at least moderate intensity (incidence greater than or equal to 10%) in adult HIV-1 clinical trials were nausea, headache, malaise and fatigue, nausea and vomiting, and dreams/sleep disorders. ( )  6.1   
 *    The most commonly reported adverse reactions of at least moderate intensity (incidence greater than or equal to 5%) in pediatric HIV-1 clinical trials were fever and/or chills, nausea and vomiting, skin rashes, and ear/nose/throat infections. ( )  6.2   
 *      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact ViiV Healthcare at 1-877-844-8872 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
      EXCERPT:   
   6.1 Clinical Trials Experience in Adult Subjects

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared with rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice.



   Serious and Fatal Abacavir-associated Hypersensitivity Reactions  



 In clinical trials, serious and sometimes fatal hypersensitivity reactions have occurred with abacavir These reactions have been characterized by 2 or more of the following signs or symptoms: (1) fever; (2) rash; (3) gastrointestinal symptoms (including nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, or abdominal pain); (4) constitutional symptoms (including generalized malaise, fatigue, or achiness); (5) respiratory symptoms (including dyspnea, cough, or pharyngitis). Almost all abacavir hypersensitivity reactions include fever and/or rash as part of the syndrome.  [see Boxed Warning, Warnings and Precautions (5.1)].  



 Other signs and symptoms have included lethargy, headache, myalgia, edema, arthralgia, and paresthesia. Anaphylaxis, liver failure, renal failure, hypotension, adult respiratory distress syndrome, respiratory failure, myolysis, and death have occurred in association with these hypersensitivity reactions. Physical findings have included lymphadenopathy, mucous membrane lesions (conjunctivitis and mouth ulcerations), and maculopapular or urticarial rash (although some patients had other types of rashes and others did not have a rash). There were reports of erythema multiforme. Laboratory abnormalities included elevated liver chemistries, elevated creatine phosphokinase, elevated creatinine, and lymphopenia, and abnormal chest x-ray findings (predominantly infiltrates, which were localized).



   Additional Adverse Reactions with Use of ZIAGEN  



 naive Treatment-emergent clinical adverse reactions (rated by the investigator as moderate or severe) with a greater than or equal to 5% frequency during therapy with ZIAGEN 300 mg twice daily, lamivudine 150 mg twice daily, and efavirenz 600 mg daily compared with zidovudine 300 mg twice daily, lamivudine 150 mg twice daily, and efavirenz 600 mg daily from CNA30024 are listed in Table 2.  Therapy-    Adults:  



 Table 2. Treatment-emergent (All Causality) Adverse Reactions of at Least Moderate Intensity (Grades 2-4, Greater than or Equal to 5% Frequency) in Therapy-naive Adults (CNA30024 ) through 48 Weeks of Treatment a 
  Adverse Reaction               ZIAGEN plus Lamivudine plus Efavirenz  (n = 324)    Zidovudine plus Lamivudine plus Efavirenz  (n = 325)    
  Dreams/sleep disorders         10%                                  10%                                  
  Drug hypersensitivity          9%                                   &lt;1% b                                
  Headaches/migraine             7%                                   11%                                  
  Nausea                         7%                                   11%                                  
  Fatigue/malaise                7%                                   10%                                  
  Diarrhea                       7%                                   6%                                   
  Rashes                         6%                                   12%                                  
  Abdominal pain/gastritis/ gastrointestinal signs and symptoms    6%                                   8%                                   
  Depressive disorders           6%                                   6%                                   
  Dizziness                      6%                                   6%                                   
  Musculoskeletal pain           6%                                   5%                                   
  Bronchitis                     4%                                   5%                                   
  Vomiting                       2%                                   9%                                   
         This trial used double-blind ascertainment of suspected hypersensitivity reactions. During the blinded portion of the trial, suspected hypersensitivity to abacavir was reported by investigators in 9% of 324 subjects in the abacavir group and 3% of 325 subjects in the zidovudine group.  a  
 

 Ten (3%) cases of suspected drug hypersensitivity were reclassified as not being due to abacavir following unblinding.  b  



 Treatment-emergent clinical adverse reactions (rated by the investigator as moderate or severe) with a greater than or equal to 5% frequency during therapy with ZIAGEN 300 mg twice daily, lamivudine 150 mg twice daily, and zidovudine 300 mg twice daily compared with indinavir 800 mg 3 times daily, lamivudine 150 mg twice daily, and zidovudine 300 mg twice daily from CNA3005 are listed in Table 3.



 Table 3. Treatment-emergent (All Causality) Adverse Reactions of at Least Moderate Intensity (Grades 2-4, Greater than or Equal to 5% Frequency) in Therapy-naive Adults (CNA3005) through 48 Weeks of Treatment 
  Adverse Reaction           ZIAGEN plus Lamivudine/Zidovudine  (n = 262)    Indinavir plus Lamivudine/Zidovudine  (n = 264)    
  Nausea                     19%                                    17%                                    
  Headache                   13%                                    9%                                     
  Malaise and fatigue        12%                                    12%                                    
  Nausea and vomiting        10%                                    10%                                    
  Hypersensitivity reaction    8%                                     2%                                     
  Diarrhea                   7%                                     5%                                     
  Fever and/or chills        6%                                     3%                                     
  Depressive disorders       6%                                     4%                                     
  Musculoskeletal pain       5%                                     7%                                     
  Skin rashes                5%                                     4%                                     
  Ear/nose/throat infections    5%                                     4%                                     
  Viral respiratory infections    5%                                     5%                                     
  Anxiety                    5%                                     3%                                     
  Renal signs/symptoms       &lt;1%                                    5%                                     
  Pain (non-site-specific)    &lt;1%                                    5%                                     
         Five subjects receiving ZIAGEN in CNA3005 experienced worsening of pre-existing depression compared with none in the indinavir arm. The background rates of pre-existing depression were similar in the 2 treatment arms.
 

 Treatment-emergent clinical adverse reactions (rated by the investigator as at least moderate) with a greater than or equal to 5% frequency during therapy with ZIAGEN 600 mg once daily or ZIAGEN 300 mg twice daily, both in combination with lamivudine 300 mg once daily and efavirenz 600 mg once daily from CNA30021, were similar. For hypersensitivity reactions, subjects receiving ZIAGEN once daily showed a rate of 9% in comparison with a rate of 7% for subjects receiving ZIAGEN twice daily. However, subjects receiving ZIAGEN 600 mg once daily experienced a significantly higher incidence of severe drug hypersensitivity reactions and severe diarrhea compared with subjects who received ZIAGEN 300 mg twice daily. Five percent (5%) of subjects receiving ZIAGEN 600 mg once daily had severe drug hypersensitivity reactions compared with 2% of subjects receiving ZIAGEN 300 mg twice daily. Two percent (2%) of subjects receiving ZIAGEN 600 mg once daily had severe diarrhea while none of the subjects receiving ZIAGEN 300 mg twice daily had this event.  ZIAGEN Once Daily versus ZIAGEN Twice Daily (CNA30021):  



 Laboratory abnormalities (Grades 3-4) in therapy-naive adults during therapy with ZIAGEN 300 mg twice daily, lamivudine 150 mg twice daily, and efavirenz 600 mg daily compared with zidovudine 300 mg twice daily, lamivudine 150 mg twice daily, and efavirenz 600 mg daily from CNA30024 are listed in Table 4.  Laboratory Abnormalities:  



 Table 4. Laboratory Abnormalities (Grades 3-4) in Therapy-naive Adults (CNA30024) through 48 Weeks of Treatment 
  Grade 3/4  Laboratory Abnormalities         ZIAGEN plus  Lamivudine plus Efavirenz  (n = 324)    Zidovudine plus  Lamivudine plus Efavirenz(n = 325)    
  Elevated CPK (&gt;4 X ULN)                     8%                             8%                             
  Elevated ALT (&gt;5 X ULN)                     6%                             6%                             
  Elevated AST (&gt;5 X ULN)                     6%                             5%                             
  Hypertriglyceridemia (&gt;750 mg/dL)           6%                             5%                             
  Hyperamylasemia (&gt;2 X ULN)                  4%                             5%                             
  Neutropenia (ANC &lt;750/mm ) 3                2%                             4%                             
  Anemia (Hgb &lt;=6.9 gm/dL)                    &lt;1%                            2%                             
  Thrombocytopenia (Platelets &lt;50,000/mm ) 3    1%                             &lt;1%                            
  Leukopenia (WBC &lt;=1,500/mm ) 3              &lt;1%                            2%                             
         ULN = Upper limit of normal.
 

 n = Number of subjects assessed.



 Laboratory abnormalities in CNA3005 are listed in Table 5.



 Table 5. Treatment-emergent Laboratory Abnormalities (Grades 3-4) in CNA3005 
  Grade 3/4  Laboratory Abnormalities    ZIAGEN plus Lamivudine/Zidovudine  (n = 262)    Indinavir plus Lamivudine/Zidovudine  (n = 264)    
  Elevated CPK (&gt;4 x ULN)              18 (7%)                            18 (7%)                            
  ALT (&gt;5.0 x ULN)                     16 (6%)                            16 (6%)                            
  Neutropenia (&lt;750/mm ) 3             13 (5%)                            13 (5%)                            
  Hypertriglyceridemia (&gt;750 mg/dL)    5 (2%)                             3 (1%)                             
  Hyperamylasemia (&gt;2.0 x ULN)         5 (2%)                             1 (&lt;1%)                            
  Hyperglycemia (&gt;13.9 mmol/L)         2 (&lt;1%)                            2 (&lt;1%)                            
  Anemia (Hgb &lt;=6.9 g/dL)              0 (0%)                             3 (1%)                             
         ULN = Upper limit of normal.
 

 n = Number of subjects assessed.



 The frequencies of treatment-emergent laboratory abnormalities were comparable between treatment groups in CNA30021.



   6.2 Clinical Trials Experience in Pediatric Subjects

    Therapy-experienced Pediatric Subjects (Twice-daily Dosing)  



 Treatment-emergent clinical adverse reactions (rated by the investigator as moderate or severe) with a greater than or equal to 5% frequency during therapy with ZIAGEN 8 mg per kg twice daily, lamivudine 4 mg per kg twice daily, and zidovudine 180 mg per m twice daily compared with lamivudine 4 mg per kg twice daily and zidovudine 180 mg per m twice daily from CNA3006 are listed in Table 6.  2    2  



 Table 6. Treatment-emergent (All Causality) Adverse Reactions of at Least Moderate Intensity (Grades 2-4, Greater than or Equal to 5% Frequency) in Therapy-experienced Pediatric Subjects (CNA3006) through 16 Weeks of Treatment 
  Adverse Reaction            ZIAGEN plus Lamivudine plus Zidovudine  (n = 102)    Lamivudine plus Zidovudine  (n = 103)    
  Fever and/or chills         9%                                     7%                                     
  Nausea and vomiting         9%                                     2%                                     
  Skin rashes                 7%                                     1%                                     
  Ear/nose/throat infections    5%                                     1%                                     
  Pneumonia                   4%                                     5%                                     
  Headache                    1%                                     5%                                     
         In CNA3006, laboratory abnormalities (anemia, neutropenia, liver function test abnormalities, and CPK elevations) were observed with similar frequencies as in a trial of therapy-naive adults (CNA30024). Mild elevations of blood glucose were more frequent in pediatric subjects receiving ZIAGEN (CNA3006) as compared with adult subjects (CNA30024).  Laboratory Abnormalities:  
 

   Other Adverse Events  



 In addition to adverse reactions and laboratory abnormalities reported in Tables 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6, other adverse reactions observed in the expanded access program were pancreatitis and increased GGT.



 The safety of once-daily compared with twice-daily dosing of ZIAGEN was assessed in the ARROW trial. Primary safety assessment in the ARROW trial was based on Grade 3 and Grade 4 adverse events. The frequency of Grade 3 and 4 adverse events was similar among subjects randomized to once-daily dosing compared with subjects randomized to twice-daily dosing. One event of Grade 4 hepatitis in the once-daily cohort was considered as uncertain causality by the investigator and all other Grade 3 or 4 adverse events were considered not related by the investigator.  Pediatric Subjects Once-daily versus Twice-daily Dosing (COL105677):  



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during postmarketing use of ZIAGEN. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of unknown size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposures.



   Body as a Whole  



 Redistribution/accumulation of body fat.



   Cardiovascular  



 Myocardial infarction.



   Hepatic  



 Lactic acidosis and hepatic steatosis .  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]  



   Skin  



 Suspected Stevens-Johnson syndrome (SJS) and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN) have been reported in patients receiving abacavir primarily in combination with medications known to be associated with SJS and TEN, respectively. Because of the overlap of clinical signs and symptoms between hypersensitivity to abacavir and SJS and TEN, and the possibility of multiple drug sensitivities in some patients, abacavir should be discontinued and not restarted in such cases.



 There have also been reports of erythema multiforme with abacavir use .  [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: HYPERSENSITIVITY REACTIONS, and LACTIC ACIDOSIS AND SEVERE HEPATOMEGALY

  WARNING: HYPERSENSITIVITY REACTIONS, and LACTIC ACIDOSIS AND SEVERE HEPATOMEGALY

      Hypersensitivity Reactions    



     Serious and sometimes fatal hypersensitivity reactions, with multiple organ involvement, have occurred with ZIAGEN(r) (abacavir).    



     Patients who carry the HLA-B*5701 allele are at a higher risk of a hypersensitivity reaction to abacavir; although, hypersensitivity reactions have occurred in patients who do not carry the HLA-B*5701 allele .

                                      [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]      



     ZIAGEN is contraindicated in patients with a prior hypersensitivity reaction to abacavir and in HLA-B*5701-positive patients . All patients should be screened for the HLA-B*5701 allele prior to initiating therapy with ZIAGEN or reinitiation of therapy with ZIAGEN, unless patients have a previously documented HLA-B*5701 allele assessment. Discontinue ZIAGEN immediately if a hypersensitivity reaction is suspected, regardless of HLA-B*5701 status and even when other diagnoses are possible .

                                      [see Contraindications (4), Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]    [see Contraindications (4), Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]      



     Following a hypersensitivity reaction to ZIA        GEN        , NE        VER        restart ZIA        GEN        or any other abacavir-containing product because more severe symptoms, including death can occur within hours. Similar severe reactions have also occurred rarely following the reintroduction of abacavir-containing products in patients who have no history of abacavir hypersensitivity .

                                      [see Warnings and Precautions (5.1)]      



     Lactic Acidosis and Severe Hepatomegaly with Steatosis    



     Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogues and other antiretrovirals. Discontinue ZIAGEN if clinical or laboratory findings suggestive of lactic acidosis or pronounced hepatotoxicity occur .

                                      [see Warnings and Precautions (5.2)]      



   EXCERPT:   WARNING: HYPERSENSITIVITY REACTIONS, and LACTIC ACIDOSIS AND SEVERE HEPATOMEGALY



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



     Hypersensitivity Reactions    



 *  Serious and sometimes fatal hypersensitivity reactions have occurred with ZIAGEN (abacavir). ( ) 5.1 
 *  Hypersensitivity to ZIAGEN is a multi-organ clinical syndrome. ( ) 5.1 
 *  Patients who carry the HLA-B*5701 allele are at a higher risk of experiencing a hypersensitivity reaction to abacavir. ( ) 5.1 
 *  ZIAGEN is contraindicated in patients with a prior hypersensitivity reaction to abacavir and in HLA-B*5701-positive patients. ( ) 4 
 *  Discontinue ZIAGEN as soon as a hypersensitivity reaction is suspected. Regardless of HLA-B*5701 status, permanently discontinue ZIAGEN if hypersensitivity cannot be ruled out, even when other diagnoses are possible. ( ) 5.1 
 *  Following a hypersensitivity reaction to ZIAGEN, NEVER restart ZIAGEN or any other abacavir-containing product. ( ) 5.1 
        Lactic Acidosis and Severe Hepatomegaly with Steatosis    
 

 *  Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogues. ( ) 5.2 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Immune reconstitution syndrome and redistribution/accumulation of body fat have been reported in patients treated with combination antiretroviral therapy. ( , )  5.3    5.4   
 *    Administration of ZIAGEN with other products containing abacavir is not recommended. (5.6) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions



   Serious and sometimes fatal hypersensitivity reactions have occurred with ZIAGEN (abacavir). These hypersensitivity reactions have included multi-organ failure and anaphylaxis and typically occurred within the first 6 weeks of treatment with ZIAGEN (median time to onset was 9 days); although abacavir hypersensitivity reactions have occurred any time during treatment . Patients who carry the HLA-B*5701 allele are at a higher risk of abacavir hypersensitivity reactions; although, patients who do not carry the HLA-B*5701 allele have developed hypersensitivity reactions. Hypersensitivity to abacavir was reported in approximately 206 (8%) of 2,670 patients in 9 clinical trials with abacavir-containing products where HLA-B*5701 screening was not performed. The incidence of suspected abacavir hypersensitivity reactions in clinical trials was 1% when subjects carrying the HLA-B*5701 allele were excluded. In any patient treated with abacavir, the clinical diagnosis of hypersensitivity reaction must remain the basis of clinical decision making. [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]    



  Due to the potential for severe, serious, and possibly fatal hypersensitivity reactions with ZIAGEN:  



 *     All patients should be screened for the HLA-B*5701 allele prior to initiating therapy with ZIAGEN or reinitiation of therapy with ZIAGEN, unless patients have a previously documented HLA-B*5701 allele assessment.  
 *     ZIAGEN is contraindicated in patients with a prior hypersensitivity reaction to abacavir and in HLA-B*5701-positive patients.  
 *     Before starting ZIAGEN, review medical history for prior exposure to any abacavir-containing product. NE  VER  restart ZIA  GEN  or any other abacavir-containing product following a hypersensitivity reaction to abacavir, regardless of HLA-B*5701 status.  
 *     To reduce the risk of a life-threatening hypersensitivity reaction, regardless of HLA-B*5701 status, discontinue ZIAGEN immediately if a hypersensitivity reaction is suspected, even when other diagnoses are possible (e.g., acute onset respiratory diseases such as pneumonia, bronchitis, pharyngitis, or influenza; gastroenteritis; or reactions to other medications).  
 *     If a hypersensitivity reaction cannot be ruled out, do not restart ZIAGEN or any other abacavir-containing products because more severe symptoms which may include life-threatening hypotension and death can occur within hours.  
 *    If a hypersensitivity reaction is ruled out, patients may restart ZIAGEN. Rarely, patients who have stopped abacavir for reasons other than symptoms of hypersensitivity have also experienced life-threatening reactions within hours of reinitiating abacavir therapy. Therefore, reintroduction of ZIAGEN or any other abacavir-containing product is recommended only if medical care can be readily accessed. 
 *     A Medication Guide and Warning Card that provide information about recognition of hypersensitivity reactions should be dispensed with each new prescription and refill.  
       5.2 Lactic Acidosis and Severe Hepatomegaly with Steatosis
 

  Lactic acidosis and severe hepatomegaly with steatosis, including fatal cases, have been reported with the use of nucleoside analogues and other antiretrovirals. A majority of these cases have been in women. Obesity and prolonged nucleoside exposure may be risk factors. Caution should be exercised when administering ZIAGEN to any patient with known risk factors for liver disease; however, cases have also been reported in patients with no known risk factors. Treatment with ZIAGEN should be suspended in any patient who develops clinical or laboratory findings suggestive of lactic acidosis or pronounced hepatotoxicity (which may include hepatomegaly and steatosis even in the absence of marked transaminase elevations).



    5.3 Immune Reconstitution Syndrome



  Immune reconstitution syndrome has been reported in patients treated with combination antiretroviral therapy, including ZIAGEN. During the initial phase of combination antiretroviral treatment, patients whose immune systems respond may develop an inflammatory response to indolent or residual opportunistic infections (such as infection, cytomegalovirus, pneumonia [PCP], or tuberculosis), which may necessitate further evaluation and treatment. Mycobacterium avium   Pneumocystis jirovecii  



 Autoimmune disorders (such as Graves' disease, polymyositis, and Guillain-Barre syndrome) have also been reported to occur in the setting of immune reconstitution; however, the time to onset is more variable and can occur many months after initiation of treatment.



    5.4 Fat Redistribution



  Redistribution/accumulation of body fat including central obesity, dorsocervical fat enlargement (buffalo hump), peripheral wasting, facial wasting, breast enlargement, and "cushingoid appearance" have been observed in patients receiving antiretroviral therapy. The mechanism and long-term consequences of these events are currently unknown. A causal relationship has not been established.



    5.5 Myocardial Infarction



  In a published prospective, observational, epidemiological trial designed to investigate the rate of myocardial infarction (MI) in patients on combination antiretroviral therapy, the use of abacavir within the previous 6 months was correlated with an increased risk of MI. In a sponsor-conducted pooled analysis of clinical trials, no excess risk of MI was observed in abacavir-treated subjects as compared with control subjects. In totality, the available data from the observational cohort and from clinical trials are inconclusive.



 As a precaution, the underlying risk of coronary heart disease should be considered when prescribing antiretroviral therapies, including abacavir, and action taken to minimize all modifiable risk factors (e.g., hypertension, hyperlipidemia, diabetes mellitus, smoking).



    5.6 Related Products that are Not Recommended



   ZIAGEN is one of multiple abacavir-containing products. Concomitant administration of ZIAGEN with other products containing abacavir is not recommended.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
