<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="ziana" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Observed local adverse reactions in patients treated with ZIANA Gel were skin erythema, scaling, itching, burning, and stinging. Other most commonly reported adverse events (&gt;= 1% in patients treated with ZIANA Gel) were nasopharyngitis, pharyngolaryngeal pain, dry skin, cough, and sinusitis. (  6.1  )



  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Medicis, The Dermatology Company at 1-800-900-6389 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under prescribed conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trial may not reflect the rates observed in practice. The adverse reaction information from clinical trials does, however, provide a basis for identifying the adverse reactions that appear to be related to drug use for approximating rates.



 The safety data presented in Table 1 (below) reflects exposure to ZIANA Gel in 1,853 patients with acne vulgaris. Patients were 12 years and older and were treated once daily for 12 weeks. Adverse reactions that were reported in &gt;= 1% of patients treated with ZIANA Gel were compared to adverse reactions in patients treated with clindamycin phosphate 1.2% in vehicle gel, tretinoin 0.025% in vehicle gel, and the vehicle gel alone:



 Table 1: Adverse Reactions Reported in at Least 1% of Patients Treated with ZIANA Gel: 12-Week Studies 
                                 ZIANA Gel    N=1853    N (%)      Clindamycin    N=1428    N (%)      Tretinoin    N=846    N (%)      Vehicle    N=423    N (%)     
  
  PATIENTS WITH AT LEAST ONE AR    497 (27)            342 (24)            225 (27)            91 (22)             
  Nasopharyngitis               65 (4)              64 (5)              16 (2)              5 (1)               
  Pharyngolaryngeal pain        29 (2)              18 (1)              5 (1)               7 (2)               
  Dry skin                      23 (1)              7 (1)               3 (&lt;1)              0 (0)               
  Cough                         19 (1)              21 (2)              9 (1)               2 (1)               
  Sinusitis                     19 (1)              19 (1)              15 (2)              4 (1)               
  Note: Formulations used in all treatment arms were in the ZIANA vehicle gel.    
           Cutaneous safety and tolerance evaluations were conducted at each study visit in all of the clinical trials by assessment of erythema, scaling, itching, burning, and stinging:
 

 Table 2: ZIANA Gel-Treated Patients with Local Skin Reactions 
   Local Reaction                 Baseline    N=1835    N (%)      End of Treatment    N=1614    N (%)     
  
  Erythema                       636 (35)                      416 (26)                       
  Scaling                        237 (13)                      280 (17)                       
  Itching                        189 (10)                      70 (4)                         
  Burning                        38 (2)                        56 (4)                         
  Stinging                       33 (2)                        27 (2)                         
         At each study visit, application site reactions on a scale of 0 (none), 1 (mild), 2 (moderate), and 3 (severe), and the mean scores were calculated for each of the local skin reactions. In Studies 1 and 2, 1277 subjects enrolled with moderate to severe acne, 854 subjects treated with ZIANA Gel and 423 treated with vehicle. Analysis over the twelve week period demonstrated that cutaneous irritation scores for erythema, scaling, itching, burning, and stinging peaked at two weeks of therapy, and were slightly higher for the ZIANA-treated group, decreasing thereafter.
 

 One open-label 12-month safety study for ZIANA Gel showed a similar adverse reaction profile as seen in the 12-week studies. Eighteen out of 442 subjects (4%) reported gastrointestinal symptoms.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Colitis: Clindamycin can cause severe colitis, which may result in death. Diarrhea, bloody diarrhea, and colitis (including pseudomembranous colitis) have been reported with the use of clindamycin. ZIANA Gel should be discontinued if significant diarrhea occurs. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Ultraviolet Light and Environmental Exposures: Avoid exposure to sunlight and sunlamps. Wear sunscreen daily. (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Colitis



  Systemic absorption of clindamycin has been demonstrated following topical use of this product. Diarrhea, bloody diarrhea, and colitis (including pseudomembranous colitis) have been reported with the use of topical clindamycin. When significant diarrhea occurs, ZIANA Gel should be discontinued.



 Severe colitis has occurred following oral or parenteral administration of clindamycin with an onset of up to several weeks following cessation of therapy. Antiperistaltic agents such as opiates and diphenoxylate with atropine may prolong and/or worsen severe colitis. Severe colitis may result in death.



 Studies indicate a toxin(s) produced by clostridia is one primary cause of antibiotic-associated colitis. The colitis is usually characterized by severe persistent diarrhea and severe abdominal cramps and may be associated with the passage of blood and mucus. Stool cultures for Clostridium difficile  and stool assay for C. difficile  toxin may be helpful diagnostically.



    5.2 Ultraviolet Light and Environmental Exposure



  Exposure to sunlight, including sunlamps, should be avoided during the use of ZIANA Gel, and patients with sunburn should be advised not to use the product until fully recovered because of heightened susceptibility to sunlight as a result of the use of tretinoin. Patients who may be required to have considerable sun exposure due to occupation and those with inherent sensitivity to the sun should exercise particular caution. Daily use of sunscreen products and protective apparel (e.g., a hat) are recommended. Weather extremes, such as wind or cold, also may be irritating to patients under treatment with ZIANA Gel.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
