<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="zocor" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=5.0%) are: upper respiratory infection, headache, abdominal pain, constipation, and nausea. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In the pre-marketing controlled clinical studies and their open extensions (2,423 patients with median duration of follow-up of approximately 18 months), 1.4% of patients were discontinued due to adverse reactions. The most common adverse reactions that led to treatment discontinuation were: gastrointestinal disorders (0.5%), myalgia (0.1%), and arthralgia (0.1%). The most commonly reported adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=5%) in simvastatin controlled clinical trials were: upper respiratory infections (9.0%), headache (7.4%), abdominal pain (7.3%), constipation (6.6%), and nausea (5.4%).



   Scandinavian Simvastatin Survival Study  



 In 4S involving 4,444 (age range 35-71 years, 19% women, 100% Caucasians) treated with 20-40 mg/day of ZOCOR (n=2,221) or placebo (n=2,223) over a median of 5.4 years, adverse reactions reported in &gt;=2% of patients and at a rate greater than placebo are shown in Table 2.



 Table 2: Adverse Reactions Reported Regardless of Causality by &gt;=2% of Patients Treated with ZOCOR and Greater than Placebo in 4S 
                                                     ZOCOR(N = 2,221)%          Placebo(N = 2,223)%        
  
   Body as a Whole      Edema/swelling    Abdominal pain  2.75.9                     2.35.8                     
     Cardiovascular System Disorders        Atrial fibrillation  5.7                        5.1                        
     Digestive System Disorders        Constipation    Gastritis  2.24.9                     1.63.9                     
   Endocrine Disorders      Diabetes mellitus        4.2                        3.6                        
   Musculoskeletal Disorders      Myalgia            3.7                        3.2                        
   Nervous System / Psychiatric Disorders      Headache    Insomnia    Vertigo  2.54.04.5                  2.13.84.2                  
   Respiratory System Disorders      Bronchitis    Sinusitis  6.62.3                     6.31.8                     
   Skin / Skin Appendage Disorders      Eczema       4.5                        3.0                        
   Urogenital System Disorders      Infection, urinary tract  3.2                        3.1                        
           Heart Protection Study  
 

 In the Heart Protection Study (HPS), involving 20,536 patients (age range 40-80 years, 25% women, 97% Caucasians, 3% other races) treated with ZOCOR 40 mg/day (n=10,269) or placebo (n=10,267) over a mean of 5 years, only serious adverse reactions and discontinuations due to any adverse reactions were recorded. Discontinuation rates due to adverse reactions were 4.8% in patients treated with ZOCOR compared with 5.1% in patients treated with placebo. The incidence of myopathy/rhabdomyolysis was &lt;0.1% in patients treated with ZOCOR.



   Other Clinical Studies  



 In a clinical trial in which 12,064 patients with a history of myocardial infarction were treated with ZOCOR (mean follow-up 6.7 years), the incidence of myopathy (defined as unexplained muscle weakness or pain with a serum creatine kinase [CK] &gt;10 times upper limit of normal [ULN]) in patients on 80 mg/day was approximately 0.9% compared with 0.02% for patients on 20 mg/day. The incidence of rhabdomyolysis (defined as myopathy with a CK &gt;40 times ULN) in patients on 80 mg/day was approximately 0.4% compared with 0% for patients on 20 mg/day. The incidence of myopathy, including rhabdomyolysis, was highest during the first year and then notably decreased during the subsequent years of treatment. In this trial, patients were carefully monitored and some interacting medicinal products were excluded.



 Other adverse reactions reported in clinical trials were: diarrhea, rash, dyspepsia, flatulence, and asthenia.



   Laboratory Tests  



 Marked persistent increases of hepatic transaminases have been noted  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ].  Elevated alkaline phosphatase and gamma-glutamyl transpeptidase have also been reported. About 5% of patients had elevations of CK levels of 3 or more times the normal value on one or more occasions. This was attributable to the noncardiac fraction of CK.  [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  .]  



   Adolescent Patients (ages 10-17 years)  



 In a 48-week, controlled study in adolescent boys and girls who were at least 1 year post-menarche, 10-17 years of age (43.4% female, 97.7% Caucasians, 1.7% Hispanics, 0.6% Multiracial) with heterozygous familial hypercholesterolemia (n=175), treated with placebo or ZOCOR (10-40 mg daily), the most common adverse reactions observed in both groups were upper respiratory infection, headache, abdominal pain, and nausea  [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.4)  and  Clinical Studies (14.2)  ]  .



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  Because the below reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is generally not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure. The following additional adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of simvastatin: pruritus, alopecia, a variety of skin changes (e.g., nodules, discoloration, dryness of skin/mucous membranes, changes to hair/nails), dizziness, muscle cramps, myalgia, pancreatitis, paresthesia, peripheral neuropathy, vomiting, anemia, erectile dysfunction, interstitial lung disease, rhabdomyolysis, hepatitis/jaundice, fatal and non-fatal hepatic failure, and depression.



 There have been rare reports of immune-mediated necrotizing myopathy associated with statin use  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .



 An apparent hypersensitivity syndrome has been reported rarely which has included some of the following features: anaphylaxis, angioedema, lupus erythematous-like syndrome, polymyalgia rheumatica, dermatomyositis, vasculitis, purpura, thrombocytopenia, leukopenia, hemolytic anemia, positive ANA, ESR increase, eosinophilia, arthritis, arthralgia, urticaria, asthenia, photosensitivity, fever, chills, flushing, malaise, dyspnea, toxic epidermal necrolysis, erythema multiforme, including Stevens-Johnson syndrome.



 There have been rare postmarketing reports of cognitive impairment (e.g., memory loss, forgetfulness, amnesia, memory impairment, confusion) associated with statin use. These cognitive issues have been reported for all statins. The reports are generally nonserious, and reversible upon statin discontinuation, with variable times to symptom onset (1 day to years) and symptom resolution (median of 3 weeks).
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *   Patients should be advised of the increased risk of myopathy including rhabdomyolysis with the 80-mg dose. (  5.1  )  
 *  Skeletal muscle effects (e.g., myopathy and rhabdomyolysis): Risks increase with higher doses and concomitant use of certain medicines. Predisposing factors include advanced age (&gt;=65), female gender, uncontrolled hypothyroidism, and renal impairment. Rare cases of rhabdomyolysis with acute renal failure secondary to myoglobinuria have been reported. (  4  ,  5.1  ,  8.5  ,  8.6  ) 
 *  Patients should be advised to report promptly any unexplained and/or persistent muscle pain, tenderness, or weakness. ZOCOR therapy should be discontinued immediately if myopathy is diagnosed or suspected. See Drug Interaction table. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Liver enzyme abnormalities: Persistent elevations in hepatic transaminases can occur. Check liver enzyme tests before initiating therapy and as clinically indicated thereafter. (  5.2  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Myopathy/Rhabdomyolysis



  Simvastatin occasionally causes myopathy manifested as muscle pain, tenderness or weakness with creatine kinase (CK) above ten times the upper limit of normal (ULN). Myopathy sometimes takes the form of rhabdomyolysis with or without acute renal failure secondary to myoglobinuria, and rare fatalities have occurred. The risk of myopathy is increased by high levels of statin activity in plasma. Predisposing factors for myopathy include advanced age (&gt;=65 years), female gender, uncontrolled hypothyroidism, and renal impairment.



  The risk of myopathy, including rhabdomyolysis, is dose related.  In a clinical trial database in which 41,413 patients were treated with ZOCOR, 24,747 (approximately 60%) of whom were enrolled in studies with a median follow-up of at least 4 years, the incidence of myopathy was approximately 0.03% and 0.08% at 20 and 40 mg/day, respectively. The incidence of myopathy with 80 mg (0.61%) was disproportionately higher than that observed at the lower doses. In these trials, patients were carefully monitored and some interacting medicinal products were excluded.



 In a clinical trial in which 12,064 patients with a history of myocardial infarction were treated with ZOCOR (mean follow-up 6.7 years), the incidence of myopathy (defined as unexplained muscle weakness or pain with a serum creatine kinase [CK] &gt;10 times upper limit of normal [ULN]) in patients on 80 mg/day was approximately 0.9% compared with 0.02% for patients on 20 mg/day. The incidence of rhabdomyolysis (defined as myopathy with a CK &gt;40 times ULN) in patients on 80 mg/day was approximately 0.4% compared with 0% for patients on 20 mg/day. The incidence of myopathy, including rhabdomyolysis, was highest during the first year and then notably decreased during the subsequent years of treatment. In this trial, patients were carefully monitored and some interacting medicinal products were excluded.



  The risk of myopathy, including rhabdomyolysis, is greater in patients on simvastatin 80 mg compared with other statin therapies with similar or greater LDL-C-lowering efficacy and compared with lower doses of simvastatin. Therefore, the 80-mg dose of ZOCOR should be used only in patients who have been taking simvastatin 80 mg chronically (e.g., for 12 months or more) without evidence of muscle toxicity [see  Dosage and Administration, Restricted Dosing for 80 mg (2.2)  ].  If, however, a patient who is currently tolerating the 80-mg dose of ZOCOR needs to be initiated on an interacting drug that is contraindicated or is associated with a dose cap for simvastatin, that patient should be switched to an alternative statin with less potential for the drug-drug interaction. Patients should be advised of the increased risk of myopathy, including rhabdomyolysis, and to report promptly any unexplained muscle pain, tenderness or weakness. If symptoms occur, treatment should be discontinued immediately.   [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  .]  



 There have been rare reports of immune-mediated necrotizing myopathy (IMNM), an autoimmune myopathy, associated with statin use. IMNM is characterized by: proximal muscle weakness and elevated serum creatine kinase, which persist despite discontinuation of statin treatment; muscle biopsy showing necrotizing myopathy without significant inflammation; improvement with immunosuppressive agents.



  All patients starting therapy with ZOCOR, or whose dose of ZOCOR is being increased, should be advised of the risk of myopathy, including rhabdomyolysis, and told to report promptly any unexplained muscle pain, tenderness or weakness particularly if accompanied by malaise or fever or if muscle signs and symptoms persist after discontinuing ZOCOR. ZOCOR therapy should be discontinued immediately if myopathy is diagnosed or suspected.  In most cases, muscle symptoms and CK increases resolved when treatment was promptly discontinued. Periodic CK determinations may be considered in patients starting therapy with ZOCOR or whose dose is being increased, but there is no assurance that such monitoring will prevent myopathy.



 Many of the patients who have developed rhabdomyolysis on therapy with simvastatin have had complicated medical histories, including renal insufficiency usually as a consequence of long-standing diabetes mellitus. Such patients merit closer monitoring. ZOCOR therapy should be discontinued if markedly elevated CPK levels occur or myopathy is diagnosed or suspected. ZOCOR therapy should also be temporarily withheld in any patient experiencing an acute or serious condition predisposing to the development of renal failure secondary to rhabdomyolysis, e.g., sepsis; hypotension; major surgery; trauma; severe metabolic, endocrine, or electrolyte disorders; or uncontrolled epilepsy.



  Drug Interactions  



 The risk of myopathy and rhabdomyolysis is increased by high levels of statin activity in plasma. Simvastatin is metabolized by the cytochrome P450 isoform 3A4. Certain drugs which inhibit this metabolic pathway can raise the plasma levels of simvastatin and may increase the risk of myopathy. These include itraconazole, ketoconazole, posaconazole, voriconazole, the macrolide antibiotics erythromycin and clarithromycin, and the ketolide antibiotic telithromycin, HIV protease inhibitors, boceprevir, telaprevir, the antidepressant nefazodone, cobicistat-containing products, or grapefruit juice [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  . Combination of these drugs with simvastatin is contraindicated. If short-term treatment with strong CYP3A4 inhibitors is unavoidable, therapy with simvastatin must be suspended during the course of treatment. [See  Contraindications (4)  and  Drug Interactions (7.1)  .]  



 The combined use of simvastatin with gemfibrozil, cyclosporine, or danazol is contraindicated [see  Contraindications (4)  and Drug Interactions (  7.1  and  7.2  )].  



 Caution should be used when prescribing other fibrates with simvastatin, as these agents can cause myopathy when given alone and the risk is increased when they are coadministered [see  Drug Interactions (7.2)  ]  .



 Cases of myopathy, including rhabdomyolysis, have been reported with simvastatin coadministered with colchicine, and caution should be exercised when prescribing simvastatin with colchicine [see  Drug Interactions (7.7)  ]  .



 The benefits of the combined use of simvastatin with the following drugs should be carefully weighed against the potential risks of combinations: other lipid-lowering drugs (other fibrates, &gt;=1 g/day of niacin, or, for patients with HoFH, lomitapide), amiodarone, dronedarone, verapamil, diltiazem, amlodipine, or ranolazine [see  Drug Interactions (7.3)  and  Table 3  in Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)] [also see  Dosage and Administration, Patients with Homozygous Familial Hypercholesterolemia (2.4)  ]  .



 Cases of myopathy, including rhabdomyolysis, have been observed with simvastatin coadministered with lipid-modifying doses (&gt;=1 g/day niacin) of niacin-containing products. In an ongoing, double-blind, randomized cardiovascular outcomes trial, an independent safety monitoring committee identified that the incidence of myopathy is higher in Chinese compared with non-Chinese patients taking simvastatin 40 mg coadministered with lipid-modifying doses of a niacin-containing product. Caution should be used when treating Chinese patients with simvastatin in doses exceeding 20 mg/day coadministered with lipid-modifying doses of niacin-containing products. Because the risk for myopathy is dose-related, Chinese patients should not receive simvastatin 80 mg coadministered with lipid-modifying doses of niacin-containing products. It is unknown if the risk for myopathy with coadministration of simvastatin with lipid-modifying doses of niacin-containing products observed in Chinese patients applies to other Asian patients [see  Drug Interactions (7.4)  ]  .



 Prescribing recommendations for interacting agents are summarized in Table 1 [see also  Dosage and Administration (2.3  ,  2.4)  ,  Drug Interactions (7)  ,  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ].  



 Table 1: Drug Interactions Associated with Increased Risk of Myopathy/Rhabdomyolysis 
 Interacting Agents                            Prescribing Recommendations                                
  
  Strong CYP3A4 Inhibitors, e.g.:        Itraconazole        Ketoconazole        Posaconazole        Voriconazole        Erythromycin        Clarithromycin        Telithromycin        HIV protease inhibitors        Boceprevir        Telaprevir        Nefazodone        Cobicistat-containing products  Gemfibrozil  Cyclosporine  Danazol   Contraindicated with simvastatin                           
  Verapamil  Diltiazem  Dronedarone            Do not exceed 10 mg simvastatin daily                      
  Amiodarone  Amlodipine  Ranolazine           Do not exceed 20 mg simvastatin daily                      
  Lomitapide                                   For patients with HoFH, do not exceed 20 mg simvastatin daily   
  Grapefruit juice                             Avoid grapefruit juice                                     
           5.2 Liver Dysfunction
 

   Persistent increases (to more than 3X the ULN) in serum transaminases have occurred in approximately 1% of patients who received simvastatin in clinical studies  . When drug treatment was interrupted or discontinued in these patients, the transaminase levels usually fell slowly to pretreatment levels. The increases were not associated with jaundice or other clinical signs or symptoms. There was no evidence of hypersensitivity.



 In the Scandinavian Simvastatin Survival Study (4S) [see  Clinical Studies (14.1)  ]  , the number of patients with more than one transaminase elevation to &gt;3X ULN, over the course of the study, was not significantly different between the simvastatin and placebo groups (14 [0.7%] vs. 12 [0.6%]). Elevated transaminases resulted in the discontinuation of 8 patients from therapy in the simvastatin group (n=2,221) and 5 in the placebo group (n=2,223). Of the 1,986 simvastatin treated patients in 4S with normal liver function tests (LFTs) at baseline, 8 (0.4%) developed consecutive LFT elevations to &gt;3X ULN and/or were discontinued due to transaminase elevations during the 5.4 years (median follow-up) of the study. Among these 8 patients, 5 initially developed these abnormalities within the first year. All of the patients in this study received a starting dose of 20 mg of simvastatin; 37% were titrated to 40 mg.



 In 2 controlled clinical studies in 1,105 patients, the 12-month incidence of persistent hepatic transaminase elevation without regard to drug relationship was 0.9% and 2.1% at the 40- and 80-mg dose, respectively. No patients developed persistent liver function abnormalities following the initial 6 months of treatment at a given dose.



  It is recommended that liver function tests be performed before the initiation of treatment, and thereafter when clinically indicated.  There have been rare postmarketing reports of fatal and non-fatal hepatic failure in patients taking statins, including simvastatin. If serious liver injury with clinical symptoms and/or hyperbilirubinemia or jaundice occurs during treatment with ZOCOR, promptly interrupt therapy. If an alternate etiology is not found do not restart ZOCOR. Note that ALT may emanate from muscle, therefore ALT rising with CK may indicate myopathy [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  .



 The drug should be used with caution in patients who consume substantial quantities of alcohol and/or have a past history of liver disease. Active liver diseases or unexplained transaminase elevations are contraindications to the use of simvastatin.



 Moderate (less than 3X ULN) elevations of serum transaminases have been reported following therapy with simvastatin. These changes appeared soon after initiation of therapy with simvastatin, were often transient, were not accompanied by any symptoms and did not require interruption of treatment.



    5.3 Endocrine Function



  Increases in HbA1c and fasting serum glucose levels have been reported with HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors, including ZOCOR.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
