<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="zohydro" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions are discussed elsewhere in the labeling:



 *  Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  
 *  Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  
 *  Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ]  
 *  Interactions with Other CNS Depressants [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  ]  
 *  Hypotensive Effect [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)  ]  
 *  Gastrointestinal Conditions [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)  ]  
 *  Seizures [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.10)  ]  
      EXCERPT:   Adverse reactions in &gt;=2% of patients in placebo-controlled trials include constipation, nausea, somnolence, fatigue, headache, dizziness, dry mouth, vomiting, pruritus, abdominal pain, edema peripheral, upper respiratory tract infection, muscle spasms, urinary tract infection, back pain, and tremor. (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pernix Therapeutics, LLC. at 1-800-793-2145 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trial Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in clinical practice. The safety of ZOHYDRO ER was evaluated in a total of 1,148 subjects in Phase 3 clinical trials.



 Table 3 lists the most frequently occurring adverse reactions occurring at a greater frequency than placebo from the placebo-controlled trial in subjects with moderate-to-severe chronic lower back pain.



 Table 3. Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events in &gt;=2% of Subjects During the Open-Label Titration Period and/or the Double-Blind Treatment Period, by Preferred Term - Number (%) of Treated Subjects (Placebo-Controlled Study in Opioid-Experienced Subjects with Moderate-to-Severe Chronic Lower Back Pain) 
                            Open-Label Titration Period  Double-Blind Treatment Period   
                                   ZOHYDRO ER                 ZOHYDRO ER                   Placebo            
 Preferred Term                     (N = 510)                  (n = 151)                  (n = 151)           
  
 Constipation                       56 (11%)                    12 (8%)                    0 (0%)             
 Nausea                             50 (10%)                    11 (7%)                    5 (3%)             
 Somnolence                          24 (5%)                    1 (1%)                     0 (0%)             
 Fatigue                             21 (4%)                    1 (1%)                     2 (1%)             
 Headache                            19 (4%)                    0 (0%)                     2 (1%)             
 Dizziness                           17 (3%)                    3 (2%)                     1 (1%)             
 Dry mouth                           16 (3%)                    0 (0%)                     0 (0%)             
 Vomiting                            14 (3%)                    7 (5%)                     1 (1%)             
 Pruritus                            13 (3%)                    0 (0%)                     0 (0%)             
 Abdominal pain                      8 (2%)                     4 (3%)                     0 (0%)             
 Edema peripheral                    7 (1%)                     4 (3%)                     0 (0%)             
 Upper respiratory tract infection           7 (1%)                     5 (3%)                     1 (1%)             
 Muscle spasms                       6 (1%)                     4 (3%)                     2 (1%)             
 Urinary tract infection             4 (1%)                     8 (5%)                     3 (2%)             
 Back pain                           4 (1%)                     6 (4%)                     5 (3%)             
 Tremor                              1 (0%)                     4 (3%)                     1 (1%)             
          The  common  (&gt;=1% to &lt;10%) adverse drug reactions reported at least once by subjects treated with ZOHYDRO ER in the Phase 3 clinical trials and not represented in Table 3 were:
 

   Gastrointestinal Disorders:  abdominal discomfort, abdominal pain, gastroesophageal reflux disease



   General Disorders and Administration Site Conditions:  non-cardiac chest pain, pain, peripheral edema, pyrexia



   Injury, Poisoning and Procedural Complications:  contusion, fall, foot fracture, joint injury, joint sprain, muscle strain, skin laceration



   Investigations:  increased blood cholesterol, increased gamma-glutamyltransferase



   Metabolism and Nutrition Disorders:  dehydration, hypokalemia



   Musculoskeletal and Connective Tissue Disorders:  arthralgia, musculoskeletal pain, myalgia, neck pain, osteoarthritis, pain in extremity



   Nervous System Disorders:  lethargy, migraine, paresthesia



   Psychiatric Disorders:  anxiety, depression, insomnia



   Respiratory, Thoracic, and Mediastinal Disorders:  cough, dyspnea



   Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue Disorders:  hyperhidrosis, night sweats, rash



   Vascular Disorders:  hot flush
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: ADDICTION, ABUSE, AND MISUSE; LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL INGESTION; NEONATAL OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME; INTERACTION WITH ALCOHOL; and CYTOCHROME P450 3A4 INTERACTION

    WARNING: ADDICTION, ABUSE, AND MISUSE; LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL INGESTION; NEONATAL OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME; INTERACTION WITH ALCOHOL; and CYTOCHROME P450 3A4 INTERACTION  

  EXCERPT:   WARNING: ADDICTION, ABUSE, AND MISUSE; LIFE-THREATENING RESPIRATORY DEPRESSION; ACCIDENTAL INGESTION; NEONATAL OPIOID WITHDRAWAL SYNDROME; INTERACTION WITH ALCOHOL; and CYTOCHROME P450 3A4 INTERACTION



   See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.  



 *  ZOHYDRO ER exposes users to risks of addiction, abuse, and misuse, which can lead to overdose and death. Assess each patient's risk before prescribing, and monitor regularly for development of these behaviors or conditions. (5.1) 
 *  Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression may occur. Monitor closely, especially upon initiation or following a dose increase. Instruct patients to swallow ZOHYDRO ER whole to avoid exposure to a potentially fatal dose of hydrocodone. (5.2) 
 *  Accidental ingestion of ZOHYDRO ER, especially in children, can result in a fatal overdose of hydrocodone. (5.2) 
 *  Prolonged use of ZOHYDRO ER during pregnancy can result in neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, which may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated. If opioid use is required for a prolonged period in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available. (5.3) 
 *  Instruct patients not to consume alcohol or any products containing alcohol while taking ZOHYDRO ER because co-ingestion can result in fatal plasma hydrocodone levels. (5.4) 
 *  Initiation of CYP3A4 inhibitors (or discontinuation of CYP3A4 inducers) can result in a fatal overdose of hydrocodone from ZOHYDRO ER. (5.13) 
    
 

      Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse    



 ZOHYDRO ER exposes patients and other users to the risks of opioid addiction, abuse, and misuse, which can lead to overdose and death. Assess each patient's risk prior to prescribing ZOHYDRO ER and monitor all patients regularly for the development of these behaviors or conditions   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.1)  ]  . 



     Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression  



 Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression may occur with use of ZOHYDRO ER. Monitor for respiratory depression, especially during initiation of ZOHYDRO ER or following a dose increase  .   Instruct patients to swallow ZOHYDRO ER capsules whole; crushing, chewing, or dissolving ZOHYDRO ER capsules can cause rapid release and absorption of a potentially fatal dose of hydrocodone   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  . 



     Accidental Ingestion  



 Accidental ingestion of even one dose of ZOHYDRO ER, especially by children, can result in a fatal overdose of hydrocodone   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  .



     Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome  



 Prolonged use of ZOHYDRO ER during pregnancy can result in neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, which may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated, and requires management according to protocols developed by neonatology experts. If opioid use is required for a prolonged period in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.3)  ].  



     Interaction with Alcohol  



 Instruct patients not to consume alcoholic beverages or use prescription or non-prescription products that contain alcohol while taking ZOHYDRO ER. The co-ingestion of alcohol with ZOHYDRO ER may result in increased plasma levels and a potentially fatal overdose of hydrocodone   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   and   Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .



     Cytochrome P450 3A4 Interaction   



 The concomitant use of ZOHYDRO ER with all cytochrome P450 3A4 inhibitors may result in an increase in hydrocodone plasma concentrations, which could increase or prolong adverse drug effects and may cause potentially fatal respiratory depression. In addition, discontinuation of a concomitantly used cytochrome P450 3A4 inducer may result in an increase in hydrocodone plasma concentration. Monitor patients receiving ZOHYDRO ER and any CYP3A4 inhibitor or inducer   [see   Warnings and Precautions (5.13)   and   Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  EXCERPT:    See  Boxed WARNINGS    



 *  Interactions with CNS depressants: Concomitant use may cause profound sedation, respiratory depression, and death. If coadministration is required, consider dose reduction of one or both drugs. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Elderly, cachectic, debilitated patients, and those with chronic pulmonary disease: Monitor closely because of increased risk for life-threatening respiratory depression. (  5.5  ,  5.6  ) 
 *  Hypotensive effects: Monitor during dose initiation and titration. (  5.7  ) 
 *  Patients with head injury or increased intracranial pressure: Monitor for sedation and respiratory depression. Avoid use of ZOHYDRO ER in patients with impaired consciousness or coma susceptible to intracranial effects of CO2retention. (  5.8  ) 
 *  Concomitant use of CYP3A4 inhibitors may increase opioid effects. (  5.13  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Addiction, Abuse, and Misuse



   ZOHYDRO ER contains hydrocodone, a Schedule II controlled substance. As an opioid, ZOHYDRO ER exposes users to the risks of addiction, abuse, and misuse [see  Drug Abuse and Dependence (9)  ]  . As modified-release products such as ZOHYDRO ER deliver the opioid over an extended period of time, there is a greater risk for overdose and death due to the larger amount of hydrocodone present.  



 Although the risk of addiction in any individual is unknown, it can occur in patients appropriately prescribed ZOHYDRO ER and in those who obtain the drug illicitly. Addiction can occur at recommended doses and if the drug is misused or abused.



 Assess each patient's risk for opioid addiction, abuse, or misuse prior to prescribing ZOHYDRO ER, and monitor all patients receiving ZOHYDRO ER for the development of these behaviors or conditions. Risks are increased in patients with a personal or family history of substance abuse (including drug or alcohol addiction or abuse) or mental illness (e.g., major depression). The potential for these risks should not, however, prevent the prescribing of ZOHYDRO ER for the proper management of pain in any given patient. Patients at increased risk may be prescribed modified-release opioid formulations such as ZOHYDRO ER, but use in such patients necessitates intensive counseling about the risks and proper use of ZOHYDRO ER along with intensive monitoring for signs of addiction, abuse, and misuse.



 Abuse or misuse of ZOHYDRO ER by crushing, chewing, snorting, or injecting the dissolved product will result in the uncontrolled delivery of the hydrocodone and can result in overdose and death [see  Overdosage (10)  ]  .



 Opioid agonists such as ZOHYDRO ER are sought by drug abusers and people with addiction disorders and are subject to criminal diversion. Consider these risks when prescribing or dispensing ZOHYDRO ER. Strategies to reduce these risks include prescribing the drug in the smallest appropriate quantity and advising the patient on the proper disposal of unused drug [see  Patient Counseling Information (17)  ]  . Contact local state professional licensing board or state controlled substances authority for information on how to prevent and detect abuse or diversion of this product.



    5.2 Life-Threatening Respiratory Depression



  Serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression has been reported with the use of modified-release opioids, even when used as recommended. Respiratory depression from opioid use, if not immediately recognized and treated, may lead to respiratory arrest and death. Management of respiratory depression may include close observation, supportive measures, and use of opioid antagonists, depending on the patient's clinical status [see  Overdosage (10)  ]  . Carbon dioxide (CO2) retention from opioid-induced respiratory depression can exacerbate the sedating effects of opioids.



 While serious, life-threatening, or fatal respiratory depression can occur at any time during the use of ZOHYDRO ER, the risk is greatest during the initiation of therapy or following a dose increase. Closely monitor patients for respiratory depression when initiating therapy with ZOHYDRO ER and following dose increases.



 To reduce the risk of respiratory depression, proper dosing and titration of ZOHYDRO ER are essential [see  Dosage and Administration (2)  ]  . Overestimating the ZOHYDRO ER dose when converting patients from another opioid product can result in fatal overdose with the first dose.



 Accidental ingestion of even one dose of ZOHYDRO ER, especially by children, can result in respiratory depression and death due to an overdose of hydrocodone.



    5.3 Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome



  Prolonged use of ZOHYDRO ER during pregnancy can result in withdrawal signs in the neonate. Neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome, unlike opioid withdrawal syndrome in adults, may be life-threatening if not recognized and treated, and requires management according to protocols developed by neonatology experts. If opioid use is required for a prolonged period in a pregnant woman, advise the patient of the risk of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome and ensure that appropriate treatment will be available. Neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome presents as irritability, hyperactivity and abnormal sleep pattern, high pitched cry, tremor, vomiting, diarrhea and failure to gain weight. The onset, duration, and severity of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome vary based on the specific opioid used, duration of use, timing and amount of last maternal use, and rate of elimination of the drug by the newborn.



    5.4 Interactions with Central Nervous System Depressants



  Patients must not consume alcoholic beverages, or prescription or non-prescription products containing alcohol, while on ZOHYDRO ER therapy. The co-ingestion of alcohol with ZOHYDRO ER may result in increased plasma levels and a potentially fatal overdose of hydrocodone [see  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ].  



 Hypotension, profound sedation, coma, respiratory depression, and death may result if ZOHYDRO ER is used concomitantly with alcohol or other central nervous system (CNS) depressants (e.g., sedatives, anxiolytics, hypnotics, neuroleptics, other opioids).



 When considering the use of ZOHYDRO ER in a patient taking a CNS depressant, assess the duration of use of the CNS depressant and the patient's response, including the degree of tolerance that has developed to CNS depression. Additionally, evaluate the patient's use of alcohol or illicit drugs that cause CNS depression. If the decision to begin ZOHYDRO ER is made, start with a lower ZOHYDRO ER dose than usual (i.e., 20%-30% less), monitor patients for signs of sedation and respiratory depression, and consider using a lower dose of the concomitant CNS depressant [see  Drug Interactions (7.2)  ].  



    5.5 Use in Elderly, Cachectic, and Debilitated Patients



  Life-threatening respiratory depression is more likely to occur in elderly, cachectic, or debilitated patients as they may have altered pharmacokinetics or altered clearance compared to younger, healthier patients. Monitor such patients closely, particularly when initiating and titrating ZOHYDRO ER and when ZOHYDRO ER is given concomitantly with other drugs that depress respiration [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  .



    5.6 Use in Patients with Chronic Pulmonary Disease



  Monitor for respiratory depression in patients with significant chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or cor pulmonale, and patients having a substantially decreased respiratory reserve, hypoxia, hypercapnia, or preexisting respiratory depression, particularly when initiating therapy and titrating with ZOHYDRO ER, as in these patients, even usual therapeutic doses of ZOHYDRO ER may decrease respiratory drive to the point of apnea [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ].  Consider the use of alternative non-opioid analgesics in these patients if possible.



    5.7 Hypotensive Effect



  ZOHYDRO ER may cause severe hypotension including orthostatic hypotension and syncope in ambulatory patients. There is an added risk to individuals whose ability to maintain blood pressure has been compromised by a depleted blood volume, or after concurrent administration with drugs such as phenothiazines or other agents which compromise vasomotor tone. Monitor these patients for signs of hypotension after initiating or titrating the dose of ZOHYDRO ER. In patients with circulatory shock, ZOHYDRO ER may cause vasodilation that can further reduce cardiac output and blood pressure. Avoid the use of ZOHYDRO ER in patients with circulatory shock.



    5.8 Use in Patients with Head Injury and Increased Intracranial Pressure



  Monitor patients taking ZOHYDRO ER who may be susceptible to the intracranial effects of CO2retention (e.g., those with evidence of increased intracranial pressure or brain tumors) for signs of sedation and respiratory depression, particularly when initiating therapy with ZOHYDRO ER. ZOHYDRO ER may reduce respiratory drive, and the resultant CO2retention can further increase intracranial pressure. Opioids may also obscure the clinical course in a patient with a head injury.



 Avoid the use of ZOHYDRO ER in patients with impaired consciousness or coma.



    5.9 Use in Patients with Gastrointestinal Conditions



  ZOHYDRO ER is contraindicated in patients with known or suspected paralytic ileus. Opioids diminish propulsive peristaltic waves in the gastrointestinal tract and decrease bowel motility. Monitor for decreased bowel motility in post-operative patients receiving opioids. The administration of ZOHYDRO ER may obscure the diagnosis or clinical course in patients with acute abdominal conditions. Hydrocodone may cause spasm of the sphincter of Oddi. Monitor patients with biliary tract disease, including acute pancreatitis.



    5.10 Use in Patients with Convulsive or Seizure Disorders



  The hydrocodone in ZOHYDRO ER may aggravate convulsions in patients with convulsive disorders, and may induce or aggravate seizures in some clinical settings. Monitor patients with a history of seizure disorders for worsened seizure control during ZOHYDRO ER therapy.



    5.11 Avoidance of Withdrawal



  Avoid the use of mixed agonist/antagonist (i.e., pentazocine, nalbuphine, and butorphanol) or partial agonist (buprenorphine) analgesics in patients who have received, or are receiving, a course of therapy with a full opioid agonist analgesic, including ZOHYDRO ER. In these patients, mixed agonist/antagonist and partial agonist analgesics may reduce the analgesic effect and/or may precipitate withdrawal symptoms [see  Drug Interactions (7.4)    ].



    5.12 Driving and Operating Machinery



  ZOHYDRO ER may impair the mental and physical abilities needed to perform potentially hazardous activities such as driving a car or operating machinery. Warn patients not to drive or operate dangerous machinery unless they are tolerant to the effects of ZOHYDRO ER and know how they will react to the medication.



    5.13 Cytochrome P450 CYP3A4 Inhibitors and Inducers



  Since the CYP3A4 isoenzyme plays a major role in the metabolism of ZOHYDRO ER, drugs that alter CYP3A4 activity may cause changes in clearance of hydrocodone which could lead to changes in hydrocodone plasma concentrations.



 Inhibition of CYP3A4 activity by its inhibitors such as macrolide antibiotics (e.g., erythromycin), azole-antifungal agents, (e.g., ketoconazole), and protease inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir), may increase plasma concentrations of hydrocodone and prolong opioid effects.



 CYP3A4 inducers, such as rifampin, carbamazepine, and phenytoin, may induce the metabolism of hydrocodone and, therefore, may cause increased clearance of the drug which could lead to a decrease in hydrocodone plasma concentrations, lack of efficacy or, possibly, development of an abstinence syndrome in a patient who had developed physical dependence to hydrocodone.



 If co-administration is necessary, monitor patients closely who are currently taking, or discontinuing, CYP3A4 inhibitors or inducers. Evaluate these patients at frequent intervals and consider dose adjustments until stable drug effects are achieved [see  Drug Interactions (7.3)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
