<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="zoladex1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common, clinically significant adverse reactions occurring in &gt;10% of men: hot flashes, sexual dysfunction, decreased erections and lower urinary tract symptoms  (6)  



 Tumor flare can occur on the initiation of ZOLADEX therapy (  5.1  ,  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact AstraZeneca at 1-800-236-9933 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch for voluntary reporting of adverse reactions.  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials

  ZOLADEX has been found to be generally well tolerated in clinical trials. Adverse reactions reported in these trials were rarely severe enough to result in the patients' withdrawal from ZOLADEX treatment. As seen with other hormonal therapies, the most commonly observed adverse events during ZOLADEX therapy were due to the expected physiological effects from decreased testosterone levels. These included hot flashes, sexual dysfunction and decreased erections.



   Tumor Flare Phenomenon:  Initially, ZOLADEX, like other GnRH agonists, causes transient increases in serum levels of testosterone. A small percentage of patients experienced a temporary worsening of signs and symptoms, usually manifested by an increase in cancer-related pain which was managed symptomatically. Isolated cases of exacerbation of disease symptoms, either ureteral obstruction or spinal cord compression, occurred at similar rates in controlled clinical trials with both ZOLADEX and orchiectomy. The relationship of these events to therapy is uncertain  [see      Warnings and Precautions (5.1)      and  Patient Counseling Information (17.1)  ]  .



   6.2 Stage B2-C Prostatic Carcinoma

  Treatment with ZOLADEX and flutamide did not add substantially to the toxicity of radiation treatment alone. The following adverse experiences were reported during a multicenter clinical trial comparing ZOLADEX + flutamide + radiation versus radiation alone. The most frequently reported (greater than 5%) adverse experiences are listed below:



 Table 1 ADVERSE EVENTS DURING ACUTE RADIATION THERAPY (within first 90 days of radiation therapy) 
                                 (n=231)    flutamide + ZOLADEX + Radiation    % All      (n = 235)    Radiation Only    % All     
  
  Rectum/Large Bowel            80                     76                     
  Bladder                       58                     60                     
  Skin                          37                     37                     
        Table 2 ADVERSE EVENTS DURING LATE RADIATION PHASE (after 90 days of radiation therapy) 
                                 (n=231)    flutamide + ZOLADEX + Radiation    % All      (n = 235)    Radiation Only    % All     
  
  Diarrhea                      36                     40                     
  Cystitis                      16                     16                     
  Rectal Bleeding               14                     20                     
  Proctitis                     8                      8                      
  Hematuria                     7                      12                     
         Additional adverse event data was collected for the combination therapy with radiation group over both the hormonal treatment and hormonal treatment plus radiation phases of the study. Adverse experiences occurring in more than 5% of patients in this group, over both parts of the study, were hot flashes (46%), diarrhea (40%), nausea (9%), and skin rash (8%).
 

   6.3 Prostatic Carcinoma

  Two controlled clinical trials using ZOLADEX 10.8 mg versus ZOLADEX 3.6 mg were conducted. During a comparative phase, patients were randomized to receive either a single 10.8 mg implant or three consecutive 3.6 mg implants every 4 weeks over weeks 0-12. During this phase, the only adverse event reported in greater than 5% of patients was hot flashes, with an incidence of 47% in the ZOLADEX 10.8 mg group and 48% in the ZOLADEX 3.6 mg group.



 From weeks 12-48 all patients were treated with a 10.8 mg implant every 12 weeks. During this noncomparative phase, the following adverse events were reported in greater than 5% of patients:



 Table 3 Adverse Events were reported in greater than 5% of patients 
   Adverse Event      ZOLADEX 10.8 mg    (n=157)    %     
  
  Hot Flashes        64                      
  Pain (general)     14                      
  Gynecomastia       8                       
  Pelvic Pain        6                       
  Bone Pain          6                       
  Asthenia           5                       
        The following adverse events were reported in greater than 1%, but less than 5% of patients treated with ZOLADEX 10.8 mg implant every 12 weeks. Some of these are commonly reported in elderly patients.
 

 WHOLE BODY - Abdominal pain, Back pain, Flu syndrome, Headache, Sepsis, Aggravation reaction



 CARDIOVASCULAR - Angina pectoris, Cerebral ischemia, Cerebrovascular accident, Heart failure, Pulmonary embolus, Varicose veins



 DIGESTIVE - Diarrhea, Hematemesis



 ENDOCRINE - Diabetes mellitus



 HEMATOLOGIC - Anemia



 METABOLIC -Peripheral edema



 NERVOUS SYSTEM - Dizziness, Paresthesia, Urinary retention



 RESPIRATORY - Cough increased, Dyspnea, Pneumonia



 SKIN - Herpes simplex, Pruritus



 UROGENITAL - Bladder neoplasm, Breast pain, Hematuria, Impotence, Urinary frequency, Urinary incontinence, Urinary tract disorder, Urinary tract infection, Urination impaired



 The following adverse events not already listed above were reported in patients receiving ZOLADEX 3.6 mg in other clinical trials. Inclusion does not necessarily represent a causal relationship to ZOLADEX 10.8 mg.



 WHOLE BODY: Allergic reaction, Chills, Fever, Infection, Injection site reaction, Lethargy, Malaise



 CARDIOVASCULAR: Arrhythmia, Chest pain, Hemorrhage, Hypertension, Migraine, Myocardial infarction, Palpitations, Peripheral vascular disorder, Tachycardia



 DIGESTIVE: Anorexia, Constipation, Dry mouth, Dyspepsia, Flatulence, Increased appetite, Nausea, Ulcer, Vomiting



 HEMATOLOGIC: Ecchymosis



 METABOLIC: Edema, Gout, Hyperglycemia, Weight increase



 MUSCULOSKELETAL: Arthralgia, Hypertonia, Joint disorder, Leg cramps, Myalgia, Osteoporosis



 NERVOUS SYSTEM: Anxiety, Depression, Emotional lability, Headache, Insomnia, Nervousness, Somnolence, Thinking abnormal



 RESPIRATORY: Bronchitis, Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, Epistaxis, Rhinitis, Sinusitis, Upper respiratory infection, Voice alterations



 SKIN: Acne, Alopecia, Dry skin, Hair disorders, Rash, Seborrhea, Skin discoloration, Sweating



 SPECIAL SENSES: Amblyopia, Dry eyes



 UROGENITAL: Breast tenderness, Decreased erections, Renal insufficiency, Sexual dysfunction, Urinary obstruction



   6.4 Changes in Laboratory Values During Treatment

    Plasma Enzymes:  Elevation of liver enzymes (AST, ALT) have been reported in female patients exposed to ZOLADEX 3.6 mg (representing less than 1% of all patients). There was no other evidence of abnormal liver function. Causality between these changes and ZOLADEX have not been established.



   Lipids:  In a controlled trial in females, ZOLADEX 3.6 mg implant therapy resulted in a minor, but statistically significant effect on serum lipids (i.e., increases in LDL cholesterol of 21.3 mg/dL; increases in HDL cholesterol of 2.7 mg/dL; and triglycerides increased by 8.0 mg/dL).



   6.5 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of ZOLADEX. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Hypercalcemia:  In patients with bone metastases.



   Bone Mineral Density:  Osteoporosis, decreased bone mineral density and bony fracture in men  [see  Patient Counseling Information (17.1)  ]  .



   Changes in Blood Pressure:  Hypotension and hypertension have been reported. These changes are usually transient, resolving either during continued therapy or after cessation of therapy.



   Pituitary Apoplexy and Tumors:  Pituitary apoplexy (a clinical syndrome secondary to infarction of the pituitary gland) and pituitary adenoma have been diagnosed. Most of the pituitary apoplexy cases occurred within 2 weeks of the first dose, and some occurred within the first hour. In these cases, pituitary apoplexy has presented as sudden headache, vomiting, visual changes, ophthalmoplegia, altered mental status, and sometimes cardiovascular collapse. Immediate medical attention has been required. Pituitary tumors have been reported.



   Acne:  Usually within one month of starting treatment.



   Other Adverse Reactions:  Psychotic disorders, convulsions and mood swings.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Tumor Flare Phenomenon: Transient worsening of tumor symptoms may occur during the first few weeks of treatment with ZOLADEX, which may include ureteral obstruction and spinal cord compression. Monitor patients at risk for complications of tumor flare (  5.1  ,  6.1  ) 
 *    Hypersensitivity: Systemic hypersensitivity has been reported in patients receiving goserelin implants (  4.1  ,  5.2  ) 
 *    Hyperglycemia and Diabetes: Hyperglycemia and an increased risk of developing diabetes have been reported in men receiving GnRH analogs. Monitor blood glucose level and manage according to current clinical practice  (5.3)   
 *    Cardiovascular Diseases: Increased risk of myocardial infarction, sudden cardiac death and stroke has been reported in association with use of GnRH analogs in men. Monitor for cardiovascular disease and manage according to current clinical practice  (5.4)   
 *    Effect on QT/QTc Interval: Androgen deprivation therapy may prolong the QT interval. Consider risks and benefits  (5.5)   
 *    Injection Site Injury: Injection site injury, such as pain, hematoma, hemorrhage and vascular injury, has been reported during treatment with ZOLADEX  (5.6)   
    
 

   5.1 Tumor Flare Phenomenon



  Initially, ZOLADEX, like other GnRH agonists, causes transient increases in serum levels of testosterone. Transient worsening of symptoms, or the occurrence of additional signs and symptoms of prostatic cancer, may occasionally develop during the first few weeks of ZOLADEX treatment. A small number of patients may experience a temporary increase in bone pain, which can be managed symptomatically. As with other GnRH agonists, isolated cases of ureteral obstruction and spinal cord compression have been observed. If spinal cord compression or renal impairment secondary to ureteral obstruction develops, standard treatment of these complications should be instituted, and in extreme cases an immediate orchiectomy [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  and  Patient Counseling Information (17.1)  ]  .



    5.2 Hypersensitivity



  Hypersensitivity, antibody formation and acute anaphylactic reactions have been reported with GnRH agonist analogues [see  Contraindications (4.1)  ]  .



 Of 115 women worldwide treated with ZOLADEX and tested for development of binding to goserelin following treatment with ZOLADEX, one patient showed low-titer binding to goserelin. On further testing of this patient's plasma obtained following treatment, her goserelin binding component was found not to be precipitated with rabbit antihuman immunoglobulin polyvalent sera. These findings suggest the possibility of antibody formation.



    5.3 Hyperglycemia and Diabetes



  Hyperglycemia and an increased risk of developing diabetes have been reported in men receiving GnRH agonists. Hyperglycemia may represent development of diabetes mellitus or worsening of glycemic control in patients with diabetes. Monitor blood glucose and/or glycosylated hemoglobin (HbA1c) periodically in patients receiving a GnRH agonist and manage with current practice for treatment of hyperglycemia or diabetes [see     Patient Counseling Information (17.1)  ].  



    5.4 Cardiovascular Diseases



  Increased risk of developing myocardial infarction, sudden cardiac death and stroke has been reported in association with use of GnRH agonists in men. The risk appears low based on the reported odds ratios, and should be evaluated carefully along with cardiovascular risk factors when determining a treatment for patients with prostate cancer. Patients receiving a GnRH agonist should be monitored for symptoms and signs suggestive of development of cardiovascular disease and be managed according to current clinical practice [see  Patient Counseling Information (17.1)  ]  .



     5.5 Effect on QT/QTc Interval  



   Androgen deprivation therapy may prolong the QT/QTc interval. Providers should consider whether the benefits of androgen deprivation therapy outweigh the potential risks in patients with congenital long QT syndrome, congestive heart failure, frequent electrolyte abnormalities, and in patients taking drugs known to prolong the QT interval. Electrolyte abnormalities should be corrected. Consider periodic monitoring of electrocardiograms and electrolytes  .



     5.6 Injection Site Injury  



   Injection site injury has been reported with ZOLADEX, such as pain, hematoma, hemorrhage and vascular injury, including cases resulting in hemorrhagic shock, requiring blood transfusions and surgical intervention. Extra care should be taken when administering ZOLADEX to patients with low BMI and/or receiving full anticoagulation medications [see     Dosage and Administration (2.5)     and        Patient Counseling Information (17.1)        ]  .  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
