<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="zoladex0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common, clinically significant adverse reactions occurring in &gt;10% of men: hot flashes, sexual dysfunction, decreased erections and lower urinary tract symptoms  (6)  



 The adverse event profile was similar for women treated for breast cancer, dysfunctional uterine bleeding or endometriosis and included (&gt;20%): hot flushes, headache, sweating, acne, emotional lability, depression, decreased libido, vaginitis, breast atrophy, seborrhea, and peripheral edema  (6)  



 Tumor flare can occur on the initiation of ZOLADEX for both men and women being treated for cancer  (6)  



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact AstraZeneca at 1-800-236-9933 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Stage B2-C Prostatic Carcinoma

  Treatment with ZOLADEX and flutamide did not add substantially to the toxicity of radiation treatment alone. The following adverse experiences were reported during a multicenter clinical trial comparing ZOLADEX + flutamide + radiation versus radiation alone. The most frequently reported (greater than 5%) adverse experiences are listed below:



 Table 1 ADVERSE EVENTS DURING ACUTE RADIATION THERAPY (within first 90 days of radiation therapy) 
                              (n=231) flutamide + ZOLADEX + Radiation    (n=235) Radiation Only    
                              % All             %All             
  Rectum/Large Bowel          80                76               
  Bladder                     58                60               
  Skin                        37                37               
        Table 2 ADVERSE EVENTS DURING LATE RADIATION PHASE (after 90 days of radiation therapy) 
                              (n=231) flutamide + ZOLADEX + Radiation    (n=235) Radiation Only    
                              % All             %All             
  Diarrhea                    36                40               
  Cystitis                    16                16               
  Rectal Bleeding             14                20               
  Proctitis                   8                 8                
  Hematuria                   7                 12               
         Additional adverse event data was collected for the combination therapy with radiation group over both the hormonal treatment and hormonal treatment plus radiation phases of the study. Adverse experiences occurring in more than 5% of patients in this group, over both parts of the study, were hot flashes (46%), diarrhea (40%), nausea (9%), and skin rash (8%).
 

   6.2 Prostatic Carcinoma

  ZOLADEX has been found to be generally well tolerated in clinical trials. Adverse reactions reported in these trials were rarely severe enough to result in the patients' withdrawal from ZOLADEX treatment. As seen with other hormonal therapies, the most commonly observed adverse events during ZOLADEX therapy were due to the expected physiological effects from decreased testosterone levels. These included hot flashes, sexual dysfunction and decreased erections.



   Tumor Flare Phenomenon:  Initially, ZOLADEX, like other GnRH agonists, causes transient increases in serum levels of testosterone. A small percentage of patients experienced a temporary worsening of signs and symptoms, usually manifested by an increase in cancer-related pain which was managed symptomatically. Isolated cases of exacerbation of disease symptoms, either ureteral obstruction or spinal cord compression, occurred at similar rates in controlled clinical trials with both ZOLADEX and orchiectomy. The relationship of these events to therapy is uncertain  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ].  



 In the controlled clinical trials of ZOLADEX versus orchiectomy, the following events were reported as adverse reactions in greater than 5% of the patients.



 Table 3 TREATMENT RECEIVED 
                                            ZOLADEX    (n=242)      ORCHIECTOMY    (n=254)     
   ADVERSE EVENT                            %               %                    
  
  Hot Flashes                              62              53                    
  Sexual Dysfunction                       21              15                    
  Decreased Erections                      18              16                    
  Lower Urinary Tract Symptoms             13              8                     
  Lethargy                                 8               4                     
  Pain (worsened in the first 30 days)     8               3                     
  Edema                                    7               8                     
  Upper Respiratory Infection              7               2                     
  Rash                                     6               1                     
  Sweating                                 6               4                     
  Anorexia                                 5               2                     
  Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease    5               3                     
  Congestive Heart Failure                 5               1                     
  Dizziness                                5               4                     
  Insomnia                                 5               1                     
  Nausea                                   5               2                     
  Complications of Surgery                 0               18Complications related to surgery were reported in 18% of the orchiectomy patients, while only 3% of ZOLADEX patients reported adverse reactions at the injection site. The surgical complications included scrotal infection (5.9%), groin pain (4.7%), wound seepage (3.1%), scrotal hematoma (2.8%), incisional discomfort (1.6%) and skin necrosis (1.2%).    
         The following additional adverse reactions were reported in greater than 1% but less than 5% of the patients treated with ZOLADEX: CARDIOVASCULAR - arrhythmia, cerebrovascular accident, hypertension, myocardial infarction, peripheral vascular disorder, chest pain; CENTRAL NERVOUS SYSTEM - anxiety, depression, headache; GASTROINTESTINAL - constipation, diarrhea, ulcer, vomiting; HEMATOLOGIC - anemia; METABOLIC/NUTRITIONAL - gout, hyperglycemia, weight increase; MISCELLANEOUS - chills, fever; UROGENITAL - renal insufficiency, urinary obstruction, urinary tract infection, breast swelling and tenderness.
 

   6.3 Females

  As would be expected with a drug that results in hypoestrogenism, the most frequently reported adverse reactions were those related to this effect.



   6.4 Endometriosis

  In controlled clinical trials comparing ZOLADEX every 28 days and danazol daily for the treatment of endometriosis, the following events were reported at a frequency of 5% or greater:



 Table 4 TREATMENT RECEIVED 
                               ZOLADEX    (n=411)      DANAZOL    (n=207)     
   ADVERSE EVENT               %               %              
  
  Hot Flushes                 96              67              
  Vaginitis                   75              43              
  Headache                    75              63              
  Emotional Lability          60              56              
  Libido Decreased            61              44              
  Sweating                    45              30              
  Depression                  54              48              
  Acne                        42              55              
  Breast Atrophy              33              42              
  Seborrhea                   26              52              
  Peripheral Edema            21              34              
  Breast Enlargement          18              15              
  Pelvic Symptoms             18              23              
  Pain                        17              16              
  Dyspareunia                 14              5               
  Libido Increased            12              19              
  Infection                   13              11              
  Asthenia                    11              13              
  Nausea                      8               14              
  Hirsutism                   7               15              
  Insomnia                    11              4               
  Breast Pain                 7               4               
  Abdominal Pain              7               7               
  Back Pain                   7               13              
  Flu Syndrome                5               5               
  Dizziness                   6               4               
  Application Site Reaction    6               -               
  Voice Alterations           3               8               
  Pharyngitis                 5               2               
  Hair Disorders              4               11              
  Myalgia                     3               11              
  Nervousness                 3               5               
  Weight Gain                 3               23              
  Leg Cramps                  2               6               
  Increased Appetite          2               5               
  Pruritus                    2               6               
  Hypertonia                  1               10              
         The following adverse events not already listed above were reported at a frequency of 1% or greater, regardless of causality, in ZOLADEX-treated women from all clinical trials: WHOLE BODY - allergic reaction, chest pain, fever, malaise; CARDIOVASCULAR - hemorrhage, hypertension, migraine, palpitations, tachycardia; DIGESTIVE - anorexia, constipation, diarrhea, dry mouth, dyspepsia, flatulence; HEMATOLOGIC - ecchymosis; METABOLIC AND NUTRITIONAL - edema; MUSCULOSKELETAL - arthralgia, joint disorder; CNS - anxiety, paresthesia, somnolence, thinking abnormal; RESPIRATORY - bronchitis, cough increased, epistaxis, rhinitis, sinusitis; SKIN - alopecia, dry skin, rash, skin discoloration; SPECIAL SENSES - amblyopia, dry eyes; UROGENITAL - dysmenorrhea, urinary frequency, urinary tract infection, vaginal hemorrhage.
 

   6.5 Endometrial Thinning

  The following adverse events were reported at a frequency of 5% or greater in premenopausal women presenting with dysfunctional uterine bleeding in Trial 0022 for endometrial thinning. These results indicate that headache, hot flushes and sweating were more common in the ZOLADEX group than in the placebo group.



 Table 5 ADVERSE EVENTS REPORTED AT A FREQUENCY OF 5% OR GREATER IN ZOLADEX AND PLACEBO TREATMENT GROUPS OF TRIAL 0022 
                            ZOLADEX3.6 mg(n=180)      Placebo    (n=177)     
   ADVERSE EVENT            %               %          
  
  Whole Body                                           
  Headache                 32              22          
  Abdominal Pain           11              10          
  Pelvic Pain              9               6           
  Back Pain                4               7           
  Cardiovascular                                       
  Vasodilatation           57              18          
  Migraine                 7               4           
  Hypertension             6               2           
  Digestive                                            
  Nausea                   5               6           
  Nervous                                              
  Nervousness              5               3           
  Depression               3               7           
  Respiratory                                          
  Pharyngitis              6               9           
  Sinusitis                3               6           
  Skin and appendages                                  
  Sweating                 16              5           
  Urogenital                                           
  Dysmenorrhea             7               9           
  Uterine Hemorrhage       6               4           
  Vulvovaginitis           5               1           
  Menorrhagia              4               5           
  Vaginitis                1               6           
           6.6 Breast Cancer
   The adverse event profile for women with advanced breast cancer treated with ZOLADEX is consistent with the profile described above for women treated with ZOLADEX for endometriosis. In a controlled clinical trial (SWOG-8692) comparing ZOLADEX with oophorectomy in premenopausal and perimenopausal women with advanced breast cancer, the following events were reported at a frequency of 5% or greater in either treatment group regardless of causality.



 Table 6 TREATMENT RECEIVED 
                               ZOLADEX    (n=57)      OOPHORECTOMY    (n=55)     
   ADVERSE EVENT               % of Pts.       % of Pts.               
  
  Hot Flashes                 70              47                       
  Tumor Flare                 23              4                        
  Nausea                      11              7                        
  Edema                       5               0                        
  Malaise/Fatigue/Lethargy    5               2                        
  Vomiting                    4               7                        
         In the Phase II clinical trial program in 333 pre- and perimenopausal women with advanced breast cancer, hot flashes were reported in 75.9% of patients and decreased libido was noted in 47.7% of patients. These two adverse events reflect the pharmacological actions of ZOLADEX.
 

 Injection site reactions were reported in less than 1% of patients.



   6.7 Hormone Replacement Therapy

  Clinical studies suggest the addition of Hormone Replacement Therapy (estrogens and/or progestins) to ZOLADEX may decrease the occurrence of vasomotor symptoms and vaginal dryness associated with hypoestrogenism without compromising the efficacy of ZOLADEX in relieving pelvic symptoms. The optimal drugs, dose and duration of treatment has not been established.



   6.8 Changes in Bone Mineral Density

  After 6 months of ZOLADEX treatment, 109 female patients treated with ZOLADEX showed an average 4.3% decrease of vertebral trabecular bone mineral density (BMD) as compared to pretreatment values. BMD was measured by dual-photon absorptiometry or dual energy x-ray absorptiometry. Sixty-six of these patients were assessed for BMD loss 6 months after the completion (posttherapy) of the 6-month therapy period. Data from these patients showed an average 2.4% BMD loss compared to pretreatment values. Twenty-eight of the 109 patients were assessed for BMD at 12 months posttherapy. Data from these patients showed an average decrease of 2.5% in BMD compared to pretreatment values. These data suggest a possibility of partial reversibility. Clinical studies suggest the addition of Hormone Replacement Therapy (estrogens and/or progestins) to ZOLADEX is effective in reducing the bone mineral loss which occurs with ZOLADEX alone without compromising the efficacy of ZOLADEX in relieving the symptoms of endometriosis. The optimal drugs, dose and duration of treatment has not been established  [see  Patient Counseling Information (17.2)  ].  



   6.9 Changes in Laboratory Values During Treatment

    Plasma Enzymes:  Elevation of liver enzymes (AST, ALT) have been reported in female patients exposed to ZOLADEX (representing less than 1% of all patients).



   Lipids:  In a controlled trial, ZOLADEX therapy resulted in a minor, but statistically significant effect on serum lipids. In patients treated for endometriosis at 6 months following initiation of therapy, danazol treatment resulted in a mean increase in LDL cholesterol of 33.3 mg/dL and a decrease in HDL cholesterol of 21.3 mg/dL compared to increases of 21.3 and 2.7 mg/dL in LDL cholesterol and HDL cholesterol, respectively, for ZOLADEX-treated patients. Triglycerides increased by 8.0 mg/dL in ZOLADEX-treated patients compared to a decrease of 8.9 mg/dL in danazol-treated patients.



 In patients treated for endometriosis, ZOLADEX increased total cholesterol and LDL cholesterol during 6 months of treatment. However, ZOLADEX therapy resulted in HDL cholesterol levels which were significantly higher relative to danazol therapy. At the end of 6 months of treatment, HDL cholesterol fractions (HDL2and HDL3) were decreased by 13.5 and 7.7 mg/dL, respectively, for danazol-treated patients compared to treatment increases of 1.9 and 0.8 mg/dL, respectively, for ZOLADEX-treated patients.



   6.10 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of ZOLADEX. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Bone Mineral Density:  Osteoporosis, decreased bone mineral density and bone fracture in men  [see Patient Counseling Information  (17.1)  and  (17.2)  ]  .



   Cardiovascular:  Deep vein thrombosis, pulmonary embolism, myocardial infarction, stroke, and transient ischemic attack have been observed in women treated with GnRH agonists. Although a temporal relationship was reported in some cases, most cases were confounded by risk factors or concomitant medication use. It is unknown if there is a causal association between the use of GnRH analogs and these events.



   Ovarian Cyst:  Ovarian cyst formation and, in combination with gonadotropins, ovarian hyperstimulation syndrome (OHSS).



   Changes in Blood Pressure:  Hypotension and hypertension have been reported. These changes are usually transient, resolving either during continued therapy or after cessation of therapy.



   Pituitary Apoplexy and Tumors:  Pituitary apoplexy (a clinical syndrome secondary to infarction of the pituitary gland) and pituitary adenoma have been diagnosed. Most of the pituitary apoplexy cases occurred within 2 weeks of the first dose, and some occurred within the first hour. In these cases, pituitary apoplexy has presented as sudden headache, vomiting, visual changes, ophthalmoplegia, altered mental status, and sometimes cardiovascular collapse. Immediate medical attention has been required. Pituitary tumors have been reported.



   Acne:  Usually within one month of starting treatment.



   Other Adverse Reactions:  Psychotic disorders, convulsions and mood swings.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Women of Childbearing Potential and Pregnancy: Pregnancy must be excluded for use in benign gynecological conditions. Women should avoid pregnancy  (5.1)   
 *    Tumor Flare Phenomenon: Transient worsening of tumor symptoms may occur during the first few weeks of treatment with ZOLADEX, which may include ureteral obstruction and spinal cord compression. Monitor patients at risk for complications of tumor flare (  5.2  ,  6.2  ) 
 *    Hyperglycemia and Diabetes: Hyperglycemia and an increased risk of developing diabetes have been reported in men receiving GnRH analogs. Monitor blood glucose level and manage according to current clinical practice  (5.3)   
 *    Cardiovascular Diseases: Increased risk of myocardial infarction, sudden cardiac death and stroke has been reported in association with use of GnRH analogs in men. Monitor for cardiovascular disease and manage according to current clinical practice  (5.4)   
 *    Hypercalcemia: Hypercalcemia has been reported in patients with bone metastases treated with ZOLADEX. Monitor and manage appropriately  (5.5)   
 *    Hypersensitivity: Systemic hypersensitivity has been reported in patients receiving goserelin/ZOLADEX implants (  4.1  ,  5.6  ) 
 *    Cervical Resistance: Increase in cervical resistance may occur. Caution is recommended when dilating the cervix for endometrial ablation  (5.7)   
 *    Effect on QT/QTc Interval: Androgen deprivation therapy may prolong the QT interval. Consider risks and benefits  (5.8)   
 *    Injection Site Injury: Injection site injury and vascular injury have been reported during administration of ZOLADEX  (5.9)   
    
 

   5.1 Women of Childbearing Potential and Pregnancy



  Before starting treatment with ZOLADEX, pregnancy must be excluded for women using ZOLADEX for benign gynecological conditions. Women of childbearing potential should be advised to avoid becoming pregnant.



 Effective nonhormonal contraception must be used by all premenopausal women during ZOLADEX therapy and for 12 weeks following discontinuation of therapy. When used every 28 days, ZOLADEX usually inhibits ovulation and stops menstruation; however, pregnancy prevention is not ensured. Effects on reproductive function are expected to occur with chronic administration as a result of the anti-gonadotrophic properties of the drug.



 Based on mechanism of action in humans and findings of increased pregnancy loss in animal studies, ZOLADEX can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. If this drug is used during pregnancy for the palliative treatment of breast cancer, then the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus [see  Use in Specific Populations (8.1)  ].  



    5.2 Tumor Flare Phenomenon



  Initially, ZOLADEX, like other GnRH agonists, causes transient increases in serum levels of testosterone in men with prostate cancer, and estrogen in women with breast cancer. Transient worsening of symptoms, or the occurrence of additional signs and symptoms of prostate or breast cancer, may occasionally develop during the first few weeks of ZOLADEX treatment. A small number of patients may experience a temporary increase in bone pain, which can be managed symptomatically.



 As with other GnRH agonists, isolated cases of ureteral obstruction and spinal cord compression have been observed in patients with prostate cancer. If spinal cord compression or renal impairment secondary to ureteral obstruction develops, standard treatment of these complications should be instituted. For extreme cases in prostate cancer patients, an immediate orchiectomy should be considered.



    5.3 Hyperglycemia and Diabetes



  Hyperglycemia and an increased risk of developing diabetes have been reported in men receiving GnRH agonists. Hyperglycemia may represent development of diabetes mellitus or worsening of glycemic control in patients with diabetes. Monitor blood glucose and/or glycosylated hemoglobin (HbA1c) periodically in patients receiving a GnRH agonist and manage with current practice for treatment of hyperglycemia or diabetes [see  Patient Counseling Information (17.1)  ].  



    5.4 Cardiovascular Diseases



  Increased risk of developing myocardial infarction, sudden cardiac death and stroke has been reported in association with use of GnRH agonists in men. The risk appears low based on the reported odds ratios, and should be evaluated carefully along with cardiovascular risk factors when determining a treatment for patients with prostate cancer. Patients receiving a GnRH agonist should be monitored for symptoms and signs suggestive of development of cardiovascular disease and be managed according to current clinical practice [see  Patient Counseling Information (17.1)  ].  



    5.5 Hypercalcemia



  As with other GnRH agonists or hormonal therapies (antiestrogens, estrogens, etc.), hypercalcemia has been reported in some prostate and breast cancer patients with bone metastases after starting treatment with ZOLADEX. If hypercalcemia does occur, appropriate treatment measures should be initiated.



    5.6 Hypersensitivity



  Hypersensitivity, antibody formation and acute anaphylactic reactions have been reported with GnRH agonist analogues [see  Contraindications (4.1)  ].  



 Of 115 women worldwide treated with ZOLADEX and tested for development of binding to goserelin following treatment with ZOLADEX, one patient showed low-titer binding to goserelin. On further testing of this patient's plasma obtained following treatment, her goserelin binding component was found not to be precipitated with rabbit antihuman immunoglobulin polyvalent sera. These findings suggest the possibility of antibody formation.



    5.7 Cervical Resistance



  The pharmacologic action of ZOLADEX on the uterus and cervix may cause an increase in cervical resistance. Therefore, care should be taken when dilating the cervix for endometrial ablation.



    5.8 Effect on QT/QTc Interval



  Androgen deprivation therapy may prolong the QT/QTc interval. Providers should consider whether the benefits of androgen deprivation therapy outweigh the potential risks in patients with congenital long QT syndrome, congestive heart failure, frequent electrolyte abnormalities, and in patients taking drugs known to prolong the QT interval. Electrolyte abnormalities should be corrected. Consider periodic monitoring of electrocardiograms and electrolytes.



    5.9 Injection Site Injury



  Injection site injury and vascular injury including pain, hematoma, hemorrhage and hemorrhagic shock, requiring blood transfusions and surgical intervention, have been reported with ZOLADEX. Extra care should be taken when administering ZOLADEX to patients with a low BMI and/or to patients receiving full dose anticoagulation [see     Dosage and Administration (2.7)     and   Patient Counseling Information  (17.1  and  17.2)  ]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
