<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="zolinza" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following serious adverse reactions have been associated with ZOLINZA in clinical trials and are discussed in greater detail in other sections of the label [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5)    ].



 Thromboembolism [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)    ]



 Myelosuppression [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ]



 Gastrointestinal Toxicity [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)    ]



 Hyperglycemia [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)    ]



 Clinical Chemistry Abnormalities [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)    ]



 Severe thrombocytopenia when combined with other Histone Deacetylase (HDAC) Inhibitors [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)    ]



 The most common drug-related adverse reactions can be classified into 4 symptom complexes: gastrointestinal symptoms (diarrhea, nausea, anorexia, weight decrease, vomiting, constipation), constitutional symptoms (fatigue, chills), hematologic abnormalities (thrombocytopenia, anemia), and taste disorders (dysgeusia, dry mouth). The most common serious drug-related adverse reactions were pulmonary embolism and anemia.



    EXCERPT:    *  The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;=20%) are diarrhea, fatigue, nausea, thrombocytopenia, anorexia and dysgeusia. (  6  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp., a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Co., Inc., at 1-877-888-4231 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch.  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 The safety of ZOLINZA was evaluated in 107 CTCL patients in two single arm clinical studies in which 86 patients received 400 mg once daily.



 The data described below reflect exposure to ZOLINZA 400 mg once daily in the 86 patients for a median number of 97.5 days on therapy (range 2 to 480+ days). Seventeen (19.8%) patients were exposed beyond 24 weeks and 8 (9.3%) patients were exposed beyond 1 year. The population of CTCL patients studied was 37 to 83 years of age, 47.7% female, 52.3% male, and 81.4% white, 16.3% black, and 1.2% Asian or multi-racial.



       Common Adverse Reactions    



   Table 1  summarizes the frequency of CTCL patients with specific adverse reactions, using the National Cancer Institute-Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI-CTCAE, version 3.0).



 Table 1: Clinical or Laboratory Adverse Reactions Occurring in CTCL Patients (Incidence &gt;=10% of patients) 
                               ZOLINZA 400 mg once daily (N=86)   
 Adverse Reactions                 All Grades          Grades 3-5       
                                       n                   %                   n                   %            
  
 Fatigue                               45                 52.3                 3                  3.5           
 Diarrhea                              45                 52.3                 0                  0.0           
 Nausea                                35                 40.7                 3                  3.5           
 Dysgeusia                             24                 27.9                 0                  0.0           
 Thrombocytopenia                      22                 25.6                 5                  5.8           
 Anorexia                              21                 24.4                 2                  2.3           
 Weight Decreased                      18                 20.9                 1                  1.2           
 Muscle Spasms                         17                 19.8                 2                  2.3           
 Alopecia                              16                 18.6                 0                  0.0           
 Dry Mouth                             14                 16.3                 0                  0.0           
 Blood Creatinine Increased            14                 16.3                 0                  0.0           
 Chills                                14                 16.3                 1                  1.2           
 Vomiting                              13                 15.1                 1                  1.2           
 Constipation                          13                 15.1                 0                  0.0           
 Dizziness                             13                 15.1                 1                  1.2           
 Anemia                                12                 14.0                 2                  2.3           
 Decreased Appetite                    12                 14.0                 1                  1.2           
 Peripheral Edema                      11                 12.8                 0                  0.0           
 Headache                              10                 11.6                 0                  0.0           
 Pruritus                              10                 11.6                 1                  1.2           
 Cough                                 9                  10.5                 0                  0.0           
 Upper Respiratory Infection           9                  10.5                 0                  0.0           
 Pyrexia                               9                  10.5                 1                  1.2           
           The frequencies of more severe thrombocytopenia, anemia  [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)  ]  and fatigue were increased at doses higher than 400 mg once daily of ZOLINZA.
 

       Serious Adverse Reactions    



 The most common serious adverse reactions in the 86 CTCL patients in two clinical trials were pulmonary embolism reported in 4.7% (4/86) of patients, squamous cell carcinoma reported in 3.5% (3/86) of patients and anemia reported in 2.3% (2/86) of patients. There were single events of cholecystitis, death (of unknown cause), deep vein thrombosis, enterococcal infection, exfoliative dermatitis, gastrointestinal hemorrhage, infection, lobar pneumonia, myocardial infarction, ischemic stroke, pelviureteric obstruction, sepsis, spinal cord injury, streptococcal bacteremia, syncope, T-cell lymphoma, thrombocytopenia and ureteric obstruction.



       Discontinuations    



 Of the CTCL patients who received the 400-mg once daily dose, 9.3% (8/86) of patients discontinued ZOLINZA due to adverse reactions. These adverse reactions, regardless of causality, included anemia, angioneurotic edema, asthenia, chest pain, exfoliative dermatitis, death, deep vein thrombosis, ischemic stroke, lethargy, pulmonary embolism, and spinal cord injury.



       Dose Modifications    



 Of the CTCL patients who received the 400-mg once daily dose, 10.5% (9/86) of patients required a dose modification of ZOLINZA due to adverse reactions. These adverse reactions included increased serum creatinine, decreased appetite, hypokalemia, leukopenia, nausea, neutropenia, thrombocytopenia and vomiting. The median time to the first adverse reactions resulting in dose reduction was 42 days (range 17 to 263 days).



       Laboratory Abnormalities    



 Laboratory abnormalities were reported in all of the 86 CTCL patients who received the 400-mg once-daily dose.



 Increased serum glucose was reported as a laboratory abnormality in 69% (59/86) of CTCL patients who received the 400-mg once daily dose; only 4 of these abnormalities were severe (Grade 3). Increased serum glucose was reported as an adverse reaction in 8.1% (7/86) of CTCL patients who received the 400-mg once daily dose.  [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)  .]  



 Transient increases in serum creatinine were detected in 46.5% (40/86) of CTCL patients who received the 400-mg once daily dose. Of these laboratory abnormalities, 34 were NCI CTCAE Grade 1, 5 were Grade 2, and 1 was Grade 3.



 Proteinuria was detected as a laboratory abnormality (51.4%) in 38 of 74 patients tested. The clinical significance of this finding is unknown.



       Dehydration    



 Based on reports of dehydration as a serious drug-related adverse reaction in clinical trials, patients were instructed to drink at least 2 L/day of fluids for adequate hydration.  [See  Warnings and Precautions (5.3  ,  5.5)  .]  



       Adverse Reactions in Non-CTCL Patients    



 The frequencies of individual adverse reactions were substantially higher in the non-CTCL population. Drug-related serious adverse reactions reported in the non-CTCL population which were not observed in the CTCL population included single events of blurred vision, asthenia, hyponatremia, tumor hemorrhage, Guillain-Barre syndrome, renal failure, urinary retention, cough, hemoptysis, hypertension, and vasculitis.



 In patients recovering from bowel surgery and treated perioperatively with ZOLINZA, anastomotic healing complications including fistulas, perforations, and abscess formation have occurred.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Pulmonary embolism and deep vein thrombosis: Monitor for pertinent signs and symptoms. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Thrombocytopenia and anemia: May require dose modification or discontinuation. Monitor blood counts every 2 weeks during the first 2 months of therapy and monthly thereafter. (  2.2  ,  5.2  ,  6  ) 
 *  Gastrointestinal Toxicity: Nausea, vomiting and diarrhea; patients may require antiemetics, antidiarrheals, and fluid and electrolyte replacement to prevent dehydration. (  5.3  ,  6  ,  17.1  ) 
 *  Hyperglycemia: Monitor blood glucose every 2 weeks during the first 2 months of therapy and monthly thereafter. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Clinical chemistry abnormalities: Measure and correct abnormal electrolytes, creatinine, magnesium and calcium at baseline. Monitor every 2 weeks during the first 2 months of therapy and at least monthly during treatment. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Severe thrombocytopenia with gastrointestinal bleeding has been reported with concomitant use of ZOLINZA and other HDAC inhibitors (e.g., valproic acid). Monitor platelet counts more frequently. (  5.6  ,  7.2  ) 
 *  Fetal harm can occur when administered to a pregnant woman. Women should be apprised of the potential harm to the fetus. (  5.7  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Thromboembolism



  Pulmonary embolism occurred in 5% (4/86) of patients receiving ZOLINZA, and deep vein thrombosis has also been reported. Monitor for signs and symptoms of these events, particularly in patients with a prior history of thromboembolic events [see  Adverse Reactions (6)  ]  .



    5.2 Myelosuppression



  Treatment with ZOLINZA can cause dose-related thrombocytopenia and anemia. Monitor blood counts every 2 weeks during the first 2 months of therapy and monthly thereafter. Adjust dosage or discontinue treatment with ZOLINZA as clinically appropriate. [See  Dosage and Administration (2.2)  ,  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)  and  Adverse Reactions (6)  .]  



    5.3 Gastrointestinal Toxicity



  Gastrointestinal disturbances, including nausea, vomiting and diarrhea, have been reported [see  Adverse Reactions (6)  ]  and may require the use of antiemetic and antidiarrheal medications. Fluid and electrolytes should be replaced to prevent dehydration [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . Pre-existing nausea, vomiting, and diarrhea should be adequately controlled before beginning therapy with ZOLINZA.



    5.4 Hyperglycemia



  Hyperglycemia has been observed in patients receiving ZOLINZA and was severe in 5% (4/86) of patients [see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)  ]  . Monitor serum glucose every 2 weeks during the first 2 months of therapy and monthly thereafter.



    5.5 Clinical Chemistry Abnormalities



  Obtain chemistry tests, including serum electrolytes, creatinine, magnesium, and calcium, every 2 weeks during the first 2 months of therapy and monthly thereafter. Correct hypokalemia and hypomagnesemia prior to administration of ZOLINZA. Monitor potassium and magnesium more frequently in symptomatic patients (e.g., patients with nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, fluid imbalance or cardiac symptoms).



    5.6 Severe thrombocytopenia when combined with other Histone Deacetylase (HDAC) Inhibitors



  Severe thrombocytopenia leading to gastrointestinal bleeding has been reported with concomitant use of ZOLINZA and other HDAC inhibitors (e.g., valproic acid). Monitor platelet counts more frequently. [See  Drug Interactions (7.2)  ]  .



    5.7 Pregnancy



  Pregnancy Category D



 ZOLINZA can cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. There are no adequate and well-controlled studies of ZOLINZA in pregnant women. Results of animal studies indicate that vorinostat crosses the placenta and is found in fetal plasma at levels up to 50% of maternal concentrations. Doses up to 50 and 150 mg/kg/day were tested in rats and rabbits, respectively (~0.5 times the human exposure based on AUC0-24 hours). Treatment-related, developmental effects including decreased mean live fetal weights, incomplete ossifications of the skull, thoracic vertebra, sternebra, and skeletal variations (cervical ribs, supernumerary ribs, vertebral count and sacral arch variations) in rats at the highest dose of vorinostat tested. Reductions in mean live fetal weight and an elevated incidence of incomplete ossification of the metacarpals were seen in rabbits dosed at 150 mg/kg/day. The no observed effect levels (NOELs) for these findings were 15 and 50 mg/kg/day (&lt;0.1 times the human exposure based on AUC) in rats and rabbits, respectively. A dose-related increase in the incidence of malformations of the gall bladder was noted in all drug treatment groups in rabbits versus the concurrent control. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to the fetus.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
