<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="zolmitriptan" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  The following adverse reactions are described elsewhere in other sections of the prescribing information:



 *    Myocardial Ischemia, Myocardial Infarction, and Prinzmetal's Angina [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)   ]. 
 *    Arrthymias [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)   ]. 
 *    Chest and or Throat, Neck and Jaw Pain/Tightness/Pressure [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)   ]. 
 *    Cerebrovascular Events [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.4)   ]. 
 *    Other Vasospasm Reactions [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.5)   ]. 
 *    Medication Overuse Headache [see  Warnings and Precautions (5.6)   ]. 
 *    Serotonin Syndrome [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)   ]. 
 *    Increase in Blood Pressure [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)   ]. 
 *    Risks in Patients with Phenylketonuria [ see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)   ]. 
      EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5% and &gt; placebo) were neck/throat/jaw pain/tightness/pressure, dizziness, paresthesia, asthenia, somnolence, warm/cold sensation, nausea, heaviness sensation, and dry mouth (  6.1  )
 

   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Impax Pharmaceuticals at 1-877-994-6729 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical studies are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical studies of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical studies of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 In a long-term, open-label study where patients were allowed to treat multiple migraine attacks for up to 1 year, 8% (167 out of 2,058) withdrew from the trial because of adverse reaction.



 The most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5% and &gt; placebo) in these trials were neck/throat/jaw pain, dizziness, paresthesia, asthenia, somnolence, warm/cold sensation, nausea, heaviness sensation, and dry mouth.



 Table 1 lists the adverse reactions that occurred in &gt;= 2% of the 2,074 patients in any one of the zolmitriptan tablets 1 mg, 2.5 mg, or 5 mg dose groups in the controlled clinical trials of zolmitriptan tablets in patients with migraines (Studies 1, 2, 3, 4, and 5) [  see  Clinical Studies (14)    ]. Only adverse reactions that were at least 2% more frequent in a zolmitriptan tablets group compared to the placebo group are included.



 Several of the adverse reactions appear dose related, notably paresthesia, sensation of heaviness or tightness in chest, neck, jaw, and throat, dizziness, somnolence and possibly asthenia and nausea.



 Table 1: Adverse Reaction Incidence in Five Pooled Placebo-Controlled Migraine Clinical TrialsOnly adverse reactions that were at least 2% more frequent in a zolmitriptan group compared to the placebo group are included. 
                                 Placebo  (n=401)    Zolmitriptan  1 mg  (n=163)    Zolmitriptan  2.5 mg  (n=498)    Zolmitriptan  5 mg  (n=1012)    
  ATYPICAL SENSATIONS            6%                12%                  12%                    18%                     
  Paresthesia (all types)        2%                5%                   7%                     9%                      
  Warm/cold sensation            4%                6%                   5%                     7%                      
  PAIN AND PRESSURE SENSATIONS    7%                13%                  14%                    22%                     
  Chest - pain/tightness/pressure and/or heaviness    1%                2%                   3%                     4%                      
  Neck/throat/jaw - pain/tightness/pressure    3%                4%                   7%                     10%                     
  Heaviness other than chest or neck    1%                1%                   2%                     5%                      
  Other- Pressure/tightness/heaviness    0%                2%                   2%                     2%                      
  DIGESTIVE                      8%                11%                  16%                    14%                     
  Dry mouth                      2%                5%                   3%                     3%                      
  Dyspepsia                      1%                3%                   2%                     1%                      
  Dysphagia                      0%                0%                   0%                     2%                      
  Nausea                         4%                4%                   9%                     6%                      
  NEUROLOGICAL                   10%               11%                  17%                    21%                     
  Dizziness                      4%                6%                   8%                     10%                     
  Somnolence                     3%                5%                   6%                     8%                      
  Vertigo                        0%                0%                   0%                     2%                      
  OTHER                                                                                                                
  Asthenia                       3%                5%                   3%                     9%                      
  Sweating                       1%                0%                   2%                     3%                      
           There were no differences in the incidence of adverse reactions in controlled clinical trials in the following subgroups: gender, weight, age, use of prophylactic medications, or presence of aura. There were insufficient data to assess the impact of race on the incidence of adverse reactions.
 

     Less Common Adverse Reactions with Zolmitriptan Tablets:    



 In the paragraphs that follow, the frequencies of less commonly reported adverse clinical reactions are presented. Because the reports include reactions observed in open and uncontrolled studies, the role of zolmitriptan in their causation cannot be reliably determined. Furthermore, variability associated with adverse reaction reporting, the terminology used to describe adverse reactions, etc., limit the value of the quantitative frequency estimates provided. Adverse reaction frequencies were calculated as the number of patients who used zolmitriptan tablets and reported a reaction divided by the total number of patients exposed to zolmitriptan tablets (n=4,027). Reactions were further classified within body system categories and enumerated in order of decreasing frequency using the following definitions: infrequent adverse reactions (those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1,000 patients) and rare adverse reactions (those occurring in less than 1/1,000 patients).



   General    :  Infrequent were allergic reactions.



   Cardiovascular    :  Infrequent were arrhythmias, hypertension, and syncope. Rare was tachycardia.



   Neurological    :  Infrequent were agitation, anxiety, depression, emotional lability and insomnia; Rare were amnesia, hallucinations, and cerebral ischemia.



   Skin    :  Infrequent were pruritus, rash and urticaria.



   Urogenital:  Infrequent were polyuria, urinary frequency and urinary urgency.



 



     Adverse Reactions with Zolmitriptan Orally Disintegrating Tablets    



 The adverse reaction profile seen with zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets was similar to that seen with zolmitriptan tablets.



   6.2 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions were identified during post approval use of zolmitriptan tablets and zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 



 The reactions enumerated include all except those already listed in the Clinical Trials Experience section above or the Warnings and Precautions section.



 



   Hypersensitivity Reactions:  



 As with other 5-HT1B/1Dagonists, there have been reports of anaphylaxis, anaphylactoid, and hypersensitivity reactions including angioedema in patients receiving zolmitriptan tablets and zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets. Zolmitriptan tablets and zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets are contraindicated in patients with a history of hypersensitivity reaction to zolmitriptan tablets or zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *     Myocardial Ischemia/Infarction, and Prinzmetal  Angina : Perform cardiac evaluation in patients with multiple cardiovascular risk factors  (5.1)   
 *     Arrhythmias : Discontinue zolmitriptan tablets/ zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets if occurs  (5.2)   
 *     Chest/Throat/Neck/Jaw Pain, Tightness, and Pressure : Generally not associated with myocardial ischemia; evaluate for CAD in patients at high risk  (5.3)   
 *     Cerebral Hemorrhage, Subarachnoid Hemorrhage, and Stroke : Discontinue zolmitriptan tablets/ zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets if occurs  (5.4)   
 *     Gastrointestinal Ischemic Reactions and Peripheral Vasospastic Reactions : Discontinue zolmitriptan tablets/ zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets if occurs  (5.5)   
 *     Medication Overuse Headache : Detoxification may be necessary  (5.6)   
 *     Serotonin Syndrome : Discontinue zolmitriptan tablets/ zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets if occurs (  5.7  ,  7.4  ) 
 *     Patients with Phenylketonuria : zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets contain phenylalanine (  5.9  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Myocardial Ischemia, Myocardial Infarction, and Prinzmetal Angina



  Zolmitriptan tablets and zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets are contraindicated in patients with ischemic or vasospastic coronary artery disease (CAD) .  There have been rare reports of serious cardiac adverse reactions, including acute myocardial infarction, occurring within a few hours following administration of zolmitriptan tablets/ zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets. Some of these reactions occurred in patients without known CAD. 5-HT1agonists including zolmitriptan tablets and zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets may cause coronary artery vasospasm (Prinzmetal Angina), even in patients without a history of CAD.



 Perform a cardiovascular evaluation in triptan-naive patients who have multiple cardiovascular risk factors (e.g., increased age, diabetes, hypertension, smoking, obesity, strong family history of CAD) prior to receiving zolmitriptan tablets or zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets. Do not administer zolmitriptan tablets or zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets if there is evidence of CAD or coronary artery vasospasm [ see  Contraindications (4)    ]. For patients with multiple cardiovascular risk factors who have a negative cardiovascular evaluation, consider administrating the first zolmitriptan tablets or zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets dose in a medically-supervised setting and performing an electrocardiogram (ECG) immediately following zolmitriptan tablets or zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets administration. For such patients, consider periodic cardiovascular evaluation in intermittent long-term users of zolmitriptan tablets and zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets.



    5.2 Arrhythmias



  Life-threatening disturbances of cardiac rhythm including ventricular tachycardia and ventricular fibrillation leading to death have been reported within a few hours following the administration of 5-HT1agonists. Discontinue zolmitriptan tablets/ zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets if these disturbances occur. Zolmitriptan tablets and zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets are contraindicated in patients with Wolff-Parkinson-White Syndrome or arrhythmias associated with other cardiac accessory conduction pathway disorders [ see  Contraindications (4)    ].



    5.3 Chest, Throat, Neck and Jaw Pain/Tightness/Pressure



  As with other 5-HT1agonists, sensations of tightness, pain, and pressure in the chest, throat, neck, and jaw commonly occur after treatment with zolmitriptan tablets/ zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets and is usually non-cardiac in origin. However, perform a cardiac evaluation if these patients are at high cardiac risk. 5-HT1agonists including zolmitriptan tablets and zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets are contraindicated in patients with CAD or Prinzmetal's variant angina [ see  Contraindications (4)    ] .  



    5.4 Cerebrovascular Events



  Cerebral hemorrhage, subarachnoid hemorrhage, and stroke have occurred in patients treated with 5-HT1agonists, and some have resulted in fatalities. In a number of cases, it appears possible that the cerebrovascular events were primary, the 5-HT1agonist having been administered in the incorrect belief that the symptoms experienced were a consequence of migraine, when they were not.



 As with other acute migraine therapies, before treating headaches in patients not previously diagnosed as migraineurs, and in migraineurs who present with symptoms atypical for migraine, exclude other potentially serious neurological conditions. Zolmitriptan tablets and zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets are contraindicated in patients with a history of stroke or transient ischemic attack [see  Contraindications (4)    ].



    5.5 Other Vasospasm Reactions



  5-HT1agonists, including zolmitriptan tablets and zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets, may cause non-coronary vasospastic reactions, such as peripheral vascular ischemia, gastrointestinal vascular ischemia and infarction (presenting with abdominal pain and bloody diarrhea), splenic infarction, and Raynaud's syndrome. In patients who experience symptoms or signs suggestive of a vasospastic reaction following the use of any 5-HT1agonist, rule out a vasospastic reaction before receiving additional zolmitriptan tablets or zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets doses [ see  Contraindications (4)    ].



 Reports of transient and permanent blindness and significant partial vision loss have been reported with the use of 5-HT1agonists. Since visual disorders may be part of a migraine attack, a causal relationship between these events and the use of 5-HT1 agonists have not been clearly established.



    5.6 Medication Overuse Headache



   Overuse of acute migraine drugs (e.g. ergotamine, triptans, opioids, or a combination of drugs for 10 or more days per month) may lead to exacerbation of headache (medication overuse headache). Medication overuse headache may present as migraine-like daily headaches or as a marked increase in frequency of migraine attacks. Detoxification of patients, including withdrawal of the overused drugs, and treatment of withdrawal symptoms (which often includes a transient worsening of headache) may be necessary.  



    5.7 Serotonin Syndrome



  Serotonin syndrome may occur with triptans, including zolmitriptan tablets and zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets, particularly during co-administration with selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs), serotonin norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs), tricyclic antidepressants (TCAs), and MAO inhibitors [ see  Drug Interactions (7.5)    ]. Serotonin syndrome symptoms may include mental status changes (e.g., agitation, hallucinations, coma), autonomic instability (e.g., tachycardia, labile blood pressure, hyperthermia), neuromuscular aberrations (e.g., hyperreflexia, incoordination), and/or gastrointestinal symptoms (e.g., nausea, vomiting, diarrhea). The onset of symptoms usually rapidly occurs within minutes to hours of receiving a new or a greater dose of a serotonergic medication. Discontinue zolmitriptan tablets or zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets if serotonin syndrome is suspected [ see  Drug Interactions (7.4)    ].



    5.8 Increase in Blood Pressure



  Significant elevations in systemic blood pressure have been reported in patients treated with 5-HT1 agonists including patients without a history of hypertension; very rarely, these increases in blood pressure have been associated with serious adverse reactions. In healthy subjects treated with 5 mg of zolmitriptan, an increase of 1 and 5 mm Hg in the systolic and diastolic blood pressure, respectively, was seen. In a study of patients with moderate to severe liver impairment, 7 of 27 patients experienced 20 to 80 mm Hg elevations in systolic and/or diastolic blood pressure after a dose of 10 mg of zolmitriptan.



 As with all triptans, blood pressure should be monitored in zolmitriptan tablets and zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets -treated patients. Zolmitriptan tablets and zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets are contraindicated in patients with uncontrolled hypertension [ see  Contraindications (4)    ].



    5.9 Risks in Patients with Phenylketonuria



  Phenylalanine can be harmful to patients with phenylketonuria (PKU). Zolmitriptan orally disintegrating tablets contain phenylalanine (a component of aspartame). Each 2.5 mg and 5 mg orally disintegrating tablet contains 2.81 and 5.62 mg of phenylalanine, respectively. Zolmitriptan tablets do not contain phenylalanine.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
