<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="zometa" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      6     ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse events (greater than 25%) were nausea, fatigue, anemia, bone pain, constipation, fever, vomiting, and dyspnea (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation at 1-888-669-6682 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1     Clinical Studies Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



   Hypercalcemia of Malignancy  



 The safety of Zometa was studied in 185 patients with hypercalcemia of malignancy (HCM) who received either Zometa 4 mg given as a 5-minute intravenous infusion (n=86) or pamidronate 90 mg given as a 2-hour intravenous infusion (n=103). The population was aged 33-84 years, 60% male and 81% Caucasian, with breast, lung, head and neck, and renal cancer as the most common forms of malignancy. NOTE: pamidronate 90 mg was given as a 2-hour intravenous infusion. The relative safety of pamidronate 90 mg given as a 2-hour intravenous infusion compared to the same dose given as a 24-hour intravenous infusion has not been adequately studied in controlled clinical trials.



   Renal Toxicity  



 Administration of Zometa 4 mg given as a 5-minute intravenous infusion has been shown to result in an increased risk of renal toxicity, as measured by increases in serum creatinine, which can progress to renal failure. The incidence of renal toxicity and renal failure has been shown to be reduced when Zometa 4 mg is given as a 15-minute intravenous infusion. Zometa should be administered by intravenous infusion over no less than 15 minutes  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.3), Dosage and Administration (2.4)]  .



 The most frequently observed adverse events were fever, nausea, constipation, anemia, and dyspnea (see Table 4).



 Table 4 provides adverse events that were reported by 10% or more of the 189 patients treated with Zometa 4 mg or pamidronate 90 mg from the two HCM trials. Adverse events are listed regardless of presumed causality to study drug.



 Table 4: Percentage of Patients with Adverse Events &gt;=10% Reported in Hypercalcemia of Malignancy Clinical Trials by Body System 
                    Zometa           Pamidronate     
                    4 mg             90 mg           
                    n (%)            n (%)           
   Patients Studied                                                                         
 Total No. of Patients Studied  86               (100)            103              (100)             
 Total No. of Patients with any AE  81               (94)             95               (92)              
   Body as a Whole                                                                         
 Fever            38               (44)             34               (33)              
 Progression of Cancer  14               (16)             21               (20)              
   Cardiovascular                                                                         
 Hypotension      9                (11)             2                (2)               
   Digestive                                                                           
 Nausea           25               (29)             28               (27)              
 Constipation     23               (27)             13               (13)              
 Diarrhea         15               (17)             17               (17)              
 Abdominal Pain   14               (16)             13               (13)              
 Vomiting         12               (14)             17               (17)              
 Anorexia         8                (9)              14               (14)              
   Hemic and Lymphatic System                                                                         
 Anemia           19               (22)             18               (18)              
   Infections                                                                          
 Moniliasis       10               (12)             4                (4)               
   Laboratory Abnormalities                                                                         
 Hypophosphatemia  11               (13)             2                (2)               
 Hypokalemia      10               (12)             16               (16)              
 Hypomagnesemia   9                (11)             5                (5)               
   Musculoskeletal                                                                         
 Skeletal Pain    10               (12)             10               (10)              
   Nervous                                                                             
 Insomnia         13               (15)             10               (10)              
 Anxiety          12               (14)             8                (8)               
 Confusion        11               (13)             13               (13)              
 Agitation        11               (13)             8                (8)               
   Respiratory                                                                         
 Dyspnea          19               (22)             20               (19)              
 Coughing         10               (12)             12               (12)              
   Urogenital                                                                          
 Urinary Tract Infection  12               (14)             15               (15)              
           The following adverse events from the two controlled multicenter HCM trials (n=189) were reported by a greater percentage of patients treated with Zometa 4 mg than with pamidronate 90 mg and occurred with a frequency of greater than or equal to 5% but less than 10%. Adverse events are listed regardless of presumed causality to study drug: asthenia, chest pain, leg edema, mucositis, dysphagia, granulocytopenia, thrombocytopenia, pancytopenia, nonspecific infection, hypocalcemia, dehydration, arthralgias, headache and somnolence.
 

 Rare cases of rash, pruritus, and chest pain have been reported following treatment with Zometa.



   Acute Phase Reaction  



 Within three days after Zometa administration, an acute phase reaction has been reported in patients, with symptoms including pyrexia, fatigue, bone pain and/or arthralgias, myalgias, chills, and influenza-like illness. These symptoms usually resolve within a few days. Pyrexia has been the most commonly associated symptom, occurring in 44% of patients.



   Mineral and Electrolyte Abnormalities  



 Electrolyte abnormalities, most commonly hypocalcemia, hypophosphatemia, and hypomagnesemia, can occur with bisphosphonate use.



 Grade 3 and Grade 4 laboratory abnormalities for serum creatinine, serum calcium, serum phosphorus, and serum magnesium observed in two clinical trials of Zometa in patients with HCM are shown in Table 5 and 6.



 Table 5: Grade 3 Laboratory Abnormalities for Serum Creatinine, Serum Calcium, Serum Phosphorus, and Serum Magnesium in Two Clinical Trials in Patients with HCM 
                    Grade 3         
   Laboratory Parameter      Zometa           Pamidronate     
                    4 mg             90 mg           
                    n/N              (%)              n/N              (%)             
 Serum Creatinine  1    2/86             (2%)             3/100            (3%)              
 Hypocalcemia  2    1/86             (1%)             2/100            (2%)              
 Hypophosphatemia  3    36/70            (51%)            27/81            (33%)             
 Hypomagnesemia  4    0/71             -                0/84             -                 
          Table 6: Grade 4 Laboratory Abnormalities for Serum Creatinine, Serum Calcium, Serum Phosphorus, and Serum Magnesium in Two Clinical Trials in Patients with HCM 
   1  Grade 3 (greater than 3x Upper Limit of Normal); Grade 4 (greater than 6x Upper Limit of Normal)  2  Grade 3 (less than 7 mg/dL); Grade 4 (less than 6 mg/dL)  3  Grade 3 (less than 2 mg/dL); Grade 4 (less than 1 mg/dL)  4  Grade 3 (less than 0.8 mEq/L); Grade 4 (less than 0.5 mEq/L)   
  
                    Grade 4         
   Laboratory Parameter      Zometa           Pamidronate     
                    4 mg             90 mg           
                    n/N              (%)              n/N              (%)             
 Serum Creatinine  1    0/86             -                1/100            (1%)              
 Hypocalcemia  2    0/86             -                0/100            -                 
 Hypophosphatemia  3    1/70             (1%)             4/81             (5%)              
 Hypomagnesemia  4    0/71             -                1/84             (1%)              
             Injection Site Reactions  
 

 Local reactions at the infusion site, such as redness or swelling, were observed infrequently. In most cases, no specific treatment is required and the symptoms subside after 24-48 hours.



   Ocular Adverse Events  



 Ocular inflammation such as uveitis and scleritis can occur with bisphosphonate use, including Zometa. No cases of iritis, scleritis, or uveitis were reported during these clinical trials. However, cases have been seen in postmarketing use  [see Adverse Reactions (6.2)]  .



   Multiple Myeloma and Bone Metastases of Solid Tumors  



 The safety analysis includes patients treated in the core and extension phases of the trials. The analysis includes the 2042 patients treated with Zometa 4 mg, pamidronate 90 mg, or placebo in the three controlled multicenter bone metastases trials, including 969 patients completing the efficacy phase of the trial, and 619 patients that continued in the safety extension phase. Only 347 patients completed the extension phases and were followed for 2 years (or 21 months for the other solid tumor patients). The median duration of exposure for safety analysis for Zometa 4 mg (core plus extension phases) was 12.8 months for breast cancer and multiple myeloma, 10.8 months for prostate cancer, and 4.0 months for other solid tumors.



 Table 7 describes adverse events that were reported by 10% or more of patients. Adverse events are listed regardless of presumed causality to study drug.



 Table 7: Percentage of Patients with Adverse Events &gt;=10% Reported in Three Bone Metastases Clinical Trials by Body System 
                    Zometa           Pamidronate      Placebo         
                    4 mg             90 mg                            
                    n (%)            n (%)            n (%)           
   Patients Studied                                                                                                           
 Total No. of Patients  1031             (100)            556              (100)            455              (100)             
 Total No. of Patients with any AE  1015             (98)             548              (99)             445              (98)              
   Blood and Lymphatic                                                                                                           
 Anemia           344              (33)             175              (32)             128              (28)              
 Neutropenia      124              (12)             83               (15)             35               (8)               
 Thrombocytopenia  102              (10)             53               (10)             20               (4)               
   Gastrointestinal                                                                                                           
 Nausea           476              (46)             266              (48)             171              (38)              
 Vomiting         333              (32)             183              (33)             122              (27)              
 Constipation     320              (31)             162              (29)             174              (38)              
 Diarrhea         249              (24)             162              (29)             83               (18)              
 Abdominal Pain   143              (14)             81               (15)             48               (11)              
 Dyspepsia        105              (10)             74               (13)             31               (7)               
 Stomatitis       86               (8)              65               (12)             14               (3)               
 Sore Throat      82               (8)              61               (11)             17               (4)               
   General Disorders and Administration Site                                                                                                           
 Fatigue          398              (39)             240              (43)             130              (29)              
 Pyrexia          328              (32)             172              (31)             89               (20)              
 Weakness         252              (24)             108              (19)             114              (25)              
 Edema Lower Limb  215              (21)             126              (23)             84               (19)              
 Rigors           112              (11)             62               (11)             28               (6)               
   Infections                                                                                                            
 Urinary Tract Infection  124              (12)             50               (9)              41               (9)               
 Upper Respiratory Tract Infection  101              (10)             82               (15)             30               (7)               
   Metabolism                                                                                                            
 Anorexia         231              (22)             81               (15)             105              (23)              
 Weight Decreased  164              (16)             50               (9)              61               (13)              
 Dehydration      145              (14)             60               (11)             59               (13)              
 Appetite Decreased  130              (13)             48               (9)              45               (10)              
   Musculoskeletal                                                                                                           
 Bone Pain        569              (55)             316              (57)             284              (62)              
 Myalgia          239              (23)             143              (26)             74               (16)              
 Arthralgia       216              (21)             131              (24)             73               (16)              
 Back Pain        156              (15)             106              (19)             40               (9)               
 Pain in Limb     143              (14)             84               (15)             52               (11)              
   Neoplasms                                                                                                             
 Malignant Neoplasm Aggravated  205              (20)             97               (17)             89               (20)              
   Nervous                                                                                                               
 Headache         191              (19)             149              (27)             50               (11)              
 Dizziness (excluding vertigo)  180              (18)             91               (16)             58               (13)              
 Insomnia         166              (16)             111              (20)             73               (16)              
 Paresthesia      149              (15)             85               (15)             35               (8)               
 Hypoesthesia     127              (12)             65               (12)             43               (10)              
   Psychiatric                                                                                                           
 Depression       146              (14)             95               (17)             49               (11)              
 Anxiety          112              (11)             73               (13)             37               (8)               
 Confusion        74               (7)              39               (7)              47               (10)              
   Respiratory                                                                                                           
 Dyspnea          282              (27)             155              (28)             107              (24)              
 Cough            224              (22)             129              (23)             65               (14)              
   Skin                                                                                                                  
 Alopecia         125              (12)             80               (14)             36               (8)               
 Dermatitis       114              (11)             74               (13)             38               (8)               
             Grade 3 and Grade 4 laboratory abnormalities for serum creatinine, serum calcium, serum phosphorus, and serum magnesium observed in three clinical trials of Zometa in patients with bone metastases are shown in Tables 8 and 9.
 

 Table 8: Grade 3 Laboratory Abnormalities for Serum Creatinine, Serum Calcium, Serum Phosphorus, and Serum Magnesium in Three Clinical Trials in Patients with Bone Metastases 
   1  Grade 3 (greater than 3x Upper Limit of Normal); Grade 4 (greater than 6x Upper Limit of Normal)  *  Serum creatinine data for all patients randomized after the 15-minute infusion amendment  2  Grade 3 (less than 7 mg/dL); Grade 4 (less than 6 mg/dL)  3  Grade 3 (less than 2 mg/dL); Grade 4 (less than 1 mg/dL)  4  Grade 3 (greater than 3 mEq/L); Grade 4 (greater than 8 mEq/L)  5  Grade 3 (less than 0.9 mEq/L); Grade 4 (less than 0.7 mEq/L)   
  
                    Grade 3         
   Laboratory Parameter      Zometa           Pamidronate      Placebo         
                    4 mg             90 mg                            
                    n/N              (%)              n/N              (%)              n/N              (%)             
   Serum Creatinine      1*      7/529            (1%)             4/268            (2%)             4/241            (2%)              
   Hypocalcemia      2      6/973            (&lt;1%)            4/536            (&lt;1%)            0/415            -                 
   Hypophosphatemia      3      115/973          (12%)            38/537           (7%)             14/415           (3%)              
   Hypermagnesemia      4      19/971           (2%)             2/535            (&lt;1%)            8/415            (2%)              
   Hypomagnesemia      5      1/971            (&lt;1%)            0/535            -                1/415            (&lt;1%)             
            Table 9: Grade 4 Laboratory Abnormalities for Serum Creatinine, Serum Calcium, Serum Phosphorus, and Serum Magnesium in Three Clinical Trials in Patients with Bone Metastases 
   1  Grade 3 (greater than 3x Upper Limit of Normal); Grade 4 (greater than 6x Upper Limit of Normal)  *  Serum creatinine data for all patients randomized after the 15-minute infusion amendment  2  Grade 3 (less than 7 mg/dL); Grade 4 (less than 6 mg/dL)  3  Grade 3 (less than 2 mg/dL); Grade 4 (less than 1 mg/dL)  4  Grade 3 (greater than 3 mEq/L); Grade 4 (greater than 8 mEq/L)  5  Grade 3 (less than 0.9 mEq/L); Grade 4 (less than 0.7 mEq/L)   
  
                    Grade 4         
   Laboratory Parameter      Zometa           Pamidronate      Placebo         
                    4 mg             90 mg                            
                    n/N              (%)              n/N              (%)              n/N              (%)             
   Serum Creatinine      1*      2/529            (&lt;1%)            1/268            (&lt;1%)            0/241            -                 
   Hypocalcemia      2      7/973            (&lt;1%)            3/536            (&lt;1%)            2/415            (&lt;1%)             
   Hypophosphatemia      3      5/973            (&lt;1%)            0/537            -                1/415            (&lt;1%)             
   Hypermagnesemia      4      0/971            -                0/535            -                2/415            (&lt;1%)             
   Hypomagnesemia      5      2/971            (&lt;1%)            1/535            (&lt;1%)            0/415            -                 
             Among the less frequently occurring adverse events (less than 15% of patients), rigors, hypokalemia, influenza-like illness, and hypocalcemia showed a trend for more events with bisphosphonate administration (Zometa 4 mg and pamidronate groups) compared to the placebo group.
 

 Less common adverse events reported more often with Zometa 4 mg than pamidronate included decreased weight, which was reported in 16% of patients in the Zometa 4 mg group compared with 9% in the pamidronate group. Decreased appetite was reported in slightly more patients in the Zometa 4 mg group (13%) compared with the pamidronate (9%) and placebo (10%) groups, but the clinical significance of these small differences is not clear.



   Renal Toxicity  



 In the bone metastases trials, renal deterioration was defined as an increase of 0.5 mg/dL for patients with normal baseline creatinine (less than 1.4 mg/dL) or an increase of 1.0 mg/dL for patients with an abnormal baseline creatinine (greater than or equal to1.4 mg/dL). The following are data on the incidence of renal deterioration in patients receiving Zometa 4 mg over 15 minutes in these trials (see Table 10).



 Table 10: Percentage of Patients with Treatment-Emergent Renal Function Deterioration by Baseline Serum Creatinine* 
 *Table includes only patients who were randomized to the trial after a protocol amendment that lengthened the infusion duration of Zometa to 15 minutes.   
  
   Patient Population/Baseline Creatinine     
   Multiple Myeloma and Breast Cancer      Zometa 4 mg      Pamidronate 90 mg     
                    n/N              (%)              n/N              (%)             
 Normal           27/246           (11%)            23/246           (9%)              
 Abnormal         2/26             (8%)             2/22             (9%)              
 Total            29/272           (11%)            25/268           (9%)              
   Solid Tumors      Zometa 4 mg      Placebo         
                    n/N              (%)              n/N              (%)             
 Normal           17/154           (11%)            10/143           (7%)              
 Abnormal         1/11             (9%)             1/20             (5%)              
 Total            18/165           (11%)            11/163           (7%)              
   Prostate Cancer      Zometa 4 mg      Placebo         
                    n/N              (%)              n/N              (%)             
 Normal           12/82            (15%)            8/68             (12%)             
 Abnormal         4/10             (40%)            2/10             (20%)             
 Total            16/92            (17%)            10/78            (13%)             
           The risk of deterioration in renal function appeared to be related to time on study, whether patients were receiving Zometa (4 mg over 15 minutes), placebo, or pamidronate.
 

 In the trials and in postmarketing experience, renal deterioration, progression to renal failure, and dialysis have occurred in patients with normal and abnormal baseline renal function, including patients treated with 4 mg infused over a 15-minute period. There have been instances of this occurring after the initial Zometa dose.



   6.2     Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been reported during postapproval use of Zometa. Because these reports are from a population of uncertain size and are subject to confounding factors, it is not possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Osteonecrosis of the Jaw  



 Cases of osteonecrosis (primarily involving the jaws) have been reported predominantly in cancer patients treated with intravenous bisphosphonates including Zometa. Many of these patients were also receiving chemotherapy and corticosteroids which may be a risk factor for ONJ. Caution is advised when Zometa is administered with anti-angiogenic drugs as an increased incidence of ONJ has been observed with concomitant use of these drugs. Data suggests a greater frequency of reports of ONJ in certain cancers, such as advanced breast cancer and multiple myeloma. The majority of the reported cases are in cancer patients following invasive dental procedures, such as tooth extraction. It is therefore prudent to avoid invasive dental procedures as recovery may be prolonged  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.4)]  .



   Acute Phase Reaction  



 Within three days after Zometa administration, an acute phase reaction has been reported, with symptoms including pyrexia, fatigue, bone pain and/or arthralgias, myalgias, chills, influenza-like illness and arthritis with subsequent joint swelling; these symptoms usually resolve within three days of onset, but resolution could take up to 7 to 14 days. However, some of these symptoms have been reported to persist for a longer duration.



   Musculoskeletal Pain  



 Severe and occasionally incapacitating bone, joint, and/or muscle pain has been reported with bisphosphonate use  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.5)]  .



   Atypical Subtrochanteric and Diaphyseal Femoral Fractures  



 Atypical subtrochanteric and diaphyseal femoral fractures have been reported with bisphosphonate therapy, including Zometa  [see Warnings and Precautions (5.6)]  .



   Ocular Adverse Events  



 Cases of uveitis, scleritis, episcleritis, conjunctivitis, iritis, and orbital inflammation including orbital edema have been reported during postmarketing use. In some cases, symptoms resolved with topical steroids.



   Hypersensitivity Reactions  



 There have been rare reports of allergic reaction with intravenous zoledronic acid including angioedema and bronchoconstriction. Very rare cases of anaphylactic reaction/shock have been reported. Cases of Stevens-Johnson syndrome and toxic epidermal necrolysis have also been reported.



 Additional adverse reactions reported in postmarketing use include:



   CNS:  taste disturbance, hyperesthesia, tremor;  Special Senses:  blurred vision; uveitis;  Gastrointestinal:  dry mouth;  Skin:  Increased sweating;  Musculoskeletal:  muscle cramps;  Cardiovascular:  hypertension, bradycardia, hypotension (associated with syncope or circulatory collapse primarily in patients with underlying risk factors);  Respiratory:  bronchospasms, interstitial lung disease (ILD) with positive rechallenge;  Renal:  hematuria, proteinuria;  General Disorders and Administration Site:  weight increase, influenza-like illness (pyrexia, asthenia, fatigue or malaise) persisting for greater than 30 days;  Laboratory Abnormalities:  hyperkalemia, hypernatremia, hypocalcemia (cardiac arrhythmias and neurologic adverse events including seizures, tetany, and numbness have been reported due to severe hypocalcemia).
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">     5     WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS  



   EXCERPT:    *  Patients being treated with Zometa should not be treated with Reclast  (r)  . (  5.1  ) 
 *  Adequately rehydrate patients with hypercalcemia of malignancy prior to administration of Zometa and monitor electrolytes during treatment. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Renal toxicity may be greater in patients with renal impairment. Do not use doses greater than 4 mg. Treatment in patients with severe renal impairment is not recommended. Monitor serum creatinine before each dose. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Osteonecrosis of the jaw has been reported. Preventive dental exams should be performed before starting Zometa. Avoid invasive dental procedures. (  5.4  ) 
 *  Severe incapacitating bone, joint, and/or muscle pain may occur. Discontinue Zometa if severe symptoms occur. (  5.5  )  
 *  Zometa can cause fetal harm. Women of childbearing potential should be advised of the potential hazard to the fetus and to avoid becoming pregnant. (  5.9  ,  8.1  ) 
 *  Atypical subtrochanteric and diaphyseal femoral fractures have been reported in patients receiving bisphosphonate therapy. These fractures may occur after minimal or no trauma. Evaluate patients with thigh or groin pain to rule out a femoral fracture. Consider drug discontinuation in patients suspected to have an atypical femur fracture. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Hypocalcemia: Correct before initiating Zometa. Adequately supplement patients with calcium and vitamin D. Monitor serum calcium closely with concomitant administration of other drugs known to cause hypocalcemia to avoid severe or life-threatening hypocalcemia (  5.10  ) 
    
 

   5.1     Drugs with Same Active Ingredient or in the Same Drug Class



  Zometa contains the same active ingredient as found in Reclast  (r)  (zoledronic acid). Patients being treated with Zometa should not be treated with Reclast or other bisphosphonates.



    5.2     Hydration and Electrolyte Monitoring



  Patients with hypercalcemia of malignancy must be adequately rehydrated prior to administration of Zometa. Loop diuretics should not be used until the patient is adequately rehydrated and should be used with caution in combination with Zometa in order to avoid hypocalcemia. Zometa should be used with caution with other nephrotoxic drugs.



 Standard hypercalcemia-related metabolic parameters, such as serum levels of calcium, phosphate, and magnesium, as well as serum creatinine, should be carefully monitored following initiation of therapy with Zometa. If hypocalcemia, hypophosphatemia, or hypomagnesemia occur, short-term supplemental therapy may be necessary.



    5.3     Renal Impairment



  Zometa is excreted intact primarily via the kidney, and the risk of adverse reactions, in particular renal adverse reactions, may be greater in patients with impaired renal function. Safety and pharmacokinetic data are limited in patients with severe renal impairment and the risk of renal deterioration is increased [see Adverse Reactions (6.1)]  . Preexisting renal insufficiency and multiple cycles of Zometa and other bisphosphonates are risk factors for subsequent renal deterioration with Zometa. Factors predisposing to renal deterioration, such as dehydration or the use of other nephrotoxic drugs, should be identified and managed, if possible.



 Zometa treatment in patients with hypercalcemia of malignancy with severe renal impairment should be considered only after evaluating the risks and benefits of treatment [see Dosage and Administration (2.1)]  . In the clinical studies, patients with serum creatinine greater than 400 umol/L or greater than 4.5 mg/dL were excluded.



 Zometa treatment is not recommended in patients with bone metastases with severe renal impairment. In the clinical studies, patients with serum creatinine greater than 265 umol/L or greater than 3.0 mg/dL were excluded and there were only 8 of 564 patients treated with Zometa 4 mg by 15-minute infusion with a baseline creatinine greater than 2 mg/dL. Limited pharmacokinetic data exists in patients with creatinine clearance less than 30 mL/min [see Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)   ].  



    5.4     Osteonecrosis of the Jaw



   Osteonecrosis of the jaw (ONJ) has been reported predominantly in cancer patients treated with intravenous bisphosphonates, including Zometa. Many of these patients were also receiving chemotherapy and corticosteroids which may be risk factors for ONJ. The risk of ONJ may increase with duration of exposure to bisphosphonates.  



 Postmarketing experience and the literature suggest a greater frequency of reports of ONJ based on tumor type (advanced breast cancer, multiple myeloma), and dental status (dental extraction, periodontal disease, local trauma including poorly fitting dentures). Many reports of ONJ involved patients with signs of local infection including osteomyelitis.



 Cancer patients should maintain good oral hygiene and should have a dental examination with preventive dentistry prior to treatment with bisphosphonates.



 While on treatment, these patients should avoid invasive dental procedures if possible. For patients who develop ONJ while on bisphosphonate therapy, dental surgery may exacerbate the condition. For patients requiring dental procedures, there are no data available to suggest whether discontinuation of bisphosphonate treatment reduces the risk of ONJ. Clinical judgment of the treating physician should guide the management plan of each patient based on individual benefit/risk assessment [see Adverse Reactions (6.2)]  .



    5.5     Musculoskeletal Pain



  In postmarketing experience, severe and occasionally incapacitating bone, joint, and/or muscle pain has been reported in patients taking bisphosphonates, including Zometa. The time to onset of symptoms varied from one day to several months after starting the drug. Discontinue use if severe symptoms develop. Most patients had relief of symptoms after stopping. A subset had recurrence of symptoms when rechallenged with the same drug or another bisphosphonate [see Adverse Reactions (6.2)]  .



    5.6     Atypical Subtrochanteric and Diaphyseal Femoral Fractures



  Atypical subtrochanteric and diaphyseal femoral fractures have been reported in patients receiving bisphosphonate therapy, including Zometa. These fractures can occur anywhere in the femoral shaft from just below the lesser trochanter to just above the supracondylar flare and are transverse or short oblique in orientation without evidence of comminution. These fractures occur after minimal or no trauma. Patients may experience thigh or groin pain weeks to months before presenting with a completed femoral fracture. Fractures are often bilateral; therefore the contralateral femur should be examined in bisphosphonate-treated patients who have sustained a femoral shaft fracture. Poor healing of these fractures has also been reported. A number of case reports noted that patients were also receiving treatment with glucocorticoids (such as prednisone or dexamethasone) at the time of fracture. Causality with bisphosphonate therapy has not been established.



 Any patient with a history of bisphosphonate exposure who presents with thigh or groin pain in the absence of trauma should be suspected of having an atypical fracture and should be evaluated. Discontinuation of Zometa therapy in patients suspected to have an atypical femur fracture should be considered pending evaluation of the patient, based on an individual benefit risk assessment. It is unknown whether the risk of atypical femur fracture continues after stopping therapy.



    5.7     Patients with Asthma



  While not observed in clinical trials with Zometa, there have been reports of bronchoconstriction in aspirin-sensitive patients receiving bisphosphonates.



    5.8     Hepatic Impairment



  Only limited clinical data are available for use of Zometa to treat hypercalcemia of malignancy in patients with hepatic insufficiency, and these data are not adequate to provide guidance on dosage selection or how to safely use Zometa in these patients.



    5.9     Use in Pregnancy



  Bisphosphonates, such as Zometa, are incorporated into the bone matrix, from where they are gradually released over periods of weeks to years. There may be a risk of fetal harm (e.g., skeletal and other abnormalities) if a woman becomes pregnant after completing a course of bisphosphonate therapy.



 Zometa may cause fetal harm when administered to a pregnant woman. In reproductive studies in pregnant rats, subcutaneous doses equivalent to 2.4 or 4.8 times the human systemic exposure resulted in pre- and postimplantation losses, decreases in viable fetuses and fetal skeletal, visceral, and external malformations. There are no adequate and well controlled studies in pregnant women. If this drug is used during pregnancy, or if the patient becomes pregnant while taking this drug, the patient should be apprised of the potential hazard to a fetus [see Use in Specific Populations (8.1)]  .



    5.10     Hypocalcemia



   Hypocalcemia has been reported in patients treated with Zometa. Cardiac arrhythmias and neurologic adverse events (seizures, tetany, and numbness) have been reported secondary to cases of severe hypocalcemia. In some instances, hypocalcemia may be life-threatening. Caution is advised when Zometa is administered with drugs known to cause hypocalcemia, as severe hypocalcemia may develop, [see Drug Interactions (7)]  . Serum calcium should be measured and hypocalcemia must be corrected before initiating Zometa. Adequately supplement patients with calcium and vitamin D.  
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
