<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="zonegran" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">      ADVERSE REACTIONS  

  The most common adverse reactions with ZONEGRAN (an incidence at least 4% greater than placebo) in controlled clinical trials and shown in descending order of frequency were somnolence, anorexia, dizziness, ataxia, agitation/irritability, and difficulty with memory and/or concentration.



 In controlled clinical trials, 12% of patients receiving ZONEGRAN as adjunctive therapy discontinued due to an adverse reaction compared to 6% receiving placebo. Approximately 21% of the 1,336 patients with epilepsy who received ZONEGRAN in clinical studies discontinued treatment because of an adverse reaction. The most common adverse reactions leading to discontinuation were somnolence, fatigue and/or ataxia (6%), anorexia (3%), difficulty concentrating (2%), difficulty with memory, mental slowing, nausea/vomiting (2%), and weight loss (1%). Many of these adverse reactions were dose-related (see    WARNINGS    and    PRECAUTIONS    ).



     Adverse Reaction Incidence in Controlled Clinical Trials:  

  Table 4 lists adverse reactions that occurred in at least 2% of patients treated with ZONEGRAN in controlled clinical trials that were numerically more common in the ZONEGRAN group. In these studies, either ZONEGRAN or placebo was added to the patient's current AED therapy.



 Table 4. Adverse Reactions in Placebo-Controlled, Add-On Trials (Events that occurred in at least 2% of ZONEGRAN-treated patients and occurred more frequently in ZONEGRAN-treated than placebo-treated patients) 
   BODY SYSTEM/PREFERRED TERM      ZONEGRAN    (n=269)    %      PLACEBO    (n=230)    %     
   BODY AS A WHOLE                                       
  Headache               10        8                                  
  Abdominal Pain          6         3                                 
  Flu Syndrome            4         3                                 
   DIGESTIVE                                         
  Anorexia               13         6                                 
  Nausea                   9        6                                 
  Diarrhea                 5         2                                
  Dyspepsia                3         1                                
  Constipation             2        1                                 
  Dry Mouth                2        1                                 
   HEMATOLOGIC AND LYMPHATIC                                       
  Ecchymosis               2        1                                 
   METABOLIC AND NUTRITIONAL                                       
  Weight Loss              3        2                                 
   NERVOUS SYSTEM                                       
  Dizziness               13         7                                
  Ataxia                    6      1                                  
  Nystagmus                 4      2                                  
  Paresthesia               4      1                                  
   NEUROPSYCHIATRIC AND COGNITIVE DYSFUNCTION-ALTERED COGNITIVE FUNCTION                                                        
  Confusion                 6      3                                  
  Difficulty Concentrating            6      2                                  
  Difficulty with Memory            6      2                                  
  Mental Slowing            4      2                                  
   NEUROPSYCHIATRIC AND COGNITIVE DYSFUNCTION-BEHAVIORAL ABNORMALITIES (NON-PSYCHOSIS-RELATED)                                                        
  Agitation/Irritability            9      4                                  
  Depression                6      3                                  
  Insomnia                  6      3                                  
  Anxiety                   3      2                                  
  Nervousness               2      1                                  
   NEUROPSYCHIATRIC AND COGNITIVE DYSFUNCTION-BEHAVIORAL ABNORMALITIES (PSYCHOSIS-RELATED)                                                        
  Schizophrenic/Schizophreniform Behavior            2       0                                 
   NEUROPSYCHIATRIC AND COGNITIVE DYSFUNCTION-CNS DEPRESSION                                                        
  Somnolence               17        7                                
  Fatigue                   8      6                                  
  Tiredness                 7      5                                  
   NEUROPSYCHIATRIC AND COGNITIVE DYSFUNCTION-SPEECH AND LANGUAGE ABNORMALITIES                                                        
  Speech Abnormalities            5       2                                 
  Difficulties in Verbal Expression            2      &lt;1                                 
   RESPIRATORY                                       
  Rhinitis                  2        1                                
   SKIN AND APPENDAGES                                       
  Rash                      3        2                                
   SPECIAL SENSES                                       
  Diplopia                  6       3                                 
  Taste Perversion            2        0                                
      
 

     Other Adverse Reactions in Clinical Trials:  

  ZONEGRAN has been administered to 1,598 individuals during all clinical trials, only some of which were placebo-controlled. The frequencies represent the proportion of the 1,598 individuals exposed to ZONEGRAN who experienced an event on at least one occasion. All events are included except those already listed in the previous table or discussed in    WARNINGS    or    PRECAUTIONS    , trivial events, those too general to be informative, and those not reasonably associated with ZONEGRAN.



 Events are further classified within each category and listed in order of decreasing frequency as follows:  frequent  occurring in at least 1:100 patients;  infrequent  occurring in 1:100 to 1:1000 patients;  rare  occurring in fewer than 1:1000 patients.



     Body as a Whole:      Frequent:  Accidental injury, asthenia.  Infrequent:  Chest pain, flank pain, malaise, allergic reaction, face edema, neck rigidity.  Rare:  Lupus erythematosus.



     Cardiovascular:      Infrequent:  Palpitation, tachycardia, vascular insufficiency, hypotension, hypertension, thrombophlebitis, syncope, bradycardia.  Rare:  Atrial fibrillation, heart failure, pulmonary embolus, ventricular extrasystoles.



     Digestive:      Frequent:  Vomiting.  Infrequent:  Flatulence, gingivitis, gum hyperplasia, gastritis, gastroenteritis, stomatitis, cholelithiasis, glossitis, melena, rectal hemorrhage, ulcerative stomatitis, gastro-duodenal ulcer, dysphagia, gum hemorrhage.  Rare:  Cholangitis, hematemesis, cholecystitis, cholestatic jaundice, colitis, duodenitis, esophagitis, fecal incontinence, mouth ulceration.



     Hematologic and Lymphatic:      Infrequent:  Leukopenia, anemia, immunodeficiency, lymphadenopathy.  Rare:  Thrombocytopenia, microcytic anemia, petechia.



     Metabolic and Nutritional:      Infrequent:  Peripheral edema, weight gain, edema, thirst, dehydration.  Rare:  Hypoglycemia, hyponatremia, lactic dehydrogenase increased, SGOT increased, SGPT increased.



     Musculoskeletal:      Infrequent:  Leg cramps, myalgia, myasthenia, arthralgia, arthritis.



     Nervous System:      Frequent:  Tremor, convulsion, abnormal gait, hyperesthesia, incoordination.  Infrequent:  Hypertonia, twitching, abnormal dreams, vertigo, libido decreased, neuropathy, hyperkinesia, movement disorder, dysarthria, cerebrovascular accident, hypotonia, peripheral neuritis, reflexes increased.  Rare:  Dyskinesia, dystonia, encephalopathy, facial paralysis, hypokinesia, hyperesthesia, myoclonus, oculogyric crisis.



     Behavioral Abnormalities -Non-Psychosis-Related:      Infrequent:  Euphoria.



     Respiratory:      Frequent:  Pharyngitis, cough increased.  Infrequent  : Dyspnea.  Rare:  Apnea, hemoptysis.



     Skin and Appendages:      Frequent:  Pruritus.  Infrequent:  Maculopapular rash, acne, alopecia, dry skin, sweating, eczema, urticaria, hirsutism, pustular rash, vesiculobullous rash.



     Special Senses:      Frequent:  Amblyopia, tinnitus.  Infrequent:  Conjunctivitis, parosmia, deafness, visual field defect, glaucoma.  Rare:  Photophobia, iritis.



     Urogenital:      Infrequent:  Urinary frequency, dysuria, urinary incontinence, hematuria, impotence, urinary retention, urinary urgency, amenorrhea, polyuria, nocturia.  Rare:  Albuminuria, enuresis, bladder pain, bladder calculus, gynecomastia, mastitis, menorrhagia.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
