<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="zosyn" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   The most common adverse reactions (incidence &gt;5%) are diarrhea, constipation, nausea, headache and insomnia. (  6.1  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer Inc. at 1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch  .  



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



 During the initial clinical investigations, 2621 patients worldwide were treated with ZOSYN in phase 3 trials. In the key North American monotherapy clinical trials (n=830 patients), 90% of the adverse events reported were mild to moderate in severity and transient in nature. However, in 3.2% of the patients treated worldwide, ZOSYN was discontinued because of adverse events primarily involving the skin (1.3%), including rash and pruritus; the gastrointestinal system (0.9%), including diarrhea, nausea, and vomiting; and allergic reactions (0.5%).



 Table 3: Adverse Reactions from ZOSYN Monotherapy Clinical Trials 
 System Organ Class  Adverse Reaction                                                                   
  
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                           
   Diarrhea (11.3%)                                                                                     
   Constipation (7.7%)                                                                                  
   Nausea (6.9%)                                                                                        
   Vomiting (3.3%)                                                                                      
   Dyspepsia (3.3%)                                                                                     
   Abdominal pain (1.3%)                                                                                
   Pseudomembranous colitis (&lt;=1%)                                                                      
   General disorders and administration site conditions                                                 
   Fever (2.4%)                                                                                         
   Injection site reaction (&lt;=1%)                                                                       
   Rigors (&lt;=1%)                                                                                        
   Immune system disorders                                                                              
   Anaphylaxis (&lt;=1%)                                                                                   
   Infections and infestations                                                                          
   Candidiasis (1.6%)                                                                                   
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders                                                                   
    Hypoglycemia (&lt;=1%)                                                                                 
   Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders                                                      
   Myalgia(&lt;=1%)                                                                                        
   Arthralgia (&lt;=1%)                                                                                    
   Nervous system disorders                                                                             
   Headache (7.7%)                                                                                      
   Insomnia (6.6%)                                                                                      
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                                                               
   Rash (4.2%, including maculopapular, bullous, and urticarial)                                        
   Pruritus (3.1%)                                                                                      
   Vascular disorders                                                                                   
   Phlebitis (1.3%)                                                                                     
   Thrombophlebitis (&lt;=1%)                                                                              
   Hypotension (&lt;=1%)                                                                                   
   Purpura (&lt;=1%)                                                                                       
   Epistaxis (&lt;=1%)                                                                                     
   Flushing (&lt;=1%)                                                                                      
         Nosocomial Pneumonia Trials
 

 Two trials of nosocomial lower respiratory tract infections were conducted. In one study, 222 patients were treated with ZOSYN in a dosing regimen of 4.5 g every 6 hours in combination with an aminoglycoside and 215 patients were treated with imipenem/cilastatin (500 mg/500 mg q6h) in combination with an aminoglycoside. In this trial, treatment-emergent adverse events were reported by 402 patients, 204 (91.9%) in the piperacillin/tazobactam group and 198 (92.1%) in the imipenem/cilastatin group. Twenty-five (11.0%) patients in the piperacillin/tazobactam group and 14 (6.5%) in the imipenem/cilastatin group (p &gt; 0.05) discontinued treatment due to an adverse event.



 The second trial used a dosing regimen of 3.375 g given every 4 hours with an aminoglycoside.



 Table 4: Adverse Reactions from ZOSYN Plus Aminoglycoside Clinical TrialsFor adverse drug reactions that appeared in both studies the higher frequency is presented. 
 System Organ Class  Adverse Reaction                                                                   
  
   Blood and lymphatic system disorders                                                                 
   Thrombocythemia (1.4%)                                                                               
   Anemia (&lt;=1%)                                                                                        
   Thrombocytopenia (&lt;=1%)                                                                              
   Eosinophilia (&lt;=1%)                                                                                  
   Gastrointestinal disorders                                                                           
   Diarrhea (20%)                                                                                       
   Constipation (8.4%)                                                                                  
   Nausea (5.8%)                                                                                        
   Vomiting (2.7%)                                                                                      
   Dyspepsia (1.9%)                                                                                     
   Abdominal pain (1.8%)                                                                                
   Stomatitis (&lt;=1%)                                                                                    
   General disorders and administration site conditions                                                 
   Fever (3.2%)                                                                                         
   Injection site reaction (&lt;=1%)                                                                       
   Infections and infestations                                                                          
   Oral candidiasis (3.9%)                                                                              
   Candidiasis (1.8%)                                                                                   
   Investigations                                                                                       
   BUN increased (1.8%)                                                                                 
   Blood creatinine increased (1.8%)                                                                    
   Liver function test abnormal (1.4%)                                                                  
   Alkaline phosphatase increased (&lt;=1%)                                                                
   Aspartate aminotransferase increased (&lt;=1%)                                                          
   Alanine aminotransferase increased (&lt;=1%)                                                            
   Metabolism and nutrition disorders                                                                   
   Hypoglycemia (&lt;=1%)                                                                                  
   Hypokalemia (&lt;=1%)                                                                                   
   Nervous system disorders                                                                             
   Headache (4.5%)                                                                                      
   Insomnia (4.5%)                                                                                      
   Renal and urinary disorders                                                                          
   Renal failure (&lt;=1%)                                                                                 
   Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders                                                               
   Rash (3.9%)                                                                                          
   Pruritus (3.2%)                                                                                      
   Vascular disorders                                                                                   
   Thrombophlebitis (1.3%)                                                                              
   Hypotension (1.3%)                                                                                   
         Pediatrics
 

 Studies of ZOSYN in pediatric patients suggest a similar safety profile to that seen in adults. In a prospective, randomized, comparative, open-label clinical trial of pediatric patients with severe intra-abdominal infections (including appendicitis and/or peritonitis), 273 patients were treated with ZOSYN (112.5 mg/kg every 8 hours) and 269 patients were treated with cefotaxime (50 mg/kg) plus metronidazole (7.5 mg/kg) every 8 hours. In this trial, treatment-emergent adverse events were reported by 146 patients, 73 (26.7%) in the ZOSYN group and 73 (27.1%) in the cefotaxime/metronidazole group. Six patients (2.2%) in the ZOSYN group and 5 patients (1.9%) in the cefotaxime/metronidazole group discontinued due to an adverse event.



   Adverse Laboratory Events (Seen During Clinical Trials)



 Of the trials reported, including that of nosocomial lower respiratory tract infections in which a higher dose of ZOSYN was used in combination with an aminoglycoside, changes in laboratory parameters include:



   Hematologic  -decreases in hemoglobin and hematocrit, thrombocytopenia, increases in platelet count, eosinophilia, leukopenia, neutropenia. These patients were withdrawn from therapy; some had accompanying systemic symptoms (e.g., fever, rigors, chills).



   Coagulation  -positive direct Coombs' test, prolonged prothrombin time, prolonged partial thromboplastin time



   Hepatic  -transient elevations of AST (SGOT), ALT (SGPT), alkaline phosphatase, bilirubin



   Renal  -increases in serum creatinine, blood urea nitrogen



 Additional laboratory events include abnormalities in electrolytes (i.e., increases and decreases in sodium, potassium, and calcium), hyperglycemia, decreases in total protein or albumin, blood glucose decreased, gamma-glutamyltransferase increased, hypokalemia, and bleeding time prolonged.



   6.2 Post-Marketing Experience

  In addition to the adverse drug reactions identified in clinical trials in Table 3 and Table 4, the following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of ZOSYN. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish causal relationship to drug exposure.



   Gastrointestinal  -hepatitis, jaundice



   Hematologic  -hemolytic anemia, agranulocytosis, pancytopenia



   Immune  -hypersensitivity reactions, anaphylactic/anaphylactoid reactions (including shock)



   Renal  -interstitial nephritis



   Skin and Appendages  -erythema multiforme, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, drug reaction with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms (DRESS), acute generalized exanthematous pustulosis (AGEP)



   6.3 Additional Experience with piperacillin

  The following adverse reaction has also been reported for piperacillin for injection:



   Skeletal  -prolonged muscle relaxation [  see  Drug Interactions (7.4)  ].  



 Post-marketing experience with ZOSYN in pediatric patients suggests a similar safety profile to that seen in adults.
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Serious hypersensitivity reactions (anaphylactic/anaphylactoid) reactions have been reported in patients receiving ZOSYN. Discontinue ZOSYN if a reaction occurs. (  5.1  ) 
 *  ZOSYN may cause severe cutaneous adverse reactions, such as Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, drug reaction with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms, and acute generalized exanthematous pustulosis (  5.2  ). Discontinue ZOSYN for progressive rashes. 
 *   Clostridium difficile associated diarrhea: evaluate patients if diarrhea occurs. (  5.3  ) 
 *  Hematological effects (including bleeding, leukopenia and neutropenia) have occurred. Monitor hematologic tests during prolonged therapy. (  5.4  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Hypersensitivity Reactions



  Serious and occasionally fatal hypersensitivity (anaphylactic/anaphylactoid) reactions (including shock) have been reported in patients receiving therapy with ZOSYN. These reactions are more likely to occur in individuals with a history of penicillin, cephalosporin, or carbapenem hypersensitivity or a history of sensitivity to multiple allergens. Before initiating therapy with ZOSYN, careful inquiry should be made concerning previous hypersensitivity reactions. If an allergic reaction occurs, ZOSYN should be discontinued and appropriate therapy instituted.



    5.2 Severe Skin Reactions



  ZOSYN may cause severe cutaneous adverse reactions, such as Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, drug reaction with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms, and acute generalized exanthematous pustulosis. If patients develop a skin rash they should be monitored closely and ZOSYN discontinued if lesions progress.



    5.3 Clostridium difficile  Associated Diarrhea



   Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea (CDAD) has been reported with use of nearly all antibacterial agents, including ZOSYN, and may range in severity from mild diarrhea to fatal colitis. Treatment with antibacterial agents alters the normal flora of the colon leading to overgrowth of C. difficile  .



  C. difficile  produces toxins A and B which contribute to the development of CDAD. Hypertoxin producing strains of C. difficile  cause increased morbidity and mortality, as these infections can be refractory to antimicrobial therapy and may require colectomy. CDAD must be considered in all patients who present with diarrhea following antibacterial drug use. Careful medical history is necessary since CDAD has been reported to occur over two months after the administration of antibacterial agents.



 If CDAD is suspected or confirmed, ongoing antibacterial drug use not directed against C. difficile  may need to be discontinued. Appropriate fluid and electrolyte management, protein supplementation, antibacterial treatment of C. difficile  , and surgical evaluation should be instituted as clinically indicated.



    5.4 Hematologic Effects



  Bleeding manifestations have occurred in some patients receiving beta-lactam drugs, including piperacillin. These reactions have sometimes been associated with abnormalities of coagulation tests such as clotting time, platelet aggregation and prothrombin time, and are more likely to occur in patients with renal failure. If bleeding manifestations occur, ZOSYN should be discontinued and appropriate therapy instituted.



 The leukopenia/neutropenia associated with ZOSYN administration appears to be reversible and most frequently associated with prolonged administration.



 Periodic assessment of hematopoietic function should be performed, especially with prolonged therapy, ie, &gt;= 21 days [ see  Adverse Reactions (6.1)    ].



    5.5 Central Nervous System Effects



  As with other penicillins, patients may experience neuromuscular excitability or convulsions if higher than recommended doses are given intravenously (particularly in the presence of renal failure).



    5.6 Electrolyte Effects



  ZOSYN contains a total of 2.79 mEq (64 mg) of Na  +  per gram of piperacillin in the combination product. This should be considered when treating patients requiring restricted salt intake. Periodic electrolyte determinations should be performed in patients with low potassium reserves, and the possibility of hypokalemia should be kept in mind with patients who have potentially low potassium reserves and who are receiving cytotoxic therapy or diuretics.



    5.7 Development of Drug-Resistant Bacteria



  Prescribing ZOSYN in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of development of drug-resistant bacteria.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
