<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="zylet" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  Adverse reactions have occurred with steroid/anti-infective combination drugs which can be attributed to the steroid component, the anti-infective component, or the combination.



   Zylet:  



 In a 42 day safety study comparing Zylet to placebo, ocular adverse reactions included injection (approximately 20%) and superficial punctuate keratitis (approximately 15%). Increased intraocular pressure was reported in 10% (Zylet) and 4% (placebo) of subjects. Nine percent (9%) of Zylet subjects reported burning and stinging upon instillation.



 Ocular reactions reported with an incidence less than 4% include vision disorders, discharge, itching, lacrimation disorder, photophobia, corneal deposits, ocular discomfort, eyelid disorder, and other unspecified eye disorders.



 The incidence of non-ocular reactions reported in approximately 14% of subjects was headache; all other non ocular reactions had an incidence of less than 5%.



   Loteprednol etabonate ophthalmic suspension 0.2% - 0.5%:  



 Reactions associated with ophthalmic steroids include elevated intraocular pressure, which may be associated with infrequent optic nerve damage, visual acuity and field defects, posterior subcapsular cataract formation, delayed wound healing and secondary ocular infection from pathogens including herpes simplex, and perforation of the globe where there is thinning of the cornea or sclera.



 In a summation of controlled, randomized studies of individuals treated for 28 days or longer with loteprednol etabonate, the incidence of significant elevation of intraocular pressure (&gt;=10 mm Hg) was 2% (15/901) among patients receiving loteprednol etabonate, 7% (11/164) among patients receiving 1% prednisolone acetate and 0.5% (3/583) among patients receiving placebo.



   Tobramycin ophthalmic solution 0.3%:  



 The most frequent adverse reactions to topical tobramycin are hypersensitivity and localized ocular toxicity, including lid itching and swelling and conjunctival erythema. These reactions occur in less than 4% of patients. Similar reactions may occur with the topical use of other aminoglycoside antibiotics.



   Secondary Infection:  



 The development of secondary infection has occurred after use of combinations containing steroids and antimicrobials. Fungal infections of the cornea are particularly prone to develop coincidentally with long-term applications of steroids.



 The possibility of fungal invasion must be considered in any persistent corneal ulceration where steroid treatment has been used.



 Secondary bacterial ocular infection following suppression of host responses also occurs.



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions reported in patients were injection and superficial punctuate keratitis, increased intraocular pressure, burning and stinging upon instillation.(  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Bausch &amp; Lomb at 1-800-323-0000 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch    
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *    Intraocular pressure (IOP) - Prolonged use of corticosteroids may result in glaucoma with damage to the optic nerve, defects in visual acuity and fields of vision. If this product is used for 10 days or longer, IOP should be monitored. (  5.1  ) 
 *    Cataracts - Use of corticosteroids may result in posterior subcapsular cataract formation. (  5.2  ) 
 *    Delayed healing - The use of steroids after cataract surgery may delay healing and increase the incidence of bleb formation. In those diseases causing thinning of the cornea or sclera, perforations have been known to occur with the use of topical steroids. The initial prescription and renewal of the medication order should be made by a physician only after examination of the patient with the aid of a magnification such as slit lamp biomicroscopy and, where appropriate, fluorescein staining. (  5.3  ) 
 *    Bacterial infections - Prolonged use of corticosteroids may suppress the host response and thus increase the hazard of secondary ocular infection. In acute purulent conditions, steroids may mask infection or enhance existing infection. If signs and symptoms fail to improve after 2 days, the patient should be re-evaluated. (  5.4  ) 
 *    Viral infections - Employment of a corticosteroid medication in the treatment of patients with a history of herpes simplex requires great caution. Use of ocular steroids may prolong the course and may exacerbate the severity of many viral infections of the eye (including herpes simplex). (  5.5  ) 
 *    Fungal infections - Fungal infections of the cornea are particularly prone to develop coincidentally with long-term local steroid application. Fungus invasion must be considered in any persistent corneal ulceration where a steroid has been used or is in use. (  5.6  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Intraocular Pressure (IOP) Increase



  Prolonged use of corticosteroids may result in glaucoma with damage to the optic nerve, defects in visual acuity and fields of vision.. Steroids should be used with caution in the presence of glaucoma.



 If this product is used for 10 days or longer, intraocular pressure should be monitored.



    5.2 Cataracts



  Use of corticosteroids may result in posterior subcapsular cataract formation.



    5.3 Delayed Healing



  The use of steroids after cataract surgery may delay healing and increase the incidence of bleb formation. In those diseases causing thinning of the cornea or sclera, perforations have been known to occur with the use of topical steroids. The initial prescription and renewal of the medication order should be made by a physician only after examination of the patient with the aid of magnification such as a slit lamp biomicroscopy and, where appropriate, fluorescein staining.



    5.4 Bacterial Infections



  Prolonged use of corticosteroids may suppress the host response and thus increase the hazard of secondary ocular infections. In acute purulent conditions of the eye, steroids may mask infection or enhance existing infection. If signs and symptoms fail to improve after 2 days, the patient should be re-evaluated.



    5.5 Viral Infections



  Employment of a corticosteroid medication in the treatment of patients with a history of herpes simplex requires great caution. Use of ocular steroids may prolong the course and may exacerbate the severity of many viral infections of the eye (including herpes simplex).



    5.6 Fungal Infections



  Fungal infections of the cornea are particularly prone to develop coincidentally with long-term local steroid application. Fungus invasion must be considered in any persistent corneal ulceration where a steroid has been used or is in use. Fungal cultures should be taken when appropriate.



    5.7 Aminoglycoside Hypersensitivity



  Sensitivity to topically applied aminoglycosides may occur in some patients. If hypersensitivity develops with this product, discontinue use and institute appropriate therapy.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
