<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="zyprexa0" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  When using ZYPREXA and fluoxetine in combination, also refer to the Adverse Reactions section of the package insert for Symbyax.



   EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;=5% and at least twice that for placebo) associated with:



   Oral Olanzapine Monotherapy:  



 *   Schizophrenia (Adults) - postural hypotension, constipation, weight gain, dizziness, personality disorder, akathisia (  6.1  ) 
 *   Schizophrenia (Adolescents) - sedation, weight increased, headache, increased appetite, dizziness, abdominal pain, pain in extremity, fatigue, dry mouth (  6.1  ) 
 *   Manic or Mixed Episodes, Bipolar I Disorder (Adults) - asthenia, dry mouth, constipation, increased appetite, somnolence, dizziness, tremor (  6.1  ) 
 *   Manic or Mixed Episodes, Bipolar I Disorder (Adolescents) - sedation, weight increased, increased appetite, headache, fatigue, dizziness, dry mouth, abdominal pain, pain in extremity (  6.1  ) 
      Combination of ZYPREXA and Lithium or Valproate:  
 

 *   Manic or Mixed Episodes, Bipolar I Disorder (Adults) - dry mouth, weight gain, increased appetite, dizziness, back pain, constipation, speech disorder, increased salivation, amnesia, paresthesia (  6.1  ) 
      ZYPREXA and Fluoxetine in Combination:  Also refer to the Adverse Reactions section of the package insert for Symbyax. (  6  )
 

   ZYPREXA IntraMuscular for Injection:  



 *  Agitation with Schizophrenia and Bipolar I Mania (Adults) - somnolence (  6.1  ) 
      To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Eli Lilly and Company at 1-800-LillyRx (1-800-545-5979) or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or www.fda.gov/medwatch  
 

 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect or predict the rates observed in practice.



     Clinical Trials in Adults  



 The information below for olanzapine is derived from a clinical trial database for olanzapine consisting of 8661 adult patients with approximately 4165 patient-years of exposure to oral olanzapine and 722 patients with exposure to intramuscular olanzapine for injection. This database includes: (1) 2500 patients who participated in multiple-dose oral olanzapine premarketing trials in schizophrenia and Alzheimer's disease representing approximately 1122 patient-years of exposure as of February 14, 1995; (2) 182 patients who participated in oral olanzapine premarketing bipolar I disorder (manic or mixed episodes) trials representing approximately 66 patient-years of exposure; (3) 191 patients who participated in an oral olanzapine trial of patients having various psychiatric symptoms in association with Alzheimer's disease representing approximately 29 patient-years of exposure; (4) 5788 patients from 88 additional oral olanzapine clinical trials as of December 31, 2001; and (5) 722 patients who participated in intramuscular olanzapine for injection premarketing trials in agitated patients with schizophrenia, bipolar I disorder (manic or mixed episodes), or dementia. In addition, information from the premarketing 6-week clinical study database for olanzapine in combination with lithium or valproate, consisting of 224 patients who participated in bipolar I disorder (manic or mixed episodes) trials with approximately 22 patient-years of exposure, is included below.



 The conditions and duration of treatment with olanzapine varied greatly and included (in overlapping categories) open-label and double-blind phases of studies, inpatients and outpatients, fixed-dose and dose-titration studies, and short-term or longer-term exposure. Adverse reactions were assessed by collecting adverse reactions, results of physical examinations, vital signs, weights, laboratory analytes, ECGs, chest x-rays, and results of ophthalmologic examinations.



 Certain portions of the discussion below relating to objective or numeric safety parameters, namely, dose-dependent adverse reactions, vital sign changes, weight gain, laboratory changes, and ECG changes are derived from studies in patients with schizophrenia and have not been duplicated for bipolar I disorder (manic or mixed episodes) or agitation. However, this information is also generally applicable to bipolar I disorder (manic or mixed episodes) and agitation.



 Adverse reactions during exposure were obtained by spontaneous report and recorded by clinical investigators using terminology of their own choosing. Consequently, it is not possible to provide a meaningful estimate of the proportion of individuals experiencing adverse reactions without first grouping similar types of reactions into a smaller number of standardized reaction categories. In the tables and tabulations that follow, MedDRA and COSTART Dictionary terminology has been used to classify reported adverse reactions.



 The stated frequencies of adverse reactions represent the proportion of individuals who experienced, at least once, a treatment-emergent adverse reaction of the type listed. A reaction was considered treatment emergent if it occurred for the first time or worsened while receiving therapy following baseline evaluation. The reported reactions do not include those reaction terms that were so general as to be uninformative. Reactions listed elsewhere in labeling may not be repeated below. It is important to emphasize that, although the reactions occurred during treatment with olanzapine, they were not necessarily caused by it. The entire label should be read to gain a complete understanding of the safety profile of olanzapine.



 The prescriber should be aware that the figures in the tables and tabulations cannot be used to predict the incidence of side effects in the course of usual medical practice where patient characteristics and other factors differ from those that prevailed in the clinical trials. Similarly, the cited frequencies cannot be compared with figures obtained from other clinical investigations involving different treatments, uses, and investigators. The cited figures, however, do provide the prescribing physician with some basis for estimating the relative contribution of drug and nondrug factors to the adverse reactions incidence in the population studied.



     Incidence of Adverse Reactions in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled and Combination Trials  



 The following findings are based on premarketing trials of (1) oral olanzapine for schizophrenia, bipolar I disorder (manic or mixed episodes), a subsequent trial of patients having various psychiatric symptoms in association with Alzheimer's disease, and premarketing combination trials, and (2) intramuscular olanzapine for injection in agitated patients with schizophrenia or bipolar I mania.



     Adverse Reactions Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Trials  



     Schizophrenia  - Overall, there was no difference in the incidence of discontinuation due to adverse reactions (5% for oral olanzapine vs 6% for placebo). However, discontinuations due to increases in ALT were considered to be drug related (2% for oral olanzapine vs 0% for placebo).



     Bipolar I Disorder (Manic or Mixed Episodes) Monotherapy  - Overall, there was no difference in the incidence of discontinuation due to adverse reactions (2% for oral olanzapine vs 2% for placebo).



     Agitation  - Overall, there was no difference in the incidence of discontinuation due to adverse reactions (0.4% for intramuscular olanzapine for injection vs 0% for placebo).



     Adverse Reactions Associated with Discontinuation of Treatment in Short-Term Combination Trials  



     Bipolar I Disorder (Manic or Mixed Episodes), Olanzapine as Adjunct to Lithium or Valproate   - In a study of patients who were already tolerating either lithium or valproate as monotherapy, discontinuation rates due to adverse reactions were 11% for the combination of oral olanzapine with lithium or valproate compared to 2% for patients who remained on lithium or valproate monotherapy. Discontinuations with the combination of oral olanzapine and lithium or valproate that occurred in more than 1 patient were: somnolence (3%), weight gain (1%), and peripheral edema (1%).



     Commonly Observed Adverse Reactions in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Trials  



 The most commonly observed adverse reactions associated with the use of oral olanzapine (incidence of 5% or greater) and not observed at an equivalent incidence among placebo-treated patients (olanzapine incidence at least twice that for placebo) were:



 Table 9: Common Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions Associated with the Use of Oral Olanzapine in 6-Week Trials - SCHIZOPHRENIA 
  a Personality disorder is the COSTART term for designating nonaggressive objectionable behavior.    
  
   Adverse Reaction                   Percentage of Patients Reporting Event     
   Olanzapine(N=248)                  Placebo(N=118)                    
 Postural hypotension               5                                  2                                   
 Constipation                       9                                  3                                   
 Weight gain                        6                                  1                                   
 Dizziness                          11                                 4                                   
 Personality disorder  a            8                                  4                                   
 Akathisia                          5                                  1                                   
        Table 10: Common Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions Associated with the Use of Oral Olanzapine in 3-Week and 4-Week Trials - Bipolar I Disorder (Manic or Mixed Episodes) 
   Adverse Reaction                   Percentage of Patients Reporting Event     
   Olanzapine(N=125)                  Placebo(N=129)                    
 Asthenia                           15                                 6                                   
 Dry mouth                          22                                 7                                   
 Constipation                       11                                 5                                   
 Dyspepsia                          11                                 5                                   
 Increased appetite                 6                                  3                                   
 Somnolence                         35                                 13                                  
 Dizziness                          18                                 6                                   
 Tremor                             6                                  3                                   
             Olanzapine Intramuscular   - There was 1 adverse reaction (somnolence) observed at an incidence of 5% or greater among intramuscular olanzapine for injection-treated patients and not observed at an equivalent incidence among placebo-treated patients (olanzapine incidence at least twice that for placebo) during the placebo-controlled premarketing studies. The incidence of somnolence during the 24 hour IM treatment period in clinical trials in agitated patients with schizophrenia or bipolar I mania was 6% for intramuscular olanzapine for injection and 3% for placebo.
 

     Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of 2% or More among Oral Olanzapine-Treated Patients in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Trials  



   Table 11  enumerates the incidence, rounded to the nearest percent, of treatment-emergent adverse reactions that occurred in 2% or more of patients treated with oral olanzapine (doses &gt;=2.5 mg/day) and with incidence greater than placebo who participated in the acute phase of placebo-controlled trials.



 Table 11: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions: Incidence in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials with Oral Olanzapine 
   Body System/Adverse Reaction       Percentage of Patients Reporting Event     
   Olanzapine(N=532)                  Placebo(N=294)                    
   Body as a Whole                                                                                         
 Accidental injury                  12                                 8                                   
 Asthenia                           10                                 9                                   
 Fever                              6                                  2                                   
 Back pain                          5                                  2                                   
 Chest pain                         3                                  1                                   
   Cardiovascular System                                                                                   
 Postural hypotension               3                                  1                                   
 Tachycardia                        3                                  1                                   
 Hypertension                       2                                  1                                   
   Digestive System                                                                                        
 Dry mouth                          9                                  5                                   
 Constipation                       9                                  4                                   
 Dyspepsia                          7                                  5                                   
 Vomiting                           4                                  3                                   
 Increased appetite                 3                                  2                                   
   Hemic and Lymphatic System                                                                              
 Ecchymosis                         5                                  3                                   
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders                                                                           
 Weight gain                        5                                  3                                   
 Peripheral edema                   3                                  1                                   
   Musculoskeletal System                                                                                  
 Extremity pain (other than joint)  5                                  3                                   
 Joint pain                         5                                  3                                   
   Nervous System                                                                                          
 Somnolence                         29                                 13                                  
 Insomnia                           12                                 11                                  
 Dizziness                          11                                 4                                   
 Abnormal gait                      6                                  1                                   
 Tremor                             4                                  3                                   
 Akathisia                          3                                  2                                   
 Hypertonia                         3                                  2                                   
 Articulation impairment            2                                  1                                   
   Respiratory System                                                                                      
 Rhinitis                           7                                  6                                   
 Cough increased                    6                                  3                                   
 Pharyngitis                        4                                  3                                   
   Special Senses                                                                                          
 Amblyopia                          3                                  2                                   
   Urogenital System                                                                                       
 Urinary incontinence               2                                  1                                   
 Urinary tract infection            2                                  1                                   
             Commonly Observed Adverse Reactions in Short-Term Trials of Oral Olanzapine as Adjunct to Lithium or Valproate  
 

 In the bipolar I disorder (manic or mixed episodes) adjunct placebo-controlled trials, the most commonly observed adverse reactions associated with the combination of olanzapine and lithium or valproate (incidence of &gt;=5% and at least twice placebo) were:



 Table 12: Common Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions Associated with the Use of Oral Olanzapine in 6-Week Adjunct to Lithium or Valproate Trials - Bipolar I Disorder (Manic or Mixed Episodes) 
   Adverse Reaction                   Percentage of Patients Reporting Event     
   Olanzapine with lithium or valproate(N=229)      Placebo with lithium or valproate(N=115)     
 Dry mouth                          32                                 9                                   
 Weight gain                        26                                 7                                   
 Increased appetite                 24                                 8                                   
 Dizziness                          14                                 7                                   
 Back pain                          8                                  4                                   
 Constipation                       8                                  4                                   
 Speech disorder                    7                                  1                                   
 Increased salivation               6                                  2                                   
 Amnesia                            5                                  2                                   
 Paresthesia                        5                                  2                                   
             Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of 2% or More among Oral Olanzapine-Treated Patients in Short-Term Trials of Olanzapine as Adjunct to Lithium or Valproate  
 

   Table 13  enumerates the incidence, rounded to the nearest percent, of treatment-emergent adverse reactions that occurred in 2% or more of patients treated with the combination of olanzapine (doses &gt;=5 mg/day) and lithium or valproate and with incidence greater than lithium or valproate alone who participated in the acute phase of placebo-controlled combination trials.



 Table 13: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions: Incidence in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials of Oral Olanzapine as Adjunct to Lithium or Valproate 
  a Denominator used was for females only (olanzapine, N=128; placebo, N=51).    
  
   Body System/Adverse Reaction       Percentage of Patients Reporting Event     
   Olanzapine with lithium or valproate(N=229)      Placebo with lithium or valproate(N=115)     
   Body as a Whole                                                                                         
 Asthenia                           18                                 13                                  
 Back pain                          8                                  4                                   
 Accidental injury                  4                                  2                                   
 Chest pain                         3                                  2                                   
   Cardiovascular System                                                                                   
 Hypertension                       2                                  1                                   
   Digestive System                                                                                        
 Dry mouth                          32                                 9                                   
 Increased appetite                 24                                 8                                   
 Thirst                             10                                 6                                   
 Constipation                       8                                  4                                   
 Increased salivation               6                                  2                                   
   Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders                                                                           
 Weight gain                        26                                 7                                   
 Peripheral edema                   6                                  4                                   
 Edema                              2                                  1                                   
   Nervous System                                                                                          
 Somnolence                         52                                 27                                  
 Tremor                             23                                 13                                  
 Depression                         18                                 17                                  
 Dizziness                          14                                 7                                   
 Speech disorder                    7                                  1                                   
 Amnesia                            5                                  2                                   
 Paresthesia                        5                                  2                                   
 Apathy                             4                                  3                                   
 Confusion                          4                                  1                                   
 Euphoria                           3                                  2                                   
 Incoordination                     2                                  0                                   
   Respiratory System                                                                                      
 Pharyngitis                        4                                  1                                   
 Dyspnea                            3                                  1                                   
   Skin and Appendages                                                                                     
 Sweating                           3                                  1                                   
 Acne                               2                                  0                                   
 Dry skin                           2                                  0                                   
   Special Senses                                                                                          
 Amblyopia                          9                                  5                                   
 Abnormal vision                    2                                  0                                   
   Urogenital System                                                                                       
 Dysmenorrhea  a                    2                                  0                                   
 Vaginitis  a                       2                                  0                                   
         For specific information about the adverse reactions observed with lithium or valproate, refer to the Adverse Reactions section of the package inserts for these other products.
 

     Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of 1% or More among Intramuscular Olanzapine for Injection-Treated Patients in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Trials  



   Table 14  enumerates the incidence, rounded to the nearest percent, of treatment-emergent adverse reactions that occurred in 1% or more of patients treated with intramuscular olanzapine for injection (dose range of 2.5-10 mg/injection) and with incidence greater than placebo who participated in the short-term, placebo-controlled trials in agitated patients with schizophrenia or bipolar I mania.



 Table 14: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions: Incidence in Short-Term (24 Hour), Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials with Intramuscular Olanzapine for Injection in Agitated Patients with Schizophrenia or Bipolar I Mania 
   Body System/Adverse Reaction       Percentage of Patients Reporting Event     
   Olanzapine(N=415)                  Placebo(N=150)                    
   Body as a Whole                                                                                         
 Asthenia                           2                                  1                                   
   Cardiovascular System                                                                                   
 Hypotension                        2                                  0                                   
 Postural hypotension               1                                  0                                   
   Nervous System                                                                                          
 Somnolence                         6                                  3                                   
 Dizziness                          4                                  2                                   
 Tremor                             1                                  0                                   
             Additional Findings Observed in Clinical Trials  
 

     Dose Dependency of Adverse Reactions in Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Trials  



     Extrapyramidal Symptoms:  The following table enumerates the percentage of patients with treatment-emergent extrapyramidal symptoms as assessed by categorical analyses of formal rating scales during acute therapy in a controlled clinical trial comparing oral olanzapine at 3 fixed doses with placebo in the treatment of schizophrenia in a 6-week trial.



 Table 15: Treatment-Emergent Extrapyramidal Symptoms Assessed by Rating Scales Incidence in a Fixed Dosage Range, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trial of Oral Olanzapine in Schizophrenia - Acute Phase 
  a Percentage of patients with a Simpson-Angus Scale total score &gt;3.    
  b Percentage of patients with a Barnes Akathisia Scale global score &gt;=2.    
  
                         Percentage of Patients Reporting Event     
   Placebo               Olanzapine5 +/- 2.5 mg/day      Olanzapine10 +/- 2.5 mg/day      Olanzapine15 +/- 2.5 mg/day     
 Parkinsonism  a       15                    14                    12                    14                     
 Akathisia  b          23                    16                    19                    27                     
           The following table enumerates the percentage of patients with treatment-emergent extrapyramidal symptoms as assessed by spontaneously reported adverse reactions during acute therapy in the same controlled clinical trial comparing olanzapine at 3 fixed doses with placebo in the treatment of schizophrenia in a 6-week trial.
 

 Table 16: Treatment-Emergent Extrapyramidal Symptoms Assessed by Adverse Reactions Incidence in a Fixed Dosage Range, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trial of Oral Olanzapine in Schizophrenia - Acute Phase 
  a Patients with the following COSTART terms were counted in this category: dystonia, generalized spasm, neck rigidity, oculogyric crisis, opisthotonos, torticollis.    
  b Patients with the following COSTART terms were counted in this category: akinesia, cogwheel rigidity, extrapyramidal syndrome, hypertonia, hypokinesia, masked facies, tremor.    
  c Patients with the following COSTART terms were counted in this category: akathisia, hyperkinesia.    
  d Patients with the following COSTART terms were counted in this category: buccoglossal syndrome, choreoathetosis, dyskinesia, tardive dyskinesia.    
  e Patients with the following COSTART terms were counted in this category: movement disorder, myoclonus, twitching.    
  
                            Percentage of Patients Reporting Event     
   Placebo(N=68)            Olanzapine5 +/- 2.5 mg/day(N=65)      Olanzapine10 +/- 2.5 mg/day(N=64)      Olanzapine15 +/- 2.5 mg/day(N=69)     
 Dystonic events  a       1                    3                    2                    3                     
 Parkinsonism events  b    10                   8                    14                   20                    
 Akathisia events  c      1                    5                    11                   10                    
 Dyskinetic events  d     4                    0                    2                    1                     
 Residual events  e       1                    2                    5                    1                     
 Any extrapyramidal event  16                   15                   25                   32                    
           The following table enumerates the percentage of adolescent patients with treatment-emergent extrapyramidal symptoms as assessed by spontaneously reported adverse reactions during acute therapy (dose range: 2.5 to 20 mg/day).
 

 Table 17: Treatment-Emergent Extrapyramidal Symptoms Assessed by Adverse Reactions Incidence in Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials of Oral Olanzapine in Schizophrenia and Bipolar I Disorder - Adolescents 
  a Categories are based on Standard MedDRA Queries (SMQ) for extrapyramidal symptoms as defined in MedDRA version 12.0.    
  
                                      Percentage of Patients Reporting Event     
                                      Placebo                            Olanzapine                        
   Categories    a                    (N=89)                             (N=179)                           
 Dystonic events                    0                                  1                                   
 Parkinsonism events                2                                  1                                   
 Akathisia events                   4                                  6                                   
 Dyskinetic events                  0                                  1                                   
 Nonspecific events                 0                                  4                                   
 Any extrapyramidal event           6                                  10                                  
         The following table enumerates the percentage of patients with treatment-emergent extrapyramidal symptoms as assessed by categorical analyses of formal rating scales during controlled clinical trials comparing fixed doses of intramuscular olanzapine for injection with placebo in agitation. Patients in each dose group could receive up to 3 injections during the trials  [see Clinical Studies (  14.3  )]  . Patient assessments were conducted during the 24 hours following the initial dose of intramuscular olanzapine for injection.
 

 Table 18: Treatment-Emergent Extrapyramidal Symptoms Assessed by Rating Scales Incidence in a Fixed Dose, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trial of Intramuscular Olanzapine for Injection in Agitated Patients with Schizophrenia 
  a Percentage of patients with a Simpson-Angus Scale total score &gt;3.    
  b Percentage of patients with a Barnes Akathisia Scale global score &gt;=2.    
  
                     Percentage of Patients Reporting Event     
   Placebo           OlanzapineIM2.5 mg      OlanzapineIM5 mg      OlanzapineIM7.5 mg      OlanzapineIM10 mg     
 Parkinsonism  a    0                 0                 0                 0                 3                  
 Akathisia  b      0                 0                 5                 0                 0                  
            The following table enumerates the percentage of patients with treatment-emergent extrapyramidal symptoms as assessed by spontaneously reported adverse reactions in the same controlled clinical trial comparing fixed doses of intramuscular olanzapine for injection with placebo in agitated patients with schizophrenia.
 

 Table 19: Treatment-Emergent Extrapyramidal Symptoms Assessed by Adverse Reactions Incidence in a Fixed Dose, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trial of Intramuscular Olanzapine for Injection in Agitated Patients with Schizophrenia 
  a Patients with the following COSTART terms were counted in this category: dystonia, generalized spasm, neck rigidity, oculogyric crisis, opisthotonos, torticollis.    
  b Patients with the following COSTART terms were counted in this category: akinesia, cogwheel rigidity, extrapyramidal syndrome, hypertonia, hypokinesia, masked facies, tremor.    
  c Patients with the following COSTART terms were counted in this category: akathisia, hyperkinesia.    
  d Patients with the following COSTART terms were counted in this category: buccoglossal syndrome, choreoathetosis, dyskinesia, tardive dyskinesia.    
  e Patients with the following COSTART terms were counted in this category: movement disorder, myoclonus, twitching.    
  
                           Percentage of Patients Reporting Event     
   Placebo    (N=45)       OlanzapineIM2.5 mg(N=48)      OlanzapineIM5 mg(N=45)      OlanzapineIM7.5 mg(N=46)      OlanzapineIM10 mg(N=46)     
 Dystonic events  a      0                0                0                0                0                 
 Parkinsonism events  b    0                4                2                0                0                 
 Akathisia events  c     0                2                0                0                0                 
 Dyskinetic events  d    0                0                0                0                0                 
 Residual events  e      0                0                0                0                0                 
 Any extrapyramidal events  0                4                2                0                0                 
                Dystonia, Class Effect:  Symptoms of dystonia, prolonged abnormal contractions of muscle groups, may occur in susceptible individuals during the first few days of treatment. Dystonic symptoms include: spasm of the neck muscles, sometimes progressing to tightness of the throat, swallowing difficulty, difficulty breathing, and/or protrusion of the tongue. While these symptoms can occur at low doses, the frequency and severity are greater with high potency and at higher doses of first generation antipsychotic drugs. In general, an elevated risk of acute dystonia may be observed in males and younger age groups receiving antipsychotics; however, events of dystonia have been reported infrequently (&lt;1%) with olanzapine use.
 

     Other Adverse Reactions:  The following table addresses dose relatedness for other adverse reactions using data from a schizophrenia trial involving fixed dosage ranges of oral olanzapine. It enumerates the percentage of patients with treatment-emergent adverse reactions for the 3 fixed-dose range groups and placebo. The data were analyzed using the Cochran-Armitage test, excluding the placebo group, and the table includes only those adverse reactions for which there was a trend.



 Table 20: Percentage of Patients from a Schizophrenia Trial with Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions for the 3 Dose Range Groups and Placebo 
   Adverse Reaction         Percentage of Patients Reporting Event     
   Placebo    (N=68)        Olanzapine5 +/- 2.5 mg/day(N=65)      Olanzapine10 +/- 2.5 mg/day(N=64)      Olanzapine15 +/- 2.5 mg/day(N=69)     
 Asthenia                 15                   8                    9                    20                    
 Dry mouth                4                    3                    5                    13                    
 Nausea                   9                    0                    2                    9                     
 Somnolence               16                   20                   30                   39                    
 Tremor                   3                    0                    5                    7                     
               Differences among Fixed-Dose Groups Observed in Other Olanzapine Clinical Trials  
 

 In a single 8-week randomized, double-blind, fixed-dose study comparing 10 (N=199), 20 (N=200) and 40 (N=200) mg/day of oral olanzapine in patients with schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder, differences among 3 dose groups were observed for the following safety outcomes: weight gain, prolactin elevation, fatigue and dizziness. Mean baseline to endpoint increase in weight (10 mg/day: 1.9 kg; 20 mg/day: 2.3 kg; 40 mg/day: 3 kg) was observed with significant differences between 10 vs 40 mg/day. Incidence of treatment-emergent prolactin elevation &gt;24.2 ng/mL (female) or &gt;18.77 ng/mL (male) at any time during the trial (10 mg/day: 31.2%; 20 mg/day: 42.7%; 40 mg/day: 61.1%) with significant differences between 10 vs 40 mg/day and 20 vs 40 mg/day; fatigue (10 mg/day: 1.5%; 20 mg/day: 2.1%; 40 mg/day: 6.6%) with significant differences between 10 vs 40 and 20 vs 40 mg/day; and dizziness (10 mg/day: 2.6%; 20 mg/day: 1.6%; 40 mg/day: 6.6%) with significant differences between 20 vs 40 mg, was observed.



     Other Adverse Reactions Observed During the Clinical Trial Evaluation of Oral Olanzapine  



 Following is a list of treatment-emergent adverse reactions reported by patients treated with oral olanzapine (at multiple doses &gt;=1 mg/day) in clinical trials. This listing is not intended to include reactions (1) already listed in previous tables or elsewhere in labeling, (2) for which a drug cause was remote, (3) which were so general as to be uninformative, (4) which were not considered to have significant clinical implications, or (5) which occurred at a rate equal to or less than placebo. Reactions are classified by body system using the following definitions: frequent adverse reactions are those occurring in at least 1/100 patients; infrequent adverse reactions are those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1000 patients; rare reactions are those occurring in fewer than 1/1000 patients.



 *      Body as a Whole - Infrequent: chills, face edema, photosensitivity reaction, suicide attempt  1  ; Rare:  chills and fever, hangover effect, sudden death  1  . 
 *      Cardiovascular System - Infrequent: cerebrovascular accident, vasodilatation. 
 *      Digestive System - Infrequent: nausea and vomiting, tongue edema; Rare:  ileus, intestinal obstruction, liver fatty deposit. 
 *      Hemic and Lymphatic System - Infrequent: leukopenia, thrombocytopenia. 
 *      Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders - Infrequent: alkaline phosphatase increased, bilirubinemia, hypoproteinemia. 
 *      Musculoskeletal System - Rare: osteoporosis. 
 *      Nervous System - Infrequent: ataxia, dysarthria, libido decreased, stupor; Rare:  coma. 
 *      Respiratory System - Infrequent: epistaxis; Rare:  lung edema. 
 *      Skin and Appendages - Infrequent: alopecia. 
 *      Special Senses - Infrequent: abnormality of accommodation, dry eyes; Rare:  mydriasis. 
 *      Urogenital System - Infrequent: amenorrhea  2  , breast pain, decreased menstruation, impotence  2  , increased menstruation  2  , menorrhagia  2  , metrorrhagia  2  , polyuria  2  , urinary frequency, urinary retention, urinary urgency, urination impaired. 
      1  These terms represent serious adverse events but do not meet the definition for adverse drug reactions. They are included here because of their seriousness.
 

   2  Adjusted for gender.



     Other Adverse Reactions Observed During the Clinical Trial Evaluation of Intramuscular Olanzapine for Injection  



 Following is a list of treatment-emergent adverse reactions reported by patients treated with intramuscular olanzapine for injection (at 1 or more doses &gt;=2.5 mg/injection) in clinical trials. This listing is not intended to include reactions (1) already listed in previous tables or elsewhere in labeling, (2) for which a drug cause was remote, (3) which were so general as to be uninformative, (4) which were not considered to have significant clinical implications, or (5) for which occurred at a rate equal to or less than placebo. Reactions are classified by body system using the following definitions: frequent adverse reactions are those occurring in at least 1/100 patients; infrequent adverse reactions are those occurring in 1/100 to 1/1000 patients.



 *      Body as a Whole - Frequent: injection site pain. 
 *      Cardiovascular System - Infrequent: syncope. 
 *      Digestive System - Infrequent: nausea. 
 *      Metabolic and Nutritional Disorders - Infrequent: creatine phosphokinase increased. 
        Clinical Trials in Adolescent Patients (age 13 to 17 years)  
 

     Commonly Observed Adverse Reactions in Oral Olanzapine Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Trials  



 Adverse reactions in adolescent patients treated with oral olanzapine (doses &gt;=2.5 mg) reported with an incidence of 5% or more and reported at least twice as frequently as placebo-treated patients are listed in  Table 21  .



 Table 21: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions of &gt;=5% Incidence among Adolescents (13-17 Years Old) with Schizophrenia or Bipolar I Disorder (Manic or Mixed Episodes) 
  a Patients with the following MedDRA terms were counted in this category: hypersomnia, lethargy, sedation, somnolence.    
  b Patients with the following MedDRA terms were counted in this category: abdominal pain, abdominal pain lower, abdominal pain upper.    
  
   Adverse Reactions      Percentage of Patients Reporting Event     
   6 Week Trial% Schizophrenia Patients      3 Week Trial% Bipolar Patients     
   Olanzapine(N=72)      Placebo(N=35)         Olanzapine(N=107)      Placebo(N=54)        
 Sedation  a           39                    9                     48                    9                      
 Weight increased      31                    9                     29                    4                      
 Headache              17                    6                     17                    17                     
 Increased appetite    17                    9                     29                    4                      
 Dizziness             8                     3                     7                     2                      
 Abdominal pain  b     6                     3                     6                     7                      
 Pain in extremity     6                     3                     5                     0                      
 Fatigue               3                     3                     14                    6                      
 Dry mouth             4                     0                     7                     0                      
               Adverse Reactions Occurring at an Incidence of 2% or More among Oral Olanzapine-Treated Patients in Short-Term (3-6 weeks), Placebo-Controlled Trials  
 

 Adverse reactions in adolescent patients treated with oral olanzapine (doses &gt;=2.5 mg) reported with an incidence of 2% or more and greater than placebo are listed in  Table 22  .



 Table 22: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions of &gt;=2% Incidence among Adolescents (13-17 Years Old) (Combined Incidence from Short-Term, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trials of Schizophrenia or Bipolar I Disorder [Manic or Mixed Episodes]) 
  a Patients with the following MedDRA terms were counted in this category: hypersomnia, lethargy, sedation, somnolence.    
  b The terms alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), and hepatic enzyme were combined under liver enzymes.    
  c Patients with the following MedDRA terms were counted in this category: lower respiratory tract infection, respiratory tract infection, respiratory tract infection viral, upper respiratory tract infection, viral upper respiratory tract infection.    
  
   Adverse Reaction                   Percentage of Patients Reporting Event     
   Olanzapine(N=179)                  Placebo(N=89)                     
 Sedation  a                        44                                 9                                   
 Weight increased                   30                                 6                                   
 Increased appetite                 24                                 6                                   
 Headache                           17                                 12                                  
 Fatigue                            9                                  4                                   
 Dizziness                          7                                  2                                   
 Dry mouth                          6                                  0                                   
 Pain in extremity                  5                                  1                                   
 Constipation                       4                                  0                                   
 Nasopharyngitis                    4                                  2                                   
 Diarrhea                           3                                  0                                   
 Restlessness                       3                                  2                                   
 Liver enzymes increased  b         8                                  1                                   
 Dyspepsia                          3                                  1                                   
 Epistaxis                          3                                  0                                   
 Respiratory tract infection  c     3                                  2                                   
 Sinusitis                          3                                  0                                   
 Arthralgia                         2                                  0                                   
 Musculoskeletal stiffness          2                                  0                                   
           6.2 Vital Signs and Laboratory Studies
     Vital Sign Changes  - Oral olanzapine was associated with orthostatic hypotension and tachycardia in clinical trials. Intramuscular olanzapine for injection was associated with bradycardia, hypotension, and tachycardia in clinical trials  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5  )]  .



     Laboratory Changes  



     Olanzapine Monotherapy in Adults:  An assessment of the premarketing experience for olanzapine revealed an association with asymptomatic increases in ALT, AST, and GGT. Within the original premarketing database of about 2400 adult patients with baseline ALT &lt;=90 IU/L, the incidence of ALT elevations to &gt;200 IU/L was 2% (50/2381). None of these patients experienced jaundice or other symptoms attributable to liver impairment and most had transient changes that tended to normalize while olanzapine treatment was continued.



 In placebo-controlled olanzapine monotherapy studies in adults, clinically significant ALT elevations (change from &lt;3 times the upper limit of normal [ULN] at baseline to &gt;=3 times ULN) were observed in 5% (77/1426) of patients exposed to olanzapine compared to 1% (10/1187) of patients exposed to placebo. ALT elevations &gt;=5 times ULN were observed in 2% (29/1438) of olanzapine-treated patients, compared to 0.3% (4/1196) of placebo-treated patients. ALT values returned to normal, or were decreasing, at last follow-up in the majority of patients who either continued treatment with olanzapine or discontinued olanzapine. No patient with elevated ALT values experienced jaundice, liver failure, or met the criteria for Hy's Rule.



 Rare postmarketing reports of hepatitis have been received. Very rare cases of cholestatic or mixed liver injury have also been reported in the postmarketing period.



 Caution should be exercised in patients with signs and symptoms of hepatic impairment, in patients with pre-existing conditions associated with limited hepatic functional reserve, and in patients who are being treated with potentially hepatotoxic drugs.



 Olanzapine administration was also associated with increases in serum prolactin  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.15  )]  , with an asymptomatic elevation of the eosinophil count in 0.3% of patients, and with an increase in CPK.



     Olanzapine Monotherapy in Adolescents:  In placebo-controlled clinical trials of adolescent patients with schizophrenia or bipolar I disorder (manic or mixed episodes), greater frequencies for the following treatment-emergent findings, at anytime, were observed in laboratory analytes compared to placebo: elevated ALT (&gt;=3X ULN in patients with ALT at baseline &lt;3X ULN), (12% vs 2%); elevated AST (28% vs 4%); low total bilirubin (22% vs 7%); elevated GGT (10% vs 1%); and elevated prolactin (47% vs 7%).



 In placebo-controlled olanzapine monotherapy studies in adolescents, clinically significant ALT elevations (change from &lt;3 times ULN at baseline to &gt;=3 times ULN) were observed in 12% (22/192) of patients exposed to olanzapine compared to 2% (2/109) of patients exposed to placebo. ALT elevations &gt;=5 times ULN were observed in 4% (8/192) of olanzapine-treated patients, compared to 1% (1/109) of placebo-treated patients. ALT values returned to normal, or were decreasing, at last follow-up in the majority of patients who either continued treatment with olanzapine or discontinued olanzapine. No adolescent patient with elevated ALT values experienced jaundice, liver failure, or met the criteria for Hy's Rule.



     ECG Changes  - In pooled studies of adults as well as pooled studies of adolescents, there were no significant differences between olanzapine and placebo in the proportions of patients experiencing potentially important changes in ECG parameters, including QT, QTc (Fridericia corrected), and PR intervals. Olanzapine use was associated with a mean increase in heart rate compared to placebo (adults: +2.4 beats per minute vs no change with placebo; adolescents: +6.3 beats per minute vs -5.1 beats per minute with placebo). This increase in heart rate may be related to olanzapine's potential for inducing orthostatic changes  [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  .



   6.3 Postmarketing Experience

  The following adverse reactions have been identified during post-approval use of ZYPREXA. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is difficult to reliably estimate their frequency or evaluate a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Adverse reactions reported since market introduction that were temporally (but not necessarily causally) related to ZYPREXA therapy include the following: allergic reaction (e.g., anaphylactoid reaction, angioedema, pruritus or urticaria), diabetic coma, diabetic ketoacidosis, discontinuation reaction (diaphoresis, nausea or vomiting), jaundice, neutropenia, pancreatitis, priapism, rash, rhabdomyolysis, and venous thromboembolic events (including pulmonary embolism and deep venous thrombosis). Random cholesterol levels of &gt;=240 mg/dL and random triglyceride levels of &gt;=1000 mg/dL have been reported.
</Section>
    <Section name="boxed warnings" id="S2">

    BOXED WARNING: WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS 

  WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS 

    Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. Analyses of seventeen placebo-controlled trials (modal duration of 10 weeks), largely in patients taking atypical antipsychotic drugs, revealed a risk of death in drug-treated patients of between 1.6 to 1.7 times the risk of death in placebo-treated patients. Over the course of a typical 10-week controlled trial, the rate of death in drug-treated patients was about 4.5%, compared to a rate of about 2.6% in the placebo group. Although the causes of death were varied, most of the deaths appeared to be either cardiovascular (e.g., heart failure, sudden death) or infectious (e.g., pneumonia) in nature. Observational studies suggest that, similar to atypical antipsychotic drugs, treatment with conventional antipsychotic drugs may increase mortality. The extent to which the findings of increased mortality in observational studies may be attributed to the antipsychotic drug as opposed to some characteristic(s) of the patients is not clear. ZYPREXA (olanzapine) is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis       [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ,   5.14  ) and Patient Counseling Information (  17.2  )]    . 



   When using ZYPREXA and fluoxetine in combination, also refer to the Boxed Warning section of the package insert for Symbyax.  



   EXCERPT:     WARNING: INCREASED MORTALITY IN ELDERLY PATIENTS WITH DEMENTIA-RELATED PSYCHOSIS  



     See full prescribing information for complete boxed warning.    



 *  Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. ZYPREXA is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis. (5.1, 5.14, 17.2) When using ZYPREXA and fluoxetine in combination, also refer to the Boxed Warning section of the package insert for Symbyax. 
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S3">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



  When using ZYPREXA and fluoxetine in combination, also refer to the Warnings and Precautions section of the package insert for Symbyax.



    EXCERPT:    *   Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis: Increased risk of death and increased incidence of cerebrovascular adverse events (e.g., stroke, transient ischemic attack). (  5.1  ) 
 *   Suicide: The possibility of a suicide attempt is inherent in schizophrenia and in bipolar I disorder, and close supervision of high-risk patients should accompany drug therapy; when using in combination with fluoxetine, also refer to the Boxed Warning and Warnings and Precautions sections of the package insert for Symbyax. (  5.2  ) 
 *   Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome: Manage with immediate discontinuation and close monitoring. (  5.3  ) 
 *   Hyperglycemia: In some cases extreme and associated with ketoacidosis or hyperosmolar coma or death, has been reported in patients taking olanzapine. Patients taking olanzapine should be monitored for symptoms of hyperglycemia and undergo fasting blood glucose testing at the beginning of, and periodically during, treatment. (  5.4  ) 
 *   Hyperlipidemia: Undesirable alterations in lipids have been observed. Appropriate clinical monitoring is recommended, including fasting blood lipid testing at the beginning of, and periodically during, treatment. (  5.5  ) 
 *   Weight Gain: Potential consequences of weight gain should be considered. Patients should receive regular monitoring of weight. (  5.6  ) 
 *   Tardive Dyskinesia: Discontinue if clinically appropriate. (  5.7  ) 
 *   Orthostatic Hypotension: Orthostatic hypotension associated with dizziness, tachycardia, bradycardia and, in some patients, syncope, may occur especially during initial dose titration. Use caution in patients with cardiovascular disease, cerebrovascular disease, and those conditions that could affect hemodynamic responses. (  5.8  ) 
 *   Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis: Has been reported with antipsychotics, including ZYPREXA. Patients with a history of a clinically significant low white blood cell count (WBC) or drug induced leukopenia/neutropenia should have their complete blood count (CBC) monitored frequently during the first few months of therapy and discontinuation of ZYPREXA should be considered at the first sign of a clinically significant decline in WBC in the absence of other causative factors. (  5.9  ) 
 *   Seizures: Use cautiously in patients with a history of seizures or with conditions that potentially lower the seizure threshold. (  5.11  ) 
 *   Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment: Has potential to impair judgment, thinking, and motor skills. Use caution when operating machinery. (  5.12  ) 
 *   Hyperprolactinemia: May elevate prolactin levels. (  5.15  ) 
 *   Use in Combination with Fluoxetine, Lithium or Valproate: Also refer to the package inserts for Symbyax, lithium, or valproate. (  5.16  ) 
 *   Laboratory Tests: Monitor fasting blood glucose and lipid profiles at the beginning of, and periodically during, treatment. (  5.17  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Elderly Patients with Dementia-Related Psychosis



    Increased Mortality     - Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with antipsychotic drugs are at an increased risk of death. ZYPREXA is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis    [see  Boxed Warning  , Warnings and Precautions (  5.14  ), and Patient Counseling Information (  17.2  )]    .



 In placebo-controlled clinical trials of elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis, the incidence of death in olanzapine-treated patients was significantly greater than placebo-treated patients (3.5% vs 1.5%, respectively).



    Cerebrovascular Adverse Events (CVAE), Including Stroke  - Cerebrovascular adverse events (e.g., stroke, transient ischemic attack), including fatalities, were reported in patients in trials of olanzapine in elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis. In placebo-controlled trials, there was a significantly higher incidence of cerebrovascular adverse events in patients treated with olanzapine compared to patients treated with placebo. Olanzapine is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis [see  Boxed Warning  and Patient Counseling Information (  17.2  )]  .



    5.2 Suicide



  The possibility of a suicide attempt is inherent in schizophrenia and in bipolar I disorder, and close supervision of high-risk patients should accompany drug therapy. Prescriptions for olanzapine should be written for the smallest quantity of tablets consistent with good patient management, in order to reduce the risk of overdose.



    5.3 Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS)



  A potentially fatal symptom complex sometimes referred to as Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome (NMS) has been reported in association with administration of antipsychotic drugs, including olanzapine. Clinical manifestations of NMS are hyperpyrexia, muscle rigidity, altered mental status and evidence of autonomic instability (irregular pulse or blood pressure, tachycardia, diaphoresis and cardiac dysrhythmia). Additional signs may include elevated creatinine phosphokinase, myoglobinuria (rhabdomyolysis), and acute renal failure.



 The diagnostic evaluation of patients with this syndrome is complicated. In arriving at a diagnosis, it is important to exclude cases where the clinical presentation includes both serious medical illness (e.g., pneumonia, systemic infection, etc.) and untreated or inadequately treated extrapyramidal signs and symptoms (EPS). Other important considerations in the differential diagnosis include central anticholinergic toxicity, heat stroke, drug fever, and primary central nervous system pathology.



 The management of NMS should include: 1) immediate discontinuation of antipsychotic drugs and other drugs not essential to concurrent therapy; 2) intensive symptomatic treatment and medical monitoring; and 3) treatment of any concomitant serious medical problems for which specific treatments are available. There is no general agreement about specific pharmacological treatment regimens for NMS.



 If a patient requires antipsychotic drug treatment after recovery from NMS, the potential reintroduction of drug therapy should be carefully considered. The patient should be carefully monitored, since recurrences of NMS have been reported [see Patient Counseling Information (  17.3  )]  .



    5.4 Hyperglycemia



  Physicians should consider the risks and benefits when prescribing olanzapine to patients with an established diagnosis of diabetes mellitus, or having borderline increased blood glucose level (fasting 100-126 mg/dL, nonfasting 140-200 mg/dL). Patients taking olanzapine should be monitored regularly for worsening of glucose control. Patients starting treatment with olanzapine should undergo fasting blood glucose testing at the beginning of treatment and periodically during treatment. Any patient treated with atypical antipsychotics should be monitored for symptoms of hyperglycemia including polydipsia, polyuria, polyphagia, and weakness. Patients who develop symptoms of hyperglycemia during treatment with atypical antipsychotics should undergo fasting blood glucose testing. In some cases, hyperglycemia has resolved when the atypical antipsychotic was discontinued; however, some patients required continuation of anti-diabetic treatment despite discontinuation of the suspect drug [see Patient Counseling Information (  17.4  )]  .



 Hyperglycemia, in some cases extreme and associated with ketoacidosis or hyperosmolar coma or death, has been reported in patients treated with atypical antipsychotics including olanzapine. Assessment of the relationship between atypical antipsychotic use and glucose abnormalities is complicated by the possibility of an increased background risk of diabetes mellitus in patients with schizophrenia and the increasing incidence of diabetes mellitus in the general population. Epidemiological studies suggest an increased risk of treatment-emergent hyperglycemia-related adverse reactions in patients treated with the atypical antipsychotics. While relative risk estimates are inconsistent, the association between atypical antipsychotics and increases in glucose levels appears to fall on a continuum and olanzapine appears to have a greater association than some other atypical antipsychotics.



 Mean increases in blood glucose have been observed in patients treated (median exposure of 9.2 months) with olanzapine in phase 1 of the Clinical Antipsychotic Trials of Intervention Effectiveness (CATIE). The mean increase of serum glucose (fasting and nonfasting samples) from baseline to the average of the 2 highest serum concentrations was 15.0 mg/dL.



 In a study of healthy volunteers, subjects who received olanzapine (N=22) for 3 weeks had a mean increase compared to baseline in fasting blood glucose of 2.3 mg/dL. Placebo-treated subjects (N=19) had a mean increase in fasting blood glucose compared to baseline of 0.34 mg/dL.



    Olanzapine Monotherapy in Adults  - In an analysis of 5 placebo-controlled adult olanzapine monotherapy studies with a median treatment duration of approximately 3 weeks, olanzapine was associated with a greater mean change in fasting glucose levels compared to placebo (2.76 mg/dL versus 0.17 mg/dL). The difference in mean changes between olanzapine and placebo was greater in patients with evidence of glucose dysregulation at baseline (patients diagnosed with diabetes mellitus or related adverse reactions, patients treated with anti-diabetic agents, patients with a baseline random glucose level &gt;=200 mg/dL, and/or a baseline fasting glucose level &gt;=126 mg/dL). Olanzapine-treated patients had a greater mean HbA1c increase from baseline of 0.04% (median exposure 21 days), compared to a mean HbA1c decrease of 0.06% in placebo-treated subjects (median exposure 17 days).



 In an analysis of 8 placebo-controlled studies (median treatment exposure 4-5 weeks), 6.1% of olanzapine-treated subjects (N=855) had treatment-emergent glycosuria compared to 2.8% of placebo-treated subjects (N=599).  Table 2  shows short-term and long-term changes in fasting glucose levels from adult olanzapine monotherapy studies.



 Table 2: Changes in Fasting Glucose Levels from Adult Olanzapine Monotherapy Studies 
  a Not Applicable.    
  
                                                                         Up to 12 weeks exposure     At least 48 weeks exposure     
  Laboratory Analyte     Category Change (at least once)from Baseline     Treatment Arm     N         Patients     N         Patients     
 FastingGlucose  Normal to High(&lt;100 mg/dL to &gt;=126 mg/dL)  Olanzapine    543       2.2%      345       12.8%      
 Placebo         293                                      3.4%          NA  a     NA  a      
 Borderline to High(&gt;=100 mg/dL and &lt;126 mg/dL to &gt;=126 mg/dL)  Olanzapine                               178           17.4%     127       26.0%      
 Placebo         96                                       11.5%         NA  a     NA  a      
             The mean change in fasting glucose for patients exposed at least 48 weeks was 4.2 mg/dL (N=487). In analyses of patients who completed 9-12 months of olanzapine therapy, mean change in fasting and nonfasting glucose levels continued to increase over time.
 

    Olanzapine Monotherapy in Adolescents  - The safety and efficacy of olanzapine have not been established in patients under the age of 13 years. In an analysis of 3 placebo-controlled olanzapine monotherapy studies of adolescent patients, including those with schizophrenia (6 weeks) or bipolar I disorder (manic or mixed episodes) (3 weeks), olanzapine was associated with a greater mean change from baseline in fasting glucose levels compared to placebo (2.68 mg/dL versus -2.59 mg/dL). The mean change in fasting glucose for adolescents exposed at least 24 weeks was 3.1 mg/dL (N=121).  Table 3  shows short-term and long-term changes in fasting blood glucose from adolescent olanzapine monotherapy studies.



 Table 3: Changes in Fasting Glucose Levels from Adolescent Olanzapine Monotherapy Studies 
  a Not Applicable.    
  
                                                                         Up to 12 weeks exposure     At least 24 weeks exposure     
  Laboratory Analyte     Category Change (at least once)from Baseline     Treatment Arm     N         Patients     N         Patients     
 FastingGlucose  Normal to High(&lt;100 mg/dL to &gt;=126 mg/dL)  Olanzapine    124       0%        108       0.9%       
 Placebo         53                                       1.9%          NA  a     NA  a      
 Borderline to High(&gt;=100 mg/dL and &lt;126 mg/dL to &gt;=126 mg/dL)  Olanzapine                               14            14.3%     13        23.1%      
 Placebo         13                                       0%            NA  a     NA  a      
                5.5 Hyperlipidemia
 

  Undesirable alterations in lipids have been observed with olanzapine use. Clinical monitoring, including baseline and periodic follow-up lipid evaluations in patients using olanzapine, is recommended [see Patient Counseling Information (  17.5  )]  .



 Clinically significant, and sometimes very high (&gt;500 mg/dL), elevations in triglyceride levels have been observed with olanzapine use. Modest mean increases in total cholesterol have also been seen with olanzapine use.



    Olanzapine Monotherapy in Adults  - In an analysis of 5 placebo-controlled olanzapine monotherapy studies with treatment duration up to 12 weeks, olanzapine-treated patients had increases from baseline in mean fasting total cholesterol, LDL cholesterol, and triglycerides of 5.3 mg/dL, 3.0 mg/dL, and 20.8 mg/dL respectively compared to decreases from baseline in mean fasting total cholesterol, LDL cholesterol, and triglycerides of 6.1 mg/dL, 4.3 mg/dL, and 10.7 mg/dL for placebo-treated patients. For fasting HDL cholesterol, no clinically meaningful differences were observed between olanzapine-treated patients and placebo-treated patients. Mean increases in fasting lipid values (total cholesterol, LDL cholesterol, and triglycerides) were greater in patients without evidence of lipid dysregulation at baseline, where lipid dysregulation was defined as patients diagnosed with dyslipidemia or related adverse reactions, patients treated with lipid lowering agents, or patients with high baseline lipid levels.



 In long-term studies (at least 48 weeks), patients had increases from baseline in mean fasting total cholesterol, LDL cholesterol, and triglycerides of 5.6 mg/dL, 2.5 mg/dL, and 18.7 mg/dL, respectively, and a mean decrease in fasting HDL cholesterol of 0.16 mg/dL. In an analysis of patients who completed 12 months of therapy, the mean nonfasting total cholesterol did not increase further after approximately 4-6 months.



 The proportion of patients who had changes (at least once) in total cholesterol, LDL cholesterol or triglycerides from normal or borderline to high, or changes in HDL cholesterol from normal or borderline to low, was greater in long-term studies (at least 48 weeks) as compared with short-term studies.  Table 4  shows categorical changes in fasting lipids values.



 Table 4: Changes in Fasting Lipids Values from Adult Olanzapine Monotherapy Studies 
  a Not Applicable.    
  
                                                                         Up to 12 weeks exposure     At least 48 weeks exposure     
  Laboratory Analyte     Category Change (at least once)from Baseline     Treatment Arm     N         Patients     N         Patients     
 FastingTriglycerides  Increase by &gt;=50 mg/dL                   Olanzapine    745       39.6%     487       61.4%      
 Placebo         402                                      26.1%         NA  a     NA  a      
 Normal to High(&lt;150 mg/dL to &gt;=200 mg/dL)  Olanzapine                               457           9.2%      293       32.4%      
 Placebo         251                                      4.4%          NA  a     NA  a      
 Borderline to High(&gt;=150 mg/dL and &lt;200 mg/dL to &gt;=200 mg/dL)  Olanzapine                               135           39.3%     75        70.7%      
 Placebo         65                                       20.0%         NA  a     NA  a      
                                                                                                                 
 Fasting TotalCholesterol  Increase by &gt;=40 mg/dL                   Olanzapine    745       21.6%     489       32.9%      
 Placebo         402                                      9.5%          NA  a     NA  a      
 Normal to High(&lt;200 mg/dL to &gt;=240 mg/dL)  Olanzapine                               392           2.8%      283       14.8%      
 Placebo         207                                      2.4%          NA  a     NA  a      
 Borderline to High(&gt;=200 mg/dL and &lt;240 mg/dL to &gt;=240 mg/dL)  Olanzapine                               222           23.0%     125       55.2%      
 Placebo         112                                      12.5%         NA  a     NA  a      
                                                                                                                 
 Fasting LDLCholesterol  Increase by &gt;=30 mg/dL                   Olanzapine    536       23.7%     483       39.8%      
 Placebo         304                                      14.1%         NA  a     NA  a      
 Normal to High(&lt;100 mg/dL to &gt;=160 mg/dL)  Olanzapine                               154           0%        123       7.3%       
 Placebo         82                                       1.2%          NA  a     NA  a      
 Borderline to High(&gt;=100 mg/dL and &lt;160 mg/dL to &gt;=160 mg/dL)  Olanzapine                               302           10.6%     284       31.0%      
 Placebo         173                                      8.1%          NA  a     NA  a      
             In phase 1 of the Clinical Antipsychotic Trials of Intervention Effectiveness (CATIE), over a median exposure of 9.2 months, the mean increase in triglycerides in patients taking olanzapine was 40.5 mg/dL. In phase 1 of CATIE, the mean increase in total cholesterol was 9.4 mg/dL.
 

    Olanzapine Monotherapy in Adolescents  - The safety and efficacy of olanzapine have not been established in patients under the age of 13 years. In an analysis of 3 placebo-controlled olanzapine monotherapy studies of adolescents, including those with schizophrenia (6 weeks) or bipolar I disorder (manic or mixed episodes) (3 weeks), olanzapine-treated adolescents had increases from baseline in mean fasting total cholesterol, LDL cholesterol, and triglycerides of 12.9 mg/dL, 6.5 mg/dL, and 28.4 mg/dL, respectively, compared to increases from baseline in mean fasting total cholesterol and LDL cholesterol of 1.3 mg/dL and 1.0 mg/dL, and a decrease in triglycerides of 1.1 mg/dL for placebo-treated adolescents. For fasting HDL cholesterol, no clinically meaningful differences were observed between olanzapine-treated adolescents and placebo-treated adolescents.



 In long-term studies (at least 24 weeks), adolescents had increases from baseline in mean fasting total cholesterol, LDL cholesterol, and triglycerides of 5.5 mg/dL, 5.4 mg/dL, and 20.5 mg/dL, respectively, and a mean decrease in fasting HDL cholesterol of 4.5 mg/dL.  Table 5  shows categorical changes in fasting lipids values in adolescents.



 Table 5: Changes in Fasting Lipids Values from Adolescent Olanzapine Monotherapy Studies 
  a Not Applicable.    
  
                                                                         Up to 6 weeks exposure     At least 24 weeks exposure     
  Laboratory Analyte     Category Change (at least once)from Baseline     Treatment Arm     N         Patients     N         Patients     
 FastingTriglycerides  Increase by &gt;=50 mg/dL                   Olanzapine    138       37.0%     122       45.9%      
 Placebo         66                                       15.2%         NA  a     NA  a      
 Normal to High(&lt;90 mg/dL to &gt;130 mg/dL)  Olanzapine                               67            26.9%     66        36.4%      
 Placebo         28                                       10.7%         NA  a     NA  a      
 Borderline to High(&gt;=90 mg/dL and &lt;=130 mg/dL to &gt;130 mg/dL)  Olanzapine                               37            59.5%     31        64.5%      
 Placebo         17                                       35.3%         NA  a     NA  a      
                                                                                                                 
 Fasting TotalCholesterol  Increase by &gt;=40 mg/dL                   Olanzapine    138       14.5%     122       14.8%      
 Placebo         66                                       4.5%          NA  a     NA  a      
 Normal to High(&lt;170 mg/dL to &gt;=200 mg/dL)  Olanzapine                               87            6.9%      78        7.7%       
 Placebo         43                                       2.3%          NA  a     NA  a      
 Borderline to High(&gt;=170 mg/dL and &lt;200 mg/dL to &gt;=200 mg/dL)  Olanzapine                               36            38.9%     33        57.6%      
 Placebo         13                                       7.7%          NA  a     NA  a      
                                                                                                                 
 Fasting LDLCholesterol  Increase by &gt;=30 mg/dL                   Olanzapine    137       17.5%     121       22.3%      
 Placebo         63                                       11.1%         NA  a     NA  a      
 Normal to High(&lt;110 mg/dL to &gt;=130 mg/dL)  Olanzapine                               98            5.1%      92        10.9%      
 Placebo         44                                       4.5%          NA  a     NA  a      
 Borderline to High(&gt;=110 mg/dL and &lt;130 mg/dL to &gt;=130 mg/dL)  Olanzapine                               29            48.3%     21        47.6%      
 Placebo         9                                        0%            NA  a     NA  a      
                5.6 Weight Gain
 

  Potential consequences of weight gain should be considered prior to starting olanzapine. Patients receiving olanzapine should receive regular monitoring of weight [see Patient Counseling Information (  17.6  )]  .



    Olanzapine Monotherapy in Adults  - In an analysis of 13 placebo-controlled olanzapine monotherapy studies, olanzapine-treated patients gained an average of 2.6 kg (5.7 lb) compared to an average 0.3 kg (0.6 lb) weight loss in placebo-treated patients with a median exposure of 6 weeks; 22.2% of olanzapine-treated patients gained at least 7% of their baseline weight, compared to 3% of placebo-treated patients, with a median exposure to event of 8 weeks; 4.2% of olanzapine-treated patients gained at least 15% of their baseline weight, compared to 0.3% of placebo-treated patients, with a median exposure to event of 12 weeks. Clinically significant weight gain was observed across all baseline Body Mass Index (BMI) categories. Discontinuation due to weight gain occurred in 0.2% of olanzapine-treated patients and in 0% of placebo-treated patients.



 In long-term studies (at least 48 weeks), the mean weight gain was 5.6 kg (12.3 lb) (median exposure of 573 days, N=2021). The percentages of patients who gained at least 7%, 15%, or 25% of their baseline body weight with long-term exposure were 64%, 32%, and 12%, respectively. Discontinuation due to weight gain occurred in 0.4% of olanzapine-treated patients following at least 48 weeks of exposure.



   Table 6  includes data on adult weight gain with olanzapine pooled from 86 clinical trials. The data in each column represent data for those patients who completed treatment periods of the durations specified.



 Table 6: Weight Gain with Olanzapine Use in Adults 
  Amount Gainedkg (lb)     6 Weeks(N=7465)(%)     6 Months(N=4162)(%)     12 Months(N=1345)(%)     24 Months(N=474)(%)     36 Months(N=147)(%)     
 &lt;=0                   26.2             24.3             20.8             23.2             17.0              
 0 to &lt;=5 (0-11 lb)    57.0             36.0             26.0             23.4             25.2              
 &gt;5 to &lt;=10 (11-22 lb)  14.9             24.6             24.2             24.1             18.4              
 &gt;10 to &lt;=15 (22-33 lb)  1.8              10.9             14.9             11.4             17.0              
 &gt;15 to &lt;=20 (33-44 lb)  0.1              3.1              8.6              9.3              11.6              
 &gt;20 to &lt;=25 (44-55 lb)  0                0.9              3.3              5.1              4.1               
 &gt;25 to &lt;=30 (55-66 lb)  0                0.2              1.4              2.3              4.8               
 &gt;30 (&gt;66 lb)          0                0.1              0.8              1.2              2                 
               Olanzapine Monotherapy in Adolescents  - The safety and efficacy of olanzapine have not been established in patients under the age of 13 years. Mean increase in weight in adolescents was greater than in adults. In 4 placebo-controlled trials, discontinuation due to weight gain occurred in 1% of olanzapine-treated patients, compared to 0% of placebo-treated patients.
 

 Table 7: Weight Gain with Olanzapine Use in Adolescents from 4 Placebo-Controlled Trials 
                                     Olanzapine-treated patients        Placebo-treated patients           
 Mean change in body weight from baseline (median exposure = 3 weeks)  4.6 kg (10.1 lb)                   0.3 kg (0.7 lb)                     
 Percentage of patients who gained at least 7% of baseline body weight  40.6%                              9.8%                                
 (median exposure to 7% = 4 weeks)  (median exposure to 7% = 8 weeks)   
 Percentage of patients who gained at least 15% of baseline body weight  7.1%                               2.7%                                
 (median exposure to 15% = 19 weeks)  (median exposure to 15% = 8 weeks)   
         In long-term studies (at least 24 weeks), the mean weight gain was 11.2 kg (24.6 lb); (median exposure of 201 days, N=179). The percentages of adolescents who gained at least 7%, 15%, or 25% of their baseline body weight with long-term exposure were 89%, 55%, and 29%, respectively. Among adolescent patients, mean weight gain by baseline BMI category was 11.5 kg (25.3 lb), 12.1 kg (26.6 lb), and 12.7 kg (27.9 lb), respectively, for normal (N=106), overweight (N=26) and obese (N=17). Discontinuation due to weight gain occurred in 2.2% of olanzapine-treated patients following at least 24 weeks of exposure.
 

   Table 8  shows data on adolescent weight gain with olanzapine pooled from 6 clinical trials. The data in each column represent data for those patients who completed treatment periods of the durations specified. Little clinical trial data is available on weight gain in adolescents with olanzapine beyond 6 months of treatment.



 Table 8: Weight Gain with Olanzapine Use in Adolescents 
  Amount Gainedkg (lb)               6 Weeks(N=243)(%)                  6 Months(N=191)(%)                 
 &lt;=0                                2.9                                2.1                                 
 0 to &lt;=5 (0-11 lb)                 47.3                               24.6                                
 &gt;5 to &lt;=10 (11-22 lb)              42.4                               26.7                                
 &gt;10 to &lt;=15 (22-33 lb)             5.8                                22.0                                
 &gt;15 to &lt;=20 (33-44 lb)             0.8                                12.6                                
 &gt;20 to &lt;=25 (44-55 lb)             0.8                                9.4                                 
 &gt;25 to &lt;=30 (55-66 lb)             0                                  2.1                                 
 &gt;30 to &lt;=35 (66-77 lb)             0                                  0                                   
 &gt;35 to &lt;=40 (77-88 lb)             0                                  0                                   
 &gt;40 (&gt;88 lb)                       0                                  0.5                                 
            5.7 Tardive Dyskinesia
 

  A syndrome of potentially irreversible, involuntary, dyskinetic movements may develop in patients treated with antipsychotic drugs. Although the prevalence of the syndrome appears to be highest among the elderly, especially elderly women, it is impossible to rely upon prevalence estimates to predict, at the inception of antipsychotic treatment, which patients are likely to develop the syndrome. Whether antipsychotic drug products differ in their potential to cause tardive dyskinesia is unknown.



 The risk of developing tardive dyskinesia and the likelihood that it will become irreversible are believed to increase as the duration of treatment and the total cumulative dose of antipsychotic drugs administered to the patient increase. However, the syndrome can develop, although much less commonly, after relatively brief treatment periods at low doses or may even arise after discontinuation of treatment.



 There is no known treatment for established cases of tardive dyskinesia, although the syndrome may remit, partially or completely, if antipsychotic treatment is withdrawn. Antipsychotic treatment, itself, however, may suppress (or partially suppress) the signs and symptoms of the syndrome and thereby may possibly mask the underlying process. The effect that symptomatic suppression has upon the long-term course of the syndrome is unknown.



 Given these considerations, olanzapine should be prescribed in a manner that is most likely to minimize the occurrence of tardive dyskinesia. Chronic antipsychotic treatment should generally be reserved for patients (1) who suffer from a chronic illness that is known to respond to antipsychotic drugs, and (2) for whom alternative, equally effective, but potentially less harmful treatments are not available or appropriate. In patients who do require chronic treatment, the smallest dose and the shortest duration of treatment producing a satisfactory clinical response should be sought. The need for continued treatment should be reassessed periodically.



 If signs and symptoms of tardive dyskinesia appear in a patient on olanzapine, drug discontinuation should be considered. However, some patients may require treatment with olanzapine despite the presence of the syndrome.



 For specific information about the warnings of lithium or valproate, refer to the Warnings section of the package inserts for these other products.



    5.8 Orthostatic Hypotension



  Olanzapine may induce orthostatic hypotension associated with dizziness, tachycardia, bradycardia and, in some patients, syncope, especially during the initial dose-titration period, probably reflecting its alpha1-adrenergic antagonistic properties [see Patient Counseling Information (  17.7  )]  .



 For oral olanzapine therapy, the risk of orthostatic hypotension and syncope may be minimized by initiating therapy with 5 mg QD [see Dosage and Administration (  2  )]  . A more gradual titration to the target dose should be considered if hypotension occurs.



 Hypotension, bradycardia with or without hypotension, tachycardia, and syncope were also reported during the clinical trials with intramuscular olanzapine for injection. In an open-label clinical pharmacology study in nonagitated patients with schizophrenia in which the safety and tolerability of intramuscular olanzapine were evaluated under a maximal dosing regimen (three 10 mg doses administered 4 hours apart), approximately one-third of these patients experienced a significant orthostatic decrease in systolic blood pressure (i.e., decrease &gt;=30 mmHg) [see Dosage and Administration (  2.4  )]  . Syncope was reported in 0.6% (15/2500) of olanzapine-treated patients in phase 2-3 oral olanzapine studies and in 0.3% (2/722) of olanzapine-treated patients with agitation in the intramuscular olanzapine for injection studies. Three normal volunteers in phase 1 studies with intramuscular olanzapine experienced hypotension, bradycardia, and sinus pauses of up to 6 seconds that spontaneously resolved (in 2 cases the reactions occurred on intramuscular olanzapine, and in 1 case, on oral olanzapine). The risk for this sequence of hypotension, bradycardia, and sinus pause may be greater in nonpsychiatric patients compared to psychiatric patients who are possibly more adapted to certain effects of psychotropic drugs. For intramuscular olanzapine for injection therapy, patients should remain recumbent if drowsy or dizzy after injection until examination has indicated that they are not experiencing postural hypotension, bradycardia, and/or hypoventilation.



 Olanzapine should be used with particular caution in patients with known cardiovascular disease (history of myocardial infarction or ischemia, heart failure, or conduction abnormalities), cerebrovascular disease, and conditions which would predispose patients to hypotension (dehydration, hypovolemia, and treatment with antihypertensive medications) where the occurrence of syncope, or hypotension and/or bradycardia might put the patient at increased medical risk.



    Caution is necessary in patients who receive treatment with other drugs having effects that can induce hypotension, bradycardia, respiratory or central nervous system depression [see Drug Interactions (  7  )]  . Concomitant administration of intramuscular olanzapine and parenteral benzodiazepine is not recommended due to the potential for excessive sedation and cardiorespiratory depression.



    5.9 Leukopenia, Neutropenia, and Agranulocytosis



   Class Effect  - In clinical trial and/or postmarketing experience, events of leukopenia/neutropenia have been reported temporally related to antipsychotic agents, including ZYPREXA. Agranulocytosis has also been reported.



 Possible risk factors for leukopenia/neutropenia include pre-existing low white blood cell count (WBC) and history of drug induced leukopenia/neutropenia. Patients with a history of a clinically significant low WBC or drug induced leukopenia/neutropenia should have their complete blood count (CBC) monitored frequently during the first few months of therapy and discontinuation of ZYPREXA should be considered at the first sign of a clinically significant decline in WBC in the absence of other causative factors.



 Patients with clinically significant neutropenia should be carefully monitored for fever or other symptoms or signs of infection and treated promptly if such symptoms or signs occur. Patients with severe neutropenia (absolute neutrophil count &lt;1000/mm  3  ) should discontinue ZYPREXA and have their WBC followed until recovery.



    5.10 Dysphagia



  Esophageal dysmotility and aspiration have been associated with antipsychotic drug use. Aspiration pneumonia is a common cause of morbidity and mortality in patients with advanced Alzheimer's disease. Olanzapine is not approved for the treatment of patients with Alzheimer's disease.



    5.11 Seizures



  During premarketing testing, seizures occurred in 0.9% (22/2500) of olanzapine-treated patients. There were confounding factors that may have contributed to the occurrence of seizures in many of these cases. Olanzapine should be used cautiously in patients with a history of seizures or with conditions that potentially lower the seizure threshold, e.g., Alzheimer's dementia. Olanzapine is not approved for the treatment of patients with Alzheimer's disease. Conditions that lower the seizure threshold may be more prevalent in a population of 65 years or older.



    5.12 Potential for Cognitive and Motor Impairment



  Somnolence was a commonly reported adverse reaction associated with olanzapine treatment, occurring at an incidence of 26% in olanzapine patients compared to 15% in placebo patients. This adverse reaction was also dose related. Somnolence led to discontinuation in 0.4% (9/2500) of patients in the premarketing database.



 Since olanzapine has the potential to impair judgment, thinking, or motor skills, patients should be cautioned about operating hazardous machinery, including automobiles, until they are reasonably certain that olanzapine therapy does not affect them adversely [see Patient Counseling Information (  17.8  )]  .



    5.13 Body Temperature Regulation



  Disruption of the body's ability to reduce core body temperature has been attributed to antipsychotic agents. Appropriate care is advised when prescribing olanzapine for patients who will be experiencing conditions which may contribute to an elevation in core body temperature, e.g., exercising strenuously, exposure to extreme heat, receiving concomitant medication with anticholinergic activity, or being subject to dehydration [see Patient Counseling Information (  17.9  )]  .



    5.14 Use in Patients with Concomitant Illness



  Clinical experience with olanzapine in patients with certain concomitant systemic illnesses is limited [see Clinical Pharmacology (  12.3  )]  .



 Olanzapine exhibits in vitro muscarinic receptor affinity. In premarketing clinical trials with olanzapine, olanzapine was associated with constipation, dry mouth, and tachycardia, all adverse reactions possibly related to cholinergic antagonism. Such adverse reactions were not often the basis for discontinuations from olanzapine, but olanzapine should be used with caution in patients with clinically significant prostatic hypertrophy, narrow angle glaucoma, or a history of paralytic ileus or related conditions.



 In 5 placebo-controlled studies of olanzapine in elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis (n=1184), the following treatment-emergent adverse reactions were reported in olanzapine-treated patients at an incidence of at least 2% and significantly greater than placebo-treated patients: falls, somnolence, peripheral edema, abnormal gait, urinary incontinence, lethargy, increased weight, asthenia, pyrexia, pneumonia, dry mouth and visual hallucinations. The rate of discontinuation due to adverse reactions was greater with olanzapine than placebo (13% vs 7%). Elderly patients with dementia-related psychosis treated with olanzapine are at an increased risk of death compared to placebo. Olanzapine is not approved for the treatment of patients with dementia-related psychosis [see  Boxed Warning  , Warnings and Precautions (  5.1  ), and Patient Counseling Information (  17.2  )]  .



 Olanzapine has not been evaluated or used to any appreciable extent in patients with a recent history of myocardial infarction or unstable heart disease. Patients with these diagnoses were excluded from premarketing clinical studies. Because of the risk of orthostatic hypotension with olanzapine, caution should be observed in cardiac patients [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.8  )]  .



    5.15 Hyperprolactinemia



     As with other drugs that antagonize dopamine D2receptors, olanzapine elevates prolactin levels, and the elevation persists during chronic administration. Hyperprolactinemia may suppress hypothalamic GnRH, resulting in reduced pituitary gonadotropin secretion. This, in turn, may inhibit reproductive function by impairing gonadal steroidogenesis in both female and male patients. Galactorrhea, amenorrhea, gynecomastia, and impotence have been reported in patients receiving prolactin-elevating compounds. Long-standing hyperprolactinemia when associated with hypogonadism may lead to decreased bone density in both female and male subjects.



    Tissue culture experiments indicate that approximately one-third of human breast cancers are prolactin dependent in vitro, a factor of potential importance if the prescription of these drugs is contemplated in a patient with previously detected breast cancer. As is common with compounds which increase prolactin release, an increase in mammary gland neoplasia was observed in the olanzapine carcinogenicity studies conducted in mice and rats [see Nonclinical Toxicology (  13.1  )]  . Neither clinical studies nor epidemiologic studies conducted to date have shown an association between chronic administration of this class of drugs and tumorigenesis in humans; the available evidence is considered too limited to be conclusive at this time.



    In placebo-controlled olanzapine clinical studies (up to 12 weeks), changes from normal to high in prolactin concentrations were observed in 30% of adults treated with olanzapine as compared to 10.5% of adults treated with placebo. In a pooled analysis from clinical studies including 8136 adults treated with olanzapine, potentially associated clinical manifestations included menstrual-related events  1  (2% [49/3240] of females), sexual function-related events  2  (2% [150/8136] of females and males), and breast-related events  3  (0.7% [23/3240] of females, 0.2% [9/4896] of males).



    In placebo-controlled olanzapine monotherapy studies in adolescent patients (up to 6 weeks) with schizophrenia or bipolar I disorder (manic or mixed episodes), changes from normal to high in prolactin concentrations were observed in 47% of olanzapine-treated patients compared to 7% of placebo-treated patients. In a pooled analysis from clinical trials including 454 adolescents treated with olanzapine, potentially associated clinical manifestations included menstrual-related events  1  (1% [2/168] of females), sexual function-related events  2  (0.7% [3/454] of females and males), and breast-related events  3  (2% [3/168] of females, 2% [7/286] of males) [see Use in Specific Populations (  8.4  )]  .



       1   Based on a search of the following terms: amenorrhea, hypomenorrhea, menstruation delayed, and oligomenorrhea.    2   Based on a search of the following terms: anorgasmia, delayed ejaculation, erectile dysfunction, decreased libido, loss of libido, abnormal orgasm, and sexual dysfunction.  3   Based on a search of the following terms: breast discharge, enlargement or swelling, galactorrhea, gynecomastia, and lactation disorder.
 

    5.16 Use in Combination with Fluoxetine, Lithium, or Valproate



  When using ZYPREXA and fluoxetine in combination, the prescriber should also refer to the Warnings and Precautions section of the package insert for Symbyax. When using ZYPREXA in combination with lithium or valproate, the prescriber should refer to the Warnings and Precautions sections of the package inserts for lithium or valproate [see Drug Interactions (  7  )]  .



    5.17 Laboratory Tests



  Fasting blood glucose testing and lipid profile at the beginning of, and periodically during, treatment is recommended [see Warnings and Precautions (  5.4  ,  5.5  ) and Patient Counseling Information (  17.4  ,  17.5  )]  .
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
