<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Label drug="zyvox1" track="TAC2017_ADR">
  <Text>
    <Section name="adverse reactions" id="S1">    6 ADVERSE REACTIONS

  EXCERPT:   Most common adverse reactions (&gt;5% of adult and/or pediatric patients treated with ZYVOX) include: diarrhea, vomiting, headache, nausea, and anemia. (  6  )



   To report SUSPECTED ADVERSE REACTIONS, contact Pfizer Inc at 1-800-438-1985 or FDA at 1-800-FDA-1088 or  www.fda.gov/medwatch.    



 

  6.1 Clinical Trials Experience

  Because clinical trials are conducted under widely varying conditions, adverse reaction rates observed in the clinical trials of a drug cannot be directly compared to rates in the clinical trials of another drug and may not reflect the rates observed in practice.



     Adults:  



 The safety of ZYVOX formulations was evaluated in 2046 adult patients enrolled in seven Phase 3 comparator-controlled clinical trials, who were treated for up to 28 days.



 Of the patients treated for uncomplicated skin and skin structure infections (uSSSIs), 25.4% of ZYVOX-treated and 19.6% of comparator-treated patients experienced at least one drug-related adverse event. For all other indications, 20.4% of ZYVOX -treated and 14.3% of comparator-treated patients experienced at least one drug-related adverse event.



 Table 2 shows the incidence of all-causality, treatment-emergent adverse reactions reported in at least 1% of adult patients in these trials by dose of ZYVOX.



 Table 2. Incidence (%) of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt;1% of Adult Patients Treated with ZYVOX in Comparator-Controlled Clinical Trials 
 ADVERSE REACTIONS             Uncomplicated Skin and Skin Structure Infections  All Other Indications   
                               ZYVOX400 mg by mouth every 12 hours(n=548)  Clarithromycin250 mg by mouth every 12 hours(n=537)  ZYVOX600 mg every 12 hours(n=1498)  All Other Comparators(n=1464)   
  
 Headache                             8.8                 8.4                 5.7                 4.4           
 Diarrhea                             8.2                 6.1                 8.3                 6.4           
 Nausea                               5.1                 4.5                 6.6                 4.6           
 Vomiting                             2.0                 1.5                 4.3                 2.3           
 Dizziness                            2.6                 3.0                 1.8                 1.5           
 Rash                                 1.1                 1.1                 2.3                 2.6           
 Anemia                               0.4                  0                  2.1                 1.4           
 Taste alteration                     1.8                 2.0                 1.0                 0.3           
 Vaginal moniliasis                   1.8                 1.3                 1.1                 0.5           
 Oral moniliasis                      0.5                  0                  1.7                 1.0           
 Abnormal liver function tests         0.4                 0.2                 1.6                 0.8           
 Fungal infection                     1.5                 0.2                 0.3                 0.2           
 Tongue discoloration                 1.3                  0                  0.3                  0            
 Localized abdominal pain             1.3                 0.6                 1.2                 0.8           
 Generalized abdominal pain           0.9                 0.4                 1.2                 1.0           
           Of the patients treated for uSSSIs, 3.5% of ZYVOX-treated and 2.4% of comparator-treated patients discontinued treatment due to drug-related adverse events. For all other indications, discontinuations due to drug-related adverse events occurred in 2.1% of ZYVOX-treated and 1.7% of comparator-treated patients. The most common reported drug-related adverse events leading to discontinuation of treatment were nausea, headache, diarrhea, and vomiting.
 

     Pediatric Patients:  



 The safety of ZYVOX formulations was evaluated in 215 pediatric patients ranging in age from birth through 11 years, and in 248 pediatric patients aged 5 through 17 years (146 of these 248 were age 5 through 11 and 102 were age 12 to 17). These patients were enrolled in two Phase 3 comparator-controlled clinical trials and were treated for up to 28 days. In the study of hospitalized pediatric patients (birth through 11 years) with Gram-positive infections, who were randomized 2 to 1 (linezolid: vancomycin), mortality was 6.0% (13/215) in the linezolid arm and 3.0% (3/101) in the vancomycin arm. However, given the severe underlying illness in the patient population, no causality could be established.



 Of the pediatric patients treated for uSSSIs, 19.2% of ZYVOX-treated and 14.1% of comparator-treated patients experienced at least one drug-related adverse event. For all other indications, 18.8% of ZYVOX-treated and 34.3% of comparator-treated patients experienced at least one drug-related adverse event.



 Table 3 shows the incidence of all-causality, treatment-emergent adverse reactions reported in more than 1% of pediatric patients (and more than 1 patient) in either treatment group in the comparator-controlled Phase 3 trials.



 Table 3. Incidence (%) of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Reactions Occurring in &gt; 1% of Pediatric Patients (and &gt;1 Patient) in Either Treatment Group in Comparator-Controlled Clinical Trials 
 ADVERSE REACTIONS             Uncomplicated Skin and Skin Structure Infections  All Other Indications   
                                  ZYVOX(n=248)     Cefadroxil(n=251)      ZYVOX(n=215)     Vancomycin(n=101)    
  
 Diarrhea                             7.8                 8.0                 10.8                12.1          
 Vomiting                             2.9                 6.4                 9.4                 9.1           
 Headache                             6.5                 4.0                 0.9                  0            
 Anemia                                0                   0                  5.6                 7.1           
 Thrombocytopenia                      0                   0                  4.7                 2.0           
 Nausea                               3.7                 3.2                 1.9                  0            
 Generalized abdominal pain           2.4                 2.8                 0.9                 2.0           
 Localized abdominal pain             2.4                 2.8                 0.5                 1.0           
 Loose stools                         1.6                 0.8                 2.3                 3.0           
 Eosinophilia                         0.4                 0.8                 1.9                 1.0           
 Pruritus at non-application site         0.8                 0.4                 1.4                 2.0           
 Vertigo                              1.2                 0.4                  0                   0            
           Of the pediatric patients treated for uSSSIs, 1.6% of ZYVOX-treated and 2.4% of comparator-treated patients discontinued treatment due to drug-related adverse events. For all other indications, discontinuations due to drug-related adverse events occurred in 0.9% of ZYVOX-treated and 6.1% of comparator-treated patients.
 

     Laboratory Abnormalities:  



 ZYVOX has been associated with thrombocytopenia when used in doses up to and including 600 mg every 12 hours for up to 28 days. In Phase 3 comparator-controlled trials, the percentage of adult patients who developed a substantially low platelet count (defined as less than 75% of lower limit of normal and/or baseline) was 2.4% (range among studies: 0.3 to 10.0%) with ZYVOX and 1.5% (range among studies: 0.4 to 7.0%) with a comparator. In a study of hospitalized pediatric patients ranging in age from birth through 11 years, the percentage of patients who developed a substantially low platelet count (defined as less than 75% of lower limit of normal and/or baseline) was 12.9% with ZYVOX and 13.4% with vancomycin. In an outpatient study of pediatric patients aged from 5 through 17 years, the percentage of patients who developed a substantially low platelet count was 0% with ZYVOX and 0.4% with cefadroxil. Thrombocytopenia associated with the use of ZYVOX appears to be dependent on duration of therapy (generally greater than 2 weeks of treatment). The platelet counts for most patients returned to the normal range/baseline during the follow-up period. No related clinical adverse events were identified in Phase 3 clinical trials in patients developing thrombocytopenia. Bleeding events were identified in thrombocytopenic patients in a compassionate use program for ZYVOX; the role of linezolid in these events cannot be determined [  see  Warning and Precautions (5.1)    ].



 Changes seen in other laboratory parameters, without regard to drug relationship, revealed no substantial differences between ZYVOX and the comparators. These changes were generally not clinically significant, did not lead to discontinuation of therapy, and were reversible. The incidence of adult and pediatric patients with at least one substantially abnormal hematologic or serum chemistry value is presented in Tables 4, 5, 6, and 7.



 Table 4. Percent of Adult Patients who Experienced at Least One Substantially Abnormal&lt;75% (&lt;50% for neutrophils) of Lower Limit of Normal (LLN) for values normal at baseline; &lt;75% (&lt;50% for neutrophils) of LLN and of baseline for values abnormal at baseline. Hematology Laboratory Value in Comparator-Controlled Clinical Trials with ZYVOX 
 Laboratory Assay          Uncomplicated Skin and Skin Structure Infections  All Other Indications   
                           ZYVOX400 mg every 12 hours  Clarithromycin250 mg every 12 hours  ZYVOX600 mg every 12 hours  All Other Comparators   
  
 Hemoglobin (g/dL)                 0.9                  0.0                  7.1                  6.6           
 Platelet count (* 10  3  /mm  3  )          0.7                  0.8                  3.0                  1.8           
 WBC (* 10  3  /mm  3  )           0.2                  0.6                  2.2                  1.3           
 Neutrophils (* 10  3  /mm  3  )          0.0                  0.2                  1.1                  1.2           
          Table 5. Percent of Adult Patients who Experienced at Least One Substantially Abnormal&gt;2 * Upper Limit of Normal (ULN) for values normal at baseline;&gt;2 * ULN and &gt;2 * baseline for values abnormal at baseline. Serum Chemistry Laboratory Value in Comparator-Controlled Clinical Trials with ZYVOX 
 Laboratory Assay          Uncomplicated Skin and Skin Structure Infections  All Other Indications   
                           ZYVOX400 mg every 12 hours  Clarithromycin250 mg every 12 hours  ZYVOX600 mg every 12 hours  All Other Comparators   
  
 AST (U/L)                         1.7                  1.3                  5.0                  6.8           
 ALT (U/L)                         1.7                  1.7                  9.6                  9.3           
 LDH (U/L)                         0.2                  0.2                  1.8                  1.5           
 Alkaline phosphatase (U/L)          0.2                  0.2                  3.5                  3.1           
 Lipase (U/L)                      2.8                  2.6                  4.3                  4.2           
 Amylase (U/L)                     0.2                  0.2                  2.4                  2.0           
 Total bilirubin (mg/dL)           0.2                  0.0                  0.9                  1.1           
 BUN (mg/dL)                       0.2                  0.0                  2.1                  1.5           
 Creatinine (mg/dL)                0.2                  0.0                  0.2                  0.6           
          Table 6. Percent of Pediatric Patients who Experienced at Least One Substantially Abnormal&lt;75% (&lt;50% for neutrophils) of Lower Limit of Normal (LLN) for values normal at baseline; &lt;75% (&lt;50% for neutrophils) of LLN and &lt;75% (&lt;50% for neutrophils, &lt;90% for hemoglobin if baseline &lt;LLN) of baseline for values abnormal at baseline. Hematology Laboratory Value in Comparator-Controlled Clinical Trials with ZYVOX 
 Laboratory Assay          Uncomplicated Skin and Skin Structure Infections  All Other Indications   
                                  ZYVOX             Cefadroxil              ZYVOX             Vancomycin        
  
 Hemoglobin (g/dL)                 0.0                  0.0                 15.7                 12.4           
 Platelet count (* 10  3  /mm  3  )          0.0                  0.4                 12.9                 13.4           
 WBC (* 10  3  /mm  3  )           0.8                  0.8                 12.4                 10.3           
 Neutrophils (* 10  3  /mm  3  )          1.2                  0.8                  5.9                  4.3           
          Table 7. Percent of Pediatric Patients who Experienced at Least One Substantially Abnormal&gt;2 * Upper Limit of Normal (ULN) for values normal at baseline; &gt;2 * ULN and &gt;2 (&gt;1.5 for total bilirubin) * baseline for values abnormal at baseline. Serum Chemistry Laboratory Value in Comparator-Controlled Clinical Trials with ZYVOX 
 Laboratory Assay          Uncomplicated Skin and Skin Structure Infections  All Other Indications   
                                  ZYVOX             Cefadroxil              ZYVOX             Vancomycin        
  
 ALT (U/L)                         0.0                  0.0                 10.1                 12.5           
 Lipase (U/L)                      0.4                  1.2                  ---                  ---           
 Amylase (U/L)                     ---                  ---                  0.6                  1.3           
 Total bilirubin (mg/dL)           ---                  ---                  6.3                  5.2           
 Creatinine (mg/dL)                0.4                  0.0                  2.4                  1.0           
             6.2 Postmarketing Experience
   The following adverse reactions have been identified during postapproval use of ZYVOX. Because these reactions are reported voluntarily from a population of uncertain size, it is not always possible to reliably estimate their frequency or establish a causal relationship to drug exposure.



 Myelosuppression (including anemia, leukopenia, pancytopenia, and thrombocytopenia) has been reported during postmarketing use of ZYVOX [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.1)    ]. Peripheral neuropathy, and optic neuropathy sometimes progressing to loss of vision, have been reported in patients treated with ZYVOX [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.2)    ]. Lactic acidosis has been reported with the use of ZYVOX [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.7)    ]. Although these reports have primarily been in patients treated for longer than the maximum recommended duration of 28 days, these events have also been reported in patients receiving shorter courses of therapy. Serotonin syndrome has been reported in patients receiving concomitant serotonergic agents, including antidepressants such as selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) and ZYVOX [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.3)    ]. Convulsions have been reported with the use of ZYVOX [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.8)    ]. Anaphylaxis, angioedema, and bullous skin disorders such as those described as Stevens-Johnson syndrome have been reported. Superficial tooth discoloration and tongue discoloration have been reported with the use of linezolid. The tooth discoloration was removable with professional dental cleaning (manual descaling) in cases with known outcome. Hypoglycemia, including symptomatic episodes, has been reported [  see  Warnings and Precautions (5.9)    ].
</Section>
    <Section name="warnings and precautions" id="S2">    5 WARNINGS AND PRECAUTIONS



   EXCERPT:    *  Myelosuppression: Monitor complete blood counts weekly. Consider discontinuation in patients who develop or have worsening myelosuppression. (  5.1  ) 
 *  Peripheral and optic neuropathy: Reported primarily in patients treated for longer than 28 days. If patients experience symptoms of visual impairment, prompt ophthalmic evaluation is recommended. (  5.2  ) 
 *  Serotonin syndrome: Patients taking serotonergic antidepressants should receive ZYVOX only if no other therapies are available. Discontinue serotonergic antidepressants and monitor patients for signs and symptoms of both serotonin syndrome and antidepressant discontinuation. (  5.3  ) 
 *  A mortality imbalance was seen in an investigational study in linezolid-treated patients with catheter-related bloodstream infections. (  5.4  ) 
 *   Clostridium difficile associated diarrhea: Evaluate if diarrhea occurs. (  5.5  ) 
 *  Potential interactions producing elevation of blood pressure: monitor blood pressure. (  5.6  ) 
 *  Hypoglycemia: Postmarketing cases of symptomatic hypoglycemia have been reported in patients with diabetes mellitus receiving insulin or oral hypoglycemic agents. (  5.9  ) 
    
 

   5.1 Myelosuppression



  Myelosuppression (including anemia, leukopenia, pancytopenia, and thrombocytopenia) has been reported in patients receiving linezolid. In cases where the outcome is known, when linezolid was discontinued, the affected hematologic parameters have risen toward pretreatment levels. Complete blood counts should be monitored weekly in patients who receive linezolid, particularly in those who receive linezolid for longer than two weeks, those with pre-existing myelosuppression, those receiving concomitant drugs that produce bone marrow suppression, or those with a chronic infection who have received previous or concomitant antibiotic therapy. Discontinuation of therapy with linezolid should be considered in patients who develop or have worsening myelosuppression .  



    5.2 Peripheral and Optic Neuropathy



  Peripheral and optic neuropathies have been reported in patients treated with ZYVOX, primarily in those patients treated for longer than the maximum recommended duration of 28 days. In cases of optic neuropathy that progressed to loss of vision, patients were treated for extended periods beyond the maximum recommended duration. Visual blurring has been reported in some patients treated with ZYVOX for less than 28 days. Peripheral and optic neuropathy has also been reported in children.



 If patients experience symptoms of visual impairment, such as changes in visual acuity, changes in color vision, blurred vision, or visual field defect, prompt ophthalmic evaluation is recommended. Visual function should be monitored in all patients taking ZYVOX for extended periods (&gt;= 3 months) and in all patients reporting new visual symptoms regardless of length of therapy with ZYVOX. If peripheral or optic neuropathy occurs, the continued use of ZYVOX in these patients should be weighed against the potential risks.



    5.3 Serotonin Syndrome



  Spontaneous reports of serotonin syndrome including fatal cases associated with the co-administration of ZYVOX and serotonergic agents, including antidepressants such as selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs), have been reported.



 Unless clinically appropriate and patients are carefully observed for signs and/or symptoms of serotonin syndrome or neuroleptic malignant syndrome-like (NMS-like) reactions, linezolid should not be administered to patients with carcinoid syndrome and/or patients taking any of the following medications: serotonin re-uptake inhibitors, tricyclic antidepressants, serotonin 5-HT1 receptor agonists (triptans), meperidine, bupropion, or buspirone [ see  Drug Interactions (7)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)    ].



 In some cases, a patient already receiving a serotonergic antidepressant or buspirone may require urgent treatment with linezolid. If alternatives to linezolid are not available and the potential benefits of linezolid outweigh the risks of serotonin syndrome or NMS-like reactions, the serotonergic antidepressant should be stopped promptly and linezolid administered. The patient should be monitored for two weeks (five weeks if fluoxetine was taken) or until 24 hours after the last dose of linezolid, whichever comes first. Symptoms of serotonin syndrome or NMS-like reactions include hyperthermia, rigidity, myoclonus, autonomic instability, and mental status changes that include extreme agitation progressing to delirium and coma. The patient should also be monitored for discontinuation symptoms of the antidepressant (see package insert of the specified agent(s) for a description of the associated discontinuation symptoms).



    5.4 Mortality Imbalance in an Investigational Study in Patients with Catheter-Related Bloodstream Infections, including those with catheter-site infections



  An imbalance in mortality was seen in patients treated with linezolid relative to vancomycin/dicloxacillin/oxacillin in an open-label study in seriously ill patients with intravascular catheter-related infections [78/363 (21.5%) vs. 58/363 (16.0%); odds ratio 1.426, 95% CI 0.970, 2.098]. While causality has not been established, this observed imbalance occurred primarily in linezolid-treated patients in whom either Gram-negative pathogens, mixed Gram-negative and Gram-positive pathogens, or no pathogen were identified at baseline, but was not seen in patients with Gram-positive infections only.



 Linezolid is not approved and should not be used for the treatment of patients with catheter-related bloodstream infections or catheter-site infections.



 Linezolid has no clinical activity against Gram-negative pathogens and is not indicated for the treatment of Gram-negative infections. It is critical that specific Gram-negative therapy be initiated immediately if a concomitant Gram-negative pathogen is documented or suspected [ see  Indications and Usage (1)    ].



    5.5 Clostridium difficile  Associated Diarrhea



   Clostridium difficile  associated diarrhea (CDAD) has been reported with use of nearly all antibacterial agents, including ZYVOX, and may range in severity from mild diarrhea to fatal colitis. Treatment with antibacterial agents alters the normal flora of the colon leading to overgrowth of C. difficile  .



  C. difficile  produces toxins A and B which contribute to the development of CDAD. Hypertoxin producing strains of C. difficile  cause increased morbidity and mortality, as these infections can be refractory to antimicrobial therapy and may require colectomy. CDAD must be considered in all patients who present with diarrhea following antibiotic use.



 Careful medical history is necessary since CDAD has been reported to occur over two months after the administration of antibacterial agents.



 If CDAD is suspected or confirmed, ongoing antibiotic use not directed against C. difficile  may need to be discontinued. Appropriate fluid and electrolyte management, protein supplementation, antibiotic treatment of C. difficile  , and surgical evaluation should be instituted as clinically indicated.



    5.6 Potential Interactions Producing Elevation of Blood Pressure



  Unless patients are monitored for potential increases in blood pressure, linezolid should not be administered to patients with uncontrolled hypertension, pheochromocytoma, thyrotoxicosis and/or patients taking any of the following types of medications: directly and indirectly acting sympathomimetic agents (e.g., pseudoephedrine), vasopressive agents (e.g., epinephrine, norepinephrine), dopaminergic agents (e.g., dopamine, dobutamine) [ see  Drug Interactions (7)  and  Clinical Pharmacology (12.3)    ] .  



    5.7 Lactic Acidosis



  Lactic acidosis has been reported with the use of ZYVOX. In reported cases, patients experienced repeated episodes of nausea and vomiting. Patients who develop recurrent nausea or vomiting, unexplained acidosis, or a low bicarbonate level while receiving ZYVOX should receive immediate medical evaluation.



    5.8 Convulsions



  Convulsions have been reported in patients when treated with linezolid. In some of these cases, a history of seizures or risk factors for seizures was reported.



    5.9 Hypoglycemia



  Postmarketing cases of symptomatic hypoglycemia have been reported in patients with diabetes mellitus receiving insulin or oral hypoglycemic agents when treated with linezolid, a reversible, nonselective MAO inhibitor. Some MAO inhibitors have been associated with hypoglycemic episodes in diabetic patients receiving insulin or hypoglycemic agents. While a causal relationship between linezolid and hypoglycemia has not been established, diabetic patients should be cautioned of potential hypoglycemic reactions when treated with linezolid.



 If hypoglycemia occurs, a decrease in the dose of insulin or oral hypoglycemic agent, or discontinuation of oral hypoglycemic agent, insulin, or linezolid may be required.



    5.10 Development of Drug-Resistant Bacteria



  Prescribing ZYVOX in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection or a prophylactic indication is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug-resistant bacteria.
</Section>
  </Text>
  <Mentions />
  <Relations />
  <Reactions />
</Label>
